<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0"
            xmlns:fmx="http://formex.publications.europa.eu/schema/formex-05.21-20110601.xd"
            xmlns:leos="urn:eu:europa:ec:leos"
            xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema">
   <bill name="">
      <meta xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions">
         <identification source="~COM">
            <FRBRWork>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRcountry value=""/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
         </identification>
      </meta>
      <preface>
         <longTitle>
            <p>
               <docStage/>
               <docType>REGULATION (EU) 2019/1677 OF THE EUROPEAN CENTRAL BANK</docType>of 27 September 2019<docPurpose>amending Regulation (EU) No 1333/2014 concerning statistics on the money markets</docPurpose>(ECB/2019/29)</p>
         </longTitle>
      </preface>
      <preamble>
         <formula name="actingEntity">
            <p>THE GOVERNING COUNCIL OF THE EUROPEAN CENTRAL BANK,</p>
         </formula>
         <citations>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the Statute of the European System of Central Banks and of the European Central Bank, and in particular Article 5 thereof,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to Council Regulation (EC) No 2533/98 of 23 November 1998 concerning the collection of statistical information by the European Central Bank<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="1">
                     <p>OJ L 318, 27.11.1998, p. 8.</p>
                  </authorialNote>, and in particular Articles 5(1) and 6(4) thereof,</p>
            </citation>
         </citations>
         <recitals xml:id="recs_d565e70">
            <intro>
               <p>Whereas:</p>
            </intro>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d565e73">
               <num>(1)</num>
               <p>Regulation (EU) No 1333/2014 of the European Central Bank (ECB/2014/48)<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="2">
                     <p>Regulation (EU) No 1333/2014 of the European Central Bank of 26 November 2014 concerning statistics on the money markets (ECB/2014/48) (OJ L 359, 16.12.2014, p. 97).</p>
                  </authorialNote> requires the reporting of daily statistical information by reporting agents in order that the European System of Central Banks (ESCB), in the fulfilment of its tasks, may produce statistics on the euro money market.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d565e89">
               <num>(2)</num>
               <p>To further ensure the availability of high quality statistics on the euro money market, it is necessary to amend the minimum standards to be applied by reporting agents under Regulation (EU) No 1333/2014 (ECB/2014/48). In addition to the duty to provide timely reports of all transactions within the scope of the reporting obligation to the European Central Bank (ECB) or the relevant national central bank (NCB) and to ensure that the statistical information concerning these transactions is impartial, objective and reliable and is compiled and submitted in a manner that protects its integrity, reporting agents must also make themselves available to respond within set deadlines to any queries raised by the ECB or the NCBs about the accuracy of the statistical information. Maintaining these minimum standards is even more important when data is published by the ECB on a daily basis when performing its ESCB tasks.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d565e95">
               <num>(3)</num>
               <p>Given the need to ensure that the actual reporting population fulfils the additional requirement of responding to queries raised by the ECB or the NCBs, the minimum standards under Annex IV to Regulation (EU) No 1333/2014 (ECB/2014/48) should be supplemented.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d565e101">
               <num>(4)</num>
               <p>Therefore, Regulation (EU) No 1333/2014 (ECB/2014/48) should be amended accordingly,</p>
            </recital>
         </recitals>
         <formula name="enactingFormula">
            <p>HAS ADOPTED THIS REGULATION:</p>
         </formula>
      </preamble>
      <body>
         <article xml:id="art_d565e111">
            <num>Article 1</num>
            <heading>Amendment</heading>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>Annex IV to Regulation (EU) No 1333/2014 (ECB/2014/48) is replaced by the text set out in the Annex to this Regulation.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <article xml:id="art_d565e118">
            <num>Article 2</num>
            <heading>Final provisions</heading>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>This Regulation shall enter into force on the twentieth day following that of its publication in the <i>Official Journal of the European Union</i>.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <clause>
            <content>
               <p>This Regulation shall be binding in its entirety and directly applicable in the Member States in accordance with the Treaties.</p>
            </content>
         </clause>
      </body>
      <conclusions>
         <p>Done at Frankfurt am Main, 27 September 2019.</p>
         <block name="signatory">
            <signature>
               <organization refersTo="">For the Governing Council of the ECB</organization>
               <role refersTo="">The President of the ECB</role>
               <person refersTo="">Mario DRAGHI</person>
            </signature>
         </block>
      </conclusions>
   </bill>
</akomaNtoso>
