<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0"
            xmlns:fmx="http://formex.publications.europa.eu/schema/formex-05.21-20110601.xd"
            xmlns:leos="urn:eu:europa:ec:leos"
            xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema">
   <bill name="">
      <meta xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions">
         <identification source="~COM">
            <FRBRWork>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRcountry value=""/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
         </identification>
      </meta>
      <preface>
         <longTitle>
            <p>
               <docStage/>
               <docType>REGULATION (EU) 2021/1873 OF THE EUROPEAN PARLIAMENT AND OF THE COUNCIL</docType>of 20 October 2021<docPurpose>on the extension of the term of the Community plant variety rights for varieties of the species Asparagus officinalis L. and of the species groups flower bulbs, woody small fruits and woody ornamentals</docPurpose>
            </p>
         </longTitle>
      </preface>
      <preamble>
         <formula name="actingEntity">
            <p>THE EUROPEAN PARLIAMENT AND THE COUNCIL OF THE EUROPEAN UNION,</p>
         </formula>
         <citations>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union, and in particular Article 118, first paragraph, thereof,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the proposal from the European Commission,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>After transmission of the draft legislative act to the national parliaments,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the opinion of the European Economic and Social Committee<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="1">
                     <p>OJ C 220, 9.6.2021, p. 86.</p>
                  </authorialNote>,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>Acting in accordance with the ordinary legislative procedure<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="2">
                     <p>Position of the European Parliament of 14 September 2021 (not yet published in the Official Journal) and decision of the Council of 5 October 2021.</p>
                  </authorialNote>,</p>
            </citation>
         </citations>
         <recitals xml:id="recs_d617e86">
            <intro>
               <p>Whereas:</p>
            </intro>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d617e89">
               <num>(1)</num>
               <p>Technical difficulties in breeding, due to complex genetic backgrounds or to the slow or technically complicated reproduction of the species <i>Asparagus officinalis</i> L. and the species groups flower bulbs, woody small fruits and woody ornamentals, need to be addressed by means of investments in research and development activities. Once protection of plant variety rights is granted for that species and those species groups, it takes years to multiply the plants and to build up a stock that is sufficiently large to generate a reasonable income. Accordingly, the time during which the holder of the plant variety rights can generate income based on that protection is limited. To encourage investments in research and development for varieties of that species and those species groups, it is necessary to prolong the term of protection of plant variety rights and incentivise breeding activities to develop new varieties in order to meet the needs of farmers and consumers and to address the impact of climate change. Those investments require more time to be profitable than for the overwhelming majority of other species, such as agricultural crops, which often have a shorter life span and a larger and wider range of consumers.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d617e98">
               <num>(2)</num>
               <p>The market introduction and market uptake of a new variety of the species <i>Asparagus officinalis</i> L. and the species groups flower bulbs, woody small fruits and woody ornamentals require more time in order for that new variety to be profitable than for other species, as experience has shown that such a new variety reveals its commercial value only in the long term. For those reasons, an equitable refunding of investments in research and development is only possible at a fairly late stage of the protection of that species and those species groups in comparison with other species.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d617e108">
               <num>(3)</num>
               <p>Council Regulation (EC) No 2100/94<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="3">
                     <p>Council Regulation (EC) No 2100/94 of 27 July 1994 on Community plant variety rights (OJ L 227, 1.9.1994, p. 1).</p>
                  </authorialNote> establishes a system of Community plant variety rights as the sole and exclusive form of Community industrial property rights for plant varieties. In accordance with Article 19(1) of that Regulation, the term of the Community plant variety right is to run until the end of the 25th calendar year or, in the case of varieties of vine and tree species, until the end of the 30th calendar year, following the year of grant.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d617e124">
               <num>(4)</num>
               <p>In order to establish a legal environment conducive to achieving an equitable refunding, it is appropriate to extend by a further five years the term of the Community plant variety rights for varieties of the species <i>Asparagus officinalis</i> L. and of the species groups flower bulbs, woody small fruits and woody ornamentals. That extension should apply to rights granted before, on or after the date of entry into force of this Regulation.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d617e133">
               <num>(5)</num>
               <p>For reasons of consistency, such extension should apply to all Community plant variety rights for varieties of the species <i>Asparagus officinalis</i> L. and of the species groups flower bulbs, woody small fruits and woody ornamentals.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d617e142">
               <num>(6)</num>
               <p>The period of extension should be reduced if national property rights for those varieties have been effective in a Member State prior to the grant of a Community plant variety right and, accordingly, would already have allowed breeders to exploit their varieties,</p>
            </recital>
         </recitals>
         <formula name="enactingFormula">
            <p>HAVE ADOPTED THIS REGULATION:</p>
         </formula>
      </preamble>
      <body>
         <article xml:id="art_d617e151">
            <num>Article 1</num>
            <heading>Extension of the term of Community plant variety rights</heading>
            <paragraph>
               <num>1.</num>
               <content>
                  <p>The term of the Community plant variety rights, as provided for in Article 19(1) of Regulation (EC) No 2100/94, shall, for varieties of the species <i>Asparagus officinalis</i> L. and of the species groups flower bulbs, woody small fruits and woody ornamentals, be extended by five years.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph>
               <num>2.</num>
               <content>
                  <p>Paragraph 1 of this Article is without prejudice to Article 116(4), fourth indent, of Regulation (EC) No 2100/94.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <article xml:id="art_d617e169">
            <num>Article 2</num>
            <heading>Reduction of the extension</heading>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>For plant varieties for which one or more national plant variety rights have been granted prior to the grant of a Community plant variety right, but to which Article 116(4), fourth indent, of Regulation (EC) No 2100/94 does not apply, the extension of the term provided for in Article 1 of this Regulation shall be reduced by the longest period in full calendar years during which any national plant variety right or rights granted have been effective in a Member State in respect of the same variety prior to the grant of the Community plant variety rights.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <article xml:id="art_d617e176">
            <num>Article 3</num>
            <heading>Entry into force</heading>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>This Regulation shall enter into force on the twentieth day following that of its publication in the <i>Official Journal of the European Union</i>.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <clause>
            <content>
               <p>This Regulation shall be binding in its entirety and directly applicable in all Member States.</p>
            </content>
         </clause>
      </body>
      <conclusions>
         <p>Done at Strasbourg, 20 October 2021.</p>
         <block name="signatory">
            <signature>
               <organization refersTo="">For the European Parliament</organization>
               <role refersTo="">The President</role>
               <person refersTo="">D. M. SASSOLI</person>
            </signature>
            <signature>
               <organization refersTo="">For the Council</organization>
               <role refersTo="">The President</role>
               <person refersTo="">A. LOGAR</person>
            </signature>
         </block>
      </conclusions>
   </bill>
</akomaNtoso>
