<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0"
            xmlns:fmx="http://formex.publications.europa.eu/schema/formex-05.21-20110601.xd"
            xmlns:leos="urn:eu:europa:ec:leos"
            xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema">
   <bill name="">
      <meta xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions">
         <identification source="~COM">
            <FRBRWork>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRcountry value=""/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
         </identification>
      </meta>
      <preface>
         <longTitle>
            <p>
               <docStage/>
               <docType>COMMISSION REGULATION (EU) 2018/1481</docType>of 4 October 2018<docPurpose>amending Annexes II and III to Regulation (EC) No 1333/2008 of the European Parliament and of the Council and the Annex to Commission Regulation (EU) No 231/2012 as regards octyl gallate (E 311) and dodecyl gallate (E 312)</docPurpose>
            </p>
         </longTitle>
         <container name="EEArelevance">
            <p>(Text with EEA relevance)</p>
         </container>
      </preface>
      <preamble>
         <formula name="actingEntity">
            <p>THE EUROPEAN COMMISSION,</p>
         </formula>
         <citations>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to Regulation (EC) No 1333/2008 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 16 December 2008 on food additives<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="1">
                     <p>OJ L 354, 31.12.2008, p. 16.</p>
                  </authorialNote>, and in particular Article 10(3) and Article 14 thereof,</p>
            </citation>
         </citations>
         <recitals xml:id="recs_d378e71">
            <intro>
               <p>Whereas:</p>
            </intro>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d378e74">
               <num>(1)</num>
               <p>Annex II to Regulation (EC) No 1333/2008 lays down a Union list of food additives approved for use in foods and their conditions of use.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d378e80">
               <num>(2)</num>
               <p>Annex III to Regulation (EC) No 1333/2008 lays down a Union list of food additives approved for use in food additives, food enzymes, food flavourings, nutrients and their conditions of use.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d378e86">
               <num>(3)</num>
               <p>Commission Regulation (EU) No 231/2012<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="2">
                     <p>Commission Regulation (EU) No 231/2012 of 9 March 2012 laying down specifications for food additives listed in Annexes II and III to Regulation (EC) No 1333/2008 of the European Parliament and of the Council (OJ L 83, 22.3.2012, p. 1).</p>
                  </authorialNote> lays down specifications for food additives that are listed in Annexes II and III to Regulation (EC) No 1333/2008.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d378e102">
               <num>(4)</num>
               <p>Octyl gallate (E 311) and dodecyl gallate (E 312) are substances authorised as antioxidants in a variety of foods, as well as in food flavourings, in accordance with Annexes II and III to Regulation (EC) No 1333/2008.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d378e108">
               <num>(5)</num>
               <p>Article 32(1) of Regulation (EC) No 1333/2008 provides that all food additives that were already permitted in the Union before 20 January 2009 are subject to a new risk assessment by the European Food Safety Authority (&apos;the Authority&apos;).</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d378e121">
               <num>(6)</num>
               <p>For that purpose, a program for the re-evaluation of food additives is laid down in Commission Regulation (EU) No 257/2010<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="3">
                     <p>Commission Regulation (EU) No 257/2010 of 25 March 2010 setting up the program for the re-evaluation of approved food additives in accordance with Regulation (EC) No 1333/2008 of the European Parliament and of the Council on food additives (OJ L 80, 26.3.2010, p. 19).</p>
                  </authorialNote>. Pursuant to Regulation (EU) No 257/2010 the re-evaluation of antioxidants had to be completed by 31 December 2015.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d378e140">
               <num>(7)</num>
               <p>On 5 May 2015 the Authority delivered a Scientific Opinion on the re-evaluation of dodecyl gallate (E 312) as a food additive<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="4">
                     <p>EFSA Journal 2015;13(5):4086.</p>
                  </authorialNote>. The opinion stated that there was a lack of adequate toxicological data on dodecyl gallate. Consequently the Authority was not able to confirm the safety of dodecyl gallate as a food additive and concluded that the present group Acceptable Daily Intake (ADI) for propyl gallate (E 310), octyl gallate (E 311) and dodecyl gallate (E 312) should no longer be valid. The opinion stated that a sufficient toxicological database would be required for an adequate assessment of the safety of dodecyl gallate as a food additive.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d378e153">
               <num>(8)</num>
               <p>On 1 October 2015 the Authority delivered a Scientific Opinion on the re-evaluation of octyl gallate (E 311) as a food additive<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="5">
                     <p>EFSA Journal 2015;13(10):4248.</p>
                  </authorialNote>. The opinion stated that there was a lack of adequate toxicological data on octyl gallate. Consequently the Authority was not able to confirm the safety of octyl gallate as a food additive and concluded that the present group ADI for propyl gallate (E 310), octyl gallate (E 311) and dodecyl gallate (E 312) should no longer be valid. The opinion stated that a sufficient toxicological database would be required for an adequate assessment of the safety of octyl gallate as a food additive.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d378e167">
               <num>(9)</num>
               <p>On 30 May 2017 the Commission launched a public call for scientific and technological data on propyl gallate (E 310), octyl gallate (E 311) and dodecyl gallate (E 312)<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="6">
                     <p>http://ec.europa.eu/food/safety/food_improvement_agents/additives/re-evaluation_en.</p>
                  </authorialNote>, targeting the data needs identified in the Scientific Opinions on the re-evaluation of those substances as food additives. However, no business operator committed to providing the requested toxicological data for octyl gallate (E 311) and dodecyl gallate (E 312). Without those data the Authority cannot complete the re-evaluation of the safety of octyl gallate and dodecyl gallate as food additives and consequently it cannot be determined whether those substances still fulfil the conditions pursuant to Article 6(1) of Regulation (EC) No 1333/2008 for inclusion in the Union list of approved food additives.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d378e181">
               <num>(10)</num>
               <p>It is therefore appropriate to remove octyl gallate (E 311) and dodecyl gallate (E 312) from the Union list of approved food additives.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d378e187">
               <num>(11)</num>
               <p>Pursuant to Article 10(3) of Regulation (EC) No 1333/2008, the Union list of approved food additives shall be amended in accordance with the procedure referred to in Regulation (EC) No 1331/2008 of the European Parliament and of the Council<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="7">
                     <p>Regulation (EC) No 1331/2008 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 16 December 2008 establishing a common authorisation procedure for food additives, food enzymes and food flavourings (OJ L 354, 31.12.2008, p. 1).</p>
                  </authorialNote>.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d378e203">
               <num>(12)</num>
               <p>Article 3(1) of Regulation (EC) No 1331/2008 provides that the Union list of food additives may be updated either on the initiative of the Commission or following an application.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d378e209">
               <num>(13)</num>
               <p>Therefore, Annexes II and III to Regulation (EC) No 1333/2008 and the Annex to Regulation (EU) No 231/2012 should be amended by deleting octyl gallate (E 311) and dodecyl gallate (E 312) from the Union list of authorised food additives since due to the absence of appropriate toxicological data their inclusion in the list can no longer be justified.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d378e215">
               <num>(14)</num>
               <p>It is appropriate to provide for a transitional period during which foods containing octyl gallate (E 311) and/or dodecyl gallate (E 312) that have been lawfully placed on the market before the entry in force of this Regulation may continue to be marketed.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d378e221">
               <num>(15)</num>
               <p>The measures provided for in this Regulation are in accordance with the opinion of the Standing Committee on Plants, Animals, Food and Feed,</p>
            </recital>
         </recitals>
         <formula name="enactingFormula">
            <p>HAS ADOPTED THIS REGULATION:</p>
         </formula>
      </preamble>
      <body>
         <article xml:id="art_d378e230">
            <num>Article 1</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>Annexes II and III to Regulation (EC) No 1333/2008 are amended in accordance with the Annex to this Regulation.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <article xml:id="art_d378e235">
            <num>Article 2</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>In the Annex to Regulation (EU) No 231/2012, the entries for food additives octyl gallate (E 311) and dodecyl gallate (E 312) are deleted.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <article xml:id="art_d378e240">
            <num>Article 3</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>Foods containing octyl gallate (E 311) and/or dodecyl gallate (E 312) that have been lawfully placed on the market before the entry into force of this Regulation may continue to be marketed until 25 April 2019.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <article xml:id="art_d378e248">
            <num>Article 4</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>This Regulation shall enter into force on the twentieth day following that of its publication in <i>the Official Journal of the European Union</i>.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <clause>
            <content>
               <p>This Regulation shall be binding in its entirety and directly applicable in all Member States.</p>
            </content>
         </clause>
      </body>
      <conclusions>
         <p>Done at Brussels, 4 October 2018.</p>
         <block name="signatory">
            <signature>
               <organization refersTo="">For the Commission</organization>
               <role refersTo="">The President</role>
               <person refersTo="">Jean-Claude JUNCKER</person>
            </signature>
         </block>
      </conclusions>
   </bill>
</akomaNtoso>
