<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0"
            xmlns:fmx="http://formex.publications.europa.eu/schema/formex-05.21-20110601.xd"
            xmlns:leos="urn:eu:europa:ec:leos"
            xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema">
   <bill name="">
      <meta xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions">
         <identification source="~COM">
            <FRBRWork>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRcountry value=""/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
         </identification>
      </meta>
      <preface>
         <longTitle>
            <p>
               <docStage/>
               <docType>COUNCIL REGULATION (EU) 2021/90</docType>of 28 January 2021<docPurpose>fixing for 2021 the fishing opportunities for certain fish stocks and groups of fish stocks applicable in the Mediterranean and Black Seas</docPurpose>
            </p>
         </longTitle>
      </preface>
      <preamble>
         <formula name="actingEntity">
            <p>THE COUNCIL OF THE EUROPEAN UNION,</p>
         </formula>
         <citations>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union, and in particular Article 43(3) thereof,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the proposal from the European Commission,</p>
            </citation>
         </citations>
         <recitals xml:id="recs_d13e59">
            <intro>
               <p>Whereas:</p>
            </intro>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d13e62">
               <num>(1)</num>
               <p>Article 43(3) of the Treaty provides that the Council, on a proposal from the Commission, is to adopt measures on the fixing and allocation of fishing opportunities.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d13e68">
               <num>(2)</num>
               <p>Regulation (EU) No 1380/2013 of the European Parliament and of the Council<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="1">
                     <p>Regulation (EU) No 1380/2013 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 11 December 2013 on the Common Fisheries Policy, amending Council Regulations (EC) No 1954/2003 and (EC) No 1224/2009 and repealing Council Regulations (EC) No 2371/2002 and (EC) No 639/2004 and Council Decision 2004/585/EC (OJ L 354, 28.12.2013, p. 22).</p>
                  </authorialNote> requires that conservation measures be adopted taking into account available scientific, technical and economic advice, including, where relevant, reports drawn up by the Scientific, Technical and Economic Committee for Fisheries (STECF).</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d13e84">
               <num>(3)</num>
               <p>It is incumbent upon the Council to adopt measures on the fixing and allocation of fishing opportunities, including, where appropriate, certain conditions functionally linked thereto. In accordance with Article 16(4) of Regulation (EU) No 1380/2013, fishing opportunities are to be fixed in accordance with the objectives of the Common Fisheries Policy (CFP) established in Article 2(2) of that Regulation. Article 16(1) of Regulation (EU) No 1380/2013 provides that fishing opportunities be allocated to Member States in such a way as to ensure the relative stability of fishing activities of each Member State for each fish stock or fishery.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d13e90">
               <num>(4)</num>
               <p>Article 16(4) of Regulation (EU) No 1380/2013 provides that for stocks subject to specific multiannual plans, the fishing opportunities are to be established in accordance with the rules laid down in those plans.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d13e96">
               <num>(5)</num>
               <p>The multiannual plan for the fisheries exploiting demersal stocks in the western Mediterranean Sea was established by Regulation (EU) 2019/1022 of the European Parliament and of the Council<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="2">
                     <p>Regulation (EU) 2019/1022 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 20 June 2019 establishing a multiannual plan for the fisheries exploiting demersal stocks in the western Mediterranean Sea and amending Regulation (EU) No 508/2014 (OJ L 172, 26.6.2019, p. 1).</p>
                  </authorialNote> and entered into force on 16 July 2019. In accordance with Article 4(1) of that Regulation, fishing opportunities for stocks listed in Article 1 of that Regulation should be fixed to achieve fishing mortality at maximum sustainable yield (MSY) on a progressive, incremental basis by 2020 where possible, and by 1 January 2025. Fishing opportunities should be expressed as maximum allowable fishing effort and fixed in accordance with the fishing effort regime laid down in Article 7 of that Regulation.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d13e119">
               <num>(6)</num>
               <p>STECF concluded that in order to attain the MSY targets for the western Mediterranean fish stocks, swift action is needed and real reductions in fishing mortality are necessary. For 2021, the maximum allowable fishing effort should therefore be reduced by 7,5 % compared to the baseline, to be deducted from the maximum allowable fishing effort set for 2020 by Council Regulation (EU) 2019/2236<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="3">
                     <p>Council Regulation (EU) 2019/2236 of 16 December 2019 fixing for 2020 the fishing opportunities for certain fish stocks and groups of fish stocks applicable in the Mediterranean and Black Seas (OJ L 336, 30.12.2019, p. 14).</p>
                  </authorialNote>.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d13e135">
               <num>(7)</num>
               <p>At its 42nd annual meeting in 2018, the General Fisheries Commission for the Mediterranean (GFCM) adopted Recommendation GFCM/42/2018/1 on a multiannual management plan for European eel in the Mediterranean Sea, which established management measures for European eel (<i>Anguilla anguilla</i>) in the Mediterranean Sea (GFCM geographical subareas 1 to 27). Those measures include catch or effort limits and an annual closure period of three consecutive months to be defined by each Member State in accordance with the conservation objectives of Council Regulation (EC) No 1100/2007<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="4">
                     <p>Council Regulation (EC) No 1100/2007 of 18 September 2007 establishing measures for the recovery of the stock of European eel (OJ L 248, 22.9.2007, p. 17).</p>
                  </authorialNote>, the national management plan or plans for eel and the temporal migration patterns of eel in the Member State. Where national management plans resulting in effort or catch reductions of at least 30 % have been in place before the entry into force of that Recommendation, the catch or fishing effort limits already established and implemented should not be exceeded. The closure should apply to all marine waters of the Mediterranean Sea and to brackish waters such as estuaries, coastal lagoons and transitional waters, in accordance with that Recommendation. Those measures should be implemented in Union law.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d13e154">
               <num>(8)</num>
               <p>At its 42nd annual meeting in 2018, the GFCM also adopted Recommendation GFCM/42/2018/8 on further emergency measures in 2019-2021 for small pelagic stocks in the Adriatic Sea (GFCM geographical subareas 17 and 18). Those measures should be implemented in Union law. The maximum catch limits are fixed exclusively for one year and without prejudice to any other measures adopted in the future and any possible allocation scheme between Member States.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d13e160">
               <num>(9)</num>
               <p>At its 42nd annual meeting in 2018, the GFCM adopted Recommendation GFCM/42/2018/3 on a multiannual management plan for sustainable trawl fisheries targeting giant red shrimp (<i>Aristaeomorpha foliacea</i>) and blue and red shrimp (<i>Aristeus antennatus</i>) in the Levant Sea (GFCM geographical subareas 24, 25, 26 and 27), which introduced a maximum number of fishing vessels. Those measures should be implemented in Union law.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d13e173">
               <num>(10)</num>
               <p>At its 42nd annual meeting in 2018, the GFCM adopted Recommendation GFCM/42/2018/4 on a multiannual management plan for sustainable trawl fisheries targeting giant red shrimp (<i>Aristaeomorpha foliacea</i>) and blue and red shrimp (<i>Aristeus antennatus</i>) in the Ionian Sea (GFCM geographical subareas 19, 20 and 21), which introduced a maximum number of fishing vessels. Those measures should be implemented in Union law.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d13e185">
               <num>(11)</num>
               <p>At its 43rd annual meeting in 2019, the GFCM adopted Recommendation GFCM/43/2019/6 on management measures for sustainable trawl fisheries targeting giant red shrimp (<i>Aristaeomorpha foliacea</i>) and blue and red shrimp (<i>Aristeus antennatus</i>) in the Strait of Sicily (GFCM geographical subareas 12, 13, 14, 15 and 16), which introduced a maximum number of fishing vessels. Those measures should be implemented in Union law.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d13e197">
               <num>(12)</num>
               <p>At its 43rd annual meeting in 2019, the GFCM adopted Recommendation GFCM/43/2019/5 on a multiannual management plan for sustainable demersal fisheries in the Adriatic Sea (GFCM geographical subareas 17 and 18), which introduced a fishing effort regime and a fleet capacity ceiling for certain demersal stocks. Those measures should be implemented in Union law.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d13e203">
               <num>(13)</num>
               <p>Taking into account the particularities of the Slovenian fleet and their marginal impact on the stocks of small pelagic and demersal stocks, it is appropriate to preserve the existing fishing patterns and to ensure access by the Slovenian fleet to a minimum quantity of small pelagic species and a minimum effort quota for demersal stocks.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d13e210">
               <num>(14)</num>
               <p>At its 43rd annual meeting in 2019, the GFCM adopted Recommendation GFCM/43/2019/4 on a management plan for the sustainable exploitation of red coral (<i>Corallium rubrum</i>) in the Mediterranean Sea (GFCM geographical subareas 1 to 27), which introduced a maximum number of fishing authorisations and harvest limits for red coral. Those measures should be implemented in Union law.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d13e219">
               <num>(15)</num>
               <p>At its 43rd annual meeting in 2019, the GFCM adopted Recommendation GFCM/43/2019/2 on a management plan for the sustainable exploitation of blackspot seabream (<i>Pagellus bogaraveo</i>) in the Alboran Sea (GFCM geographical subareas 1 to 3), which introduced a catch and effort limit based on the average level authorised and exerted over the period 2010&#45;2015. Those measures should be implemented in Union law.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d13e228">
               <num>(16)</num>
               <p>At its 43rd annual meeting in 2019, the GFCM adopted Recommendation GFCM/43/2019/1 on a set of management measures for the use of anchored fish aggregating devices in common dolphinfish fisheries (<i>Coryphaena hippurus</i>) in the Mediterranean Sea (GFCM geographical subareas 1 to 27), which introduced a maximum number of fishing vessels targeting common dolphinfish. Those measures should be implemented in Union law.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d13e237">
               <num>(17)</num>
               <p>At its 43rd annual meeting in 2019, the GFCM adopted Recommendation GFCM/43/2019/3 amending Recommendation GFCM/41/2017/4 on a multiannual management plan for turbot fisheries in the Black Sea (GFCM geographical subarea 29). That Recommendation introduced an updated regional total allowable catch (TAC) and a quota allocation scheme for turbot and further conservation measures for that stock, in particular a two months&apos; closure period and a limitation of fishing days to 180 days per year. Those measures should be implemented in Union law.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d13e243">
               <num>(18)</num>
               <p>In accordance with the scientific advice provided by the GFCM, it is necessary to maintain the current level of fishing mortality to ensure the sustainability of the stock of sprat in the Black Sea. It is therefore appropriate to continue setting an autonomous quota for that stock.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d13e249">
               <num>(19)</num>
               <p>The fishing opportunities should be established on the basis of the available scientific advice, taking into account biological and socio-economic aspects whilst ensuring fair treatment between fishing sectors, as well as in the light of the opinions expressed during the consultation of stakeholders.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d13e256">
               <num>(20)</num>
               <p>Council Regulation (EC) No 847/96<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="5">
                     <p>Council Regulation (EC) No 847/96 of 6 May 1996 introducing additional conditions for year-to-year management of TACs and quotas (OJ L 115, 9.5.1996, p. 3).</p>
                  </authorialNote> introduced additional conditions for year-to-year management of TACs including, under Articles 3 and 4 of that Regulation, flexibility provisions for precautionary and analytical TACs. Under Article 2 of that Regulation, when fixing the TACs, the Council is to decide to which stocks Article 3 or 4 of that Regulation is not to apply, in particular on the basis of the biological status of the stocks. More recently, the year-to-year flexibility mechanism was introduced by Article 15(9) of Regulation (EU) No 1380/2013 for all stocks that are subject to the landing obligation. Therefore, in order to avoid excessive flexibility that would undermine the principle of rational and responsible exploitation of marine biological resources, hinder the achievement of the objectives of the CFP and cause the biological status of the stocks to deteriorate, it should be established that Articles 3 and 4 of Regulation (EC) No 847/96 apply to analytical TACs only where the year-to-year flexibility provided for in Article 15(9) of Regulation (EU) No 1380/2013 is not used.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d13e272">
               <num>(21)</num>
               <p>The use of fishing opportunities available to Union fishing vessels set out in this Regulation is subject to Council Regulation (EC) No 1224/2009<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="6">
                     <p>Council Regulation (EC) No 1224/2009 of 20 November 2009 establishing a Union control system for ensuring compliance with the rules of the common fisheries policy, amending Regulations (EC) No 847/96, (EC) No 2371/2002, (EC) No 811/2004, (EC) No 768/2005, (EC) No 2115/2005, (EC) No 2166/2005, (EC) No 388/2006, (EC) No 509/2007, (EC) No 676/2007, (EC) No 1098/2007, (EC) No 1300/2008, (EC) No 1342/2008 and repealing Regulations (EEC) No 2847/93, (EC) No 1627/94 and (EC) No 1966/2006 (OJ L 343, 22.12.2009, p. 1).</p>
                  </authorialNote>, and in particular to Articles 33 and 34 of that Regulation, concerning the recording of catches and fishing effort and the notification of data on the exhaustion of fishing opportunities. It is therefore necessary to specify the codes to be used by Member States when sending data to the Commission relating to landings of stocks subject to this Regulation.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d13e289">
               <num>(22)</num>
               <p>In order to avoid the interruption of fishing activities and to ensure the livelihood of Union fishermen, this Regulation should apply from 1 January 2021. For reasons of urgency, this Regulation should enter into force immediately after its publication.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d13e298">
               <num>(23)</num>
               <p>Fishing opportunities should be used in full compliance with Union law,</p>
            </recital>
         </recitals>
         <formula name="enactingFormula">
            <p>HAS ADOPTED THIS REGULATION:</p>
         </formula>
      </preamble>
      <body>
         <title>
            <num>TITLE I</num>
            <heading>GENERAL PROVISIONS</heading>
            <article xml:id="art_d13e316">
               <num>Article 1</num>
               <heading>Subject matter</heading>
               <paragraph>
                  <content>
                     <p>This Regulation fixes for 2021 the fishing opportunities applicable in the Mediterranean and Black Seas for certain fish stocks and groups of fish stocks.</p>
                  </content>
               </paragraph>
            </article>
            <article xml:id="art_d13e323">
               <num>Article 2</num>
               <heading>Scope</heading>
               <paragraph>
                  <num>1.</num>
                  <subparagraph>
                     <content>
                        <p>This Regulation applies to Union fishing vessels exploiting the following fish stocks:</p>
                     </content>
                  </subparagraph>
                  <list>
                     <point>
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <content>
                           <p>European eel (<i>Anguilla anguilla</i>), red coral (<i>Corallium rubrum</i>) and common dolphinfish (<i>Coryphaena hippurus</i>) in the Mediterranean Sea, as defined in point (b) of Article 4;</p>
                        </content>
                     </point>
                     <point>
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <content>
                           <p>blue and red shrimp (<i>Aristeus antennatus</i>), deep-water rose shrimp (<i>Parapenaeus longirostris</i>), giant red shrimp (<i>Aristaeomorpha foliacea</i>), European hake (<i>Merluccius merluccius</i>), Norway lobster (<i>Nephrops norvegicus</i>) and red mullet (<i>Mullus barbatus</i>) in the western Mediterranean Sea, as defined in point (c) of Article 4;</p>
                        </content>
                     </point>
                     <point>
                        <num>(c)</num>
                        <content>
                           <p>anchovy (<i>Engraulis encrasicolus</i>) and sardine (<i>Sardina pilchardus</i>) in the Adriatic Sea, as defined in point (d) of Article 4;</p>
                        </content>
                     </point>
                     <point>
                        <num>(d)</num>
                        <content>
                           <p>european hake (<i>Merluccius merluccius</i>), Norway lobster (<i>Nephrops norvegicus</i>), common sole (<i>Solea solea)</i>, deep-water rose shrimp (<i>Parapenaeus longirostris</i>), red mullet (<i>Mullus barbatus</i>) in the Adriatic Sea, as defined in point (d) of Article 4;</p>
                        </content>
                     </point>
                     <point>
                        <num>(e)</num>
                        <content>
                           <p>giant red shrimp (<i>Aristaeomorpha foliacea</i>) and blue and red shrimp (<i>Aristeus antennatus</i>) in the Strait of Sicily as defined in point (e) of Article 4, in the Ionian Sea as defined in point (f) of Article 4 and in the Levant Sea as defined in point (g) of Article 4;</p>
                        </content>
                     </point>
                     <point>
                        <num>(f)</num>
                        <content>
                           <p>blackspot seabream (<i>Pagellus bogaraveo</i>) in the Alborean Sea, as defined in point (h) of Article 4;</p>
                        </content>
                     </point>
                     <point>
                        <num>(g)</num>
                        <content>
                           <p>sprat (<i>Sprattus sprattus</i>) and turbot (<i>Scophthalmus maximus</i>) in the Black Sea, as defined in point (i) of Article 4.</p>
                        </content>
                     </point>
                  </list>
               </paragraph>
               <paragraph>
                  <num>2.</num>
                  <content>
                     <p>This Regulation also applies to recreational fisheries where they are expressly referred to in the relevant provisions.</p>
                  </content>
               </paragraph>
            </article>
            <article xml:id="art_d13e446">
               <num>Article 3</num>
               <heading>Definitions</heading>
               <paragraph>
                  <subparagraph>
                     <content>
                        <p>For the purposes of this Regulation, the definitions laid down in Article 4 of Regulation (EU) No 1380/2013 apply. In addition, the following definitions apply:</p>
                     </content>
                  </subparagraph>
                  <list>
                     <point>
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <content>
                           <p>&apos;international waters&apos; means waters falling outside the sovereignty or jurisdiction of any State;</p>
                        </content>
                     </point>
                     <point>
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <content>
                           <p>&apos;recreational fisheries&apos; means non-commercial fishing activities exploiting marine living aquatic resources for recreation, tourism or sport;</p>
                        </content>
                     </point>
                     <point>
                        <num>(c)</num>
                        <alinea>
                           <content>
                              <p>&apos;total allowable catch&apos; (TAC) means:</p>
                           </content>
                        </alinea>
                        <list>
                           <point>
                              <num>(i)</num>
                              <content>
                                 <p>in fisheries subject to the exemption of the landing obligation referred to in Article 15(4) to (7) of Regulation (EU) No 1380/2013, the quantity of fish that can be landed from each stock each year;</p>
                              </content>
                           </point>
                           <point>
                              <num>(ii)</num>
                              <content>
                                 <p>in all other fisheries, the quantity of fish that can be caught from each stock over the period of a year;</p>
                              </content>
                           </point>
                        </list>
                     </point>
                     <point>
                        <num>(d)</num>
                        <content>
                           <p>&apos;quota&apos; means a proportion of the TAC allocated to the Union or a Member State;</p>
                        </content>
                     </point>
                     <point>
                        <num>(e)</num>
                        <content>
                           <p>&apos;Union autonomous quota&apos; means a catch limit autonomously allocated to Union fishing vessels in the absence of an agreed TAC;</p>
                        </content>
                     </point>
                     <point>
                        <num>(f)</num>
                        <content>
                           <p>&apos;analytical quota&apos; means a Union autonomous quota for which an analytical assessment is available;</p>
                        </content>
                     </point>
                     <point>
                        <num>(g)</num>
                        <content>
                           <p>&apos;analytical assessment&apos; means a quantitative evaluation of trends in a given stock, based on data about the stock&apos;s biology and exploitation, which scientific review has indicated to be of sufficient quality to provide scientific advice on options for future catches;</p>
                        </content>
                     </point>
                     <point>
                        <num>(h)</num>
                        <content>
                           <p>&apos;fish aggregating device&apos; means any anchored equipment floating on the sea surface with the objective of attracting fish.</p>
                        </content>
                     </point>
                  </list>
               </paragraph>
            </article>
            <article xml:id="art_d13e542">
               <num>Article 4</num>
               <heading>Fishing zones</heading>
               <paragraph>
                  <subparagraph>
                     <content>
                        <p>For the purposes of this Regulation, the following zone definitions apply:</p>
                     </content>
                  </subparagraph>
                  <list>
                     <point>
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <content>
                           <p>&apos;GFCM geographical subareas&apos; mean the areas defined in Annex I to Regulation (EU) No 1343/2011 of the European Parliament and of the Council<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="7">
                                 <p>Regulation (EU) No 1343/2011 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 13 December 2011 on certain provisions for fishing in the GFCM (General Fisheries Commission for the Mediterranean) Agreement area and amending Council Regulation (EC) No 1967/2006 concerning management measures for the sustainable exploitation of fishery resources in the Mediterranean Sea (OJ L 347, 30.12.2011, p. 44).</p>
                              </authorialNote>;</p>
                        </content>
                     </point>
                     <point>
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <content>
                           <p>&apos;Mediterranean Sea&apos; means the waters in GFCM geographical subareas 1 to 27, as defined in Annex I to Regulation (EU) No 1343/2011;</p>
                        </content>
                     </point>
                     <point>
                        <num>(c)</num>
                        <content>
                           <p>&apos;western Mediterranean Sea&apos; means the waters in GFCM geographical subareas 1, 2, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10 and 11, as defined in Annex I to Regulation (EU) No 1343/2011;</p>
                        </content>
                     </point>
                     <point>
                        <num>(d)</num>
                        <content>
                           <p>&apos;Adriatic Sea&apos; means the waters in GFCM geographical subareas 17 and 18, as defined in Annex I to Regulation (EU) No 1343/2011;</p>
                        </content>
                     </point>
                     <point>
                        <num>(e)</num>
                        <content>
                           <p>&apos;Strait of Sicily&apos; means the waters in GFCM geographical subareas 12, 13, 14, 15 and 16, as defined in Annex I to Regulation (EU) No 1343/2011;</p>
                        </content>
                     </point>
                     <point>
                        <num>(f)</num>
                        <content>
                           <p>&apos;Ionian Sea&apos; means the waters in GFCM geographical subareas 19, 20 and 21, as defined in Annex I to Regulation (EU) No 1343/2011;</p>
                        </content>
                     </point>
                     <point>
                        <num>(g)</num>
                        <content>
                           <p>&apos;Levant Sea&apos; means the waters in GFCM geographical subareas 24, 25, 26 and 27, as defined in Annex I to Regulation (EU) No 1343/2011;</p>
                        </content>
                     </point>
                     <point>
                        <num>(h)</num>
                        <content>
                           <p>&apos;Alboran Sea&apos; means the waters in GFCM geographical subareas 1 to 3, as defined in Annex I to Regulation (EU) No 1343/2011;</p>
                        </content>
                     </point>
                     <point>
                        <num>(i)</num>
                        <content>
                           <p>&apos;Black Sea&apos; means the waters in GFCM geographical subarea 29, as defined in Annex I to Regulation (EU) No 1343/2011.</p>
                        </content>
                     </point>
                  </list>
               </paragraph>
            </article>
         </title>
         <title>
            <num>TITLE II</num>
            <heading>FISHING OPPORTUNITIES</heading>
            <chapter>
               <num>CHAPTER I</num>
               <heading>Mediterranean Sea</heading>
               <article xml:id="art_d13e663">
                  <num>Article 5</num>
                  <heading>European eel</heading>
                  <paragraph>
                     <num>1.</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>This Article applies to all activities by Union fishing vessels and other Union fishing activities catching European eel (<i>Anguilla anguilla</i>), namely targeted, incidental and recreational fisheries, in all marine waters of the Mediterranean Sea, including freshwaters and transitional brackish waters, such as lagoons and estuaries.</p>
                     </content>
                  </paragraph>
                  <paragraph>
                     <num>2.</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>It shall be prohibited for Union fishing vessels to fish for European eel in Union and international waters of the Mediterranean Sea for a consecutive three-month period to be determined by each Member State. The fishing closure period shall be consistent with the conservation objectives set out in Regulation (EC) No 1100/2007, with national management plans and with the temporal migration patterns of European eel in the Member States concerned. Member States shall communicate the period determined to the Commission no later than one month prior to the entry into force of the closure and in any case no later than 31 January 2021.</p>
                     </content>
                  </paragraph>
                  <paragraph>
                     <num>3.</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>Member States shall not exceed the maximum level of catches or fishing effort of European eel established and implemented by means of their national management plans, adopted in accordance with Articles 2 and 4 of Regulation 1100/2007.</p>
                     </content>
                  </paragraph>
               </article>
               <article xml:id="art_d13e689">
                  <num>Article 6</num>
                  <heading>Red coral</heading>
                  <paragraph>
                     <num>1.</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>This Article applies to all activities by Union fishing vessels and other Union fishing activities harvesting red coral (<i>Corallium rubrum</i>), namely targeted and recreational fisheries in the Mediterranean Sea.</p>
                     </content>
                  </paragraph>
                  <paragraph>
                     <num>2.</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>For targeted fisheries, the maximum number of fishing authorisations and the maximum quantities of red coral stocks harvested by Union fishing vessels and Union harvesting activities shall not exceed the levels set out in Annex I.</p>
                     </content>
                  </paragraph>
                  <paragraph>
                     <num>3.</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>It shall be prohibited for Union fishing vessels subject to paragraph 2 to tranship red coral at sea.</p>
                     </content>
                  </paragraph>
                  <paragraph>
                     <num>4.</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>For recreational fisheries, Member States shall take the necessary measures to prohibit the catch and retention on board, transhipment or landing of red coral.</p>
                     </content>
                  </paragraph>
               </article>
               <article xml:id="art_d13e717">
                  <num>Article 7</num>
                  <heading>Common dolphinfish</heading>
                  <paragraph>
                     <num>1.</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>This Article applies to all commercial activities by Union fishing vessels and other Union fishing activities using fish aggregating devices for catching common dolphinfish (<i>Coryphaena hippurus</i>), in the international waters of the Mediterranean Sea.</p>
                     </content>
                  </paragraph>
                  <paragraph>
                     <num>2.</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>The maximum number of Union fishing vessels authorised to fish for common dolphinfish is set out in Annex II.</p>
                     </content>
                  </paragraph>
               </article>
            </chapter>
            <chapter>
               <num>CHAPTER II</num>
               <heading>Western Mediterranean Sea</heading>
               <article xml:id="art_d13e747">
                  <num>Article 8</num>
                  <heading>Demersal stocks</heading>
                  <paragraph>
                     <num>1.</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>This Article applies to all activities by Union fishing vessels and other Union fishing activities catching demersal stocks referred to in Article 1(2) of Regulation (EU) 2019/1022, in the western Mediterranean Sea.</p>
                     </content>
                  </paragraph>
                  <paragraph>
                     <num>2.</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>The maximum allowable fishing effort is set out in Annex III to this Regulation. Member States shall manage the maximum allowable fishing effort in accordance with Article 9 of Regulation (EU) 2019/1022.</p>
                     </content>
                  </paragraph>
               </article>
               <article xml:id="art_d13e762">
                  <num>Article 9</num>
                  <heading>Data transmission</heading>
                  <paragraph>
                     <content>
                        <p>Member States shall record and transmit the fishing effort data to the Commission in accordance with Article 10 of Regulation (EU) 2019/1022.</p>
                     </content>
                  </paragraph>
                  <paragraph>
                     <content>
                        <p>When submitting fishing effort data to the Commission in accordance with this Article, Member States shall use the fishing effort group codes set out in Annex III.</p>
                     </content>
                  </paragraph>
               </article>
            </chapter>
            <chapter>
               <num>CHAPTER III</num>
               <heading>Adriatic Sea</heading>
               <article xml:id="art_d13e782">
                  <num>Article 10</num>
                  <heading>Small pelagic stocks</heading>
                  <paragraph>
                     <num>1.</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>This Article applies to all activities by Union fishing vessels and other Union fishing activities catching sardine (<i>Sardina pilchardus</i>) and anchovy (<i>Engraulis encrasicolus</i>) in the Adriatic Sea.</p>
                     </content>
                  </paragraph>
                  <paragraph>
                     <num>2.</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>The maximum level of catches shall not exceed the levels set out in Annex IV.</p>
                     </content>
                  </paragraph>
                  <paragraph>
                     <num>3.</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>Union fishing vessels targeting sardine and anchovy in the Adriatic Sea shall not exceed 180 fishing days per year. Within that total of 180 fishing days, a maximum of 144 fishing days targeting sardine and a maximum of 144 fishing days targeting anchovy applies.</p>
                     </content>
                  </paragraph>
                  <paragraph>
                     <num>4.</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>The maximum number of Union fishing vessels authorised to fish small pelagics is set out in Annex IV.</p>
                     </content>
                  </paragraph>
               </article>
               <article xml:id="art_d13e813">
                  <num>Article 11</num>
                  <heading>Demersal stocks</heading>
                  <paragraph>
                     <num>1.</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>This Article applies to all activities by Union fishing vessels and other Union fishing activities catching European hake (<i>Merluccius merluccius</i>), Norway lobster (<i>Nephrops norvegicus</i>), Common sole (<i>Solea solea</i>), Deep-water rose shrimp (<i>Parapenaeus longirostris</i>) and Red mullet (<i>Mullus barbatus</i>) in the Adriatic Sea.</p>
                     </content>
                  </paragraph>
                  <paragraph>
                     <num>2.</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>The maximum allowable fishing effort and the maximum fleet capacity for demersal stocks within the scope of this Article are set out in Annex IV.</p>
                     </content>
                  </paragraph>
                  <paragraph>
                     <num>3.</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>Member States shall manage the maximum allowable effort in accordance with Articles 26 to 35 of Regulation (EC) No 1224/2009.</p>
                     </content>
                  </paragraph>
               </article>
               <article xml:id="art_d13e849">
                  <num>Article 12</num>
                  <heading>Data transmission</heading>
                  <paragraph>
                     <content>
                        <p>When, pursuant to Articles 33 and 34 of Regulation (EC) No 1224/2009, Member States submit to the Commission data relating to landings of quantities of stocks caught, they shall use the stock codes set out in Annex IV.</p>
                     </content>
                  </paragraph>
               </article>
            </chapter>
            <chapter>
               <num>CHAPTER IV</num>
               <heading>Ionian Sea, Levant Sea and the Strait of Sicily</heading>
               <article xml:id="art_d13e867">
                  <num>Article 13</num>
                  <heading/>
                  <paragraph>
                     <num>1.</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>This Article applies to all activities by Union fishing vessels and other Union fishing activities catching giant red shrimp (<i>Aristaeomorpha foliacea</i>) and blue and red shrimp (<i>Aristeus antennatus</i>), in the Ionian Sea, Levant Sea and the Strait of Sicily.</p>
                     </content>
                  </paragraph>
                  <paragraph>
                     <num>2.</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>The maximum number of bottom trawl vessels authorised to fish for demersal stocks is set out in Annex V.</p>
                     </content>
                  </paragraph>
               </article>
            </chapter>
            <chapter>
               <num>CHAPTER V</num>
               <heading>Alboran Sea</heading>
               <article xml:id="art_d13e897">
                  <num>Article 14</num>
                  <heading/>
                  <paragraph>
                     <num>1.</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>This Article applies to commercial fishing with longlines and handlines by Union fishing vessels catching blackspot seabream (<i>Pagellus bogaraveo</i>) in the Alboran Sea.</p>
                     </content>
                  </paragraph>
                  <paragraph>
                     <num>2.</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>The maximum level of catches shall not exceed the levels set out in Annex VI.</p>
                     </content>
                  </paragraph>
               </article>
            </chapter>
            <chapter>
               <num>CHAPTER VI</num>
               <heading>Black Sea</heading>
               <article xml:id="art_d13e924">
                  <num>Article 15</num>
                  <heading>Allocation of fishing opportunities for sprat</heading>
                  <paragraph>
                     <num>1.</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>This Article applies to all activities by Union fishing vessels and other Union fishing activities catching sprat (<i>Sprattus sprattus</i>) in the Black Sea.</p>
                     </content>
                  </paragraph>
                  <paragraph>
                     <num>2.</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>The Union autonomous quota for sprat, the allocation of such quota among Member States and the conditions functionally linked thereto, where appropriate, are set out in Annex VII.</p>
                     </content>
                  </paragraph>
               </article>
               <article xml:id="art_d13e942">
                  <num>Article 16</num>
                  <heading>Allocation of fishing opportunities for turbot</heading>
                  <paragraph>
                     <num>1.</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>This Article applies to all activities by Union fishing vessels and other Union fishing activities catching turbot (<i>Scophthalmus maximus</i>) in the Black Sea.</p>
                     </content>
                  </paragraph>
                  <paragraph>
                     <num>2.</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>The TAC for turbot applicable in Union waters in the Black Sea and the allocation of such TAC among Member States and the conditions functionally linked thereto, where appropriate, are set out in Annex VII.</p>
                     </content>
                  </paragraph>
               </article>
               <article xml:id="art_d13e961">
                  <num>Article 17</num>
                  <heading>Management of fishing effort for turbot</heading>
                  <paragraph>
                     <content>
                        <p>Union fishing vessels authorised to fish for turbot within the scope of Article 16, irrespective of the vessels&apos; overall length, shall not exceed 180 fishing days per year.</p>
                     </content>
                  </paragraph>
               </article>
               <article xml:id="art_d13e968">
                  <num>Article 18</num>
                  <heading>Closure period for turbot</heading>
                  <paragraph>
                     <content>
                        <p>It shall be prohibited for Union fishing vessels to carry out any fishing activity, including transhipment, retaining on board, landing and first sale of turbot in Union waters in the Black Sea from 15 April to 15 June.</p>
                     </content>
                  </paragraph>
               </article>
               <article xml:id="art_d13e975">
                  <num>Article 19</num>
                  <heading>Special provisions on allocations of fishing opportunities in the Black Sea</heading>
                  <paragraph>
                     <num>1.</num>
                     <subparagraph>
                        <content>
                           <p>The allocation of fishing opportunities among Member States as set out in Articles 15 and 16 of this Regulation shall be without prejudice to:</p>
                        </content>
                     </subparagraph>
                     <list>
                        <point>
                           <num>(a)</num>
                           <content>
                              <p>exchanges made pursuant to Article 16(8) of Regulation (EU) No 1380/2013;</p>
                           </content>
                        </point>
                        <point>
                           <num>(b)</num>
                           <content>
                              <p>deductions and reallocations made pursuant to Article 37 of Regulation (EC) No 1224/2009; and</p>
                           </content>
                        </point>
                        <point>
                           <num>(c)</num>
                           <content>
                              <p>deductions made pursuant to Articles 105 and 107 of Regulation (EC) No 1224/2009.</p>
                           </content>
                        </point>
                     </list>
                  </paragraph>
                  <paragraph>
                     <num>2.</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>Articles 3 and 4 of Regulation (EC) No 847/96 shall not apply where a Member State uses the year-to-year flexibility provided for in Article 15(9) of Regulation (EU) No 1380/2013.</p>
                     </content>
                  </paragraph>
               </article>
               <article xml:id="art_d13e1010">
                  <num>Article 20</num>
                  <heading>Data transmission</heading>
                  <paragraph>
                     <content>
                        <p>When, pursuant to Articles 33 and 34 of Regulation (EC) No 1224/2009, Member States submit to the Commission data relating to landings of quantities of stocks of sprat and turbot caught in Union waters in the Black Sea, they shall use the stock codes set out in Annex VII.</p>
                     </content>
                  </paragraph>
               </article>
            </chapter>
         </title>
         <title>
            <num>TITLE III</num>
            <heading>FINAL PROVISIONS</heading>
            <article xml:id="art_d13e1026">
               <num>Article 21</num>
               <heading>Entry into force</heading>
               <paragraph>
                  <content>
                     <p>This Regulation shall enter into force on the day following that of its publication in the <i>Official Journal of the European Union</i>.</p>
                  </content>
               </paragraph>
               <paragraph>
                  <content>
                     <p>It shall apply from 1 January 2021.</p>
                  </content>
               </paragraph>
            </article>
         </title>
         <clause>
            <content>
               <p>This Regulation shall be binding in its entirety and directly applicable in all Member States.</p>
            </content>
         </clause>
      </body>
      <conclusions>
         <p>Done at Brussels, 28 January 2021.</p>
         <block name="signatory">
            <signature>
               <organization refersTo="">For the Council</organization>
               <role refersTo="">The President</role>
               <person refersTo="">A. P. ZACARIAS</person>
            </signature>
         </block>
      </conclusions>
   </bill>
</akomaNtoso>
