<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0"
            xmlns:fmx="http://formex.publications.europa.eu/schema/formex-05.21-20110601.xd"
            xmlns:leos="urn:eu:europa:ec:leos"
            xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema">
   <bill name="">
      <meta xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions">
         <identification source="~COM">
            <FRBRWork>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRcountry value=""/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
         </identification>
      </meta>
      <preface>
         <longTitle>
            <p>
               <docStage/>
               <docType>COUNCIL REGULATION (EU) 2020/271</docType>of 20 February 2020<docPurpose>on the allocation of the fishing opportunities under the Protocol on the implementation of the Sustainable Fisheries Partnership Agreement between the European Union and the Republic of Seychelles (2020-2026)</docPurpose>
            </p>
         </longTitle>
      </preface>
      <preamble>
         <formula name="actingEntity">
            <p>THE COUNCIL OF THE EUROPEAN UNION,</p>
         </formula>
         <citations>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union, and in particular Article 43(3) thereof,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the proposal from the European Commission,</p>
            </citation>
         </citations>
         <recitals xml:id="recs_d64e59">
            <intro>
               <p>Whereas:</p>
            </intro>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d64e62">
               <num>(1)</num>
               <p>On 15 July 2019, the Council authorised the Commission to open negotiations with the Republic of Seychelles (&apos;Seychelles&apos;) with a view to concluding a new Sustainable Fisheries Partnership Agreement between the European Union and the Republic of Seychelles (&apos;the Partnership Agreement&apos;) and a new implementing protocol thereto (&apos;the Protocol&apos;).</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d64e84">
               <num>(2)</num>
               <p>The negotiations were successfully concluded by the initialling of the Partnership Agreement and the Protocol on 22 October 2019.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d64e93">
               <num>(3)</num>
               <p>The Partnership Agreement repeals the Fisheries Partnership Agreement between the European Community and the Republic of Seychelles<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="1">
                     <p>OJ L 290, 20.10.2006, p. 2.</p>
                  </authorialNote>, which entered into force on 2 November 2007 for a duration of six years and has been tacitly renewed and is therefore still in force.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d64e108">
               <num>(4)</num>
               <p>The most recent protocol implementing the Fisheries Partnership Agreement between the European Community and the Republic of Seychelles<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="2">
                     <p>Protocol setting out the fishing opportunities and the financial contribution provided for by the Fisheries Partnership Agreement between the European Union and the Republic of Seychelles (OJ L 4, 9.1.2014, p. 3).</p>
                  </authorialNote> was signed on 18 December 2013 and was provisionally applied from 18 January 2014. It expired on 17 January 2020.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d64e130">
               <num>(5)</num>
               <p>In accordance with Council Decision (EU) 2020/272<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="3">
                     <p>Council Decision (EU) 2020/272 of 20 February 2020 on the signing, on behalf of the European Union, and provisional application of the Sustainable Fisheries Partnership Agreement between the European Union and the Republic of Seychelles and its implementing protocol (2020‐2026) (See page 3 of this Official Journal).</p>
                  </authorialNote>, the Partnership Agreement and the Protocol were signed on 24 February 2020, subject to their conclusion at a later date.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d64e146">
               <num>(6)</num>
               <p>The fishing opportunities provided for in the Protocol should be allocated among the Member States for the entire period of application of the Protocol.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d64e152">
               <num>(7)</num>
               <p>The Partnership Agreement and the Protocol should enter into force as soon as possible in view of the economic importance of the Union fishing activities in the Seychelles fishing zone and the need to reduce the interruption of such activities as much as possible.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d64e158">
               <num>(8)</num>
               <p>The Protocol will apply on a provisional basis as from the signature thereof in order to allow for the continuation of fishing activities of Union vessels. This Regulation should therefore apply from the same date,</p>
            </recital>
         </recitals>
         <formula name="enactingFormula">
            <p>HAS ADOPTED THIS REGULATION:</p>
         </formula>
      </preamble>
      <body>
         <article xml:id="art_d64e168">
            <num>Article 1</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <subparagraph>
                  <content>
                     <p>The fishing opportunities established under the Protocol on the implementation of the Sustainable Fisheries Partnership Agreement between the European Union and Republic of Seychelles (2020‐2026) (&apos;the Protocol&apos;) shall be allocated among the Member States as follows:</p>
                  </content>
               </subparagraph>
               <list>
                  <point>
                     <num>(a)</num>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>tuna purse seine vessels:</p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <table class="TBL">
                              <tr>
                                 <td>
                                    <p>Spain:</p>
                                 </td>
                                 <td>
                                    <p>22</p>
                                 </td>
                                 <td>
                                    <p>vessels</p>
                                 </td>
                              </tr>
                              <tr>
                                 <td>
                                    <p>France:</p>
                                 </td>
                                 <td>
                                    <p>16</p>
                                 </td>
                                 <td>
                                    <p>vessels</p>
                                 </td>
                              </tr>
                              <tr>
                                 <td>
                                    <p>Italy:</p>
                                 </td>
                                 <td>
                                    <p>2</p>
                                 </td>
                                 <td>
                                    <p>vessels</p>
                                 </td>
                              </tr>
                           </table>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                  </point>
                  <point>
                     <num>(b)</num>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>surface longliners:</p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <table class="TBL">
                              <tr>
                                 <td>
                                    <p>Spain:</p>
                                 </td>
                                 <td>
                                    <p>2</p>
                                 </td>
                                 <td>
                                    <p>vessels</p>
                                 </td>
                              </tr>
                              <tr>
                                 <td>
                                    <p>France:</p>
                                 </td>
                                 <td>
                                    <p>4</p>
                                 </td>
                                 <td>
                                    <p>vessels</p>
                                 </td>
                              </tr>
                              <tr>
                                 <td>
                                    <p>Portugal:</p>
                                 </td>
                                 <td>
                                    <p>2</p>
                                 </td>
                                 <td>
                                    <p>vessels</p>
                                 </td>
                              </tr>
                           </table>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                  </point>
               </list>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <article xml:id="art_d64e239">
            <num>Article 2</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>This Regulation shall enter into force on the day following that of its publication in the <i>Official Journal of the European Union</i>.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>It shall apply from 24 February 2020.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <clause>
            <content>
               <p>This Regulation shall be binding in its entirety and directly applicable in all Member States.</p>
            </content>
         </clause>
      </body>
      <conclusions>
         <p>Done at Brussels, 20 February 2020.</p>
         <block name="signatory">
            <signature>
               <organization refersTo="">For the Council</organization>
               <role refersTo="">The President</role>
               <person refersTo="">B. DIVJAK</person>
            </signature>
         </block>
      </conclusions>
   </bill>
</akomaNtoso>
