<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0"
            xmlns:fmx="http://formex.publications.europa.eu/schema/formex-05.21-20110601.xd"
            xmlns:leos="urn:eu:europa:ec:leos"
            xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema">
   <bill name="">
      <meta xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions">
         <identification source="~COM">
            <FRBRWork>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRcountry value=""/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
         </identification>
      </meta>
      <preface>
         <longTitle>
            <p>
               <docStage/>
               <docType>COMMISSION REGULATION (EU) 2016/583</docType>of 15 April 2016<docPurpose>amending Regulation (EU) No 1332/2011 laying down common airspace usage requirements and operating procedures for airborne collision avoidance</docPurpose>
            </p>
         </longTitle>
         <container name="EEArelevance">
            <p>(Text with EEA relevance)</p>
         </container>
      </preface>
      <preamble>
         <formula name="actingEntity">
            <p>THE EUROPEAN COMMISSION,</p>
         </formula>
         <citations>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to Regulation (EC) No 216/2008 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 20 February 2008 on common rules in the field of civil aviation and establishing a European Aviation Safety Agency, and repealing Council Directive 91/670/EEC, Regulation (EC) No 1592/2002 and Directive 2004/36/EC<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="1">
                     <p>OJ L 79, 19.3.2008, p. 1.</p>
                  </authorialNote>, and in particular Article 8(5) and 9(4) thereof,</p>
            </citation>
         </citations>
         <recitals xml:id="recs_d195e71">
            <intro>
               <p>Whereas:</p>
            </intro>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d195e74">
               <num>(1)</num>
               <p>Commission Regulation (EU) No 1332/2011<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="2">
                     <p>Commission Regulation (EU) No 1332/2011 of 16 December 2011 laying down common airspace usage requirements and operating procedures for airborne collision avoidance (OJ L 336, 20.12.2011, p. 20).</p>
                  </authorialNote> requires turbine-powered aeroplanes, with a maximum certificated take-off mass (MCTOM) of more than 5700 kg or authorised to carry more than 19 passengers to be equipped with a new software version 7.1 of the airborne collision avoidance system (ACAS II) to avoid mid-air collision. This requirement also applies to operators of certain aeroplanes registered in a third country.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d195e93">
               <num>(2)</num>
               <p>Regulation (EU) No 1332/2011 also requires Union air operators who are subject to Council Regulation (EEC) No 3922/91<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="3">
                     <p>Council Regulation (EEC) No 3922/91 of 16 December 1991 on the harmonization of technical requirements and administrative procedures in the field of civil aviation (OJ L 373, 31.12.1991, p. 4).</p>
                  </authorialNote> to install the new software version 7.1 of ACAS II on their aeroplanes. However, this provision is obsolete as Regulation (EEC) No 3922/91 no longer applies to those operators since its Annex III has been deleted. Commission Regulation (EU) No 965/2012<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="4">
                     <p>Commission Regulation (EU) No 965/2012 of 5 October 2012 laying down technical requirements and administrative procedures related to air operations pursuant to Regulation (EC) No 216/2008 of the European Parliament and of the Council (OJ L 296, 25.10.2012, p. 1).</p>
                  </authorialNote> now applies to those operators instead and contains the necessary rules in this regard. The obsolete provision of Regulation (EU) No 1332/2011 should therefore be deleted.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d195e119">
               <num>(3)</num>
               <p>Regulation (EU) No 1332/2011 contains rules on operational procedures applicable in situations where ACAS II gives indication to the flight crew recommending a manoeuvre to ensure separation of the aeroplane from all threats or to maintain existing separation (resolution advisory). As those rules are safety-critical both for pilots and controllers, especially as regards the interface between them, they are better addressed in Commission Implementing Regulation (EU) No 923/2012<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="5">
                     <p>Commission Implementing Regulation (EU) No 923/2012 of 26 September 2012 laying down the common rules of the air and operational provisions regarding services and procedures in air navigation and amending Implementing Regulation (EU) No 1035/2011 and Regulations (EC) No 1265/2007, (EC) No 1794/2006, (EC) No 730/2006, (EC) No 1033/2006 and (EU) No 255/2010 (OJ L 281, 13.10.2012, p. 1).</p>
                  </authorialNote> instead. Therefore, the rules related to such operational procedures set out in Regulation (EU) No 1332/2011 should be deleted.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d195e135">
               <num>(4)</num>
               <p>Regulation (EU) No 1332/2011 should therefore be amended accordingly.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d195e141">
               <num>(5)</num>
               <p>The measures provided for in this Regulation are based on the opinion<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="6">
                     <p>European Aviation Safety Agency Opinion No 04/2014 of 16 December 2014 for the amendment to Commission Implementing Regulation (EU) No 923/2012 laying down the common rules of the air and operational provisions regarding services and procedures in air navigation (SERA Part C)</p>
                  </authorialNote> issued by the European Aviation Safety Agency in accordance with Articles 17(2)(b) and 19(1) of Regulation (EC) No 216/2008.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d195e154">
               <num>(6)</num>
               <p>The measures provided for in this Regulation are in accordance with the opinion of the Committee established by Article 65 of Regulation (EC) No 216/2008,</p>
            </recital>
         </recitals>
         <formula name="enactingFormula">
            <p>HAS ADOPTED THIS REGULATION:</p>
         </formula>
      </preamble>
      <body>
         <article xml:id="art_d195e164" leos:compliant="false">
            <num>Article 1</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <subparagraph>
                  <content>
                     <p>Regulation (EU) No 1332/2011 is amended as follows:</p>
                  </content>
               </subparagraph>
               <list>
                  <point>
                     <num>(1)</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>Article 4 is deleted;</p>
                     </content>
                  </point>
                  <point>
                     <num>(2)</num>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>in Article 5, paragraphs 2 and 3 are replaced by the following:</p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>
                              <mod>
                                 <quotedStructure startQuote="" endQuote="">
                                    <paragraph>
                                       <num>&apos;2.</num>
                                       <content>
                                          <p>Article 3 shall apply as of 1 March 2012.</p>
                                       </content>
                                    </paragraph>
                                    <paragraph>
                                       <num>3.</num>
                                       <content>
                                          <p>By way of derogation from paragraph 2, in the case of aircraft with an individual certificate of airworthiness issued before 1 March 2012, Article 3 shall apply as of 1 December 2015.&apos;;</p>
                                       </content>
                                    </paragraph>
                                 </quotedStructure>
                              </mod>
                           </p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                  </point>
                  <point>
                     <num>(3)</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>the Annex is replaced by the text in the Annex to this Regulation.</p>
                     </content>
                  </point>
               </list>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <article xml:id="art_d195e213">
            <num>Article 2</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>This Regulation shall enter into force on the twentieth day following that of its publication in the <i>Official Journal of the European Union</i>.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>It shall apply from 25 August 2016.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <clause>
            <content>
               <p>This Regulation shall be binding in its entirety and directly applicable in all Member States.</p>
            </content>
         </clause>
      </body>
      <conclusions>
         <p>Done at Brussels, 15 April 2016.</p>
         <block name="signatory">
            <signature>
               <organization refersTo="">For the Commission</organization>
               <role refersTo="">The President</role>
               <person refersTo="">Jean-Claude JUNCKER</person>
            </signature>
         </block>
      </conclusions>
   </bill>
</akomaNtoso>
