<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0"
            xmlns:fmx="http://formex.publications.europa.eu/schema/formex-05.21-20110601.xd"
            xmlns:leos="urn:eu:europa:ec:leos"
            xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema">
   <bill name="">
      <meta xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions">
         <identification source="~COM">
            <FRBRWork>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRcountry value=""/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
         </identification>
      </meta>
      <preface>
         <longTitle>
            <p>
               <docStage/>
               <docType>COMMISSION REGULATION (EU) 2019/698</docType>of 30 April 2019<docPurpose>amending Annexes III and V to Regulation (EC) No 1223/2009 of the European Parliament and of the Council on cosmetic products</docPurpose>
            </p>
         </longTitle>
         <container name="EEArelevance">
            <p>(Text with EEA relevance)</p>
         </container>
      </preface>
      <preamble>
         <formula name="actingEntity">
            <p>THE EUROPEAN COMMISSION,</p>
         </formula>
         <citations>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to Regulation (EC) No 1223/2009 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 30 November 2009 on cosmetic products<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="1">
                     <p>OJ L 342, 22.12.2009, p. 59.</p>
                  </authorialNote>, and in particular Article 31(1) thereof,</p>
            </citation>
         </citations>
         <recitals xml:id="recs_d214e71">
            <intro>
               <p>Whereas:</p>
            </intro>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d214e74">
               <num>(1)</num>
               <p>The substance 1-(4-Chlorophenoxy)-1-(imidazol-1-yl)-3,3-dimethylbutan-2-one, which has been assigned the name Climbazole under the International Nomenclature of Cosmetic Ingredients (INCI), is currently allowed as a preservative in cosmetic products at a maximum concentration of 0,5 % in ready for use preparation. It is listed in entry 32 of Annex V to Regulation (EC) No 1223/2009. In accordance with Article 14(1)(d)(ii) of Regulation (EC) No 1223/2009, Climbazole may also be contained in cosmetic products for an intended use other than as preservative, only within the concentration limit laid down in entry 32 of Annex V.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d214e80">
               <num>(2)</num>
               <p>The Scientific Committee on Consumer Safety (SCCS) concluded at its plenary meeting on 21-22 June 2018, in an addendum to its earlier opinions on Climbazole<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="2">
                     <p>Addendum to the scientific Opinions on climbazole (P64) ref. SCCS/1506/13 and SCCS/1590/17, final version adopted on 21-22 June 2018, SCCS/1600/18.</p>
                  </authorialNote>, that, under an aggregate exposure scenario, Climbazole is safe when used as a preservative in face cream, hair lotion and foot care products at a maximum concentration of 0,2 % and when used as a preservative in rinse-off shampoo at a maximum concentration of 0,5 %.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d214e102">
               <num>(3)</num>
               <p>The SCCS also concluded that, under an aggregate exposure scenario, Climbazole is safe when used as an anti-dandruff agent in rinse-off shampoo at a maximum concentration of 2 %.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d214e108">
               <num>(4)</num>
               <p>In light of the addendum, there is a potential risk to human health arising from the use of Climbazole as a preservative or as a non-preservative at the currently allowed maximum concentration of 0,5 % in all cosmetic products. The use of Climbazole as a preservative should therefore only be allowed in face cream, hair lotion, foot care products and rinse-off shampoo. The maximum concentration should be 0,2 % for face cream, hair lotion and foot care products and 0,5 % for rinse-off shampoo.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d214e114">
               <num>(5)</num>
               <p>The use of Climbazole as a non-preservative should be restricted to rinse-off shampoo, when the substance is used as an anti-dandruff agent. For such use, the maximum concentration should be 2 %.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d214e120">
               <num>(6)</num>
               <p>Regulation (EC) No 1223/2009 should therefore be amended accordingly.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d214e126">
               <num>(7)</num>
               <p>The industry should be allowed a reasonable period of time to adapt to the new requirements by making the necessary adjustments to product formulations to ensure that only products complying with the new requirements are placed on the market. The industry should also be allowed a reasonable period of time to withdraw products which do not comply with the new requirements from the market.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d214e132">
               <num>(8)</num>
               <p>The measures provided for in this Regulation are in accordance with the opinion of the Standing Committee on Cosmetic Products,</p>
            </recital>
         </recitals>
         <formula name="enactingFormula">
            <p>HAS ADOPTED THIS REGULATION:</p>
         </formula>
      </preamble>
      <body>
         <article xml:id="art_d214e141">
            <num>Article 1</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>Annex III to Regulation (EC) No 1223/2009 is amended in accordance with Annex I to this Regulation.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <article xml:id="art_d214e147">
            <num>Article 2</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>In Annex V to Regulation (EC) No 1223/2009, entry 32 is replaced by the text set out in Annex II to this Regulation.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <article xml:id="art_d214e152">
            <num>Article 3</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <num>1.</num>
               <subparagraph>
                  <content>
                     <p>From 27 November 2019 cosmetic products containing 1-(4-Chlorophenoxy)-1-(imidazol-1-yl)-3,3-dimethylbutan-2-one for other than preservation purposes and not complying with the restrictions laid down in this Regulation shall not be placed on the Union market.</p>
                  </content>
               </subparagraph>
               <subparagraph>
                  <content>
                     <p>From 27 February 2020 cosmetic products containing 1-(4-Chlorophenoxy)-1-(imidazol-1-yl)-3,3-dimethylbutan-2-one for other than preservation purposes and not complying with the restrictions laid down in this Regulation shall not be made available on the Union market.</p>
                  </content>
               </subparagraph>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph>
               <num>2.</num>
               <subparagraph>
                  <content>
                     <p>From 27 November 2019 cosmetic products containing 1-(4-Chlorophenoxy)-1-(imidazol-1-yl)-3,3-dimethylbutan-2-one for preservation purposes and not complying with the conditions laid down in this Regulation shall not be placed on the Union market.</p>
                  </content>
               </subparagraph>
               <subparagraph>
                  <content>
                     <p>From 27 February 2020 cosmetic products containing 1-(4-Chlorophenoxy)-1-(imidazol-1-yl)-3,3-dimethylbutan-2-one for preservation purposes and not complying with the conditions laid down in this Regulation shall not be made available on the Union market.</p>
                  </content>
               </subparagraph>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <article xml:id="art_d214e181">
            <num>Article 4</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>This Regulation shall enter into force on the twentieth day following that of its publication in the <i>Official Journal of the European Union</i>.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>Article 2 shall apply from 27 November 2019.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <clause>
            <content>
               <p>This Regulation shall be binding in its entirety and directly applicable in all Member States.</p>
            </content>
         </clause>
      </body>
      <conclusions>
         <p>Done at Brussels, 30 April 2019.</p>
         <block name="signatory">
            <signature>
               <organization refersTo="">For the Commission</organization>
               <role refersTo="">The President</role>
               <person refersTo="">Jean-Claude JUNCKER</person>
            </signature>
         </block>
      </conclusions>
   </bill>
</akomaNtoso>
