<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0"
            xmlns:fmx="http://formex.publications.europa.eu/schema/formex-05.21-20110601.xd"
            xmlns:leos="urn:eu:europa:ec:leos"
            xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema">
   <bill name="">
      <meta xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions">
         <identification source="~COM">
            <FRBRWork>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRcountry value=""/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
         </identification>
      </meta>
      <preface>
         <longTitle>
            <p>
               <docStage/>
               <docType>COMMISSION REGULATION (EU) 2018/290</docType>of 26 February 2018<docPurpose>amending Regulation (EC) No 1881/2006 as regards maximum levels of glycidyl fatty acid esters in vegetable oils and fats, infant formula, follow-on formula and foods for special medical purposes intended for infants and young children</docPurpose>
            </p>
         </longTitle>
         <container name="EEArelevance">
            <p>(Text with EEA relevance)</p>
         </container>
      </preface>
      <preamble>
         <formula name="actingEntity">
            <p>THE EUROPEAN COMMISSION,</p>
         </formula>
         <citations>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to Council Regulation (EEC) No 315/93 of 8 February 1993 laying down Community procedures for contaminants in food<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="1">
                     <p>OJ L 37, 13.2.1993, p. 1.</p>
                  </authorialNote>, and in particular Article 2(3) thereof,</p>
            </citation>
         </citations>
         <recitals xml:id="recs_d57e71">
            <intro>
               <p>Whereas:</p>
            </intro>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d57e74">
               <num>(1)</num>
               <p>Commission Regulation (EC) No 1881/2006<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="2">
                     <p>Commission Regulation (EC) No 1881/2006 of 19 December 2006 setting maximum levels for certain contaminants in foodstuffs (OJ L 364, 20.12.2006, p. 5).</p>
                  </authorialNote> sets maximum levels for certain contaminants in foodstuffs.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d57e90">
               <num>(2)</num>
               <p>In May of 2016, the Scientific Panel on Contaminants in the Food Chain (Contam) of the European Food Safety Authority (&apos;the Authority&apos;) adopted a scientific opinion on the Risks for human health related to the presence of 3- and 2-monochloropropanediol (MCPD), and their fatty acid esters, and glycidyl fatty acid esters in food<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="3">
                     <p>Scientific opinion on the risks for human health related to the presence of 3- and 2-monochloropropanediol (MCPD), and their fatty acid esters, and glycidyl fatty acid esters in food. <i>EFSA Journal</i> 2016;14(5): 4426, 159 pp. doi:10.2903/j.efsa.2016.4426</p>
                  </authorialNote>.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d57e107">
               <num>(3)</num>
               <p>In view of the updated guidance of its Scientific Committee on the use of the benchmark dose approach in risk assessment<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="4">
                     <p>Minutes of the 82nd Plenary meeting of the Scientific Committee held on 13-14 February 2017. Available at https://www.efsa.europa.eu/sites/default/files/event/170213-m.pdf</p>
                  </authorialNote>, the Authority has decided to re-open the assessment of 3-MCPD and its fatty acid esters, following a detailed analysis of the divergences in opinions, concerning that contaminant, between the Joint FAO/WHO Expert Committee on Food Additives<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="5">
                     <p>Joint FAO/WHO Expert Committee on Food Additives, 83rd meeting, Rome, 8&#45;17 November 2016, Summary and Conclusions. Available at http://www.fao.org/3/a-bq821e.pdf</p>
                  </authorialNote> and the Authority. Therefore it is appropriate to wait for the outcome of the assessment of 3-MCPD and its fatty acid esters before taking appropriate regulatory measures.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d57e133">
               <num>(4)</num>
               <p>Glycidyl fatty acid esters are food contaminants found at highest levels in reﬁned vegetable oils and fats. Glycidyl fatty acid esters are hydrolysed into glycidol in the gastrointestinal tract.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d57e139">
               <num>(5)</num>
               <p>The Authority concluded that glycidol is a genotoxic and carcinogenic compound. In view of the genotoxic and carcinogenic potential of glycidol, the Authority applied a margin of exposure (&apos;MoE&apos;) approach. Scenarios of exposure for infants, toddlers and other children resulted in a MoE ranging from 12800 to 4900 and for infants receiving only formula diet in a MoE of about 5500 to 2100. The Authority considered that a MoE lower than 25000 is of health concern. It is therefore appropriate to establish a maximum level for the presence of glycidyl fatty acid esters in vegetable oils and fats placed on the market for the final consumer or for use as an ingredient in food. Because of the health concern for infants, toddlers and young children it is appropriate to establish a stricter maximum level for vegetable oils and fats destined for the production of baby food and processed cereal-based food for infants and young children.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d57e165">
               <num>(6)</num>
               <p>In order to exclude any possible health concerns as regards infants, toddlers and young children, in particular, taking into account the possible exposure to glycidyl fatty acid esters of infants solely fed on infant formula, it is appropriate to establish a specific strict maximum level for infant formula, follow-on formula and food for special medical purposes intended for infants and young children. However there is a need to further reduce the presence of glycidyl fatty acid esters in infant formula, follow-on formula and food for special medical purposes intended for infants and young children and therefore it is necessary to review the maximum levels once a reliable method of analysis is available to analyse stricter levels in view of ensuring an effective enforcement of these levels.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d57e173">
               <num>(7)</num>
               <p>Food business operators should be granted enough time to adapt their production processes.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d57e179">
               <num>(8)</num>
               <p>Regulation (EC) No 1881/2006 should therefore be amended accordingly.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d57e185">
               <num>(9)</num>
               <p>The measures provided for in this Regulation are in accordance with the opinion of the Standing Committee on Plants, Animals, Food and Feed,</p>
            </recital>
         </recitals>
         <formula name="enactingFormula">
            <p>HAS ADOPTED THIS REGULATION:</p>
         </formula>
      </preamble>
      <body>
         <article xml:id="art_d57e194">
            <num>Article 1</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>The Annex to Regulation (EC) No 1881/2006 is amended in accordance with the Annex to this Regulation.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <article xml:id="art_d57e199">
            <num>Article 2</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>Foodstuffs listed in the Annex to this Regulation that were lawfully placed on the market before the entry into force of this Regulation may remain on the market until 19 September 2018.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <article xml:id="art_d57e207">
            <num>Article 3</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>This Regulation shall enter into force on the twentieth day following that of its publication in the <i>Official Journal of the European Union</i>.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <clause>
            <content>
               <p>This Regulation shall be binding in its entirety and directly applicable in all Member States.</p>
            </content>
         </clause>
      </body>
      <conclusions>
         <p>Done at Brussels, 26 February 2018.</p>
         <block name="signatory">
            <signature>
               <organization refersTo="">For the Commission</organization>
               <role refersTo="">The President</role>
               <person refersTo="">Jean-Claude JUNCKER</person>
            </signature>
         </block>
      </conclusions>
   </bill>
</akomaNtoso>
