<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0"
            xmlns:fmx="http://formex.publications.europa.eu/schema/formex-05.21-20110601.xd"
            xmlns:leos="urn:eu:europa:ec:leos"
            xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema">
   <bill name="">
      <meta xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions">
         <identification source="~COM">
            <FRBRWork>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRcountry value=""/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
         </identification>
      </meta>
      <preface>
         <longTitle>
            <p>
               <docStage/>
               <docType>COMMISSION REGULATION (EU) 2018/2026</docType>of 19 December 2018<docPurpose>amending Annex IV to Regulation (EC) No 1221/2009 of the European Parliament and of the Council on the voluntary participation by organisations in a Community eco-management and audit scheme (EMAS)</docPurpose>
            </p>
         </longTitle>
         <container name="EEArelevance">
            <p>(Text with EEA relevance)</p>
         </container>
      </preface>
      <preamble>
         <formula name="actingEntity">
            <p>THE EUROPEAN COMMISSION,</p>
         </formula>
         <citations>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to Regulation (EC) No 1221/2009 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 25 November 2009 on the voluntary participation by organisations in a Community eco-management and audit scheme (EMAS), repealing Regulation (EC) No 761/2001 and Commission Decisions 2001/681/EC and 2006/193/EC<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="1">
                     <p>OJ L 342, 22.12.2009, p. 1.</p>
                  </authorialNote>, and in particular Article 48 thereof.</p>
            </citation>
         </citations>
         <recitals xml:id="recs_d616e71">
            <intro>
               <p>Whereas:</p>
            </intro>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d616e74">
               <num>(1)</num>
               <p>An eco-management and audit scheme (EMAS) has been established under Regulation (EC) No 1221/2009. The objective of EMAS is to promote continuous improvements in the environmental performance of organisations by the establishment and implementation of environmental management systems by organisations, evaluation of the performance of such systems, provision of information on environmental performance, an open dialogue with the public and other interested parties and the active involvement of employees. To achieve this objective, Annexes I to IV to that Regulation set out specific requirements to be observed by those organisations wishing to participate in EMAS and obtain EMAS registration.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d616e80">
               <num>(2)</num>
               <p>Annex IV to Regulation (EC) No 1221/2009 sets out the requirements on environmental reporting. That Annex should be amended to address improvements identified in the light of experience gained in the operation of EMAS. Given the number and nature of these amendments, it is appropriate to replace Annex IV in its entirety in the interests of clarity.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d616e86">
               <num>(3)</num>
               <p>Regulation (EC) No 1221/2009 should therefore be amended accordingly.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d616e92">
               <num>(4)</num>
               <p>Organisations registered under EMAS are required either to prepare or update an environmental statement in accordance with Annex IV to Regulation (EC) No 1221/2009 on a yearly basis. Except in the case of small organisations exempted under Article 7 of that Regulation, the environmental statement or updated environmental statement has to be validated by an accredited or licensed environmental verifier as part of the verification of that organisation in accordance with Article 18 of that Regulation. Organisations preparing for registration under EMAS are also required to submit a validated environmental statement as part of their application for registration. A transitional period is therefore needed to provide organisations with sufficient time to address the transition to the changes made by this Regulation.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d616e98">
               <num>(5)</num>
               <p>The measures provided for in this Regulation are in accordance with the opinion of the Committee established by Article 49 of Regulation (EC) No 1221/2009,</p>
            </recital>
         </recitals>
         <formula name="enactingFormula">
            <p>HAS ADOPTED THIS REGULATION:</p>
         </formula>
      </preamble>
      <body>
         <article xml:id="art_d616e107">
            <num>Article 1</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>Annex IV to Regulation (EC) No 1221/2009 is replaced by the text in the Annex to this Regulation.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <article xml:id="art_d616e112">
            <num>Article 2</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>If the validation of an environmental statement or updated environmental statement is due to be carried out under Regulation (EC) No 1221/2009 after the date of entry into force of this Regulation but before 9 January 2020, the statement may on that occasion, in agreement with the environmental verifier and the Competent Body, be validated disregarding the amendment made by Article 1 of this Regulation.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>If a non-validated updated environmental statement is due to be forwarded to a Competent Body under Article 7(3) of Regulation (EC) No 1221/2009 after the date of entry into force of this Regulation but before 9 January 2020, the statement may on that occasion, in agreement with the Competent Body, be prepared disregarding the amendment made by Article 1 of this Regulation.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <article xml:id="art_d616e126">
            <num>Article 3</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>This Regulation shall enter into force on the twentieth day following that of its publication in the <i>Official Journal of the European Union</i>.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <clause>
            <content>
               <p>This Regulation shall be binding in its entirety and directly applicable in all Member States.</p>
            </content>
         </clause>
      </body>
      <conclusions>
         <p>Done at Brussels, 19 December 2018.</p>
         <block name="signatory">
            <signature>
               <organization refersTo="">For the Commission</organization>
               <role refersTo="">The President</role>
               <person refersTo="">Jean-Claude JUNCKER</person>
            </signature>
         </block>
      </conclusions>
   </bill>
</akomaNtoso>
