<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0"
            xmlns:fmx="http://formex.publications.europa.eu/schema/formex-05.21-20110601.xd"
            xmlns:leos="urn:eu:europa:ec:leos"
            xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema">
   <bill name="">
      <meta xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions">
         <identification source="~COM">
            <FRBRWork>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRcountry value=""/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
         </identification>
      </meta>
      <preface>
         <longTitle>
            <p>
               <docStage/>
               <docType>COMMISSION REGULATION (EU) 2017/2010</docType>of 9 November 2017<docPurpose>amending Regulation (EC) No 1099/2008 of the European Parliament and of the Council on energy statistics, as regards the updates for the annual and monthly energy statistics</docPurpose>
            </p>
         </longTitle>
         <container name="EEArelevance">
            <p>(Text with EEA relevance)</p>
         </container>
      </preface>
      <preamble>
         <formula name="actingEntity">
            <p>THE EUROPEAN COMMISSION,</p>
         </formula>
         <citations>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to Regulation (EC) No 1099/2008 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 22 October 2008 on energy statistics<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="1">
                     <p>OJ L 304, 14.11.2008, p. 1.</p>
                  </authorialNote>, and in particular Articles 4(3) and 9(2) thereof,</p>
            </citation>
         </citations>
         <recitals xml:id="recs_d514e71">
            <intro>
               <p>Whereas:</p>
            </intro>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d514e74">
               <num>(1)</num>
               <p>Regulation (EC) No 1099/2008 establishes a common framework for the production, transmission, evaluation and dissemination of comparable energy statistics in the Union.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d514e80">
               <num>(2)</num>
               <p>Energy statistics are a very dynamic statistical domain because of the intensive development of Union policies, technological progress and the importance of basing Union targets on energy data. Accordingly, regular updates are required in order to align the statistical scope to growing or changing needs.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d514e86">
               <num>(3)</num>
               <p>Regulation (EC) No 1099/2008 has conferred on the Commission the power to adjust the statistical scope. In view of the fact that new improvements and adjustments have been made to both the monthly and annual statistics, those improvements and adjustments should be reflected in Regulation (EC) No 1099/2008.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d514e92">
               <num>(4)</num>
               <p>This Regulation, among others, modifies the code numbering of items listed in the Annexes to Regulation (EC) No 1099/2008. For the purposes of Commission Implementing Decision (EU) 2015/1504<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="2">
                     <p>Commission Implementing Decision (EU) 2015/1504 of 7 September 2015, granting derogations to certain Member States as regards the provision of statistics pursuant to Regulation (EC) No 1099/2008 of the European Parliament and of the Council on energy statistics (OJ L 235, 9.9.2015, p. 24).</p>
                  </authorialNote>, it is important to state that the substance of the items for which the derogations were granted has not changed but only their code numbering. Therefore, the references to the codes listed in Implementing Decision (EU) 2015/1504 should be understood as references to the corresponding items of this Regulation.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d514e108">
               <num>(5)</num>
               <p>Regulation (EC) No 1099/2008 should therefore be amended accordingly.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d514e114">
               <num>(6)</num>
               <p>The measures provided for in this Regulation are in accordance with the opinion of the European Statistical System Committee,</p>
            </recital>
         </recitals>
         <formula name="enactingFormula">
            <p>HAS ADOPTED THIS REGULATION:</p>
         </formula>
      </preamble>
      <body>
         <article xml:id="art_d514e123">
            <num>Article 1</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>The annexes to Regulation (EC) No 1099/2008 are replaced by the text set out in the Annex to this Regulation.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <article xml:id="art_d514e128">
            <num>Article 2</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>This Regulation shall enter into force on the 20th day following that of its publication in the <i>Official Journal of the European Union</i>.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <clause>
            <content>
               <p>This Regulation shall be binding in its entirety and directly applicable in all Member States.</p>
            </content>
         </clause>
      </body>
      <conclusions>
         <p>Done at Brussels, 9 November 2017.</p>
         <block name="signatory">
            <signature>
               <organization refersTo="">For the Commission</organization>
               <role refersTo="">The President</role>
               <person refersTo="">Jean-Claude JUNCKER</person>
            </signature>
         </block>
      </conclusions>
   </bill>
</akomaNtoso>
