<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0"
            xmlns:fmx="http://formex.publications.europa.eu/schema/formex-05.21-20110601.xd"
            xmlns:leos="urn:eu:europa:ec:leos"
            xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema">
   <bill name="">
      <meta xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions">
         <identification source="~COM">
            <FRBRWork>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRcountry value=""/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
         </identification>
      </meta>
      <preface>
         <longTitle>
            <p>
               <docStage/>
               <docType>COMMISSION REGULATION (EU) 2018/401</docType>of 14 March 2018<docPurpose>amending Regulation (EU) No 139/2014 as regards the classification of runways</docPurpose>
            </p>
         </longTitle>
      </preface>
      <preamble>
         <formula name="actingEntity">
            <p>THE EUROPEAN COMMISSION,</p>
         </formula>
         <citations>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to Regulation (EC) No 216/2008 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 20 February 2008 on common rules in the field of civil aviation and establishing a European Aviation Safety Agency, and repealing Council Directive 91/670/EEC, Regulation (EC) No 1592/2002 and Directive 2004/36/EC<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="1">
                     <p>OJ L 79, 19.3.2008, p. 1.</p>
                  </authorialNote>, and in particular Article 8a(5) thereof,</p>
            </citation>
         </citations>
         <recitals xml:id="recs_d63e68">
            <intro>
               <p>Whereas:</p>
            </intro>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d63e71">
               <num>(1)</num>
               <p>Annex I to Commission Regulation (EU) No 139/2014<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="2">
                     <p>Commission Regulation (EU) No 139/2014 of 12 February 2014 laying down requirements and administrative procedures related to aerodromes pursuant to Regulation (EC) No 216/2008 of the European Parliament and of the Council (OJ L 44, 14.2.2014, p. 1).</p>
                  </authorialNote> lays down the definition of the term &apos;instrument runway&apos; for the purposes of that Regulation. The provisions of that Regulation should reflect the state of the art and the best practices in the field of aerodromes and take into account the applicable international standards.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d63e91">
               <num>(2)</num>
               <p>The International Civil Aviation Organization (ICAO), in its State letter AN 41.2.24&#45;13/20, adopted Amendment 11-B to Annex 14, Volume 1 to the Chicago Convention, which has been applicable in ICAO Contracting States as of 13 November 2014. The changes set out therein simplify the existing runway approach classification and more accurately describe the various types of approach and landing operations.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d63e100">
               <num>(3)</num>
               <p>Those changes to Annex 14 of the Chicago Convention should be reflected in Regulation (EU) No 139/2014, in particular in its provisions concerning performance-based navigation (PBN) approach operations with vertical guidance and runway requirements in relation to the approach operations. In addition, the implementation of PBN approach operations with vertical guidance by a significant number of aerodromes, without the need to upgrade their runway infrastructure, should be facilitated.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d63e106">
               <num>(4)</num>
               <p>Regulation (EU) No 139/2014 should therefore be amended accordingly.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d63e112">
               <num>(5)</num>
               <p>The measures provided for in this Regulation are based on Opinion No 03/2016 issued by the European Aviation Safety Agency in accordance with point (b) of Article 17(2) and Article 19(1) of Regulation (EC) No 216/2008.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d63e118">
               <num>(6)</num>
               <p>The measures provided for in this Regulation are in accordance with the opinion of the Committee established by Article 65 of Regulation (EC) No 216/2008,</p>
            </recital>
         </recitals>
         <formula name="enactingFormula">
            <p>HAS ADOPTED THIS REGULATION:</p>
         </formula>
      </preamble>
      <body>
         <article xml:id="art_d63e127">
            <num>Article 1</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>Annex I to Regulation (EU) No 139/2014 is amended in accordance with the Annex to this Regulation.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <article xml:id="art_d63e132">
            <num>Article 2</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>This Regulation shall enter into force on the twentieth day following that of its publication in the <i>Official Journal of the European Union</i>.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <clause>
            <content>
               <p>This Regulation shall be binding in its entirety and directly applicable in all Member States.</p>
            </content>
         </clause>
      </body>
      <conclusions>
         <p>Done at Brussels, 14 March 2018.</p>
         <block name="signatory">
            <signature>
               <organization refersTo="">For the Commission</organization>
               <role refersTo="">The President</role>
               <person refersTo="">Jean-Claude JUNCKER</person>
            </signature>
         </block>
      </conclusions>
   </bill>
</akomaNtoso>
