<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0"
            xmlns:fmx="http://formex.publications.europa.eu/schema/formex-05.21-20110601.xd"
            xmlns:leos="urn:eu:europa:ec:leos"
            xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema">
   <bill name="">
      <meta xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions">
         <identification source="~COM">
            <FRBRWork>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRcountry value=""/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
         </identification>
      </meta>
      <preface>
         <longTitle>
            <p>
               <docStage/>
               <docType>REGULATION (EU) 2017/354 OF THE EUROPEAN PARLIAMENT AND OF THE COUNCIL</docType>of 15 February 2017<docPurpose>amending Regulation (EU) 2015/936 on common rules for imports of textile products from certain third countries not covered by bilateral agreements, protocols or other arrangements, or by other specific Union import rules</docPurpose>
            </p>
         </longTitle>
      </preface>
      <preamble>
         <formula name="actingEntity">
            <p>THE EUROPEAN PARLIAMENT AND THE COUNCIL OF THE EUROPEAN UNION,</p>
         </formula>
         <citations>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union, and in particular Article 207(2) thereof,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the proposal from the European Commission,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>After transmission of the draft legislative act to the national parliaments,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>Acting in accordance with the ordinary legislative procedure<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="1">
                     <p>Position of the European Parliament of 19 January 2017 (not yet published in the Official Journal) and decision of the Council of 7 February 2017.</p>
                  </authorialNote>,</p>
            </citation>
         </citations>
         <recitals xml:id="recs_d32e75">
            <intro>
               <p>Whereas:</p>
            </intro>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d32e78">
               <num>(1)</num>
               <p>Regulation (EU) 2015/936 of the European Parliament and of the Council<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="2">
                     <p>Regulation (EU) 2015/936 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 9 June 2015 on common rules for imports of textile products from certain third countries not covered by bilateral agreements, protocols or other arrangements, or by other specific Union import rules (OJ L 160, 25.6.2015, p. 1).</p>
                  </authorialNote> lays down the common rules for imports of textile products from certain third countries not covered by bilateral agreements, protocols or other arrangements, or by other specific Union import rules.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d32e94">
               <num>(2)</num>
               <p>The release of political prisoners in the Republic of Belarus on 22 August 2015 was an important step which, together with several positive initiatives undertaken by the Republic of Belarus over the last 2 years, such as resumption of the EU-Belarus Human Rights Dialogue, contributed to the improvement of relations between the Union and the Republic of Belarus.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d32e103">
               <num>(3)</num>
               <p>EU-Belarus relations should be based on common values, in particular with regard to human rights, democracy and the rule of law, and it should be recalled that the human rights situation in the Republic of Belarus remains of concern to the Union, in particular with regard to issues such as the death penalty, which should be abolished.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d32e109">
               <num>(4)</num>
               <p>Those positive political developments between the Union and the Republic of Belarus should be recognised and bilateral relations further improved. Accordingly, this Regulation should repeal the autonomous quotas on imports of textiles and clothing originating in the Republic of Belarus, provided for in Annexes II and III to Regulation (EU) 2015/936, without prejudice to the Union&apos;s ability to have recourse to quotas in the future should the human rights situation in the Republic of Belarus seriously deteriorate.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d32e115">
               <num>(5)</num>
               <p>The removal of autonomous quotas on imports of textiles and clothing originating in the Republic of Belarus implies that the quotas on outward processing traffic are no longer necessary. As a result, Article 4(2) and Chapter V of Regulation (EU) 2015/936, together with Annex V thereto should be deleted. Article 31 of that Regulation concerning the adoption of delegated acts should also be amended accordingly. The limited use of autonomous and outward processing quotas on imports of textiles and clothing originating in the Republic of Belarus implies that the removal of those quotas would have a limited impact on Union trade.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d32e121">
               <num>(6)</num>
               <p>In order to correct erroneous Combined Nomenclature codes in categories 12, 13, 18, 68, 78, 83 (Group II B), 67, 70, 94, 96 (Group III B) and 161 (Group V), Annex I to Regulation (EU) 2015/936 should be amended.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d32e127">
               <num>(7)</num>
               <p>The official name of the Democratic People&apos;s Republic of Korea should be used in Annexes II, III and IV to Regulation (EU) 2015/936.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d32e133">
               <num>(8)</num>
               <p>In order to facilitate administrative procedures, the period of validity of import authorisations laid down in in Article 21(2) of Regulation (EU) 2015/936 should be increased from 6 to 9 months,</p>
            </recital>
         </recitals>
         <formula name="enactingFormula">
            <p>HAVE ADOPTED THIS REGULATION:</p>
         </formula>
      </preamble>
      <body>
         <article xml:id="art_d32e143" leos:compliant="false">
            <num>Article 1</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <subparagraph>
                  <content>
                     <p>Regulation (EU) 2015/936 is amended as follows:</p>
                  </content>
               </subparagraph>
               <list>
                  <point>
                     <num>(1)</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>Article 4(2) is deleted.</p>
                     </content>
                  </point>
                  <point>
                     <num>(2)</num>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>Article 21(2) is replaced by the following:</p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>
                              <mod>
                                 <quotedStructure startQuote="" endQuote="">
                                    <paragraph>
                                       <num>&apos;2.</num>
                                       <content>
                                          <p>The period of validity of import authorisations issued by the competent authorities of the Member States shall be 9 months. That period of validity may be modified where necessary, in accordance with the examination procedure referred to in Article 30(3).&apos;.</p>
                                       </content>
                                    </paragraph>
                                 </quotedStructure>
                              </mod>
                           </p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                  </point>
                  <point>
                     <num>(3)</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>Chapter V is deleted.</p>
                     </content>
                  </point>
                  <point>
                     <num>(4)</num>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>Article 31(2) and (3) are replaced by the following:</p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>
                              <mod>
                                 <quotedStructure startQuote="" endQuote="">
                                    <paragraph>
                                       <num>&apos;2.</num>
                                       <content>
                                          <p>The power to adopt delegated acts referred to in Article 3(3), Article 5(2), Article 12(3), Article 13 and Article 35 shall be conferred on the Commission for a period of 5 years from 20 February 2014. The Commission shall draw up a report in respect of the delegation of power not later than 9 months before the end of the 5-year period. The delegation of power shall be tacitly extended for periods of an identical duration, unless the European Parliament or the Council opposes such extension not later than 3 months before the end of each period.</p>
                                       </content>
                                    </paragraph>
                                    <paragraph>
                                       <num>3.</num>
                                       <content>
                                          <p>The delegation of power referred to in Article 3(3), Article 5(2), Article 12(3), Article 13 and Article 35 may be revoked at any time by the European Parliament or by the Council. A decision to revoke shall put an end to the delegation of power specified in that decision. It shall take effect the day following the publication of the decision in the <i>Official Journal of the European Union</i> or at a later date specified therein. It shall not affect the validity of any delegated acts already in force.&apos;.</p>
                                       </content>
                                    </paragraph>
                                 </quotedStructure>
                              </mod>
                           </p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                  </point>
                  <point>
                     <num>(5)</num>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>Article 31(6) is replaced by the following:</p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>
                              <mod>
                                 <quotedStructure startQuote="" endQuote="">
                                    <paragraph>
                                       <num>&apos;6.</num>
                                       <content>
                                          <p>A delegated act adopted pursuant to Article 3(3) or Article 12(3) shall enter into force only if no objection has been expressed either by the European Parliament or the Council within a period of 2 months of notification of that act to the European Parliament and the Council or if, before the expiry of that period, the European Parliament and the Council have both informed the Commission that they will not object. That period shall be extended by 4 months at the initiative of the European Parliament or of the Council.&apos;.</p>
                                       </content>
                                    </paragraph>
                                 </quotedStructure>
                              </mod>
                           </p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                  </point>
                  <point>
                     <num>(6)</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>Section A of Annex I is amended in accordance with the Annex to this Regulation and Annexes II, III and IV are replaced by texts set out in the Annex to this Regulation.</p>
                     </content>
                  </point>
                  <point>
                     <num>(7)</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>Annex V is deleted.</p>
                     </content>
                  </point>
               </list>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <article xml:id="art_d32e233">
            <num>Article 2</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>This Regulation shall enter into force on the twentieth day following that of its publication in the <i>Official Journal of the European Union</i>.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <clause>
            <content>
               <p>This Regulation shall be binding in its entirety and directly applicable in all Member States.</p>
            </content>
         </clause>
      </body>
      <conclusions>
         <p>Done at Strasbourg, 15 February 2017.</p>
         <block name="signatory">
            <signature>
               <organization refersTo="">For the European Parliament</organization>
               <role refersTo="">The President</role>
               <person refersTo="">A. TAJANI</person>
            </signature>
            <signature>
               <organization refersTo="">For the Council</organization>
               <role refersTo="">The President</role>
               <person refersTo="">I. BORG</person>
            </signature>
         </block>
      </conclusions>
   </bill>
</akomaNtoso>
