<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0"
            xmlns:fmx="http://formex.publications.europa.eu/schema/formex-05.21-20110601.xd"
            xmlns:leos="urn:eu:europa:ec:leos"
            xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema">
   <bill name="">
      <meta xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions">
         <identification source="~COM">
            <FRBRWork>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRcountry value=""/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
         </identification>
      </meta>
      <preface>
         <longTitle>
            <p>
               <docStage/>
               <docType>COUNCIL REGULATION (EU) 2018/1977</docType>of 11 December 2018<docPurpose>opening and providing for the management of autonomous Union tariff quotas for certain fishery products for the period 2019&#45;2020</docPurpose>
            </p>
         </longTitle>
      </preface>
      <preamble>
         <formula name="actingEntity">
            <p>THE COUNCIL OF THE EUROPEAN UNION,</p>
         </formula>
         <citations>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union, and in particular Article 31 thereof,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the proposal from the European Commission,</p>
            </citation>
         </citations>
         <recitals xml:id="recs_d450e59">
            <intro>
               <p>Whereas:</p>
            </intro>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d450e62">
               <num>(1)</num>
               <p>Union supplies of certain fishery products currently depend on imports from third countries. In the last 21 years, the Union has become more dependent on imports to meet its consumption of fishery products. In order not to jeopardise the Union production of fishery products and to ensure an adequate supply to the Union processing industry, import duties should be reduced or suspended for a number of fishery products within tariff quotas of an appropriate volume. To guarantee a level playing field for the Union producers, the sensitivity of individual fishery products on the Union market should be taken into consideration.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d450e68">
               <num>(2)</num>
               <p>Council Regulation (EU) 2015/2265<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="1">
                     <p>Council Regulation (EU) 2015/2265 of 7 December 2015 opening and providing for the management of autonomous Union tariff quotas for certain fishery products for the period 2016-2018 (OJ L 322, 8.12.2015, p. 4).</p>
                  </authorialNote>, which was amended by Council Regulation (EU) 2016/1184<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="2">
                     <p>Council Regulation (EU) 2016/1184 of 18 July 2016 amending Regulation (EU) 2015/2265 opening and providing for the management of autonomous Union tariff quotas for certain fishery products for the period 2016 to 2018 (OJ L 196, 21.7.2016, p. 1).</p>
                  </authorialNote>, opened and provided for the management of autonomous Union tariff quotas for certain fishery products for the period 2016&#45;2018. Given that the period of application of Regulation (EU) 2015/2265 expires on 31 December 2018, a new Regulation providing for tariff quotas should be adopted for the period 2019&#45;2020.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d450e97">
               <num>(3)</num>
               <p>Equal and uninterrupted access to the tariff quotas provided for in this Regulation should be ensured for all Union importers, and the rates laid down for the tariff quotas should be applied without interruption to all imports of the fishery products concerned into all Member States until the tariff quotas have been used up.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d450e103">
               <num>(4)</num>
               <p>Commission Implementing Regulation (EU) 2015/2447<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="3">
                     <p>Commission Implementing Regulation (EU) 2015/2447 of 24 November 2015 laying down detailed rules for implementing certain provisions of Regulation (EU) No 952/2013 of the European Parliament and of the Council laying down the Union Customs Code (OJ L 343, 29.12.2015, p. 558).</p>
                  </authorialNote> provides for a system of tariff-quota management which follows the chronological order of the dates of acceptance of the customs declarations for release for free circulation. The tariff quotas opened by this Regulation should be managed by the Commission and the Member States in accordance with that system.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d450e119">
               <num>(5)</num>
               <p>It is important to ensure transparency, predictability and legal certainty for all stakeholders. Since the tariff quotas are intended to ensure adequate supply to the Union processing industry, minimum treatment or operation should be required for quota entitlement.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d450e125">
               <num>(6)</num>
               <p>To ensure the efficiency of a common management of the tariff quotas, Member States should be permitted to draw from the tariff quota amount the necessary quantities corresponding to their actual imports. Since that method of management requires close cooperation between the Member States and the Commission, the Commission should be able to monitor the rate at which the tariff quotas are used up and should inform the Member States accordingly,</p>
            </recital>
         </recitals>
         <formula name="enactingFormula">
            <p>HAS ADOPTED THIS REGULATION:</p>
         </formula>
      </preamble>
      <body>
         <article xml:id="art_d450e135">
            <num>Article 1</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>Import duties on the products listed in the Annex shall be reduced or suspended within the tariff quotas at the rates, for the periods and up to the amounts indicated therein.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <article xml:id="art_d450e140">
            <num>Article 2</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>The tariff quotas referred to in Article 1 of this Regulation shall be managed in accordance with Articles 49 to 54 of Regulation (EU) 2015/2447.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <article xml:id="art_d450e145">
            <num>Article 3</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>The tariff quotas shall be subject to end-use customs supervision in accordance with Article 254 of Regulation (EU) No 952/2013 of the European Parliament and of the Council<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="4">
                        <p>Regulation (EU) No 952/2013 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 9 October 2013 laying down the Union Customs Code (OJ L 269, 10.10.2013, p. 1).</p>
                     </authorialNote>.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <article xml:id="art_d450e160">
            <num>Article 4</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <num>1.</num>
               <content>
                  <p>The reduction or suspension of import duties shall apply only to products intended for human consumption.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph>
               <num>2.</num>
               <content>
                  <p>The tariff quotas shall not be available for those products whose processing is carried out at retail or catering level.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph>
               <num>3.</num>
               <subparagraph>
                  <content>
                     <p>The tariff quotas shall not be available for products intended solely for one or more of the following operations:</p>
                  </content>
               </subparagraph>
               <list>
                  <indent>
                     <num>-</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>cleaning, gutting, tailing, heading;</p>
                     </content>
                  </indent>
                  <indent>
                     <num>-</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>cutting;</p>
                     </content>
                  </indent>
                  <indent>
                     <num>-</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>repacking of frozen IQF (individually quick frozen) fillets;</p>
                     </content>
                  </indent>
                  <indent>
                     <num>-</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>sampling, sorting;</p>
                     </content>
                  </indent>
                  <indent>
                     <num>-</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>labelling;</p>
                     </content>
                  </indent>
                  <indent>
                     <num>-</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>packing;</p>
                     </content>
                  </indent>
                  <indent>
                     <num>-</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>chilling;</p>
                     </content>
                  </indent>
                  <indent>
                     <num>-</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>freezing;</p>
                     </content>
                  </indent>
                  <indent>
                     <num>-</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>deep freezing;</p>
                     </content>
                  </indent>
                  <indent>
                     <num>-</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>glazing;</p>
                     </content>
                  </indent>
                  <indent>
                     <num>-</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>thawing;</p>
                     </content>
                  </indent>
                  <indent>
                     <num>-</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>separation.</p>
                     </content>
                  </indent>
               </list>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph>
               <num>4.</num>
               <subparagraph>
                  <content>
                     <p>Notwithstanding paragraph 3, the tariff quotas shall be available for products intended for one or more of the following operations:</p>
                  </content>
               </subparagraph>
               <list>
                  <indent>
                     <num>-</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>dicing;</p>
                     </content>
                  </indent>
                  <indent>
                     <num>-</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>cutting into rings and cutting into strips for materials under CN codes 03074391, 03074392, 03074399;</p>
                     </content>
                  </indent>
                  <indent>
                     <num>-</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>filleting;</p>
                     </content>
                  </indent>
                  <indent>
                     <num>-</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>production of flaps;</p>
                     </content>
                  </indent>
                  <indent>
                     <num>-</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>cutting of frozen blocks;</p>
                     </content>
                  </indent>
                  <indent>
                     <num>-</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>splitting of frozen interleaved fillet blocks to obtain individual fillets;</p>
                     </content>
                  </indent>
                  <indent>
                     <num>-</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>slicing for materials under CN codes ex03036611, 03036612, 03036613, 03036619, 03038970, 03038990;</p>
                     </content>
                  </indent>
                  <indent>
                     <num>-</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>subjecting products under CN codes 03061699 (TARIC subdivisions 20 and 30), 03061792 (TARIC subdivision 20), 03061799 (TARIC subdivision 10), 03063590 (TARIC subdivisions 12, 14, 92 and 93), 03063690 (TARIC subdivisions 20 and 30), 16052190 (TARIC subdivisions 45, 55 and 62) and 16052900 (TARIC subdivisions 50, 55 and 60) to processing treatment by packaging gases as defined in Annex I to Regulation (EC) No 1333/2008 of the European Parliament and of the Council<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="5">
                              <p>Regulation (EC) No 1333/2008 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 16 December 2008 on food additives (OJ L 354, 31.12.2008, p. 16).</p>
                           </authorialNote>;</p>
                     </content>
                  </indent>
                  <indent>
                     <num>-</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>dividing the frozen product or subjecting the frozen product to heat treatment to enable the removal of internal waste material for materials under CN codes 03061110 (TARIC subdivision 10), 03061190 (TARIC subdivision 20) and 03063100 (TARIC subdivision 10).</p>
                     </content>
                  </indent>
               </list>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <article xml:id="art_d450e382">
            <num>Article 5</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>The Commission and the customs authorities of the Member States shall cooperate closely to ensure the proper management and control of the application of this Regulation.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <article xml:id="art_d450e387">
            <num>Article 6</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>This Regulation shall enter into force on the third day following that of its publication in the <i>Official Journal of the European Union</i>.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>It shall apply from 1 January 2019 to 31 December 2020.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <clause>
            <content>
               <p>This Regulation shall be binding in its entirety and directly applicable in all Member States.</p>
            </content>
         </clause>
      </body>
      <conclusions>
         <p>Done at Brussels, 11 December 2018.</p>
         <block name="signatory">
            <signature>
               <organization refersTo="">For the Council</organization>
               <role refersTo="">The President</role>
               <person refersTo="">G. BLÜMEL</person>
            </signature>
         </block>
      </conclusions>
   </bill>
</akomaNtoso>
