<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0"
            xmlns:fmx="http://formex.publications.europa.eu/schema/formex-05.21-20110601.xd"
            xmlns:leos="urn:eu:europa:ec:leos"
            xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema">
   <bill name="">
      <meta xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions">
         <identification source="~COM">
            <FRBRWork>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRcountry value=""/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
         </identification>
      </meta>
      <preface>
         <longTitle>
            <p>
               <docStage/>
               <docType>COMMISSION REGULATION (EU) 2018/455</docType>of 16 March 2018<docPurpose>laying down additional responsibilities and tasks for the European Union reference laboratory for fish and crustacean diseases and amending Annex VII to Regulation (EC) No 882/2004 of the European Parliament and of the Council</docPurpose>
            </p>
         </longTitle>
         <container name="EEArelevance">
            <p>(Text with EEA relevance)</p>
         </container>
      </preface>
      <preamble>
         <formula name="actingEntity">
            <p>THE EUROPEAN COMMISSION,</p>
         </formula>
         <citations>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to Regulation (EC) No 882/2004 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 29 April 2004 on official controls performed to ensure the verification of compliance with feed and food law, animal health and animal welfare rules<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="1">
                     <p>OJ L 165, 30.4.2004, p. 1.</p>
                  </authorialNote>, and in particular Article 32(5) and (6) thereof,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to Council Directive 2006/88/EC of 24 October 2006 on animal health requirements for aquaculture animals and products thereof, and on the prevention and control of certain diseases in aquatic animals<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="2">
                     <p>OJ L 328, 24.11.2006, p. 14.</p>
                  </authorialNote>, and in particular Article 55(1) thereof,</p>
            </citation>
         </citations>
         <recitals xml:id="recs_d49e82">
            <intro>
               <p>Whereas:</p>
            </intro>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d49e85">
               <num>(1)</num>
               <p>Regulation (EC) No 882/2004 lays down the general tasks, duties and requirements of the European Union (EU) reference laboratories for food and feed, and for animal health. The EU reference laboratories for animal health and live animals are listed in Part II of Annex VII to Regulation (EC) No 882/2004. Point 15 of Part II of that Annex lists the Centre for Environment, Fisheries &amp; Aquaculture Science (Cefas), Weymouth, United Kingdom, as the EU reference laboratory for crustacean diseases.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d49e91">
               <num>(2)</num>
               <p>Directive 2006/88/EC lays down the animal health requirements for the placing on the market, and the importation and the transit through the Union of aquaculture animals and products thereof, and certain minimum preventive and control measures for certain diseases in those animals. Article 55(1) of Directive 2006/88/EC provides for the designation of EU reference laboratories for aquatic animal diseases relevant to that Directive.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d49e97">
               <num>(3)</num>
               <p>Commission Regulation (EC) No 737/2008<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="3">
                     <p>Commission Regulation (EC) No 737/2008 of 28 July 2008 designating the Community reference laboratories for crustacean diseases, rabies and bovine tuberculosis, laying down additional responsibilities and tasks for the Community reference laboratories for rabies and bovine tuberculosis and amending Annex VII to Regulation (EC) No 882/2004 of the European Parliament and of the Council (OJ L 201, 30.7.2008, p. 29).</p>
                  </authorialNote> designated the Centre for Environment, Fisheries &amp; Aquaculture Science (Cefas), Weymouth Laboratory, United Kingdom, as the EU reference laboratory for crustacean diseases for the period from 1 July 2008 until 30 June 2018. Article 55(3) of Directive 2006/88/EC provides for a review of the functions of that laboratory.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d49e119">
               <num>(4)</num>
               <p>As a consequence of the United Kingdom notification in accordance with Article 50 of the Treaty on European Union, the function of Cefas as EU reference laboratory for crustacean diseases cannot be continued for a further period starting on 1 July 2018.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d49e128">
               <num>(5)</num>
               <p>In view of the synergies in technical expertise, laboratory capacity and networking with national reference laboratories, the EU reference laboratory for fish diseases should also take over the tasks and functions of the EU reference laboratory for crustacean diseases.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d49e134">
               <num>(6)</num>
               <p>The &apos;Danmarks Tekniske Universitet, Veterinærinstituttet Afdeling for Diagnostik og Beredskab &#45; Fiskesygdomme, 2800 Kgs. Lyngby, Danmark&apos; which has been designated as the EU reference laboratory for fish diseases, should therefore take over the tasks and functions of the EU reference laboratory for crustacean diseases.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d49e145">
               <num>(7)</num>
               <p>The DTU Veterinærinstituttet Afdeling for Diagnostik og Beredskab &#45; Fiskesygdomme that is assuming the responsibilities of the EU reference laboratory for fish and crustacean diseases should be indicated as the EU reference laboratory for crustacean diseases for the period from 1 July 2018 to 30 June 2023. In addition, it should be listed in Part II of Annex VII to Regulation (EC) No 882/2004. Part II of Annex VII to Regulation (EC) No 882/2004 should therefore be amended accordingly.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d49e158">
               <num>(8)</num>
               <p>In order to ensure seamless continuity of the activities of the European Union reference laboratories for crustacean diseases, it is appropriate to provide for a specific date of application for the measures provided for in this Regulation.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d49e164">
               <num>(9)</num>
               <p>The measures provided for in this Regulation are in accordance with the opinion of the Standing Committee on Plants, Animals, Food and Feed,</p>
            </recital>
         </recitals>
         <formula name="enactingFormula">
            <p>HAS ADOPTED THIS REGULATION:</p>
         </formula>
      </preamble>
      <body>
         <article xml:id="art_d49e173">
            <num>Article 1</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>Danmarks Tekniske Universitet, Veterinærinstituttet Afdeling for Diagnostik og Beredskab &#45; Fiskesygdomme, 2800 Kgs. Lyngby, Denmark, shall have the responsibilities and tasks of the European Union reference laboratory for crustacean diseases from 1 July 2018 to 30 June 2023.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <article xml:id="art_d49e186" leos:compliant="false">
            <num>Article 2</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <subparagraph>
                  <content>
                     <p>Part II of Annex VII to Regulation (EC) No 882/2004 is amended as follows:</p>
                  </content>
               </subparagraph>
               <list>
                  <point>
                     <num>(1)</num>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>point 6. is replaced by the following:</p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>
                              <mod>
                                 <quotedStructure startQuote="" endQuote="">
                                    <point>
                                       <num>&apos;6.</num>
                                       <content>
                                          <p>
                                             <p><!--default P | TXT -->EU reference laboratory for fish and crustacean diseases</p>
                                             <p><!--default P | TXT -->Danmarks Tekniske Universitet</p>
                                             <p><!--default P | TXT -->Veterinærinstituttet</p>
                                             <p><!--default P | TXT -->Afdeling for Diagnostik og Beredskab &#45; Fiskesygdomme, Kemitorvet, Bygning 202</p>
                                             <p><!--default P | TXT -->2800 Kgs. Lyngby</p>
                                             <p><!--default P | TXT -->Denmark&apos;;</p>
                                          </p>
                                       </content>
                                    </point>
                                 </quotedStructure>
                              </mod>
                           </p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                  </point>
                  <point>
                     <num>(2)</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>point 15 is deleted.</p>
                     </content>
                  </point>
               </list>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <article xml:id="art_d49e227">
            <num>Article 3</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>This Regulation shall enter into force on 1 July 2018.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <clause>
            <content>
               <p>This Regulation is binding in its entirety and directly applicable in all Member States.</p>
            </content>
         </clause>
      </body>
      <conclusions>
         <p>Done at Brussels, 16 March 2018.</p>
         <block name="signatory">
            <signature>
               <organization refersTo="">For the Commission</organization>
               <role refersTo="">The President</role>
               <person refersTo="">Jean-Claude JUNCKER</person>
            </signature>
         </block>
      </conclusions>
   </bill>
</akomaNtoso>
