<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0"
            xmlns:fmx="http://formex.publications.europa.eu/schema/formex-05.21-20110601.xd"
            xmlns:leos="urn:eu:europa:ec:leos"
            xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema">
   <bill name="">
      <meta xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions">
         <identification source="~COM">
            <FRBRWork>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRcountry value=""/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
         </identification>
      </meta>
      <preface>
         <longTitle>
            <p>
               <docStage/>
               <docType>COMMISSION REGULATION (EU) 2019/2146</docType>of 26 November 2019<docPurpose>amending Regulation (EC) No 1099/2008 of the European Parliament and of the Council on energy statistics, as regards the implementation of updates for the annual, monthly and short-term monthly energy statistics</docPurpose>
            </p>
         </longTitle>
         <container name="EEArelevance">
            <p>(Text with EEA relevance)</p>
         </container>
      </preface>
      <preamble>
         <formula name="actingEntity">
            <p>THE EUROPEAN COMMISSION,</p>
         </formula>
         <citations>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to Regulation (EC) No 1099/2008 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 22 October 2008 on energy statistics<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="1">
                     <p>OJ L 304, 14.11.2008, p. 1.</p>
                  </authorialNote>, and in particular Article 4(3) and Article 9(3) thereof,</p>
            </citation>
         </citations>
         <recitals xml:id="recs_d648e71">
            <intro>
               <p>Whereas:</p>
            </intro>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d648e74">
               <num>(1)</num>
               <p>Regulation (EC) No 1099/2008 establishes a common framework for the production, transmission, evaluation and dissemination of comparable energy statistics in the Union.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d648e80">
               <num>(2)</num>
               <p>Energy statistics need to evolve continuously due to the fast pace of technological progress, the evolution of Union energy policies and the importance of basing Union targets and the monitoring of progress in reaching them on official energy data. Regular updates of the European energy statistics reporting framework are therefore required to reflect growing or changing needs.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d648e86">
               <num>(3)</num>
               <p>The Commission has identified several aspects of the annual, monthly and short-term monthly energy statistics that need to be updated. They concern notably greater disaggregation of the statistics on final energy consumption in industry, conceptual adjustments for natural gas trade definitions to improve consistency, rendering certain reporting items mandatory, and improving the timeliness of the monthly data collection for coal and electricity. The Commission has discussed and agreed with the Member States on several technical aspects, including the scope, feasibility, production costs, confidentiality and reporting burden with the Member States.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d648e92">
               <num>(4)</num>
               <p>Regulation (EC) No 1099/2008 should therefore be amended accordingly.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d648e98">
               <num>(5)</num>
               <p>The measures provided for in this Regulation are in accordance with the opinion of the European Statistical System Committee.</p>
            </recital>
         </recitals>
         <formula name="enactingFormula">
            <p>HAS ADOPTED THIS REGULATION:</p>
         </formula>
      </preamble>
      <body>
         <article xml:id="art_d648e107">
            <num>Article 1</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>The Annexes to Regulation (EC) No 1099/2008 are replaced by the text in the Annex to this Regulation.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <article xml:id="art_d648e113">
            <num>Article 2</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>This Regulation shall enter into force on the twentieth day following its publication in the <i>Official Journal of the European Union</i>.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <clause>
            <content>
               <p>This Regulation shall be binding in its entirety and directly applicable in all Member States.</p>
            </content>
         </clause>
      </body>
      <conclusions>
         <p>Done at Brussels, 26 November 2019.</p>
         <block name="signatory">
            <signature>
               <organization refersTo="">For the Commission</organization>
               <role refersTo="">The President</role>
               <person refersTo="">Jean-Claude JUNCKER</person>
            </signature>
         </block>
      </conclusions>
   </bill>
</akomaNtoso>
