<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0"
            xmlns:fmx="http://formex.publications.europa.eu/schema/formex-05.21-20110601.xd"
            xmlns:leos="urn:eu:europa:ec:leos"
            xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema">
   <bill name="">
      <meta xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions">
         <identification source="~COM">
            <FRBRWork>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRcountry value=""/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
         </identification>
      </meta>
      <preface>
         <longTitle>
            <p>
               <docStage/>
               <docType>COUNCIL REGULATION (EU) 2016/72</docType>of 22 January 2016<docPurpose>fixing for 2016 the fishing opportunities for certain fish stocks and groups of fish stocks, applicable in Union waters and, for Union fishing vessels, in certain non-Union waters, and amending Regulation (EU) 2015/104</docPurpose>
            </p>
         </longTitle>
      </preface>
      <preamble>
         <formula name="actingEntity">
            <p>THE COUNCIL OF THE EUROPEAN UNION,</p>
         </formula>
         <citations>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union, and in particular Article 43(3) thereof,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the proposal from the European Commission,</p>
            </citation>
         </citations>
         <recitals xml:id="recs_d1e59">
            <intro>
               <p>Whereas:</p>
            </intro>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d1e62">
               <num>(1)</num>
               <p>Article 43(3) of the Treaty provides that the Council, on a proposal from the Commission, is to adopt measures on the fixing and allocation of fishing opportunities.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d1e68">
               <num>(2)</num>
               <p>Regulation (EU) No 1380/2013 of the European Parliament and of the Council<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="1">
                     <p>Regulation (EU) No 1380/2013 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 11 December 2013 on the Common Fisheries Policy, amending Council Regulations (EC) No 1954/2003 and (EC) No 1224/2009 and repealing Council Regulations (EC) No 2371/2002 and (EC) No 639/2004 and Council Decision 2004/585/EC (OJ L 354, 28.12.2013, p. 22).</p>
                  </authorialNote> requires that conservation measures be adopted taking into account available scientific, technical and economic advice, including, where relevant, reports drawn up by the Scientific, Technical and Economic Committee for Fisheries (STECF) and other advisory bodies, as well as in the light of any advice received from Advisory Councils.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d1e84">
               <num>(3)</num>
               <p>It is incumbent upon the Council to adopt measures on the fixing and allocation of fishing opportunities, including certain conditions functionally linked thereto, as appropriate. In accordance with Article 16(4) of Regulation (EU) No 1380/2013, fishing opportunities should be fixed in accordance with the objectives of the Common Fisheries Policy established in Article 2(2) of that Regulation. In accordance with Article 16(1) of that Regulation, fishing opportunities should be allocated to Member States in such a way as to ensure relative stability of fishing activities of each Member State for each fish stock or fishery.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d1e90">
               <num>(4)</num>
               <p>The total allowable catch (TACs) should therefore be established, in line with Regulation (EU) No 1380/2013, on the basis of available scientific advice, taking into account biological and socio-economic aspects whilst ensuring fair treatment between fishing sectors, as well as in the light of the opinions expressed during the consultation of stakeholders, in particular at the meetings of the Advisory Councils.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d1e96">
               <num>(5)</num>
               <p>The landing obligation referred to in Article 15 of Regulation (EU) No 1380/2013 is introduced on a fishery-by-fishery basis. In the region covered by this Regulation, when a fishery falls under the landing obligation, all species in that fishery subject to catch limits should be landed. From 1 January 2016, the landing obligation applies to the species that define the fisheries. Article 16(2) of Regulation (EU) No 1380/2013 provides that, when the landing obligation in respect of a fish stock is introduced, fishing opportunities are to be fixed taking into account the change from fixing fishing opportunities that reflect landings to fixing fishing opportunities that reflect catches. On the basis of the joint recommendations submitted by the Member States and in accordance with Article 15 of Regulation (EU) No 1380/2013 the Commission adopted a number of delegated Regulations laying down specific discard plans applicable on a temporary basis for a maximum period of three years, in preparation for the full implementation of the landing obligation.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d1e107">
               <num>(6)</num>
               <p>The fishing opportunities for stocks of species falling under the landing obligation from 1 January 2016 should compensate for former discards and be based on scientific information and advice. In order to ensure fair compensation for the fish that has been previously discarded and that will have to be landed from 1 January 2016, a top-up should be calculated according to the following methodology: the new landings figure should be calculated by subtracting from the International Council for the Exploration of the Sea (ICES) figure of total catches the amounts that will continue to be discarded during the operation of the landing obligation; subsequently a top-up applied to the TAC figure should be proportional to the change between the new calculated landings figure and the previous ICES landings figure.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d1e119">
               <num>(7)</num>
               <p>According to scientific advice, sea bass (<i>Dicentrarchus labrax</i>) in the Celtic Sea, Channel, Irish Sea and southern North Sea (ICES divisions IVb, IVc and VIIa, VIId&#45;VIIh) is in a perilous state and stock continues to decline. The conservation actions to prohibit fishing for sea bass in ICES divisions VIIb, VIIc, VIIj and VIIk should be maintained and should include ICES divisions VIIa and VIIg, with the exception of the waters within 12 nautical miles of the baseline under the sovereignty of the United Kingdom. Spawning aggregations of sea bass should be protected and no catches should be allowed in the entire distribution area of the stock for the first six months of the year. Due to incidental and unavoidable by-catches of sea bass by vessels using demersal trawls and seines, such by-catches should be limited to 1 % of the weight of the total catch of marine organisms on board. Further restrictions of catches are needed to protect sea bass outside the spawning periods, therefore monthly catch limits should apply in ICES divisions IVb and IVc, as well as VIId, VIIe, VIIf and VIIh, and in the UK territorial sea in ICES divisions VIIa and VIIg. Catches of recreational fishermen should be limited further.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d1e128">
               <num>(8)</num>
               <p>For some years, certain TACs for stocks of elasmobranchs (skates, sharks, rays) have been set at 0, with a linked provision establishing an obligation to immediately release accidental catches. The reason for this specific treatment is that the conservation status of those stocks is poor and, because of their high survival rates, discards will not raise fishing mortality rates for them, but are deemed as beneficial for the conservation of these species. As of 1 January 2015, however, catches of those species in pelagic fisheries have to be landed, unless they are covered by any of the derogations from the landing obligation foreseen in Article 15 of Regulation (EU) No 1380/2013. Article 15(4)(a) of that Regulation allows such derogations for species in respect of which fishing is prohibited and which are identified as such in a Union legal act adopted in the area of the Common Fisheries Policy. Therefore, it is appropriate to prohibit the fishing of those species in the areas concerned.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d1e137">
               <num>(9)</num>
               <p>Pursuant to Article 16(4) of Regulation (EU) No 1380/2013, for stocks subject to specific multiannual plans the TACs should be established in accordance with the rules laid down in those plans. Consequently, the TACs for stocks of sole in the Western Channel, of plaice and sole in the North Sea, of cod in the Kattegat, to the west of Scotland, the Irish Sea, the North Sea, Skagerrak and the Eastern Channel and of bluefin tuna in the Eastern Atlantic and the Mediterranean should be established in accordance with the rules laid down in Council Regulations (EC) No 509/2007<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="2">
                     <p>Council Regulation (EC) No 509/2007 of 7 May 2007 establishing a multi-annual plan for the sustainable exploitation of the stock of sole in the Western Channel (OJ L 122, 11.5.2007, p. 7).</p>
                  </authorialNote>, (EC) No 676/2007<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="3">
                     <p>Council Regulation (EC) No 676/2007 of 11 June 2007 establishing a multiannual plan for fisheries exploiting stocks of plaice and sole in the North Sea (OJ L 157, 19.6.2007, p. 1).</p>
                  </authorialNote>, (EC) No 1342/2008<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="4">
                     <p>Council Regulation (EC) No 1342/2008 of 18 December 2008 establishing a long-term plan for cod stocks and the fisheries exploiting those stocks and repealing Regulation (EC) No 423/2004 (OJ L 348, 24.12.2008, p. 20).</p>
                  </authorialNote> (the &apos;Cod Plan&apos;) and (EC) No 302/2009<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="5">
                     <p>Council Regulation (EC) No 302/2009 of 6 April 2009 concerning a multiannual recovery plan for bluefin tuna in the eastern Atlantic and Mediterranean, amending Regulation (EC) No 43/2009 and repealing Regulation (EC) No 1559/2007 (OJ L 96, 15.4.2009, p. 1).</p>
                  </authorialNote>. The objective for the Southern hake stock as set out in Council Regulation (EC) No 2166/2005<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="6">
                     <p>Council Regulation (EC) No 2166/2005 of 20 December 2005 establishing measures for the recovery of the Southern hake and Norway lobster stocks in the Cantabrian Sea and Western Iberian peninsula and amending Regulation (EC) No 850/98 for the conservation of fishery resources through technical measures for the protection of juveniles of marine organisms (OJ L 345, 28.12.2005, p. 5).</p>
                  </authorialNote> is to rebuild the biomass of the stocks concerned to within safe biological limits, while staying in line with the scientific data. In accordance with scientific advice, in the absence of definitive data on a target spawning stock biomass and while taking into account changes in safe biological limits, it is appropriate, in order to contribute to the achievement of the objectives of the Common Fisheries Policy as defined in Regulation (EU) 1380/2013, to fix the TAC on the basis of maximum sustainable yield advice, as provided by ICES.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d1e200">
               <num>(10)</num>
               <p>As a result of the recent benchmark exercise, as regards the stock of herring to the west of Scotland, ICES has provided advice for the combined herring stocks in Divisions VIa, VIIb and VIIc (West of Scotland, West of Ireland). The advice covers two separate TACs (for VIaS, VIIb and VIIc on the one hand, and for Vb, VIb and VIaN on the other). According to ICES, a rebuilding plan has to be developed for these stocks. Since, according to scientific advice, the management plan for the northern stock<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="7">
                     <p>Council Regulation (EC) No 1300/2008 of 18 December 2008 establishing a multi-annual plan for the stock of herring distributed to the west of Scotland and the fisheries exploiting that stock (OJ L 344, 20.12.2008, p. 6).</p>
                  </authorialNote> cannot be applied to the combined stocks, it is appropriate, in order to contribute to the achievement of the objectives of the Common Fisheries Policy as defined in Regulation (EU) 1380/2013, to fix the TACs on the basis of the maximum sustainable yield advice.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d1e217">
               <num>(11)</num>
               <p>For stocks for which there is no sufficient or reliable data in order to provide size estimates, management measures and TAC levels should follow the precautionary approach to fisheries management as defined in Article 4(1)(8) of Regulation (EU) No 1380/2013, while taking into account stock-specific factors, including, in particular, available information on stock trends and mixed fisheries considerations.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d1e223">
               <num>(12)</num>
               <p>Council Regulation (EC) No 847/96<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="8">
                     <p>Council Regulation (EC) No 847/96 of 6 May 1996 introducing additional conditions for year-to-year management of TACs and quotas (OJ L 115, 9.5.1996, p. 3).</p>
                  </authorialNote> introduced additional conditions for year-to-year management of TACs including, under Articles 3 and 4, flexibility provisions for precautionary and analytical TACs. Under Article 2 of that Regulation, when fixing the TACs, the Council is to decide to which stocks Articles 3 or 4 shall not apply, in particular on the basis of the biological status of the stocks. More recently, the year-to-year flexibility mechanism was introduced by Article 15(9) of Regulation (EU) No 1380/2013 for all stocks that are subject to the landing obligation. Therefore, in order to avoid excessive flexibility that would undermine the principle of rational and responsible exploitation of living marine biological resources, hinder the achievement of the objectives of the CFP and deteriorate the biological status of the stocks, it should be established that Articles 3 and 4 of Regulation (EC) No 847/96 apply to analytical TACs only where the year-to-year flexibility provided for in Article 15(9) of Regulation (EU) No 1380/2013 is not used.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d1e239">
               <num>(13)</num>
               <p>Where a TAC relating to a stock is allocated to one Member State only, it is appropriate to empower that Member State in accordance with Article 2(1) of the Treaty to determine the level of such TAC. Provisions should be made to ensure that, when fixing that TAC level, the Member State concerned acts in a manner fully consistent with the principles and rules of the Common Fisheries Policy.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d1e245">
               <num>(14)</num>
               <p>It is necessary to establish the fishing effort ceilings for 2016 in accordance with Article 5 of Regulation (EC) No 509/2007, Article 9 of Regulation (EC) No 676/2007, Articles 11 and 12 of Regulation (EC) No 1342/2008 and Articles 5 and 9 of Regulation (EC) No 302/2009, while taking into account Council Regulation (EC) No 754/2009<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="9">
                     <p>Council Regulation (EC) No 754/2009 of 27 July 2009 excluding certain groups of vessels from the fishing effort regime laid down in Chapter III of Regulation (EC) No 1342/2008 (OJ L 214, 19.8.2009, p. 16).</p>
                  </authorialNote>.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d1e261">
               <num>(15)</num>
               <p>In order to guarantee full use of fishing opportunities, it is appropriate to allow for the implementation of a flexible arrangement between some of the TAC areas where the same biological stock is concerned.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d1e267">
               <num>(16)</num>
               <p>In the light of the most recent scientific advice from ICES and in accordance with the international commitments in the context of the North East Atlantic Fisheries Convention (NEAFC), it is necessary to limit the fishing effort on certain deep-sea species.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d1e273">
               <num>(17)</num>
               <p>For certain species, such as certain species of sharks, even a limited fishing activity could result in a serious risk to their conservation. Fishing opportunities for such species should therefore be fully restricted through a general prohibition on fishing those species.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d1e279">
               <num>(18)</num>
               <p>At the 11th Conference of the Parties of the Convention of Migratory Species of Wild Animals, held in Quito from 3 to 9 November 2014, a number of species were added to the lists of protected species in Appendices I and II of the Convention, with effect from 8 February 2015. Therefore, it is appropriate to provide for the protection of those species with respect to Union fishing vessels fishing in all waters and non-Union fishing vessels fishing in Union waters.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d1e295">
               <num>(19)</num>
               <p>The use of fishing opportunities available to Union fishing vessels set out in this Regulation is subject to Council Regulation (EC) No 1224/2009<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="10">
                     <p>Council Regulation (EC) No 1224/2009 of 20 November 2009 establishing a Community control system for ensuring compliance with the rules of the common fisheries policy, amending Regulations (EC) No 847/96, (EC) No 2371/2002, (EC) No 811/2004, (EC) No 768/2005, (EC) No 2115/2005, (EC) No 2166/2005, (EC) No 388/2006, (EC) No 509/2007, (EC) No 676/2007, (EC) No 1098/2007, (EC) No 1300/2008, (EC) No 1342/2008 and repealing Regulations (EEC) No 2847/93, (EC) No 1627/94 and (EC) No 1966/2006 (OJ L 343, 22.12.2009, p. 1).</p>
                  </authorialNote>, and in particular to Articles 33 and 34 of that Regulation, concerning the recording of catches and fishing effort and the notification of data on the exhaustion of fishing opportunities. It is therefore necessary to specify the codes to be used by Member States when sending data to the Commission relating to landings of stocks subject to this Regulation.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d1e311">
               <num>(20)</num>
               <p>For certain TACs Member States should be allowed to grant additional allocations for vessels participating in trials on fully documented fisheries. The aim of those trials is to test a catch-quota system in fisheries that are not yet under the landing obligation set out in Regulation (EU) No 1380/2013, i.e. a system where all catches should be landed and counted against quotas in order to avoid discards and the waste of otherwise usable fish resources they entail. Uncontrolled discards of fish are a threat to the long term sustainability of fish as a public good and thus to the Common Fisheries Policy objectives. By contrast, catch-quota systems inherently present the fishers with an incentive to optimise the catch selectivity of their operations. For the purpose of monitoring compliance with the conditions to which the fully documented fisheries trials are subject, Member States should ensure detailed and accurate documentation of all fishing trips and adequate capacity and means, such as observers, closed-circuit television (CCTV) and others. In doing so, Member States should respect the principle of efficiency and proportionality. For the use of CCTV systems, the requirements of Directive 95/46/EC of the European Parliament and of the Council<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="11">
                     <p>Directive 95/46/EC of the European Parliament and of the Council of 24 October 1995 on the protection of individuals with regard to the processing of personal data and on the free movement of such data (OJ L 281, 23.11.1995, p. 31).</p>
                  </authorialNote> should be complied with.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d1e328">
               <num>(21)</num>
               <p>In order to ensure that trials of fully documented fisheries can effectively evaluate the potential of catch-quota systems to control the absolute fishing mortality of the stocks concerned, it is necessary for all fish caught in those trials, including those under minimum landing size, to be counted against the total allocation assigned to the participating vessel, and for fishing operations to cease when that total allocation has been fully utilised by that vessel. It is also appropriate to allow transfers of allocations between vessels participating in the fully documented fisheries trials and non-participating vessels provided that it can be demonstrated that discards by non-participating vessels do not increase.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d1e334">
               <num>(22)</num>
               <p>It is appropriate, following advice from the ICES, to maintain a specific system to manage sandeel in Union waters of ICES divisions IIa and IIIa and ICES subarea IV. Given that the ICES scientific advice is expected to become available only in February 2016, it is appropriate to set the TAC and quotas for this stock provisionally at zero until such advice is released.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d1e340">
               <num>(23)</num>
               <p>In accordance with the procedure provided for in the agreements or protocols on fisheries relations with Norway<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="12">
                     <p>Agreement on fisheries between the European Economic Community and the Kingdom of Norway (OJ L 226, 29.8.1980, p. 48).</p>
                  </authorialNote> and the Faroe Islands<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="13">
                     <p>Agreement on fisheries between the European Economic Community, of the one part, and the Government of Denmark and the Home Government of the Faeroe Islands, of the other part (OJ L 226, 29.8.1980, p. 12).</p>
                  </authorialNote> the Union has held consultations on fishing rights with those partners. In accordance with the procedure provided for in the agreement and protocol on fisheries relations with Greenland<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="14">
                     <p>Fisheries Partnership Agreement between the European Community on the one hand, and the Government of Denmark and the Home Rule Government of Greenland, on the other hand (OJ L 172, 30.6.2007, p. 4) and Protocol setting out the fishing opportunities and financial contribution provided for in that Agreement (OJ L 293, 23.10.2012, p. 5).</p>
                  </authorialNote>, the Joint Committee has established the level of fishing opportunities available for the Union in Greenland waters in 2016. It is therefore necessary to include these fishing opportunities in this Regulation.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d1e370">
               <num>(24)</num>
               <p>At its Annual Meeting in 2015, NEAFC adopted a conservation measure on the redfish stock in the Irminger Sea fixing for 2016 the TAC and quotas for the contracting parties, including the Union.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d1e376">
               <num>(25)</num>
               <p>At its Annual Meeting in 2015, the International Commission for the Conservation of Atlantic Tunas (ICCAT) adopted for the 2016-2018 period a decrease of the TAC and quotas for bigeye tuna and an extension of the TACs and quotas for blue and white marlins. Furthermore, it confirmed for 2016 TACs and quotas previously established for bluefin tuna, North-Atlantic swordfish, Southern-Atlantic swordfish, Southern-Atlantic Albacore and North- Atlantic Albacore. As it is already the case for the stock of bluefin tuna, it is appropriate that catches in recreational fisheries performed on all other ICCAT stocks included in Annex ID also be subject to the catch limits adopted by that organisation in order to guarantee that the Union does not exceed its quotas. All these measures should be implemented in the law of the Union.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d1e384">
               <num>(26)</num>
               <p>At its 34<sup>th</sup> Annual Meeting in 2015, the Parties to the Commission for the Conservation of Antarctic Marine Living Resources (CCAMLR) adopted catch limits for both target and by-catch species for 2015/2016 and 2016/2017. The uptake of such quota during 2015 should be considered when setting fishing opportunities for the year 2016.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d1e393">
               <num>(27)</num>
               <p>At its Annual Meeting in 2015, the Indian Ocean Tuna Commission (IOTC) confirmed the conservation and management measures on capacity in place. The IOTC also adopted a measure on limitation of Fish Aggregating Devices (FADs). As the activities of supply vessels and the use of FADs are an integral part of the fishing effort exerted by the purse seine fleet, the measure should be implemented in the law of the Union.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d1e399">
               <num>(28)</num>
               <p>The Annual Meeting of the South Pacific Regional Fisheries Management Organisation (SPRFMO) will be held on 25-29 January 2016. It is appropriate that current measures in the SPRFMO Convention Area are provisionally maintained until such Annual Meeting is held. However, the stock of jack mackerel should not be targeted before a TAC is set as a result of that Annual Meeting.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d1e411">
               <num>(29)</num>
               <p>At its 89th Annual Meeting in 2015, the Inter-American Tropical Tuna Commission (IATTC) maintained its conservation measures for yellowfin tuna, bigeye tuna and skipjack tuna. IATTC also maintained its resolution on the conservation of oceanic whitetip sharks. Those measures should continue to be implemented in the law of the Union.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d1e417">
               <num>(30)</num>
               <p>At its Annual Meeting in 2015, the South East Atlantic Fisheries Organisation (SEAFO) adopted a conservation measure for TACs for Patagonian toothfish and deep-sea red crab, while the existing TACs for alfonsinos, orange roughy and pelagic armourhead remained in force. The currently applicable measures on allocation of fishing opportunities adopted by SEAFO should be implemented in the law of the Union.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d1e423">
               <num>(31)</num>
               <p>At its 12th Annual Meeting, the Western and Central Pacific Fisheries Commission (WCPFC) confirmed the conservation and management measures in place. Those measures should continue to be implemented in the law of the Union.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d1e430">
               <num>(32)</num>
               <p>At its Annual Meeting in 2013, the Parties to the Convention on the Conservation and Management of Pollock resources in the central Bering Sea did not modify its measures regarding fishing opportunities. Those measures should be implemented in the law of the Union.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d1e436">
               <num>(33)</num>
               <p>At its 37th Annual Meeting in 2015, the Northwest Atlantic Fisheries Organisation (NAFO) adopted a number of fishing opportunities for 2016 of certain stocks in Subareas 1-4 of the NAFO Convention Area. Those measures should be implemented in the law of the Union.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d1e442">
               <num>(34)</num>
               <p>Certain international measures which create or restrict fishing opportunities for the Union are adopted by the relevant Regional Fisheries Management Organisations (RFMOs) at the end of the year and become applicable before the entry into force of this Regulation. It is therefore necessary for the provisions that implement such measures in the law of the Union to apply retroactively. In particular, since the fishing season in CCAMLR Convention Area runs from 1 December to 30 November, and thus certain fishing opportunities or prohibitions in the CCAMLR Convention Area are laid down for a period of time starting from 1 December 2015, it is appropriate that the relevant provisions of this Regulation apply from that date. Such retroactive application does not prejudice the principle of legitimate expectations as CCAMLR members are forbidden to fish in the CCAMLR Convention Area without authorisation.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d1e451">
               <num>(35)</num>
               <p>In accordance with the declaration by the Union addressed to the Bolivarian Republic of Venezuela on the granting of fishing opportunities in EU waters to fishing vessels flying the flag of Bolivarian Republic of Venezuela in the exclusive economic zone off the coast of French Guiana<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="15">
                     <p>OJ L 6, 10.1.2012, p. 9.</p>
                  </authorialNote>, it is necessary to fix the fishing opportunities for snapper available to Venezuela in Union waters.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d1e464">
               <num>(36)</num>
               <p>Each year since 2011 Portugal has determined the TAC for the stock of whiting in ICES subareas IX and X and Union waters of CECAF 34.1.1, pursuant to relevant Regulations fixing the annual fishing opportunities. Portugal has indicated that the species caught in that area is pollack and not whiting, and ICES has confirmed that whiting is indeed rare in the area concerned. Therefore, no TAC for whiting needs to be set for this area.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d1e470">
               <num>(37)</num>
               <p>Scientific advice received from the STECF indicates that it is in line with the precautionary principle to allow a small by-catch quota for undulate ray (<i>Raja undulata</i>) in ICES subarea IX.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d1e479">
               <num>(38)</num>
               <p>In order to ensure uniform conditions for granting an individual Member State an authorisation to benefit from the system of managing its fishing effort allocations in accordance with a kilowatt days system, implementing powers should be conferred on the Commission. Those powers should be exercised in accordance with Regulation (EU) No 182/2011 of the European Parliament and of the Council<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="16">
                     <p>Regulation (EU) No 182/2011 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 16 February 2011 laying down the rules and general principles concerning mechanisms for control by Member States of the Commission&apos;s exercise of implementing powers (OJ L 55, 28.2.2011, p. 13).</p>
                  </authorialNote>.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d1e495">
               <num>(39)</num>
               <p>In order to ensure uniform conditions for the implementation of this Regulation, implementing powers should be conferred on the Commission relating to the granting of additional days at sea for permanent cessation of fishing activities and for enhanced scientific observer coverage as well as to establish the formats of spreadsheet for the collection and transmission of information concerning transfer of days at sea between fishing vessels flying the flag of a Member State.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d1e501">
               <num>(40)</num>
               <p>In order to avoid the interruption of fishing activities and to ensure the livelihood of the fishermen of the Union, this Regulation should apply from 1 January 2016, except for the provisions concerning fishing effort limits, which should apply from 1 February 2016, and certain provisions in particular regions, which should have a specific date of application. For reasons of urgency, this Regulation should enter into force immediately after its publication.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d1e513">
               <num>(41)</num>
               <p>Fishing opportunities should be used in full compliance with the applicable law of the Union.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d1e520">
               <num>(42)</num>
               <p>According to Article 3(1) of Council Regulation (EC) No 847/96, when more than 75 % of a precautionary TAC has been utilized before 31 October of the year of its application, a Member State with a quota may request an increase in the TAC. The Commission has received a request for a 10 % increase of the 2015 TAC for skates and rays in the Eastern Channel (ICES division VIId). The supporting biological information, submitted with the request, has been verified and validated by experts at the Commission&apos;s Joint Research Centre.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d1e526">
               <num>(43)</num>
               <p>Council Regulation (EU) 2015/104<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="17">
                     <p>Council Regulation (EU) 2015/104 of 19 January 2015 fixing for 2015 the fishing opportunities for certain fish stocks and groups of fish stocks, applicable in Union waters and, for Union vessels, in certain non-Union waters, amending Regulation (EU) No 43/2014 and repealing Regulation (EU) No 779/2014 (OJ L 22, 28.1.2015, p. 1).</p>
                  </authorialNote> should therefore be amended accordingly.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d1e542">
               <num>(44)</num>
               <p>The TAC for skates and rays in the Eastern Channel (ICES division VIId) provided for in Regulation (EU) 2015/104 applies from 1 January 2015. The amending provisions set out in this Regulation should also apply from that date. Such retroactive application does not prejudice the principles of legal certainty and protection of legitimate expectations as the fishing opportunities concerned are increased compared to the opportunities established in Regulation (EU) 2015/104,</p>
            </recital>
         </recitals>
         <formula name="enactingFormula">
            <p>HAS ADOPTED THIS REGULATION:</p>
         </formula>
      </preamble>
      <body>
         <title>
            <num>TITLE I</num>
            <heading>GENERAL PROVISIONS</heading>
            <article xml:id="art_d1e563">
               <num>Article 1</num>
               <heading>Subject matter</heading>
               <paragraph>
                  <num>1.</num>
                  <content>
                     <p>This Regulation fixes the fishing opportunities available in Union waters and, to Union fishing vessels, in certain non-Union waters for certain fish stocks and groups of fish stocks.</p>
                  </content>
               </paragraph>
               <paragraph>
                  <num>2.</num>
                  <subparagraph>
                     <content>
                        <p>The fishing opportunities referred to in paragraph 1 include:</p>
                     </content>
                  </subparagraph>
                  <list>
                     <point>
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <content>
                           <p>catch limits for the year 2016 and, where specified in this Regulation, for the year 2017;</p>
                        </content>
                     </point>
                     <point>
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <content>
                           <p>fishing effort limits for the period from 1 February 2016 to 31 January 2017, except where other periods are established for effort limits in Articles 9, 31 and 32 and Annex IIE;</p>
                        </content>
                     </point>
                     <point>
                        <num>(c)</num>
                        <content>
                           <p>fishing opportunities for the period from 1 December 2015 to 30 November 2016 for certain stocks in the CCAMLR Convention Area;</p>
                        </content>
                     </point>
                     <point>
                        <num>(d)</num>
                        <content>
                           <p>fishing opportunities for certain stocks in the IATTC Convention Area set out in Article 28 for the periods in 2016 and 2017 specified in that provision.</p>
                        </content>
                     </point>
                  </list>
               </paragraph>
            </article>
            <article xml:id="art_d1e617">
               <num>Article 2</num>
               <heading>Scope</heading>
               <paragraph>
                  <subparagraph>
                     <content>
                        <p>This Regulation shall apply to the following vessels:</p>
                     </content>
                  </subparagraph>
                  <list>
                     <point>
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <content>
                           <p>Union fishing vessels;</p>
                        </content>
                     </point>
                     <point>
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <content>
                           <p>third-country vessels in Union waters.</p>
                        </content>
                     </point>
                  </list>
               </paragraph>
               <paragraph>
                  <content>
                     <p>This Regulation shall also apply to recreational fisheries where they are expressly referred to in the relevant provisions.</p>
                  </content>
               </paragraph>
            </article>
            <article xml:id="art_d1e640">
               <num>Article 3</num>
               <heading>Definitions</heading>
               <paragraph>
                  <subparagraph>
                     <content>
                        <p>For the purposes of this Regulation, the definitions referred to in Article 4 of Regulation (EU) No 1380/2013 apply. In addition, the following definitions shall apply:</p>
                     </content>
                  </subparagraph>
                  <list>
                     <point>
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <content>
                           <p>&apos;third-country vessel&apos; means a fishing vessel flying the flag of, and registered in, a third country.</p>
                        </content>
                     </point>
                     <point>
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <content>
                           <p>&apos;recreational fisheries&apos; means non-commercial fishing activities exploiting marine living aquatic resources such as for recreation, tourism or sport.</p>
                        </content>
                     </point>
                     <point>
                        <num>(c)</num>
                        <content>
                           <p>&apos;international waters&apos; means waters falling outside the sovereignty or jurisdiction of any State;</p>
                        </content>
                     </point>
                     <point>
                        <num>(d)</num>
                        <alinea>
                           <content>
                              <p>&apos;total allowable catch&apos; (TAC) means:</p>
                           </content>
                        </alinea>
                        <list>
                           <point>
                              <num>(i)</num>
                              <content>
                                 <p>in fisheries subject to the landing obligation referred to in Article 15 of Regulation (EU) No 1380/2013, the quantity of fish that can be caught from each stock each year;</p>
                              </content>
                           </point>
                           <point>
                              <num>(ii)</num>
                              <content>
                                 <p>in all other fisheries, the quantity of fish that can be landed from each stock each year;</p>
                              </content>
                           </point>
                        </list>
                     </point>
                     <point>
                        <num>(e)</num>
                        <content>
                           <p>&apos;quota&apos; means a proportion of the TAC allocated to the Union, a Member State or a third country;</p>
                        </content>
                     </point>
                     <point>
                        <num>(f)</num>
                        <content>
                           <p>&apos;analytical assessments&apos; means a quantitative evaluation of trends in a given stock, based on data about the stock&apos;s biology and exploitation, which scientific review has indicated to be of sufficient quality to provide scientific advice on options for future catches;</p>
                        </content>
                     </point>
                     <point>
                        <num>(g)</num>
                        <content>
                           <p>&apos;mesh size&apos; means the mesh size of fishing nets as determined in accordance with Commission Regulation (EC) No 517/2008<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="18">
                                 <p>Commission Regulation (EC) No 517/2008 of 10 June 2008 laying down detailed rules for the implementation of Council Regulation (EC) No 850/98 as regards the determination of the mesh size and assessing the thickness of twine of fishing nets (OJ L 151, 11.6.2008, p. 5).</p>
                              </authorialNote>;</p>
                        </content>
                     </point>
                     <point>
                        <num>(h)</num>
                        <content>
                           <p>&apos;Union fishing fleet register&apos; means the register set up by the Commission in accordance with Article 24(3) of Regulation (EU) No 1380/2013;</p>
                        </content>
                     </point>
                     <point>
                        <num>(i)</num>
                        <content>
                           <p>&apos;fishing logbook&apos; means the logbook referred to in Article 14 of Regulation (EC) No 1224/2009.</p>
                        </content>
                     </point>
                  </list>
               </paragraph>
            </article>
            <article xml:id="art_d1e755">
               <num>Article 4</num>
               <heading>Fishing zones</heading>
               <paragraph>
                  <subparagraph>
                     <content>
                        <p>For the purposes of this Regulation the following zone definitions shall apply:</p>
                     </content>
                  </subparagraph>
                  <list>
                     <point>
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <content>
                           <p>ICES (International Council for the Exploration of the Sea) zones are the geographical areas specified in Annex III to Regulation (EC) No 218/2009<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="19">
                                 <p>Regulation (EC) No 218/2009 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 11 March 2009 on the submission of nominal catch statistics by Member States fishing in the north-east Atlantic (OJ L 87, 31.3.2009, p. 70).</p>
                              </authorialNote>;</p>
                        </content>
                     </point>
                     <point>
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <content>
                           <p>&apos;Skagerrak&apos; means the geographical area bounded on the west by a line drawn from the Hanstholm lighthouse to the Lindesnes lighthouse and on the south by a line drawn from the Skagen lighthouse to the Tistlarna lighthouse and from this point to the nearest point on the Swedish coast;</p>
                        </content>
                     </point>
                     <point>
                        <num>(c)</num>
                        <content>
                           <p>&apos;Kattegat&apos; means the geographical area bounded on the north by a line drawn from the Skagen lighthouse to the Tistlarna lighthouse and from this point to the nearest point on the Swedish coast and on the south by a line drawn from Hasenøre to Gnibens Spids, from Korshage to Spodsbjerg and from Gilbjerg Hoved to Kullen;</p>
                        </content>
                     </point>
                     <point>
                        <num>(d)</num>
                        <alinea>
                           <content>
                              <p>&apos;Functional Unit 16 of ICES subarea VII&apos; means the geographical area bounded by rhumb lines sequentially joining the following positions:</p>
                           </content>
                        </alinea>
                        <list>
                           <indent>
                              <num>-</num>
                              <content>
                                 <p>53° 30′ N 15° 00′ W,</p>
                              </content>
                           </indent>
                           <indent>
                              <num>-</num>
                              <content>
                                 <p>53° 30′ N 11° 00′ W,</p>
                              </content>
                           </indent>
                           <indent>
                              <num>-</num>
                              <content>
                                 <p>51° 30′ N 11° 00′ W,</p>
                              </content>
                           </indent>
                           <indent>
                              <num>-</num>
                              <content>
                                 <p>51° 30′ N 13° 00′ W,</p>
                              </content>
                           </indent>
                           <indent>
                              <num>-</num>
                              <content>
                                 <p>51° 00′ N 13° 00′ W,</p>
                              </content>
                           </indent>
                           <indent>
                              <num>-</num>
                              <content>
                                 <p>51° 00′ N 15° 00′ W,</p>
                              </content>
                           </indent>
                           <indent>
                              <num>-</num>
                              <content>
                                 <p>53° 30′ N 15° 00′ W;</p>
                              </content>
                           </indent>
                        </list>
                     </point>
                     <point>
                        <num>(e)</num>
                        <alinea>
                           <content>
                              <p>&apos;Functional Unit 26 of ICES division IXa&apos; means the geographical area bounded by rhumb lines sequentially joining the following positions:</p>
                           </content>
                        </alinea>
                        <list>
                           <indent>
                              <num>-</num>
                              <content>
                                 <p>43° 00′ N 8° 00′ W,</p>
                              </content>
                           </indent>
                           <indent>
                              <num>-</num>
                              <content>
                                 <p>43° 00′ N 10° 00′ W,</p>
                              </content>
                           </indent>
                           <indent>
                              <num>-</num>
                              <content>
                                 <p>42° 00′ N 10° 00′ W,</p>
                              </content>
                           </indent>
                           <indent>
                              <num>-</num>
                              <content>
                                 <p>42° 00′ N 8° 00′ W;</p>
                              </content>
                           </indent>
                        </list>
                     </point>
                     <point>
                        <num>(f)</num>
                        <alinea>
                           <content>
                              <p>&apos;Functional Unit 27 of ICES division IXa&apos; means the geographical area bounded by rhumb lines sequentially joining the following positions:</p>
                           </content>
                        </alinea>
                        <list>
                           <indent>
                              <num>-</num>
                              <content>
                                 <p>42° 00′ N 8° 00′ W,</p>
                              </content>
                           </indent>
                           <indent>
                              <num>-</num>
                              <content>
                                 <p>42° 00′ N 10° 00′ W,</p>
                              </content>
                           </indent>
                           <indent>
                              <num>-</num>
                              <content>
                                 <p>38° 30′ N 10° 00′ W,</p>
                              </content>
                           </indent>
                           <indent>
                              <num>-</num>
                              <content>
                                 <p>38° 30′ N 9° 00′ W,</p>
                              </content>
                           </indent>
                           <indent>
                              <num>-</num>
                              <content>
                                 <p>40° 00′ N 9° 00′ W,</p>
                              </content>
                           </indent>
                           <indent>
                              <num>-</num>
                              <content>
                                 <p>40° 00′ N 8° 00′ W;</p>
                              </content>
                           </indent>
                        </list>
                     </point>
                     <point>
                        <num>(g)</num>
                        <content>
                           <p>&apos;Gulf of Cádiz&apos; means the geographical area of ICES division IXa east of longitude 7° 23′ 48″ W;</p>
                        </content>
                     </point>
                     <point>
                        <num>(h)</num>
                        <content>
                           <p>CECAF (Committee for Eastern Central Atlantic Fisheries) areas are the geographical areas specified in Annex II to Regulation (EC) No 216/2009 of the European Parliament and of the Council<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="20">
                                 <p>Regulation (EC) No 216/2009 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 11 March 2009 on the submission of nominal catch statistics by Member States fishing in certain areas other than those of the North Atlantic (OJ L 87, 31.3.2009, p. 1).</p>
                              </authorialNote>;</p>
                        </content>
                     </point>
                     <point>
                        <num>(i)</num>
                        <content>
                           <p>NAFO (Northwest Atlantic Fisheries Organisation) areas are the geographical areas specified in Annex III to Regulation (EC) No 217/2009 of the European Parliament and of the Council<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="21">
                                 <p>Regulation (EC) No 217/2009 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 11 March 2009 on the submission of catch and activity statistics by Member States fishing in the north-west Atlantic (OJ L 87, 31.3.2009, p. 42).</p>
                              </authorialNote>;</p>
                        </content>
                     </point>
                     <point>
                        <num>(j)</num>
                        <content>
                           <p>&apos;SEAFO (South East Atlantic Fisheries Organisation) Convention Area&apos; is the geographical area defined in the Convention on the Conservation and Management of Fishery Resources in the South-East Atlantic Ocean<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="22">
                                 <p>Concluded by Council Decision 2002/738/EC (OJ L 234, 31.8.2002, p. 39).</p>
                              </authorialNote>;</p>
                        </content>
                     </point>
                     <point>
                        <num>(k)</num>
                        <content>
                           <p>&apos;ICCAT (International Commission for the Conservation of Atlantic Tunas) Convention Area&apos; is the geographical area defined in the International Convention for the Conservation of Atlantic Tunas<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="23">
                                 <p>The Union acceded by Council Decision 86/238/EEC (OJ L 162, 18.6.1986, p. 33).</p>
                              </authorialNote>;</p>
                        </content>
                     </point>
                     <point>
                        <num>(l)</num>
                        <content>
                           <p>&apos;CCAMLR (Commission for the Conservation of Antarctic Marine Living Resources) Convention Area&apos; is the geographical area defined in point (a) of Article 2 of Regulation (EC) No 601/2004<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="24">
                                 <p>Council Regulation (EC) No 601/2004 of 22 March 2004 laying down certain control measures applicable to fishing activities in the area covered by the Convention on the conservation of Antarctic marine living resources and repealing Regulations (EEC) No 3943/90, (EC) No 66/98 and (EC) No 1721/1999 (OJ L 97, 1.4.2004, p. 16).</p>
                              </authorialNote>;</p>
                        </content>
                     </point>
                     <point>
                        <num>(m)</num>
                        <content>
                           <p>&apos;IATTC (Inter-American Tropical Tuna Commission) Convention Area&apos; is the geographical area defined in the Convention for the Strengthening of the Inter-American Tropical Tuna Commission established by the 1949 Convention between the United States of America and the Republic of Costa Rica (&apos;the Antigua Convention&apos;)<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="25">
                                 <p>Concluded by Council Decision 2006/539/EC (OJ L 224, 16.8.2006, p. 22).</p>
                              </authorialNote>;</p>
                        </content>
                     </point>
                     <point>
                        <num>(n)</num>
                        <content>
                           <p>&apos;IOTC (Indian Ocean Tuna Commission) Convention Area&apos; is the geographical area defined in the Agreement for the establishment of the Indian Ocean Tuna Commission<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="26">
                                 <p>The Union acceded by Council Decision 95/399/EC (OJ L 236, 5.10.1995, p. 24).</p>
                              </authorialNote>;</p>
                        </content>
                     </point>
                     <point>
                        <num>(o)</num>
                        <content>
                           <p>&apos;SPRFMO (South Pacific Regional Fisheries Management Organisation) Convention Area&apos; is the high seas geographical area south of 10° N, north of the CCAMLR Convention Area, east of the SIOFA Convention Area as defined in the Southern Indian Ocean Fisheries Agreement<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="27">
                                 <p>Concluded by Council Decision 2008/780/EC (OJ L 268, 9.10.2008, p. 27).</p>
                              </authorialNote>, and west of the areas of fisheries jurisdictions of South American States;</p>
                        </content>
                     </point>
                     <point>
                        <num>(p)</num>
                        <content>
                           <p>&apos;the WCPFC (Western and Central Pacific Fisheries Commission) Convention Area&apos; is the geographical area defined in the Convention on the Conservation and Management of Highly Migratory Fish Stocks in the Western and Central Pacific Ocean<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="28">
                                 <p>The Union acceded by Council Decision 2005/75/EC (OJ L 32, 4.2.2005, p. 1).</p>
                              </authorialNote>;</p>
                        </content>
                     </point>
                     <point>
                        <num>(q)</num>
                        <content>
                           <p>&apos;high seas of the Bering Sea&apos; is the geographical area of the high seas of the Bering Sea beyond 200 nautical miles from the baselines from which the breadth of the territorial sea of the coastal States of the Bering Sea is measured;</p>
                        </content>
                     </point>
                     <point>
                        <num>(r)</num>
                        <alinea>
                           <content>
                              <p>&apos;overlap area between IATTC and WCPFC&apos; is the geographical area defined by the following limits:</p>
                           </content>
                        </alinea>
                        <list>
                           <indent>
                              <num>-</num>
                              <content>
                                 <p>longitude 150° W,</p>
                              </content>
                           </indent>
                           <indent>
                              <num>-</num>
                              <content>
                                 <p>longitude 130° W,</p>
                              </content>
                           </indent>
                           <indent>
                              <num>-</num>
                              <content>
                                 <p>latitude 4° S,</p>
                              </content>
                           </indent>
                           <indent>
                              <num>-</num>
                              <content>
                                 <p>latitude 50° S.</p>
                              </content>
                           </indent>
                        </list>
                     </point>
                  </list>
               </paragraph>
            </article>
         </title>
         <title>
            <num>TITLE II</num>
            <heading>FISHING OPPORTUNITIES FOR UNION FISHING VESSELS</heading>
            <chapter>
               <num>CHAPTER I</num>
               <heading>General provisions</heading>
               <article xml:id="art_d1e1096">
                  <num>Article 5</num>
                  <heading>TACs and allocations</heading>
                  <paragraph>
                     <num>1.</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>The TACs for Union fishing vessels in Union waters or certain non-Union waters and the allocation of such TACs among Member States, and the conditions functionally linked thereto, where appropriate, are set out in Annex I.</p>
                     </content>
                  </paragraph>
                  <paragraph>
                     <num>2.</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>Union fishing vessels shall be authorised to make catches, within the TACs set out in Annex I, in waters falling within the fisheries jurisdiction of the Faroe Islands, Greenland, Iceland and Norway, and the fishing zone around Jan Mayen, subject to the condition set out in Article 15 of and Annex III to this Regulation and in Regulation (EC) No 1006/2008<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="29">
                              <p>Council Regulation (EC) No 1006/2008 of 29 September 2008 concerning authorisations for fishing activities of Community fishing vessels outside Community waters and the access of third-country vessels to Community waters, amending Regulations (EEC) No 2847/93 and (EC) No 1627/94 and repealing Regulation (EC) No 3317/94 (OJ L 286, 29.10.2008, p. 33).</p>
                           </authorialNote> and its implementing provisions.</p>
                     </content>
                  </paragraph>
               </article>
               <article xml:id="art_d1e1122">
                  <num>Article 6</num>
                  <heading>TACs to be determined by Member States</heading>
                  <paragraph>
                     <num>1.</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>The TACs for certain fish stocks shall be determined by the Member State concerned. Those stocks are identified in Annex I.</p>
                     </content>
                  </paragraph>
                  <paragraph>
                     <num>2.</num>
                     <subparagraph>
                        <content>
                           <p>The TACs to be determined by a Member State shall:</p>
                        </content>
                     </subparagraph>
                     <list>
                        <point>
                           <num>(a)</num>
                           <content>
                              <p>be consistent with the principles and rules of the Common Fisheries Policy, in particular the principle of sustainable exploitation of the stock; and</p>
                           </content>
                        </point>
                        <point>
                           <num>(b)</num>
                           <alinea>
                              <content>
                                 <p>result:</p>
                              </content>
                           </alinea>
                           <list>
                              <point>
                                 <num>(i)</num>
                                 <content>
                                    <p>if analytical assessments are available, in the exploitation of the stock consistent with maximum sustainable yield from 2016 onwards, with as high a probability as possible;</p>
                                 </content>
                              </point>
                              <point>
                                 <num>(ii)</num>
                                 <content>
                                    <p>if analytical assessments are unavailable or incomplete, in the exploitation of the stock consistent with the precautionary approach to fisheries management.</p>
                                 </content>
                              </point>
                           </list>
                        </point>
                     </list>
                  </paragraph>
                  <paragraph>
                     <num>3.</num>
                     <subparagraph>
                        <content>
                           <p>By 15 March 2016, each Member State concerned shall submit the following information to the Commission:</p>
                        </content>
                     </subparagraph>
                     <list>
                        <point>
                           <num>(a)</num>
                           <content>
                              <p>the TACs adopted;</p>
                           </content>
                        </point>
                        <point>
                           <num>(b)</num>
                           <content>
                              <p>the data collected and assessed by the Member State concerned on which the TACs adopted are based;</p>
                           </content>
                        </point>
                        <point>
                           <num>(c)</num>
                           <content>
                              <p>details on how the TACs adopted comply with paragraph 2.</p>
                           </content>
                        </point>
                     </list>
                  </paragraph>
               </article>
               <article xml:id="art_d1e1193">
                  <num>Article 7</num>
                  <heading>Conditions for landing catches and by-catches</heading>
                  <paragraph>
                     <num>1.</num>
                     <subparagraph>
                        <content>
                           <p>Catches that are not subject to the landing obligation established in Article 15 of Regulation (EU) No 1380/2013 shall be retained on board or landed only if they:</p>
                        </content>
                     </subparagraph>
                     <list>
                        <point>
                           <num>(a)</num>
                           <content>
                              <p>have been taken by vessels flying the flag of a Member State having a quota and that quota has not been exhausted; or</p>
                           </content>
                        </point>
                        <point>
                           <num>(b)</num>
                           <content>
                              <p>consist of a share in a Union quota which has not been allocated by quota among Member States, and that Union quota has not been exhausted.</p>
                           </content>
                        </point>
                     </list>
                  </paragraph>
                  <paragraph>
                     <num>2.</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>The stocks of non-target species within safe biological limits referred to in Article 15(8) of Regulation (EU) No 1380/2013 are identified in Annex I of this Regulation for the purposes of the derogation from the obligation to count catches against the relevant quotas provided for in that Article.</p>
                     </content>
                  </paragraph>
               </article>
               <article xml:id="art_d1e1222">
                  <num>Article 8</num>
                  <heading>Fishing effort limits</heading>
                  <paragraph>
                     <subparagraph>
                        <content>
                           <p>For the periods referred to in Article 1(2)(b), the following fishing effort measures shall apply:</p>
                        </content>
                     </subparagraph>
                     <list>
                        <point>
                           <num>(a)</num>
                           <content>
                              <p>Annex IIA for the management of certain cod, sole, and plaice stocks in the Kattegat, the Skagerrak, that part of ICES division IIIa not covered by the Skagerrak and the Kattegat, ICES subarea IV and ICES divisions VIa, VIIa and VIId and Union waters of ICES divisions IIa and Vb;</p>
                           </content>
                        </point>
                        <point>
                           <num>(b)</num>
                           <content>
                              <p>Annex IIB for the recovery of hake and Norway lobster in ICES divisions VIIIc and IXa, with the exception of the Gulf of Cádiz;</p>
                           </content>
                        </point>
                        <point>
                           <num>(c)</num>
                           <content>
                              <p>Annex IIC for the management of the sole stock in ICES division VIIe.</p>
                           </content>
                        </point>
                     </list>
                  </paragraph>
               </article>
               <article xml:id="art_d1e1250">
                  <num>Article 9</num>
                  <heading>Catch and effort limits for deep-sea fisheries</heading>
                  <paragraph>
                     <num>1.</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>Article 3(1) of Regulation (EC) No 2347/2002<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="30">
                              <p>Council Regulation (EC) No 2347/2002 of 16 December 2002 establishing specific access requirements and associated conditions applicable to fishing for deep-sea stocks (OJ L 351, 28.12.2002, p. 6).</p>
                           </authorialNote> establishing the requirement of holding a deep-sea fishing permit shall apply to Greenland halibut. The catching, retaining on board, transhipping and landing of Greenland halibut shall be subject to the conditions referred to in that Article.</p>
                     </content>
                  </paragraph>
                  <paragraph>
                     <num>2.</num>
                     <subparagraph>
                        <content>
                           <p>This paragraph shall apply only to fishing trips on which more than 100 kg of deep-sea species, other than greater silver smelt, are caught.</p>
                        </content>
                     </subparagraph>
                     <subparagraph>
                        <content>
                           <p>Member States shall ensure that for 2016 the fishing effort levels, measured in kilowatt days absent from port, by vessels holding deep-sea fishing permits referred to in Article 3(1) of Regulation (EC) No 2347/2002, do not exceed 65 % of the average annual fishing effort deployed by the vessels of the Member State concerned in 2003 on trips when deep-sea fishing permits were held or deep-sea species, as listed in Annexes I and II to that Regulation, were caught.</p>
                        </content>
                     </subparagraph>
                  </paragraph>
               </article>
               <article xml:id="art_d1e1277">
                  <num>Article 10</num>
                  <heading>Measures on Sea bass fisheries</heading>
                  <paragraph>
                     <num>1.</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>It shall be prohibited for Union fishing vessels to fish for sea bass in ICES divisions VIIb, VIIc, VIIj and VIIk, as well as in the waters of ICES divisions VIIa and VIIg that are more than 12 nautical miles from the baseline under the sovereignty of the United Kingdom. It shall be prohibited for Union fishing vessels to retain on board, tranship, relocate or land sea bass caught in that area.</p>
                     </content>
                  </paragraph>
                  <paragraph>
                     <num>2.</num>
                     <subparagraph>
                        <content>
                           <p>From 1 January to 30 June 2016, it shall be prohibited for Union fishing vessels to fish for sea bass and to retain on board, relocate, tranship or land sea bass caught in the following areas:</p>
                        </content>
                     </subparagraph>
                     <list>
                        <point>
                           <num>(a)</num>
                           <content>
                              <p>ICES divisions IVb, IVc, VIId, VIIe, VIIf and VIIh;</p>
                           </content>
                        </point>
                        <point>
                           <num>(b)</num>
                           <content>
                              <p>waters within 12 nautical miles from baseline under the sovereignty of the United Kingdom in ICES divisions VIIa and VIIg.</p>
                           </content>
                        </point>
                     </list>
                     <subparagraph>
                        <content>
                           <p>By derogation from the first subparagraph, the following measures shall apply in the areas referred to in that subparagraph:</p>
                        </content>
                     </subparagraph>
                     <list>
                        <point>
                           <num>(a)</num>
                           <content>
                              <p>a Union fishing vessel deploying demersal trawls and seines<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="31">
                                    <p>All types of demersal trawls including Danish/Scottish seines, including OTB, OTT, PTB, TBB, SSC, SDN, SPR, SV, SB, SX, TBN, TBS, TB.</p>
                                 </authorialNote> may retain on board catches of sea bass that do not exceed 1 % of the weight of the total catches of marine organisms on board;</p>
                           </content>
                        </point>
                        <point>
                           <num>(b)</num>
                           <content>
                              <p>in January 2016 and from 1 April to 30 June 2016, Union fishing vessels using hooks and lines, and fixed gillnets<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="32">
                                    <p>All long lines or pole and line or rod and line fisheries, including LHP, LHM, LLD, LL, LTL, LX and LLS, all fixed gillnets and traps, including GTR, GNS, FYK, FPN and FIX.</p>
                                 </authorialNote> may fish for sea bass and retain on board, relocate, tranship or land sea bass caught in that area not exceeding 1300 kilograms per any vessel per month.</p>
                           </content>
                        </point>
                     </list>
                  </paragraph>
                  <paragraph>
                     <num>3.</num>
                     <subparagraph>
                        <content>
                           <p>From 1 July to 31 December 2016 it shall be prohibited for Union fishing vessels using hooks, lines and fixed gillnets to fish for sea bass in quantities exceeding 1300 kilograms per any vessel per month and for Union fishing vessels using other gears to fish for sea bass in quantities exceeding 1000 kilograms per any vessel per month in the following areas:</p>
                        </content>
                     </subparagraph>
                     <list>
                        <point>
                           <num>(a)</num>
                           <content>
                              <p>ICES divisions IVb, IVc, VIId, VIIe, VIIf and VIIh;</p>
                           </content>
                        </point>
                        <point>
                           <num>(b)</num>
                           <content>
                              <p>waters within 12 nautical miles from baseline under the sovereignty of the United Kingdom in ICES divisions VIIa and VIIg.</p>
                           </content>
                        </point>
                     </list>
                     <subparagraph>
                        <content>
                           <p>During that period, it shall also be prohibited for Union fishing vessels to retain on board, relocate, tranship or land quantities of sea bass exceeding the quantities set in the first subparagraph caught in those areas.</p>
                        </content>
                     </subparagraph>
                  </paragraph>
                  <paragraph>
                     <num>4.</num>
                     <subparagraph>
                        <content>
                           <p>The catch limits set in paragraphs 2 and 3 shall not be transferable from one month to another or between vessels. Member States shall report to the Commission catches of sea bass per type of gear not later than 20 days after the end of each month.</p>
                        </content>
                     </subparagraph>
                     <subparagraph>
                        <content>
                           <p>For Union fishing vessels using more than one gear in a single calendar month, the lowest catch limit set in paragraph 3 for either gear shall apply.</p>
                        </content>
                     </subparagraph>
                  </paragraph>
                  <paragraph>
                     <num>5.</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>From 1 January to 30 June 2016 in recreational fisheries in ICES divisions IVb, IVc, VIIa and from VIId to VIIh, only catch-and-release fishing for sea bass, including from shore, shall be allowed. During this period, it shall be prohibited to retain on board, relocate, tranship or land sea bass caught in that area.</p>
                     </content>
                  </paragraph>
                  <paragraph>
                     <num>6.</num>
                     <subparagraph>
                        <content>
                           <p>In recreational fisheries, including from shore, not more than one specimen of sea bass may be retained per fisherman per day during the following periods and in the following areas:</p>
                        </content>
                     </subparagraph>
                     <list>
                        <point>
                           <num>(a)</num>
                           <content>
                              <p>from 1 July to 31 December 2016 in ICES divisions IVb, IVc, VIIa and from VIId to VIIh;</p>
                           </content>
                        </point>
                        <point>
                           <num>(b)</num>
                           <content>
                              <p>from 1 January to 31 December 2016 in ICES divisions VIIj and VIIk.</p>
                           </content>
                        </point>
                     </list>
                  </paragraph>
               </article>
               <article xml:id="art_d1e1428">
                  <num>Article 11</num>
                  <heading>Special provisions on allocations of fishing opportunities</heading>
                  <paragraph>
                     <num>1.</num>
                     <subparagraph>
                        <content>
                           <p>The allocation of fishing opportunities among Member States as set out in this Regulation is without prejudice to:</p>
                        </content>
                     </subparagraph>
                     <list>
                        <point>
                           <num>(a)</num>
                           <content>
                              <p>exchanges made pursuant to Article 16(8) of Regulation (EU) No 1380/2013;</p>
                           </content>
                        </point>
                        <point>
                           <num>(b)</num>
                           <content>
                              <p>deductions and reallocations made pursuant to Article 37 of Regulation (EC) No 1224/2009;</p>
                           </content>
                        </point>
                        <point>
                           <num>(c)</num>
                           <content>
                              <p>reallocations made pursuant to Article 10(4) of Regulation (EC) No 1006/2008;</p>
                           </content>
                        </point>
                        <point>
                           <num>(d)</num>
                           <content>
                              <p>additional landings allowed under Article 3 of Regulation (EC) No 847/96 and Article 15(9) of Regulation 1380/2013;</p>
                           </content>
                        </point>
                        <point>
                           <num>(e)</num>
                           <content>
                              <p>quantities withheld in accordance with Article 4 of Regulation (EC) No 847/96 and Article 15(9) of Regulation 1380/2013;</p>
                           </content>
                        </point>
                        <point>
                           <num>(f)</num>
                           <content>
                              <p>deductions made pursuant to Articles 105, 106 and 107 of Regulation (EC) No 1224/2009;</p>
                           </content>
                        </point>
                        <point>
                           <num>(g)</num>
                           <content>
                              <p>quota transfers and exchanges pursuant to Article 21 of this Regulation</p>
                           </content>
                        </point>
                        <point>
                           <num>(h)</num>
                           <content>
                              <p>additional allocations pursuant to Article 15 of this Regulation.</p>
                           </content>
                        </point>
                     </list>
                  </paragraph>
                  <paragraph>
                     <num>2.</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>Stocks which are subject to precautionary or analytical TACs are identified in Annex I to this Regulation for the purposes of the year-to-year management of TACs and quotas provided for in Regulation (EC) No 847/96.</p>
                     </content>
                  </paragraph>
                  <paragraph>
                     <num>3.</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>Except where otherwise specified in Annex I to this Regulation, Article 3 of Regulation (EC) No 847/96 shall apply to stocks subject to a precautionary TAC and Article 3(2) and (3) and Article 4 of that Regulation shall apply to stocks subject to an analytical TAC.</p>
                     </content>
                  </paragraph>
                  <paragraph>
                     <num>4.</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>Articles 3 and 4 of Regulation (EC) No 847/96 shall not apply where a Member State uses the year-to-year flexibility provided for in Article 15(9) of Regulation (EU) No 1380/2013.</p>
                     </content>
                  </paragraph>
               </article>
               <article xml:id="art_d1e1504">
                  <num>Article 12</num>
                  <heading>Closed fishing seasons</heading>
                  <paragraph>
                     <num>1.</num>
                     <subparagraph>
                        <content>
                           <p>It shall be prohibited to fish or retain on board any of the following species in the Porcupine Bank during the period from 1 May to 31 May 2016: cod, megrims, anglerfish, haddock, whiting, hake, Norway lobster, plaice, pollack, saithe, skates and rays, common sole, tusk, blue ling, ling and spurdog.</p>
                        </content>
                     </subparagraph>
                     <subparagraph>
                        <content>
                           <p>For the purposes of this paragraph, the Porcupine Bank shall comprise the geographical area bounded by rhumb lines sequentially joining the following positions:</p>
                        </content>
                     </subparagraph>
                     <subparagraph>
                        <content>
                           <table class="TBL">
                              <tr>
                                 <th>
                                    <p>Point</p>
                                 </th>
                                 <th>
                                    <p>Latitude</p>
                                 </th>
                                 <th>
                                    <p>Longitude</p>
                                 </th>
                              </tr>
                              <tr>
                                 <td>
                                    <p>1</p>
                                 </td>
                                 <td>
                                    <p>52° 27′ N</p>
                                 </td>
                                 <td>
                                    <p>12° 19′ W</p>
                                 </td>
                              </tr>
                              <tr>
                                 <td>
                                    <p>2</p>
                                 </td>
                                 <td>
                                    <p>52° 40′ N</p>
                                 </td>
                                 <td>
                                    <p>12° 30′ W</p>
                                 </td>
                              </tr>
                              <tr>
                                 <td>
                                    <p>3</p>
                                 </td>
                                 <td>
                                    <p>52° 47′ N</p>
                                 </td>
                                 <td>
                                    <p>12° 39,600′ W</p>
                                 </td>
                              </tr>
                              <tr>
                                 <td>
                                    <p>4</p>
                                 </td>
                                 <td>
                                    <p>52° 47′ N</p>
                                 </td>
                                 <td>
                                    <p>12° 56′ W</p>
                                 </td>
                              </tr>
                              <tr>
                                 <td>
                                    <p>5</p>
                                 </td>
                                 <td>
                                    <p>52° 13,5′ N</p>
                                 </td>
                                 <td>
                                    <p>13° 53,830′ W</p>
                                 </td>
                              </tr>
                              <tr>
                                 <td>
                                    <p>6</p>
                                 </td>
                                 <td>
                                    <p>51° 22′ N</p>
                                 </td>
                                 <td>
                                    <p>14° 24′ W</p>
                                 </td>
                              </tr>
                              <tr>
                                 <td>
                                    <p>7</p>
                                 </td>
                                 <td>
                                    <p>51° 22′ N</p>
                                 </td>
                                 <td>
                                    <p>14° 03′ W</p>
                                 </td>
                              </tr>
                              <tr>
                                 <td>
                                    <p>8</p>
                                 </td>
                                 <td>
                                    <p>52° 10′ N</p>
                                 </td>
                                 <td>
                                    <p>13° 25′ W</p>
                                 </td>
                              </tr>
                              <tr>
                                 <td>
                                    <p>9</p>
                                 </td>
                                 <td>
                                    <p>52° 32′ N</p>
                                 </td>
                                 <td>
                                    <p>13° 07,500′ W</p>
                                 </td>
                              </tr>
                              <tr>
                                 <td>
                                    <p>10</p>
                                 </td>
                                 <td>
                                    <p>52° 43′ N</p>
                                 </td>
                                 <td>
                                    <p>12° 55′ W</p>
                                 </td>
                              </tr>
                              <tr>
                                 <td>
                                    <p>11</p>
                                 </td>
                                 <td>
                                    <p>52° 43′ N</p>
                                 </td>
                                 <td>
                                    <p>12° 43′ W</p>
                                 </td>
                              </tr>
                              <tr>
                                 <td>
                                    <p>12</p>
                                 </td>
                                 <td>
                                    <p>52° 38,800′ N</p>
                                 </td>
                                 <td>
                                    <p>12° 37′ W</p>
                                 </td>
                              </tr>
                              <tr>
                                 <td>
                                    <p>13</p>
                                 </td>
                                 <td>
                                    <p>52° 27′ N</p>
                                 </td>
                                 <td>
                                    <p>12° 23′ W</p>
                                 </td>
                              </tr>
                              <tr>
                                 <td>
                                    <p>14</p>
                                 </td>
                                 <td>
                                    <p>52° 27′ N</p>
                                 </td>
                                 <td>
                                    <p>12° 19′ W</p>
                                 </td>
                              </tr>
                           </table>
                        </content>
                     </subparagraph>
                     <subparagraph>
                        <content>
                           <p>By way of derogation from the first subparagraph, transit through the Porcupine Bank while carrying on board the species referred to in that paragraph, shall be permitted in accordance with Article 50(3), (4) and (5) of Regulation (EC) No 1224/2009.</p>
                        </content>
                     </subparagraph>
                  </paragraph>
                  <paragraph>
                     <num>2.</num>
                     <subparagraph>
                        <content>
                           <p>Commercial fishing for sandeel with demersal trawl, seine or similar towed gears with a mesh size of less than 16 mm shall be prohibited in ICES divisions IIa, IIIa and ICES subarea IV from 1 January to 31 March 2016 and from 1 August to 31 December 2016.</p>
                        </content>
                     </subparagraph>
                     <subparagraph>
                        <content>
                           <p>The prohibition set out in the first subparagraph shall also apply to third-country vessels authorised to fish for sandeel in Union waters of ICES subarea IV.</p>
                        </content>
                     </subparagraph>
                  </paragraph>
               </article>
               <article xml:id="art_d1e1652">
                  <num>Article 13</num>
                  <heading>Prohibitions</heading>
                  <paragraph>
                     <num>1.</num>
                     <subparagraph>
                        <content>
                           <p>It shall be prohibited for Union fishing vessels to fish for, to retain on board, to tranship or to land the following species:</p>
                        </content>
                     </subparagraph>
                     <list>
                        <point>
                           <num>(a)</num>
                           <content>
                              <p>starry ray (<i>Amblyraja radiata</i>) in Union waters of ICES divisions IIa, IIIa and VIId and ICES subarea IV;</p>
                           </content>
                        </point>
                        <point>
                           <num>(b)</num>
                           <content>
                              <p>white shark (<i>Carcharodon carcharías</i>) in all waters;</p>
                           </content>
                        </point>
                        <point>
                           <num>(c)</num>
                           <content>
                              <p>leafscale gulper shark (<i>Centrophorus squamosus</i>) in Union waters of ICES division IIa and subarea IV and in Union and international waters of ICES subareas I and XIV;</p>
                           </content>
                        </point>
                        <point>
                           <num>(d)</num>
                           <content>
                              <p>Portuguese dogfish (<i>Centroscymnus coelolepis</i>) in Union waters of ICES division IIa and subarea IV and in Union and international waters of ICES subareas I and XIV;</p>
                           </content>
                        </point>
                        <point>
                           <num>(e)</num>
                           <content>
                              <p>basking shark (<i>Cetorhinus maximus</i>) in all waters;</p>
                           </content>
                        </point>
                        <point>
                           <num>(f)</num>
                           <content>
                              <p>kitefin shark (<i>Dalatias licha</i>) in Union waters of ICES division IIa and subarea IV and in Union and international waters of ICES subareas I and XIV;</p>
                           </content>
                        </point>
                        <point>
                           <num>(g)</num>
                           <content>
                              <p>birdbeak dogfish (<i>Deania calcea</i>) in Union waters of ICES division IIa and subarea IV and in Union and international waters of ICES subareas I and XIV;</p>
                           </content>
                        </point>
                        <point>
                           <num>(h)</num>
                           <content>
                              <p>common skate (<i>Dipturus batis</i>) complex (<i>Dipturus</i> cf. <i>flossada</i> and <i>Dipturus</i> cf. <i>intermedia</i>) in Union waters of ICES division IIa and ICES subareas III, IV, VI, VII, VIII, IX and X;</p>
                           </content>
                        </point>
                        <point>
                           <num>(i)</num>
                           <content>
                              <p>great lanternshark (<i>Etmopterus princeps</i>) in Union waters of ICES division IIa and subarea IV and in Union and international waters of ICES subareas I and XIV;</p>
                           </content>
                        </point>
                        <point>
                           <num>(j)</num>
                           <content>
                              <p>smooth lanternshark (<i>Etmopterus pusillus</i>) in Union waters of ICES division IIa and subarea IV and in Union and international waters of ICES subareas I, V, VI, VII, VIII, XII and XIV;</p>
                           </content>
                        </point>
                        <point>
                           <num>(k)</num>
                           <content>
                              <p>tope shark (<i>Galeorhinus galeus</i>) when taken with longlines in Union waters of ICES division IIa and subarea IV and in Union and international waters of ICES subareas I, V, VI, VII, VIII, XII and XIV;</p>
                           </content>
                        </point>
                        <point>
                           <num>(l)</num>
                           <content>
                              <p>porbeagle (<i>Lamna nasus</i>) in all waters;</p>
                           </content>
                        </point>
                        <point>
                           <num>(m)</num>
                           <content>
                              <p>reef manta ray (<i>Manta alfredi</i>) in all waters;</p>
                           </content>
                        </point>
                        <point>
                           <num>(n)</num>
                           <content>
                              <p>giant manta ray (<i>Manta birostris</i>) in all waters;</p>
                           </content>
                        </point>
                        <point>
                           <num>(o)</num>
                           <alinea>
                              <content>
                                 <p>the following species of Mobula rays in all waters:</p>
                              </content>
                           </alinea>
                           <list>
                              <point>
                                 <num>(i)</num>
                                 <content>
                                    <p>devil fish (<i>Mobula mobular</i>);</p>
                                 </content>
                              </point>
                              <point>
                                 <num>(ii)</num>
                                 <content>
                                    <p>lesser Guinean devil ray (<i>Mobula rochebrunei</i>);</p>
                                 </content>
                              </point>
                              <point>
                                 <num>(iii)</num>
                                 <content>
                                    <p>spinetail mobula (<i>Mobula japanica</i>);</p>
                                 </content>
                              </point>
                              <point>
                                 <num>(iv)</num>
                                 <content>
                                    <p>smoothtail mobula (<i>Mobula thurstoni</i>);</p>
                                 </content>
                              </point>
                              <point>
                                 <num>(v)</num>
                                 <content>
                                    <p>longhorned mobula (<i>Mobula eregoodootenkee</i>);</p>
                                 </content>
                              </point>
                              <point>
                                 <num>(vi)</num>
                                 <content>
                                    <p>Munk&apos;s devil ray (<i>Mobula munkiana</i>);</p>
                                 </content>
                              </point>
                              <point>
                                 <num>(vii)</num>
                                 <content>
                                    <p>Chilean devil ray (<i>Mobula tarapacana</i>);</p>
                                 </content>
                              </point>
                              <point>
                                 <num>(viii)</num>
                                 <content>
                                    <p>shortfin devil ray (<i>Mobula kuhlii</i>);</p>
                                 </content>
                              </point>
                              <point>
                                 <num>(ix)</num>
                                 <content>
                                    <p>lesser devil ray (<i>Mobula hypostoma</i>);</p>
                                 </content>
                              </point>
                           </list>
                        </point>
                        <point>
                           <num>(p)</num>
                           <alinea>
                              <content>
                                 <p>the following species of sawfish (<i>Pristidae</i>) in all waters:</p>
                              </content>
                           </alinea>
                           <list>
                              <point>
                                 <num>(i)</num>
                                 <content>
                                    <p>narrow sawfish (<i>Anoxypristis cuspidate</i>);</p>
                                 </content>
                              </point>
                              <point>
                                 <num>(ii)</num>
                                 <content>
                                    <p>dwarf sawfish (<i>Pristis clavata</i>);</p>
                                 </content>
                              </point>
                              <point>
                                 <num>(iii)</num>
                                 <content>
                                    <p>smalltooth sawfish (<i>Pristis pectinata</i>);</p>
                                 </content>
                              </point>
                              <point>
                                 <num>(iv)</num>
                                 <content>
                                    <p>largetooth sawfish (<i>Pristis pristis</i>);</p>
                                 </content>
                              </point>
                              <point>
                                 <num>(v)</num>
                                 <content>
                                    <p>green sawfish (<i>Pristis zijsron</i>);</p>
                                 </content>
                              </point>
                           </list>
                        </point>
                        <point>
                           <num>(q)</num>
                           <content>
                              <p>thornback ray (Raja clavata) in Union waters of ICES division IIIa;</p>
                           </content>
                        </point>
                        <point>
                           <num>(r)</num>
                           <content>
                              <p>Norwegian skate (Raja (Dipturus) nidarosiensis) in Union waters of ICES divisions VIa, VIb, VIIa, VIIb, VIIc, VIIe, VIIf, VIIg, VIIh and VIIk;</p>
                           </content>
                        </point>
                        <point>
                           <num>(s)</num>
                           <content>
                              <p>undulate ray (Raja undulata) in Union waters of ICES subareas VI and X;</p>
                           </content>
                        </point>
                        <point>
                           <num>(t)</num>
                           <content>
                              <p>white skate (Raja alba) in Union waters of ICES subareas VI, VII, VIII, IX and X;</p>
                           </content>
                        </point>
                        <point>
                           <num>(u)</num>
                           <content>
                              <p>guitarfishes (Rhinobatidae) in Union waters of ICES subareas I, II, III, IV, V, VI, VII, VIII, IX, X and XII;</p>
                           </content>
                        </point>
                        <point>
                           <num>(v)</num>
                           <content>
                              <p>angel shark (Squatina squatina) in Union waters.</p>
                           </content>
                        </point>
                     </list>
                  </paragraph>
                  <paragraph>
                     <num>2.</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>When accidentally caught, species referred to in paragraph 1 shall not be harmed. Specimens shall be promptly released.</p>
                     </content>
                  </paragraph>
               </article>
               <article xml:id="art_d1e1993">
                  <num>Article 14</num>
                  <heading>Data transmission</heading>
                  <paragraph>
                     <content>
                        <p>When, pursuant to Articles 33 and 34 of Regulation (EC) No 1224/2009, Member States submit to the Commission data relating to landings of quantities of stocks caught, they shall use the stock codes set out in Annex I to this Regulation.</p>
                     </content>
                  </paragraph>
               </article>
            </chapter>
            <chapter>
               <num>CHAPTER II</num>
               <heading>Additional allocations for vessels participating in trials on fully documented fisheries</heading>
               <article xml:id="art_d1e2011">
                  <num>Article 15</num>
                  <heading>Additional allocations</heading>
                  <paragraph>
                     <num>1.</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>For certain stocks, a Member State may grant an additional allocation to vessels flying its flag and participating in trials on fully documented fisheries. Those stocks are identified in Annex I.</p>
                     </content>
                  </paragraph>
                  <paragraph>
                     <num>2.</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>The additional allocation referred to in paragraph 1 shall not exceed the overall limit set out in Annex I as a percentage of the quota allocated to that Member State.</p>
                     </content>
                  </paragraph>
               </article>
               <article xml:id="art_d1e2026">
                  <num>Article 16</num>
                  <heading>Conditions for additional allocations</heading>
                  <paragraph>
                     <num>1.</num>
                     <subparagraph>
                        <content>
                           <p>The additional allocation referred to in Article 15 shall comply with the following conditions:</p>
                        </content>
                     </subparagraph>
                     <list>
                        <point>
                           <num>(a)</num>
                           <content>
                              <p>Member States shall ensure detailed and accurate documentation of all fishing trips and adequate capacity and means, such as observers, closed-circuit television (CCTV) and others. In doing so, Member States shall respect the principle of efficiency and proportionality;</p>
                           </content>
                        </point>
                        <point>
                           <num>(b)</num>
                           <alinea>
                              <content>
                                 <p>the additional allocation granted to an individual vessel that participates in trials on fully documented fisheries shall not exceed any of the following limits:</p>
                              </content>
                           </alinea>
                           <list>
                              <point>
                                 <num>(i)</num>
                                 <content>
                                    <p>75 % of the discards of the stock, as estimated by the relevant Member State, produced by the type of vessel to which the individual vessel that has been granted the additional allocation belongs;</p>
                                 </content>
                              </point>
                              <point>
                                 <num>(ii)</num>
                                 <content>
                                    <p>30 % of the vessel&apos;s individual allocation prior to participating in the trials;</p>
                                 </content>
                              </point>
                           </list>
                        </point>
                        <point>
                           <num>(c)</num>
                           <content>
                              <p>all catches by the vessel from the stock subject to the additional allocation, including fish that are under minimum landing size as defined in Annex XII of Council Regulation (EC) No 850/98<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="33">
                                    <p>Council Regulation (EC) No 850/98 of 30 March 1998 for the conservation of fishery resources through technical measures for the protection of juveniles of marine organisms (OJ L 125, 27.4.1998, p. 1).</p>
                                 </authorialNote>, shall be counted against the individual allocation of the vessel, as resulting from any additional allocation granted under Article 15 of this Regulation;</p>
                           </content>
                        </point>
                        <point>
                           <num>(d)</num>
                           <content>
                              <p>once the individual allocation for any stock subject to the additional allocation has been fully utilised by a vessel, the vessel in question must cease all fishing activity in the relevant TAC area;</p>
                           </content>
                        </point>
                        <point>
                           <num>(e)</num>
                           <content>
                              <p>in respect of the stocks for which this Article may be used, Member States may allow transfers of the individual allocation or any part thereof from vessels not participating in trials on fully documented fisheries to vessels participating in those trials provided that it can be demonstrated that discards by the non- participating vessels do not increase.</p>
                           </content>
                        </point>
                     </list>
                  </paragraph>
                  <paragraph>
                     <num>2.</num>
                     <subparagraph>
                        <content>
                           <p>Notwithstanding paragraph 1(b)(i), a Member State may exceptionally grant to a vessel flying its flag an additional allocation exceeding 75 % of the estimated discards of the stock produced by the type of vessel to which the individual vessel that has been granted the additional allocation belongs, provided that:</p>
                        </content>
                     </subparagraph>
                     <list>
                        <point>
                           <num>(a)</num>
                           <content>
                              <p>the rate of stock discards, as estimated for the relevant type of vessel, is less than 10 %;</p>
                           </content>
                        </point>
                        <point>
                           <num>(b)</num>
                           <content>
                              <p>the inclusion of that type of vessel is important to evaluate the potential of the monitoring means used in accordance with paragraph 1(a);</p>
                           </content>
                        </point>
                        <point>
                           <num>(c)</num>
                           <content>
                              <p>an overall limit of 75 % of the estimated stock discards produced by all vessels participating in the trials is not exceeded.</p>
                           </content>
                        </point>
                     </list>
                  </paragraph>
                  <paragraph>
                     <num>3.</num>
                     <subparagraph>
                        <content>
                           <p>Prior to granting the additional allocation referred to in Article 15, a Member State shall submit the following information to the Commission:</p>
                        </content>
                     </subparagraph>
                     <list>
                        <point>
                           <num>(a)</num>
                           <content>
                              <p>the list of vessels flying its flag and participating in trials on fully documented fisheries;</p>
                           </content>
                        </point>
                        <point>
                           <num>(b)</num>
                           <content>
                              <p>the specifications of the remote electronic monitoring equipment installed on board those vessels;</p>
                           </content>
                        </point>
                        <point>
                           <num>(c)</num>
                           <content>
                              <p>the capacity, type and specification of gears used by those vessels;</p>
                           </content>
                        </point>
                        <point>
                           <num>(d)</num>
                           <content>
                              <p>the estimated discards for each type of vessel participating in the trials;</p>
                           </content>
                        </point>
                        <point>
                           <num>(e)</num>
                           <content>
                              <p>the amount of catches of the stock subject to the relevant TAC made in 2015 by the vessels participating in the trials.</p>
                           </content>
                        </point>
                     </list>
                  </paragraph>
               </article>
               <article xml:id="art_d1e2155">
                  <num>Article 17</num>
                  <heading>Processing of personal data</heading>
                  <paragraph>
                     <content>
                        <p>To the extent that the recordings obtained in accordance with Article 16(1)(a) of this Regulation involve the processing of personal data within the meaning of Directive 95/46/EC, that Directive shall apply to the processing of such data.</p>
                     </content>
                  </paragraph>
               </article>
               <article xml:id="art_d1e2162">
                  <num>Article 18</num>
                  <heading>Withdrawal of additional allocations</heading>
                  <paragraph>
                     <content>
                        <p>Where a Member State detects that a vessel participating in trials on fully documented fisheries fails to comply with the conditions set out in Article 16, it shall immediately withdraw the additional allocation granted to that vessel and exclude that vessel from participation in those trials for the remainder of the year 2016.</p>
                     </content>
                  </paragraph>
               </article>
               <article xml:id="art_d1e2170">
                  <num>Article 19</num>
                  <heading>Scientific review of discard assessments</heading>
                  <paragraph>
                     <content>
                        <p>The Commission may request any Member State that avails itself of this Chapter to submit its assessment of the discards produced per type of vessel to a scientific advisory body for review, in order to monitor the implementation of the requirement set out in Article 16(1)(b)(i). In the absence of an assessment confirming such discards, the Member State concerned shall take any appropriate measure to ensure compliance with that requirement and shall inform the Commission thereof.</p>
                     </content>
                  </paragraph>
               </article>
            </chapter>
            <chapter>
               <num>CHAPTER III</num>
               <heading>Fishing authorisations in third-country waters</heading>
               <article xml:id="art_d1e2188">
                  <num>Article 20</num>
                  <heading>Fishing authorisations</heading>
                  <paragraph>
                     <num>1.</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>The maximum number of fishing authorisations for Union fishing vessels fishing in waters of a third country is set out in Annex III.</p>
                     </content>
                  </paragraph>
                  <paragraph>
                     <num>2.</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>Where one Member State transfers quota to another Member State (&apos;swap&apos;) in the fishing areas set out in Annex III of this Regulation on the basis of Article 16(8) of Regulation (EU) No 1380/2013, the transfer shall include an appropriate transfer of fishing authorisations and shall be notified to the Commission. However, the total number of fishing authorisations for each fishing area, as set out in Annex III of this Regulation, shall not be exceeded.</p>
                     </content>
                  </paragraph>
               </article>
            </chapter>
            <chapter>
               <num>CHAPTER IV</num>
               <heading>Fishing opportunities in waters of regional fisheries management organisations</heading>
               <article xml:id="art_d1e2218">
                  <num>Article 21</num>
                  <heading>Quota transfers and exchanges</heading>
                  <paragraph>
                     <num>1.</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>Where, under the rules of a regional fisheries management organisation (&apos;RFMO&apos;), quota transfers or exchanges between the Contracting Parties to the RFMO are permitted, a Member State (&apos;the Member State concern&apos;) may discuss with a Contracting Party to the RFMO and, as appropriate, establish a possible outline of an intended quota transfer or exchange.</p>
                     </content>
                  </paragraph>
                  <paragraph>
                     <num>2.</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>Upon notification to the Commission by the Member State concerned, the Commission may endorse the outline of the intended quota transfer or exchange that the Member State has discussed with the relevant Contracting Party to the RFMO. Thereupon, the Commission shall exchange, without undue delay, the consent to be bound by such quota transfer or exchange with the relevant Contracting Party to the RFMO. The Commission shall notify the secretariat of the RFMO of the agreed quota transfer or exchange in accordance with the rules of that organisation.</p>
                     </content>
                  </paragraph>
                  <paragraph>
                     <num>3.</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>The Commission shall inform the Member States of the agreed quota transfer or exchange.</p>
                     </content>
                  </paragraph>
                  <paragraph>
                     <num>4.</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>The fishing opportunities received from or transferred to the relevant Contracting Party to the RFMO under the quota transfer or exchange shall be deemed to be quotas allocated to, or deducted from, the allocation of the Member State concerned, as of the moment that the quota transfer or exchange takes effect in accordance with the terms of the agreement reached with the relevant Contracting Party to the RFMO or in accordance with the rules of the relevant RFMO, as appropriate. Such allocation shall not change the existing distribution key for the purpose of allocating fishing opportunities among Member States in accordance with the principle of relative stability of fishing activities.</p>
                     </content>
                  </paragraph>
               </article>
               <section>
                  <num>Section 1</num>
                  <heading>ICCAT Convention Area</heading>
                  <article xml:id="art_d1e2263">
                     <num>Article 22</num>
                     <heading>Fishing, farming and fattening capacity limitations for bluefin tuna</heading>
                     <paragraph>
                        <num>1.</num>
                        <content>
                           <p>The number of Union bait boats and trolling boats authorised to fish actively for bluefin tuna between 8 kg/75 cm and 30 kg/115 cm in the Eastern Atlantic shall be limited as set out in point 1 of Annex IV.</p>
                        </content>
                     </paragraph>
                     <paragraph>
                        <num>2.</num>
                        <content>
                           <p>The number of Union coastal artisanal fishing vessels authorised to fish actively for bluefin tuna between 8 kg/75 cm and 30 kg/115 cm in the Mediterranean shall be limited as set out in point 2 of Annex IV.</p>
                        </content>
                     </paragraph>
                     <paragraph>
                        <num>3.</num>
                        <content>
                           <p>The number of Union fishing vessels fishing for bluefin tuna in the Adriatic Sea for farming purposes authorised to fish actively for bluefin tuna between 8 kg/75 cm and 30 kg/115 cm shall be limited as set out in point 3 of Annex IV.</p>
                        </content>
                     </paragraph>
                     <paragraph>
                        <num>4.</num>
                        <content>
                           <p>The number and total capacity in gross tonnage of fishing vessels authorised to fish for, retain on board, tranship, transport, or land bluefin tuna in the eastern Atlantic and Mediterranean shall be limited as set out in point 4 of Annex IV.</p>
                        </content>
                     </paragraph>
                     <paragraph>
                        <num>5.</num>
                        <content>
                           <p>The number of traps engaged in the eastern Atlantic and Mediterranean bluefin tuna fishery shall be limited as set out in point 5 of Annex IV.</p>
                        </content>
                     </paragraph>
                     <paragraph>
                        <num>6.</num>
                        <content>
                           <p>The bluefin tuna farming capacity, the fattening capacity and the maximum input of wild caught bluefin tuna allocated to the farms in the eastern Atlantic and Mediterranean shall be limited as set out in point 6 of Annex IV.</p>
                        </content>
                     </paragraph>
                  </article>
                  <article xml:id="art_d1e2298">
                     <num>Article 23</num>
                     <heading>Recreational fisheries</heading>
                     <paragraph>
                        <content>
                           <p>Where appropriate, Member States shall allocate a specific quota for recreational fisheries from their quotas allocated in Annex ID.</p>
                        </content>
                     </paragraph>
                  </article>
                  <article xml:id="art_d1e2305">
                     <num>Article 24</num>
                     <heading>Sharks</heading>
                     <paragraph>
                        <num>1.</num>
                        <content>
                           <p>Retaining on board, transhipping or landing any part or whole carcass of bigeye thresher sharks (<i>Alopias superciliosus</i>) in any fishery shall be prohibited.</p>
                        </content>
                     </paragraph>
                     <paragraph>
                        <num>2.</num>
                        <content>
                           <p>It shall be prohibited to undertake a directed fishery for species of thresher sharks of the <i>Alopias</i> genus.</p>
                        </content>
                     </paragraph>
                     <paragraph>
                        <num>3.</num>
                        <content>
                           <p>Retaining on board, transhipping or landing any part or whole carcass of hammerhead sharks of the <i>Sphyrnidae</i> family (except for the <i>Sphyrna tiburo</i>) in association with fisheries in the ICCAT Convention Area shall be prohibited.</p>
                        </content>
                     </paragraph>
                     <paragraph>
                        <num>4.</num>
                        <content>
                           <p>Retaining on board, transhipping or landing any part or whole carcass of oceanic whitetip sharks (<i>Carcharhinus longimanus</i>) taken in any fishery shall be prohibited.</p>
                        </content>
                     </paragraph>
                     <paragraph>
                        <num>5.</num>
                        <content>
                           <p>Retaining on board silky sharks (<i>Carcharhinus falciformis</i>) taken in any fishery shall be prohibited.</p>
                        </content>
                     </paragraph>
                  </article>
               </section>
               <section>
                  <num>Section 2</num>
                  <heading>CCAMLR Convention Area</heading>
                  <article xml:id="art_d1e2365">
                     <num>Article 25</num>
                     <heading>Prohibitions and catch limitations</heading>
                     <paragraph>
                        <num>1.</num>
                        <content>
                           <p>Direct fishing of the species set out in Part A of Annex V, shall be prohibited in the zones and during the periods set out therein.</p>
                        </content>
                     </paragraph>
                     <paragraph>
                        <num>2.</num>
                        <content>
                           <p>For exploratory fisheries, the TACs and by-catch limits set out in Part B of Annex V, shall apply in the subareas set out therein.</p>
                        </content>
                     </paragraph>
                  </article>
                  <article xml:id="art_d1e2380">
                     <num>Article 26</num>
                     <heading>Exploratory fisheries</heading>
                     <paragraph>
                        <num>1.</num>
                        <content>
                           <p>Only those Member States that are members of the CCAMLR may participate in longline exploratory fisheries for <i>Dissostichus</i> spp. in FAO subareas 88.1 and 88.2 as well as in divisions 58.4.1, 58.4.2 and 58.4.3a outside areas of national jurisdiction in 2016. If such a Member State intends to participate in such fisheries, it shall notify the CCAMLR Secretariat in accordance with Articles 7 and 7a of Regulation (EC) No 601/2004 and in any case no later than 1 June 2016.</p>
                        </content>
                     </paragraph>
                     <paragraph>
                        <num>2.</num>
                        <content>
                           <p>With regard to FAO subareas 88.1 and 88.2 as well as divisions 58.4.1, 58.4.2 and 58.4.3a TACs and by-catch limits per subarea and division, and their distribution among Small Scale Research Units (SSRUs) within each of them, shall be as set out in Part B of Annex V. Fishing in any SSRU shall cease when the reported catch reaches the specified TAC, and the SSRU shall be closed to fishing for the remainder of the season.</p>
                        </content>
                     </paragraph>
                     <paragraph>
                        <num>3.</num>
                        <content>
                           <p>Fishing shall take place over as large a geographical and bathymetric range as possible to obtain the information necessary to determine fishery potential and to avoid over-concentration of catch and fishing effort. However, fishing in FAO subareas 88.1 and 88.2 as well as in divisions 58.4.1, 58.4.2 and 58.4.3a shall be prohibited in depths less than 550 m.</p>
                        </content>
                     </paragraph>
                  </article>
                  <article xml:id="art_d1e2406">
                     <num>Article 27</num>
                     <heading>Krill fishery during the 2016/2017 fishing season</heading>
                     <paragraph>
                        <num>1.</num>
                        <content>
                           <p>If a Member State intends to fish for krill (<i>Euphausia superba</i>) in the CCAMLR Convention Area during the 2016/2017 fishing season, it shall notify the Commission, no later than 1 May 2016, using the format laid down in Part C of Annex V to this Regulation of its intention to fish for krill. On the basis of the information provided by Member States, the Commission shall submit the notifications to the CCAMLR Secretariat no later than 30 May 2016.</p>
                        </content>
                     </paragraph>
                     <paragraph>
                        <num>2.</num>
                        <content>
                           <p>The notification referred to in paragraph 1 of this Article shall include the information provided for in Article 3 of Regulation (EC) No 601/2004 for each vessel to be authorised by the Member State to participate in the krill fishery.</p>
                        </content>
                     </paragraph>
                     <paragraph>
                        <num>3.</num>
                        <content>
                           <p>A Member State intending to fish for krill in the CCAMLR Convention Area shall notify its intention to do so only in respect of authorised vessels either flying its flag at the time of the notification or flying the flag of another CCAMLR member that are expected, at the time the fishery takes place, to be flying the flag of that Member State.</p>
                        </content>
                     </paragraph>
                     <paragraph>
                        <num>4.</num>
                        <subparagraph>
                           <content>
                              <p>Member States shall be entitled to authorise participation in a krill fishery by vessels other than those notified to CCAMLR Secretariat in accordance with paragraphs 1, 2 and 3 of this Article, if an authorised vessel is prevented from participation due to legitimate operational reasons or <i>force majeure</i>. In such circumstances the Member States concerned shall immediately inform the CCAMLR Secretariat and the Commission, providing:</p>
                           </content>
                        </subparagraph>
                        <list>
                           <point>
                              <num>(a)</num>
                              <content>
                                 <p>full details of the intended replacement vessel(s), including information provided for in Article 3 of Council Regulation (EC) No 601/2004;</p>
                              </content>
                           </point>
                           <point>
                              <num>(b)</num>
                              <content>
                                 <p>a comprehensive account of the reasons justifying the replacement and any relevant supporting evidence or references.</p>
                              </content>
                           </point>
                        </list>
                     </paragraph>
                     <paragraph>
                        <num>5.</num>
                        <content>
                           <p>Member States shall not authorise a vessel on any CCAMLR illegal, unreported and unregulated (IUU) Vessel List to participate in krill fisheries.</p>
                        </content>
                     </paragraph>
                  </article>
               </section>
               <section>
                  <num>Section 3</num>
                  <heading>IOTC Convention Area</heading>
                  <article xml:id="art_d1e2474">
                     <num>Article 28</num>
                     <heading>Limitation of fishing capacity of vessels fishing in the IOTC Convention Area</heading>
                     <paragraph>
                        <num>1.</num>
                        <content>
                           <p>The maximum number of Union fishing vessels fishing for tropical tunas in the IOTC Convention Area and the corresponding capacity in gross tonnage shall be as set out in point 1 of Annex VI.</p>
                        </content>
                     </paragraph>
                     <paragraph>
                        <num>2.</num>
                        <content>
                           <p>The maximum number of Union fishing vessels fishing for swordfish (<i>Xiphias gladius</i>) and albacore (<i>Thunnus alalunga</i>) in the IOTC Convention Area and the corresponding capacity in gross tonnage shall be as set out in point 2 of Annex VI.</p>
                        </content>
                     </paragraph>
                     <paragraph>
                        <num>3.</num>
                        <content>
                           <p>Member States may re-allocate vessels assigned to one of the two fisheries referred to in paragraphs 1 and 2 to the other fishery, provided that they can demonstrate to the Commission that this change does not lead to an increase of fishing effort on the fish stocks involved.</p>
                        </content>
                     </paragraph>
                     <paragraph>
                        <num>4.</num>
                        <content>
                           <p>Member States shall ensure that, where there is a proposed transfer of capacity to their fleet, vessels to be transferred are on the IOTC Record of Vessels or on the record of vessels of other tuna regional fisheries organisations. Furthermore, no vessels featuring on the list of vessels engaged in IUU fishing activities (IUU vessels) of any RFMO may be transferred.</p>
                        </content>
                     </paragraph>
                     <paragraph>
                        <num>5.</num>
                        <content>
                           <p>Member States may only increase their fishing capacity beyond the ceilings referred to in paragraphs 1 and 2 within the limits set out in the development plans submitted to the IOTC.</p>
                        </content>
                     </paragraph>
                  </article>
                  <article xml:id="art_d1e2510">
                     <num>Article 29</num>
                     <heading>Drifting fish aggregating devices (FADs)</heading>
                     <paragraph>
                        <content>
                           <p>A purse seine vessel shall not deploy more than 550 active drifting fish aggregating devices (FADs) at any one time.</p>
                        </content>
                     </paragraph>
                  </article>
                  <article xml:id="art_d1e2517">
                     <num>Article 30</num>
                     <heading>Sharks</heading>
                     <paragraph>
                        <num>1.</num>
                        <content>
                           <p>Retaining on board, transhipping or landing any part or whole carcass of thresher sharks of all the species of the <i>Alopiidae</i> family in any fishery shall be prohibited.</p>
                        </content>
                     </paragraph>
                     <paragraph>
                        <num>2.</num>
                        <content>
                           <p>Retaining on board, transshipping or landing any part or whole carcass of oceanic whitetip sharks (<i>Carcharhinus longimanus</i>) in any fishery shall be prohibited, except for vessels under 24 metres overall length engaged solely in fishing operations within the Exclusive Economic Zone (EEZ) of the Member State whose flag they fly, and provided that their catch is destined solely for local consumption.</p>
                        </content>
                     </paragraph>
                     <paragraph>
                        <num>3.</num>
                        <content>
                           <p>When accidentally caught, species referred to in paragraph 1 and 2 shall not be harmed. Specimens shall be promptly released.</p>
                        </content>
                     </paragraph>
                  </article>
               </section>
               <section>
                  <num>Section 4</num>
                  <heading>SPRFMO Convention Area</heading>
                  <article xml:id="art_d1e2555">
                     <num>Article 31</num>
                     <heading>Pelagic fisheries</heading>
                     <paragraph>
                        <num>1.</num>
                        <content>
                           <p>Member States having actively exercised pelagic fisheries activities in the SPRFMO Convention Area in 2007, 2008 or 2009 shall limit the total level of gross tonnage of vessels flying their flag and fishing for pelagic stocks in 2016 to the total Union level of 78600 gross tonnage in that area.</p>
                        </content>
                     </paragraph>
                     <paragraph>
                        <num>2.</num>
                        <content>
                           <p>Only Member States having actively exercised pelagic fisheries activities in the SPRFMO Convention Area in 2007, 2008 or 2009 may fish for pelagic stocks in that area in accordance with the TACs set out in Annex IJ.</p>
                        </content>
                     </paragraph>
                     <paragraph>
                        <num>3.</num>
                        <content>
                           <p>The fishing opportunities set out in Annex IJ may only be used under the condition that Member States send to the Commission the list of vessels actively fishing or engaged in transhipment in the SPRFMO Convention Area, records from vessel monitoring systems (VMS), monthly catch reports and, where available, port calls at the latest by the fifth day of the following month, in order to communicate this information to the SPRFMO Secretariat.</p>
                        </content>
                     </paragraph>
                  </article>
                  <article xml:id="art_d1e2578">
                     <num>Article 32</num>
                     <heading>Bottom fisheries</heading>
                     <paragraph>
                        <num>1.</num>
                        <content>
                           <p>Member States shall limit their bottom fishing catch or effort in 2016 in the SPRFMO Convention Area to those parts of the Convention Area where bottom fishing has occurred from 1 January 2002 to 31 December 2006 and to a level that does not exceed the annual average levels of catches or effort parameters in that period. They may fish beyond the track record only if SPRFMO endorses their plan to fish beyond the track record.</p>
                        </content>
                     </paragraph>
                     <paragraph>
                        <num>2.</num>
                        <content>
                           <p>Member States without a track record in bottom fishing catch or effort in the SPRFMO Convention Area over the period from 1 January 2002 to 31 December 2006 shall not fish, unless SPRFMO endorses their plan to fish without the track record.</p>
                        </content>
                     </paragraph>
                  </article>
               </section>
               <section>
                  <num>Section 5</num>
                  <heading>IATTC Convention Area</heading>
                  <article xml:id="art_d1e2616">
                     <num>Article 33</num>
                     <heading>Purse-seine fisheries</heading>
                     <paragraph>
                        <num>1.</num>
                        <subparagraph>
                           <content>
                              <p>The fishing by purse-seine vessels for yellowfin tuna (<i>Thunnus albacares</i>), bigeye tuna (<i>Thunnus obesus</i>) and skipjack tuna (<i>Katsuwonus pelamis</i>) shall be prohibited:</p>
                           </content>
                        </subparagraph>
                        <list>
                           <point>
                              <num>(a)</num>
                              <alinea>
                                 <content>
                                    <p>from 29 July to 28 September 2016 or from 18 November 2016 to 18 January 2017 in the area defined by the following limits:</p>
                                 </content>
                              </alinea>
                              <list>
                                 <indent>
                                    <num>-</num>
                                    <content>
                                       <p>the Pacific coastlines of the Americas,</p>
                                    </content>
                                 </indent>
                                 <indent>
                                    <num>-</num>
                                    <content>
                                       <p>longitude 150° W,</p>
                                    </content>
                                 </indent>
                                 <indent>
                                    <num>-</num>
                                    <content>
                                       <p>latitude 40° N,</p>
                                    </content>
                                 </indent>
                                 <indent>
                                    <num>-</num>
                                    <content>
                                       <p>latitude 40° S;</p>
                                    </content>
                                 </indent>
                              </list>
                           </point>
                           <point>
                              <num>(b)</num>
                              <alinea>
                                 <content>
                                    <p>from 29 September to 29 October 2016 in the area defined by the following limits:</p>
                                 </content>
                              </alinea>
                              <list>
                                 <indent>
                                    <num>-</num>
                                    <content>
                                       <p>longitude 96° W,</p>
                                    </content>
                                 </indent>
                                 <indent>
                                    <num>-</num>
                                    <content>
                                       <p>longitude 110° W,</p>
                                    </content>
                                 </indent>
                                 <indent>
                                    <num>-</num>
                                    <content>
                                       <p>latitude 4° N,</p>
                                    </content>
                                 </indent>
                                 <indent>
                                    <num>-</num>
                                    <content>
                                       <p>latitude 3° S.</p>
                                    </content>
                                 </indent>
                              </list>
                           </point>
                        </list>
                     </paragraph>
                     <paragraph>
                        <num>2.</num>
                        <content>
                           <p>The Member States concerned shall notify the Commission of the selected period of closure referred to in paragraph 1 before 1 April 2016. All the purse-seine vessels of the Member States concerned shall stop purse-seine fishing in the areas defined in paragraph 1 during the selected period.</p>
                        </content>
                     </paragraph>
                     <paragraph>
                        <num>3.</num>
                        <content>
                           <p>Purse-seine vessels fishing for tuna in the IATTC Convention Area shall retain on board and then land or tranship all yellowfin, bigeye and skipjack tuna caught.</p>
                        </content>
                     </paragraph>
                     <paragraph>
                        <num>4.</num>
                        <subparagraph>
                           <content>
                              <p>Paragraph 3 shall not apply in the following cases:</p>
                           </content>
                        </subparagraph>
                        <list>
                           <point>
                              <num>(a)</num>
                              <content>
                                 <p>where the fish is considered unfit for human consumption for reasons other than size; or</p>
                              </content>
                           </point>
                           <point>
                              <num>(b)</num>
                              <content>
                                 <p>during the final set of a trip when there may be insufficient well space remaining to accommodate all the tuna caught in that set.</p>
                              </content>
                           </point>
                        </list>
                     </paragraph>
                  </article>
                  <article xml:id="art_d1e2728">
                     <num>Article 34</num>
                     <heading>Prohibition of fishing for oceanic whitetip sharks</heading>
                     <paragraph>
                        <num>1.</num>
                        <content>
                           <p>It shall be prohibited to fish for oceanic whitetip sharks (<i>Carcharhinus longimanus</i>) in the IATTC Convention Area, and to retain on board, to tranship, to store, to offer to sell, to sell or to land any part or whole carcass of oceanic whitetip sharks in that area.</p>
                        </content>
                     </paragraph>
                     <paragraph>
                        <num>2.</num>
                        <content>
                           <p>When accidentally caught, the species referred to in paragraph 1 shall not be harmed. Specimens shall be promptly released by vessel operators.</p>
                        </content>
                     </paragraph>
                     <paragraph>
                        <num>3.</num>
                        <subparagraph>
                           <content>
                              <p>Vessel operators shall:</p>
                           </content>
                        </subparagraph>
                        <list>
                           <point>
                              <num>(a)</num>
                              <content>
                                 <p>record the number of releases with indication of status (dead or alive);</p>
                              </content>
                           </point>
                           <point>
                              <num>(b)</num>
                              <content>
                                 <p>report the information specified in point (a) to the Member State of which they are nationals. Member States shall transmit the information collected during the previous year to the Commission by 31 January of the year in which this Regulation enters into force.</p>
                              </content>
                           </point>
                        </list>
                     </paragraph>
                  </article>
                  <article xml:id="art_d1e2765">
                     <num>Article 35</num>
                     <heading>Prohibition of fishing for Mobulid rays</heading>
                     <paragraph>
                        <content>
                           <p>It shall be prohibited for Union fishing vessels in the IATTC Convention Area to fish for, to retain on board, to tranship, to land, to store, to offer to sell or to sell any part or whole carcass of Mobulid rays (which include Manta rays and Mobula rays). As soon as Union fishing vessels notice that Mobulid rays have been caught, Union fishing vessels shall promptly release them alive and unharmed wherever possible.</p>
                        </content>
                     </paragraph>
                  </article>
               </section>
               <section>
                  <num>Section 6</num>
                  <heading>SEAFO Convention Area</heading>
                  <article xml:id="art_d1e2783">
                     <num>Article 36</num>
                     <heading>Prohibition of fishing for deep water sharks</heading>
                     <paragraph>
                        <subparagraph>
                           <content>
                              <p>Directed fishing for the following deep water sharks in the SEAFO Convention Area shall be prohibited:</p>
                           </content>
                        </subparagraph>
                        <list>
                           <indent>
                              <num>-</num>
                              <content>
                                 <p>ghost catshark (<i>Apristurus manis</i>),</p>
                              </content>
                           </indent>
                           <indent>
                              <num>-</num>
                              <content>
                                 <p>blurred smooth lanternshark (<i>Etmopterus bigelowi</i>),</p>
                              </content>
                           </indent>
                           <indent>
                              <num>-</num>
                              <content>
                                 <p>shorttail lanternshark (<i>Etmopterus brachyurus</i>),</p>
                              </content>
                           </indent>
                           <indent>
                              <num>-</num>
                              <content>
                                 <p>great lanternshark (<i>Etmopterus princeps</i>),</p>
                              </content>
                           </indent>
                           <indent>
                              <num>-</num>
                              <content>
                                 <p>smooth lanternshark (<i>Etmopterus pusillus</i>),</p>
                              </content>
                           </indent>
                           <indent>
                              <num>-</num>
                              <content>
                                 <p>skates (<i>Rajidae</i>),</p>
                              </content>
                           </indent>
                           <indent>
                              <num>-</num>
                              <content>
                                 <p>velvet dogfish (<i>Scymnodon squamulosus</i>),</p>
                              </content>
                           </indent>
                           <indent>
                              <num>-</num>
                              <content>
                                 <p>deep-sea sharks of the <i>Selachimorpha</i> super-order.</p>
                              </content>
                           </indent>
                           <indent>
                              <num>-</num>
                              <content>
                                 <p>spiny dogfish (<i>Squalus acanthias</i>),</p>
                              </content>
                           </indent>
                        </list>
                     </paragraph>
                  </article>
               </section>
               <section>
                  <num>Section 7</num>
                  <heading>WCPFC Convention Area</heading>
                  <article xml:id="art_d1e2859">
                     <num>Article 37</num>
                     <heading>Conditions for bigeye tuna, yellowfin tuna, skipjack tuna and south Pacific albacore fisheries</heading>
                     <paragraph>
                        <num>1.</num>
                        <content>
                           <p>Member States shall ensure that the number of fishing days allocated to purse-seine vessels fishing for bigeye tuna (<i>Thunnus obesus</i>), yellowfin tuna (<i>Thunnus albacares</i>) and skipjack tuna (<i>Katsuwonus pelamis</i>) in the part of the WCPFC Convention Area in the high seas and located between 20° N and 20° S does not exceed 403 days.</p>
                        </content>
                     </paragraph>
                     <paragraph>
                        <num>2.</num>
                        <content>
                           <p>Union fishing vessels shall not target south Pacific albacore (<i>Thunnus alalunga</i>) in the WCPFC Convention Area south of 20° S.</p>
                        </content>
                     </paragraph>
                     <paragraph>
                        <num>3.</num>
                        <content>
                           <p>Member States shall ensure that catches of bigeye tuna (<i>Thunnus obesus</i>) by longliners do not exceed 2000 tonnes in 2016.</p>
                        </content>
                     </paragraph>
                  </article>
                  <article xml:id="art_d1e2897">
                     <num>Article 38</num>
                     <heading>Closed area for FAD fishing</heading>
                     <paragraph>
                        <num>1.</num>
                        <subparagraph>
                           <content>
                              <p>In the part of the WCPFC Convention Area located between 20° N and 20° S, fishing activities of purse-seine vessels making use of fish aggregating devices (FADs) shall be prohibited between 00:00 hours of 1 July 2016 and 24:00 hours of 31 October 2016. During that period, a purse-seine vessel may only engage in fishing operations within that part of the WCPFC Convention Area if it carries onboard an observer to monitor that at no time does the vessel:</p>
                           </content>
                        </subparagraph>
                        <list>
                           <point>
                              <num>(a)</num>
                              <content>
                                 <p>deploy or service a FAD or associated electronic device;</p>
                              </content>
                           </point>
                           <point>
                              <num>(b)</num>
                              <content>
                                 <p>fish on schools in association with FADs.</p>
                              </content>
                           </point>
                        </list>
                     </paragraph>
                     <paragraph>
                        <num>2.</num>
                        <content>
                           <p>All purse-seine vessels fishing in the part of the WCPFC Convention Area referred to in paragraph 1 shall retain onboard and land or tranship all bigeye, yellowfin and skipjack tuna caught.</p>
                        </content>
                     </paragraph>
                     <paragraph>
                        <num>3.</num>
                        <subparagraph>
                           <content>
                              <p>Paragraph 2 shall not apply in the following cases:</p>
                           </content>
                        </subparagraph>
                        <list>
                           <point>
                              <num>(a)</num>
                              <content>
                                 <p>in the final set of a trip, if the vessel has insufficient well space left to accommodate all fish;</p>
                              </content>
                           </point>
                           <point>
                              <num>(b)</num>
                              <content>
                                 <p>where the fish is unfit for human consumption for reasons other than size; or</p>
                              </content>
                           </point>
                           <point>
                              <num>(c)</num>
                              <content>
                                 <p>when a serious malfunction of freezer equipment occurs.</p>
                              </content>
                           </point>
                        </list>
                     </paragraph>
                  </article>
                  <article xml:id="art_d1e2957">
                     <num>Article 39</num>
                     <heading>Limitations to the number of Union fishing vessels authorised to fish swordfish</heading>
                     <paragraph>
                        <content>
                           <p>The maximum number of Union fishing vessels authorised to fish for swordfish (<i>Xiphias gladius</i>) in areas south of 20° S of the WCPFC Convention Area shall be as set out in Annex VII.</p>
                        </content>
                     </paragraph>
                  </article>
                  <article xml:id="art_d1e2968">
                     <num>Article 40</num>
                     <heading>Silky sharks and oceanic whitetip sharks</heading>
                     <paragraph>
                        <num>1.</num>
                        <subparagraph>
                           <content>
                              <p>Retaining on board, transhipping, storing or landing any part or whole carcass of the following species in the WCPFC Convention Area shall be prohibited:</p>
                           </content>
                        </subparagraph>
                        <list>
                           <point>
                              <num>(a)</num>
                              <content>
                                 <p>silky sharks (<i>Carcharhinus falciformis</i>),</p>
                              </content>
                           </point>
                           <point>
                              <num>(b)</num>
                              <content>
                                 <p>oceanic whitetip sharks (<i>Carcharhinus longimanus</i>)</p>
                              </content>
                           </point>
                        </list>
                     </paragraph>
                     <paragraph>
                        <num>2.</num>
                        <content>
                           <p>When accidentally caught, species referred to in paragraph 1 shall not be harmed. Specimens shall be promptly released.</p>
                        </content>
                     </paragraph>
                  </article>
                  <article xml:id="art_d1e3003">
                     <num>Article 41</num>
                     <heading>Overlap area between IATTC and WCPFC</heading>
                     <paragraph>
                        <num>1.</num>
                        <content>
                           <p>Vessels listed exclusively in the WCPFC register shall apply the measures set out in Articles in this Section when fishing in the overlap area between IATTC and WCPFC as defined in Article 4(r).</p>
                        </content>
                     </paragraph>
                     <paragraph>
                        <num>2.</num>
                        <content>
                           <p>Vessels listed in both the WCPFC register and the IATTC register and vessels listed exclusively in the IATTC register shall apply the measures set out in Article 33(1)(a) and (2) to (4) and Article 34 when fishing in the overlap area between IATTC and WCPFC as defined in Article 4(r).</p>
                        </content>
                     </paragraph>
                  </article>
               </section>
               <section>
                  <num>Section 8</num>
                  <heading>Bering Sea</heading>
                  <article xml:id="art_d1e3029">
                     <num>Article 42</num>
                     <heading>Prohibition on fishing in the high seas of the Bering Sea</heading>
                     <paragraph>
                        <content>
                           <p>Fishing for pollock (<i>Theragra chalcogramma</i>) in the high seas of the Bering Sea shall be prohibited.</p>
                        </content>
                     </paragraph>
                  </article>
               </section>
            </chapter>
         </title>
         <title>
            <num>TITLE III</num>
            <heading>FISHING OPPORTUNITIES FOR THIRD-COUNTRY VESSELS IN UNION WATERS</heading>
            <article xml:id="art_d1e3048">
               <num>Article 43</num>
               <heading>TACs</heading>
               <paragraph>
                  <content>
                     <p>Fishing vessels flying the flag of Norway and fishing vessels registered in the Faroe Islands shall be authorised to make catches in Union waters within the TACs set out in Annex I to this Regulation and shall be subject to the conditions provided for in this Regulation and Chapter III of Regulation (EC) No 1006/2008.</p>
                  </content>
               </paragraph>
            </article>
            <article xml:id="art_d1e3055">
               <num>Article 44</num>
               <heading>Fishing authorisations</heading>
               <paragraph>
                  <content>
                     <p>The maximum number of fishing authorisations for third-country vessels fishing in Union waters shall be as set out in Annex VIII.</p>
                  </content>
               </paragraph>
            </article>
            <article xml:id="art_d1e3062">
               <num>Article 45</num>
               <heading>Conditions for landing catches and by-catches</heading>
               <paragraph>
                  <content>
                     <p>The conditions specified in Article 7 shall apply to catches and by-catches of third-country vessels fishing under the authorisations specified in Article 44.</p>
                  </content>
               </paragraph>
            </article>
            <article xml:id="art_d1e3070">
               <num>Article 46</num>
               <heading>Prohibitions</heading>
               <paragraph>
                  <num>1.</num>
                  <subparagraph>
                     <content>
                        <p>It shall be prohibited for third-country vessels to fish for, to retain on board, to tranship or to land the following species whenever they are found in Union waters:</p>
                     </content>
                  </subparagraph>
                  <list>
                     <point>
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <content>
                           <p>starry ray (<i>Amblyraja radiata</i>) in Union waters of ICES divisions IIa, IIIa and VIId and ICES subarea IV;</p>
                        </content>
                     </point>
                     <point>
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <alinea>
                           <content>
                              <p>the following species of sawfish in Union waters:</p>
                           </content>
                        </alinea>
                        <list>
                           <indent>
                              <num>-</num>
                              <content>
                                 <p>narrow sawfish (<i>Anoxypristis cuspidate</i>);</p>
                              </content>
                           </indent>
                           <indent>
                              <num>-</num>
                              <content>
                                 <p>dwarf sawfish (<i>Pristis clavata</i>);</p>
                              </content>
                           </indent>
                           <indent>
                              <num>-</num>
                              <content>
                                 <p>smalltooth sawfish (<i>Pristis pectinata</i>);</p>
                              </content>
                           </indent>
                           <indent>
                              <num>-</num>
                              <content>
                                 <p>largetooth sawfish (<i>Pristis pristis</i>);</p>
                              </content>
                           </indent>
                           <indent>
                              <num>-</num>
                              <content>
                                 <p>green sawfish (<i>Pristis zijsron</i>);</p>
                              </content>
                           </indent>
                        </list>
                     </point>
                     <point>
                        <num>(c)</num>
                        <content>
                           <p>basking shark (<i>Cetorhinus maximus</i>) and white shark (<i>Carcharodon carcharias</i>) in Union waters;</p>
                        </content>
                     </point>
                     <point>
                        <num>(d)</num>
                        <content>
                           <p>common skate (<i>Dipturus batis</i>) complex (<i>Dipturus</i> cf. <i>flossada</i> and <i>Dipturus</i> cf. <i>intermedia</i>) in Union waters of ICES division IIa and ICES subareas III, IV, VI, VII, VIII, IX and X;</p>
                        </content>
                     </point>
                     <point>
                        <num>(e)</num>
                        <content>
                           <p>tope shark (<i>Galeorhinus galeus</i>) when taken with longlines in Union waters of ICES division IIa and ICES subareas I, IV, V, VI, VII, VIII, XII and XIV;</p>
                        </content>
                     </point>
                     <point>
                        <num>(f)</num>
                        <content>
                           <p>smooth lanternshark (<i>Etmopterus pusillus</i>) in Union waters of ICES division IIa and ICES subareas I, IV, V, VI, VII, VIII, XII and XIV;</p>
                        </content>
                     </point>
                     <point>
                        <num>(g)</num>
                        <content>
                           <p>kitefin shark (<i>Dalatias licha</i>), birdbeak dogfish (<i>Deania calcea</i>), leafscale gulper shark (<i>Centrophorus squamosus</i>), great lanternshark (<i>Etmopterus princeps</i>) and Portuguese dogfish (<i>Centroscymnus coelolepis</i>) in Union waters of ICES division IIa and ICES subareas I, IV and XIV;</p>
                        </content>
                     </point>
                     <point>
                        <num>(h)</num>
                        <content>
                           <p>porbeagle (<i>Lamna nasus</i>) in Union waters;</p>
                        </content>
                     </point>
                     <point>
                        <num>(i)</num>
                        <content>
                           <p>reef manta ray (<i>Manta alfredi</i>) in Union waters;</p>
                        </content>
                     </point>
                     <point>
                        <num>(j)</num>
                        <content>
                           <p>giant manta ray (<i>Manta birostris</i>) in Union waters;</p>
                        </content>
                     </point>
                     <point>
                        <num>(k)</num>
                        <alinea>
                           <content>
                              <p>the following species of Mobula rays in Union waters:</p>
                           </content>
                        </alinea>
                        <list>
                           <point>
                              <num>(i)</num>
                              <content>
                                 <p>devil fish (<i>Mobula mobular</i>);</p>
                              </content>
                           </point>
                           <point>
                              <num>(ii)</num>
                              <content>
                                 <p>lesser Guinean devil ray (<i>Mobula rochebrunei</i>);</p>
                              </content>
                           </point>
                           <point>
                              <num>(iii)</num>
                              <content>
                                 <p>spinetail mobula (<i>Mobula japanica</i>);</p>
                              </content>
                           </point>
                           <point>
                              <num>(iv)</num>
                              <content>
                                 <p>smoothtail mobula (<i>Mobula thurstoni</i>);</p>
                              </content>
                           </point>
                           <point>
                              <num>(v)</num>
                              <content>
                                 <p>longhorned mobula (<i>Mobula eregoodootenkee</i>);</p>
                              </content>
                           </point>
                           <point>
                              <num>(vi)</num>
                              <content>
                                 <p>Munk&apos;s devil ray (<i>Mobula munkiana</i>);</p>
                              </content>
                           </point>
                           <point>
                              <num>(vii)</num>
                              <content>
                                 <p>Chilean devil ray (<i>Mobula tarapacana</i>);</p>
                              </content>
                           </point>
                           <point>
                              <num>(viii)</num>
                              <content>
                                 <p>shortfin devil ray (<i>Mobula kuhlii</i>);</p>
                              </content>
                           </point>
                           <point>
                              <num>(ix)</num>
                              <content>
                                 <p>lesser devil ray (<i>Mobula hypostoma</i>);</p>
                              </content>
                           </point>
                        </list>
                     </point>
                     <point>
                        <num>(l)</num>
                        <content>
                           <p>thornback ray (<i>Raja clavata</i>) in Union waters of ICES division IIIa;</p>
                        </content>
                     </point>
                     <point>
                        <num>(m)</num>
                        <content>
                           <p>Norwegian skate (<i>Raja</i> (<i>Dipturus</i>) <i>nidarosiensis</i>) in Union waters of ICES divisions VIa, VIb, VIIa, VIIb, VIIc, VIIe, VIIf, VIIg, VIIh and VIIk;</p>
                        </content>
                     </point>
                     <point>
                        <num>(n)</num>
                        <content>
                           <p>undulate ray (<i>Raja undulata</i>) in Union waters of ICES subareas VI, IX and X and white skate (<i>Raja alba</i>) in Union waters of ICES subareas VI, VII, VIII, IX and X;</p>
                        </content>
                     </point>
                     <point>
                        <num>(o)</num>
                        <content>
                           <p>guitarfishes (<i>Rhinobatidae</i>) in Union waters of ICES subareas I, II, III, IV, V, VI, VII, VIII, IX, X and XII;</p>
                        </content>
                     </point>
                     <point>
                        <num>(p)</num>
                        <content>
                           <p>angel shark (<i>Squatina squatina</i>) in Union waters.</p>
                        </content>
                     </point>
                  </list>
               </paragraph>
               <paragraph>
                  <num>2.</num>
                  <content>
                     <p>When accidentally caught, the species referred to in paragraph 1 shall not be harmed. Specimens shall be promptly released.</p>
                  </content>
               </paragraph>
            </article>
         </title>
         <title>
            <num>TITLE IV</num>
            <heading>FISHING OPPORTUNITIES FOR 2015</heading>
            <article xml:id="art_d1e3387">
               <num>Article 47</num>
               <heading>Amendment to Regulation (EU) 2015/104</heading>
               <paragraph>
                  <content>
                     <p>The TAC table for skates and rays in Union waters of VIId in Annex IA to Regulation (EU) 2015/104 is replaced by the following table:</p>
                  </content>
               </paragraph>
               <paragraph>
                  <content>
                     <table class="TBL">
                        <authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="34">
                           <p>Catches of cuckoo ray (<i>Leucoraja naevus</i>) (RJN/07D.), thornback ray (<i>Raja clavata</i>) (RJC/07D.), blonde ray (<i>Raja brachyura</i>) (RJH/07D.), spotted ray (<i>Raja montagui</i>) (RJM/07D.), small-eyed ray (<i>Raja microocellata</i>) (RJE/07D.) and undulate ray (<i>Raja undulata</i>) (RJU/07D.) shall be reported separately.</p>
                        </authorialNote>
                        <authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="35">
                           <p>Special condition: of which up to 5 % may be fished in Union waters of VIa, VIb, VIIa-c and VIIe-k (SRX/*67AKD). Catches of Cuckoo ray (<i>Leucoraja naevus</i>) (RJN/*67AKD), thornback ray (<i>Raja clavata</i>) (RJC/*67AKD), blonde ray (<i>Raja brachyura</i>) (RJH/*67AKD), spotted ray (<i>Raja montagui</i>) (RJM/*67AKD) and small-eyed ray (<i>Raja microocellata</i>) (RJE/*67AKD) shall be reported separately. This special condition shall not apply to undulate ray (<i>Raja undulata</i>).</p>
                        </authorialNote>
                        <authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="36">
                           <p>Shall not apply to undulate ray (<i>Raja undulata</i>). This species shall not be targeted in the areas covered by this TAC. In cases where it is not subject to the landing obligation, by-catch of undulate ray in the area covered by this TAC may only be landed whole or gutted, and provided that it does not comprise more than 20 kilograms live weight per fishing trip. The catches shall remain under the quotas shown in the table below. The former provisions are without prejudice to the prohibitions set out in Articles 12 and 44 of this Regulation for the areas specified therein. By-catches of undulate ray shall be reported separately under the following code: (RJU/07D.). Within the limits of the abovementioned quotas, no more than the quantities of undulate ray given below may be taken:</p>
                           <alinea>
                              <content>
                                 <table class="TBL">
                                    <p>Special condition:</p>
                                    <p><!--default P | TXT -->of which up to 5 % may be fished in Union waters of VIIe and reported under the following code: (RJU/*67AKD). This special condition is without prejudice to the prohibitions set out in Articles 12 and 44 of this Regulation for the areas specified therein.</p>
                                    <tr>
                                       <th>
                                          <p>
                                             <b>Species:</b>
                                          </p>
                                       </th>
                                       <th>
                                          <p>Undulate ray</p>
                                          <p>
                                             <i>Raja undulata</i>
                                          </p>
                                       </th>
                                       <th>
                                          <p>
                                             <b>Zone:</b>
                                          </p>
                                       </th>
                                       <th>
                                          <p>Union waters of VIId</p>
                                          <p>(RJU/07D.)</p>
                                       </th>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                       <td>
                                          <p>Belgium</p>
                                       </td>
                                       <td>
                                          <p>1</p>
                                       </td>
                                       <td>
                                          <p/>
                                       </td>
                                       <td>
                                          <p/>
                                       </td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                       <td>
                                          <p>France</p>
                                       </td>
                                       <td>
                                          <p>8</p>
                                       </td>
                                       <td>
                                          <p/>
                                       </td>
                                       <td>
                                          <p/>
                                       </td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                       <td>
                                          <p>The Netherlands</p>
                                       </td>
                                       <td>
                                          <p>0</p>
                                       </td>
                                       <td>
                                          <p/>
                                       </td>
                                       <td>
                                          <p/>
                                       </td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                       <td>
                                          <p>United Kingdom</p>
                                       </td>
                                       <td>
                                          <p>2</p>
                                       </td>
                                       <td>
                                          <p/>
                                       </td>
                                       <td>
                                          <p/>
                                       </td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                       <td>
                                          <p>Union</p>
                                       </td>
                                       <td>
                                          <p>11</p>
                                       </td>
                                       <td>
                                          <p/>
                                       </td>
                                       <td>
                                          <p/>
                                       </td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                       <td>
                                          <p>TAC</p>
                                       </td>
                                       <td>
                                          <p>11</p>
                                       </td>
                                       <td>
                                          <p/>
                                       </td>
                                       <td>
                                          <p><!--!!! HT is implicitely treated !!!-->Precautionary TAC</p>
                                       </td>
                                    </tr>
                                 </table>
                              </content>
                           </alinea>
                        </authorialNote>
                        <tr>
                           <th>
                              <p>
                                 <b>Species:</b>
                              </p>
                           </th>
                           <th>
                              <p>Skates and rays</p>
                              <p>
                                 <i>Rajiformes</i>
                              </p>
                           </th>
                           <th>
                              <p>
                                 <b>Zone:</b>
                              </p>
                           </th>
                           <th>
                              <p>Union waters of VIId</p>
                              <p>(SRX/07D.)</p>
                           </th>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                           <td>
                              <p>Belgium</p>
                           </td>
                           <td>
                              <p>79<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="37"/>
                                 <authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="38"/>
                                 <authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="39"/>
                              </p>
                           </td>
                           <td>
                              <p/>
                           </td>
                           <td>
                              <p/>
                           </td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                           <td>
                              <p>France</p>
                           </td>
                           <td>
                              <p>663<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="40"/>
                                 <authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="41"/>
                                 <authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="42"/>
                              </p>
                           </td>
                           <td>
                              <p/>
                           </td>
                           <td>
                              <p/>
                           </td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                           <td>
                              <p>The Netherlands</p>
                           </td>
                           <td>
                              <p>4<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="43"/>
                                 <authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="44"/>
                                 <authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="45"/>
                              </p>
                           </td>
                           <td>
                              <p/>
                           </td>
                           <td>
                              <p/>
                           </td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                           <td>
                              <p>United Kingdom</p>
                           </td>
                           <td>
                              <p>132<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="46"/>
                                 <authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="47"/>
                                 <authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="48"/>
                              </p>
                           </td>
                           <td>
                              <p/>
                           </td>
                           <td>
                              <p/>
                           </td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                           <td>
                              <p>Union</p>
                           </td>
                           <td>
                              <p>878<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="49"/>
                                 <authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="50"/>
                                 <authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="51"/>
                              </p>
                           </td>
                           <td>
                              <p/>
                           </td>
                           <td>
                              <p/>
                           </td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                           <td>
                              <p>TAC</p>
                           </td>
                           <td>
                              <p>878<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="52"/>
                              </p>
                           </td>
                           <td>
                              <p/>
                           </td>
                           <td>
                              <p><!--!!! HT is implicitely treated !!!-->Precautionary TAC</p>
                           </td>
                        </tr>
                     </table>
                  </content>
               </paragraph>
            </article>
         </title>
         <title>
            <num>TITLE V</num>
            <heading>FINAL PROVISIONS</heading>
            <article xml:id="art_d1e3632">
               <num>Article 48</num>
               <heading>Committee procedure</heading>
               <paragraph>
                  <num>1.</num>
                  <content>
                     <p>The Commission shall be assisted by the Committee for Fisheries and Aquaculture established by Regulation (EU) No 1380/2013. That committee shall be a committee within the meaning of Regulation (EU) No 182/2011.</p>
                  </content>
               </paragraph>
               <paragraph>
                  <num>2.</num>
                  <content>
                     <p>Where reference is made to this paragraph, Article 5 of Regulation (EU) No 182/2011 shall apply.</p>
                  </content>
               </paragraph>
            </article>
            <article xml:id="art_d1e3647">
               <num>Article 49</num>
               <heading>Entry into force</heading>
               <paragraph>
                  <content>
                     <p>This Regulation shall enter into force on the day following that of its publication in the <i>Official Journal of the European Union</i>.</p>
                  </content>
               </paragraph>
               <paragraph>
                  <content>
                     <p>It shall apply from 1 January 2016.</p>
                  </content>
               </paragraph>
               <paragraph>
                  <content>
                     <p>However, Article 8 shall apply from 1 February 2016.</p>
                  </content>
               </paragraph>
               <paragraph>
                  <content>
                     <p>The provisions on fishing opportunities set out in Articles 25, 26 and 27 and Annexes IE and V for the CCAMLR Convention Area shall apply from the dates specified therein.</p>
                  </content>
               </paragraph>
            </article>
         </title>
         <clause>
            <content>
               <p>This Regulation shall be binding in its entirety and directly applicable in all Member States.</p>
            </content>
         </clause>
      </body>
      <conclusions>
         <p>Done at Brussels, 22 January 2016.</p>
         <block name="signatory">
            <signature>
               <organization refersTo="">For the Council</organization>
               <role refersTo="">The President</role>
               <person refersTo="">A.G. KOENDERS</person>
            </signature>
         </block>
      </conclusions>
   </bill>
</akomaNtoso>
