<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0"
            xmlns:fmx="http://formex.publications.europa.eu/schema/formex-05.21-20110601.xd"
            xmlns:leos="urn:eu:europa:ec:leos"
            xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema">
   <bill name="">
      <meta xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions">
         <identification source="~COM">
            <FRBRWork>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRcountry value=""/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
         </identification>
      </meta>
      <preface>
         <longTitle>
            <p>
               <docStage/>
               <docType>COMMISSION REGULATION (EU) 2016/1776</docType>of 6 October 2016<docPurpose>amending Annex II to Regulation (EC) No 1333/2008 of the European Parliament and of the Council as regards the use of sucralose (E 955) as a flavour enhancer in chewing gum with added sugars or polyols</docPurpose>
            </p>
         </longTitle>
         <container name="EEArelevance">
            <p>(Text with EEA relevance)</p>
         </container>
      </preface>
      <preamble>
         <formula name="actingEntity">
            <p>THE EUROPEAN COMMISSION,</p>
         </formula>
         <citations>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to Regulation (EC) No 1333/2008 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 16 December 2008 on food additives<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="1">
                     <p>OJ L 354, 31.12.2008, p. 16.</p>
                  </authorialNote>, and in particular Article 10(3) thereof,</p>
            </citation>
         </citations>
         <recitals xml:id="recs_d223e71">
            <intro>
               <p>Whereas:</p>
            </intro>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d223e74">
               <num>(1)</num>
               <p>Annex II to Regulation (EC) No 1333/2008 lays down a Union list of food additives approved for use in food and their conditions of use.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d223e80">
               <num>(2)</num>
               <p>That list may be updated in accordance with the common procedure referred to in Article 3(1) of Regulation (EC) No 1331/2008 of the European Parliament and of the Council<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="2">
                     <p>Regulation (EC) No 1331/2008 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 16 December 2008 establishing a common authorisation procedure for food additives, food enzymes and food flavourings (OJ L 354, 31.12.2008, p. 1).</p>
                  </authorialNote>, either on the initiative of the Commission or following an application.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d223e96">
               <num>(3)</num>
               <p>On 19 January 2015 an application was submitted for authorisation of the use of sucralose (E 955) as a flavour enhancer in chewing gum with added sugars or polyols. The application was subsequently made available to the Member States pursuant to Article 4 of Regulation (EC) No 1331/2008.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d223e105">
               <num>(4)</num>
               <p>Sucralose was evaluated in 2000 by the European Union Scientific Committee on Food (SCF) which established an acceptable daily intake (ADI) of 15 mg/kg body weight/day<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="3">
                     <p>Opinion of the Scientific Committee on Food on sucralose (Adopted by the SCF on 7 September 2000) Available online: http://ec.europa.eu/food/fs/sc/scf/out68_en.pdf</p>
                  </authorialNote>.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d223e118">
               <num>(5)</num>
               <p>The use of sucralose (E 955) as a flavour enhancer in chewing gum with added sugars or polyols increases the overall intensity of the flavour of the chewing gum, and maintains that intensity over a longer period of time as the gum is chewed, compared to other food additive(s) formulations. Increasing the intensity and longevity of the flavour thus provides the consumer with a better overall experience whilst chewing the gum.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d223e124">
               <num>(6)</num>
               <p>Authorising sucralose at 1200 mg/kg in chewing gum with added sugars or polyols would lead to an increase in the intake of E 955 within the following limits: between 0 up to 0,1 % of the ADI in the case of mean consumption and between 0 up to 4,3 % of the ADI in the case of high level consumption. This is considered to be an additional minor exposure of the consumer and therefore is not of safety concern.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d223e133">
               <num>(7)</num>
               <p>Pursuant to Article 3(2) of Regulation (EC) No 1331/2008, the Commission is to seek the opinion of the European Food Safety Authority (&apos;the Authority&apos;) in order to update the Union list of food additives set out in Annex II to Regulation (EC) No 1333/2008, except where that update is not liable to have an effect on human health. Since the authorisation of use of sucralose (E 955) as a flavour enhancer in chewing gum with added sugars or polyols constitutes an update of that list which is not liable to have an effect on human health, it is not necessary to seek the opinion of the Authority.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d223e144">
               <num>(8)</num>
               <p>Therefore, it is appropriate to authorise the use of sucralose (E 955) as a flavour enhancer at a maximum level of 1200 mg/kg in chewing gum with added sugars or polyols (food subcategory 5.3).</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d223e153">
               <num>(9)</num>
               <p>Annex II to Regulation (EC) No 1333/2008 should therefore be amended accordingly.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d223e160">
               <num>(10)</num>
               <p>The measures provided for in this Regulation are in accordance with the opinion of the Standing Committee on Plants, Animals, Food and Feed,</p>
            </recital>
         </recitals>
         <formula name="enactingFormula">
            <p>HAS ADOPTED THIS REGULATION:</p>
         </formula>
      </preamble>
      <body>
         <article xml:id="art_d223e169">
            <num>Article 1</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>Annex II to Regulation (EC) No 1333/2008 is amended in accordance with the Annex to this Regulation.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <article xml:id="art_d223e174">
            <num>Article 2</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>This Regulation shall enter into force on the twentieth day following that of its publication in the <i>Official Journal of the European Union</i>.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <clause>
            <content>
               <p>This Regulation shall be binding in its entirety and directly applicable in all Member States.</p>
            </content>
         </clause>
      </body>
      <conclusions>
         <p>Done at Brussels, 6 October 2016.</p>
         <block name="signatory">
            <signature>
               <organization refersTo="">For the Commission</organization>
               <role refersTo="">The President</role>
               <person refersTo="">Jean-Claude JUNCKER</person>
            </signature>
         </block>
      </conclusions>
   </bill>
</akomaNtoso>
