<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0"
            xmlns:fmx="http://formex.publications.europa.eu/schema/formex-05.21-20110601.xd"
            xmlns:leos="urn:eu:europa:ec:leos"
            xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema">
   <bill name="">
      <meta xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions">
         <identification source="~COM">
            <FRBRWork>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRcountry value=""/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
         </identification>
      </meta>
      <preface>
         <longTitle>
            <p>
               <docStage/>
               <docType>COUNCIL REGULATION (EU) 2019/1889</docType>of 11 November 2019<docPurpose>amending Regulation (EU) 2017/2063 concerning restrictive measures in view of the situation in Venezuela</docPurpose>
            </p>
         </longTitle>
      </preface>
      <preamble>
         <formula name="actingEntity">
            <p>THE COUNCIL OF THE EUROPEAN UNION,</p>
         </formula>
         <citations>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union, and in particular Article 215 thereof,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to Council Decision (CFSP) 2017/2074 of 13 November 2017 concerning restrictive measures in view of the situation in Venezuela<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="1">
                     <p>OJ L 295, 14.11.2017, p. 60.</p>
                  </authorialNote>,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the joint proposal from the High Representative of the Union for Foreign Affairs and Security Policy and the European Commission,</p>
            </citation>
         </citations>
         <recitals xml:id="recs_d605e70">
            <intro>
               <p>Whereas:</p>
            </intro>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d605e73">
               <num>(1)</num>
               <p>Council Regulation (EU) 2017/2063<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="2">
                     <p>Council Regulation (EU) 2017/2063 of 13 November 2017 concerning restrictive measures in view of the situation in Venezuela (OJ L 295, 14.11.2017, p. 21).</p>
                  </authorialNote> gives effect to several restrictive measures provided for in Decision (CFSP) 2017/2074.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d605e89">
               <num>(2)</num>
               <p>On 11 November 2019, the Council adopted Decision (CFSP) 2019/1893<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="3">
                     <p>Council Decision (CFSP) 2019/1893 of 11 November 2019 amending Decision (CFSP) 2017/2074 concerning restrictive measures in view of the situation in Venezuela (See page 42. of this Official Journal).</p>
                  </authorialNote>, which amended Decision (CFSP) 2017/2074 by introducing an article on the processing of personal data by the Council and the High Representative.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d605e105">
               <num>(3)</num>
               <p>For the implementation of Regulation (EU) 2017/2063, and in order to ensure maximum legal certainty within the Union, the names of and other relevant data concerning natural and legal persons, entities and bodies whose funds and economic resources are frozen in accordance with that Regulation should be made public. Any processing of personal data must comply with Regulations (EU) 2016/679<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="4">
                     <p>Regulation (EU) 2016/679 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 27 April 2016 on the protection of natural persons with regard to the processing of personal data and on the free movement of such data, and repealing Directive 95/46/EC (General Data Protection Regulation) (OJ L 119, 4.5.2016, p. 1).</p>
                  </authorialNote> and (EU) 2018/1725<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="5">
                     <p>Regulation (EU) 2018/1725 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 23 October 2018 on the protection of natural persons with regard to the processing of personal data by the Union institutions, bodies, offices and agencies and on the free movement of such data, and repealing Regulation (EC) No 45/2001 and Decision No 1247/2002/EC (OJ L 295, 21.11.2018, p. 39).</p>
                  </authorialNote> of the European Parliament and of the Council.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d605e131">
               <num>(4)</num>
               <p>Regulation (EU) 2017/2063 should therefore be amended accordingly,</p>
            </recital>
         </recitals>
         <formula name="enactingFormula">
            <p>HAS ADOPTED THIS REGULATION:</p>
         </formula>
      </preamble>
      <body>
         <article xml:id="art_d605e141" leos:compliant="false">
            <num>Article 1</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>The following article is inserted in Regulation (EU) 2017/2063:</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>
                     <mod>
                        <quotedStructure startQuote="" endQuote="">
                           <alinea>
                              <content>
                                 <p>&apos;<i>Article 18a</i>
                                 </p>
                              </content>
                           </alinea>
                           <list>
                              <point>
                                 <num>1.</num>
                                 <alinea>
                                    <content>
                                       <p>The Council, the Commission and the High Representative of the Union for Foreign Affairs and Security Policy (the &quot;High Representative&quot;) may process personal data in order to carry out their tasks under this Regulation. These tasks include:</p>
                                    </content>
                                 </alinea>
                                 <list>
                                    <point>
                                       <num>(a)</num>
                                       <content>
                                          <p>as regards the Council, preparing and making amendments to Annexes IV and V;</p>
                                       </content>
                                    </point>
                                    <point>
                                       <num>(b)</num>
                                       <content>
                                          <p>as regards the High Representative, preparing amendments to Annexes IV and V;</p>
                                       </content>
                                    </point>
                                    <point>
                                       <num>(c)</num>
                                       <alinea>
                                          <content>
                                             <p>as regards the Commission:</p>
                                          </content>
                                       </alinea>
                                       <list>
                                          <point>
                                             <num>(i)</num>
                                             <content>
                                                <p>adding the contents of Annexes IV and V to the electronic consolidated list of persons, groups and entities subject to Union financial restrictive measures and in the interactive sanctions map, both publicly available;</p>
                                             </content>
                                          </point>
                                          <point>
                                             <num>(ii)</num>
                                             <content>
                                                <p>processing information on the impact of measures taken under this Regulation, such as the value of frozen funds and information on authorisations granted by the competent authorities.</p>
                                             </content>
                                          </point>
                                       </list>
                                    </point>
                                 </list>
                              </point>
                              <point>
                                 <num>2.</num>
                                 <content>
                                    <p>The Council, the Commission and the High Representative may process, where applicable, relevant data relating to criminal offences committed by listed natural persons, to criminal convictions of such persons or to security measures concerning such persons, only to the extent that such processing is necessary for the preparation of Annexes IV and V.</p>
                                 </content>
                              </point>
                              <point>
                                 <num>3.</num>
                                 <content>
                                    <p>For the purposes of this Regulation, the Council, the Commission service listed in Annex III to this Regulation and the High Representative are designated as &quot;controllers&quot; within the meaning of point (8) of Article 3 of Regulation (EU) 2018/1725 of the European Parliament and of the Council<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="6">
                                          <p>Regulation (EU) 2018/1725 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 23 October 2018 on the protection of natural persons with regard to the processing of personal data by the Union institutions, bodies, offices and agencies and on the free movement of such data, and repealing Regulation (EC) No 45/2001 and Decision No 1247/2002/EC (OJ L 295, 21.11.2018, p. 39).&apos;.</p>
                                       </authorialNote>, in order to ensure that the natural persons concerned can exercise their rights under Regulation (EU) 2018/1725.</p>
                                 </content>
                              </point>
                           </list>
                        </quotedStructure>
                     </mod>
                  </p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <article xml:id="art_d605e225">
            <num>Article 2</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>This Regulation shall enter into force on the day following that of its publication in the <i>Official Journal of the European Union</i>.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <clause>
            <content>
               <p>This Regulation shall be binding in its entirety and directly applicable in all Member States.</p>
            </content>
         </clause>
      </body>
      <conclusions>
         <p>Done at Brussels, 11 November 2019.</p>
         <block name="signatory">
            <signature>
               <organization refersTo="">For the Council</organization>
               <role refersTo="">The President</role>
               <person refersTo="">F. MOGHERINI</person>
            </signature>
         </block>
      </conclusions>
   </bill>
</akomaNtoso>
