<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0"
            xmlns:fmx="http://formex.publications.europa.eu/schema/formex-05.21-20110601.xd"
            xmlns:leos="urn:eu:europa:ec:leos"
            xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema">
   <bill name="">
      <meta xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions">
         <identification source="~COM">
            <FRBRWork>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRcountry value=""/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
         </identification>
      </meta>
      <preface>
         <longTitle>
            <p>
               <docStage/>
               <docType>COMMISSION REGULATION (EU) 2017/1261</docType>of 12 July 2017<docPurpose>amending Regulation (EU) No 142/2011 as regards an alternative method for processing certain rendered fats</docPurpose>
            </p>
         </longTitle>
         <container name="EEArelevance">
            <p>(Text with EEA relevance)</p>
         </container>
      </preface>
      <preamble>
         <formula name="actingEntity">
            <p>THE EUROPEAN COMMISSION,</p>
         </formula>
         <citations>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to Regulation (EC) No 1069/2009 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 21 October 2009 laying down health rules as regards animal by-products and derived products not intended for human consumption and repealing Regulation (EC) No 1774/2002<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="1">
                     <p>OJ L 300, 14.11.2009, p. 1.</p>
                  </authorialNote>, and in particular Article 20(11)(a) thereof,</p>
            </citation>
         </citations>
         <recitals xml:id="recs_d138e71">
            <intro>
               <p>Whereas:</p>
            </intro>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d138e74">
               <num>(1)</num>
               <p>Commission Regulation (EU) No 142/2011<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="2">
                     <p>Commission Regulation (EU) No 142/2011 of 25 February 2011 implementing Regulation (EC) No 1069/2009 of the European Parliament and of the Council laying down health rules as regards animal by-products and derived products not intended for human consumption and implementing Council Directive 97/78/EC as regards certain samples and items exempt from veterinary checks at the border under that Directive (OJ L 54, 26.2.2011, p. 1).</p>
                  </authorialNote> lays down rules implementing Regulation (EC) No 1069/2009 including procedures for adoption of an alternative processing method.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d138e90">
               <num>(2)</num>
               <p>Following an application of the competent authority of Finland for the authorisation of an alternative method for use or disposal of animal by-products or derived products, as referred to in Article 20 of Regulation (EC) No 1069/2009, the European Food Safety Authority (EFSA) published a Scientific Opinion on the use of a continuous multi-step catalytic hydro-treatment for the processing of rendered animal fat (Category 1)<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="3">
                     <p>EFSA Journal 2015;13(11):4307.</p>
                  </authorialNote>. This method may be used for the production of renewable diesel, renewable jet fuel, renewable propane and renewable gasoline. This method has been assessed by EFSA as a safe alternative method for processing of Category 1 rendered fats and the products may be declared as the end point in the manufacturing chain.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d138e100">
               <num>(3)</num>
               <p>Annex IV to Regulation (EU) No 142/2011 should therefore be amended accordingly.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d138e106">
               <num>(4)</num>
               <p>Derived products from the processing of Category 1 and 2 materials are to be permanently marked to ensure traceability and to prevent their entry into the food and feed chain. Annex VIII to Regulation (EU) No 142/2011 sets out requirements for the marking of those derived products. However, in accordance with point 3(e) of Chapter V of Annex VIII to that Regulation, marking is not required for renewable fuels referred to in point J of Section 2 of Chapter IV of Annex IV thereto.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d138e112">
               <num>(5)</num>
               <p>Since the multi-step catalytic hydro-treatment for the processing of rendered animal fat (Category 1) reduces the risks to animal and public health as efficiently as the method set out in point J of Section 2 of Chapter IV of Annex IV to Regulation (EU) No 142/2011, it should also be excluded from the marking requirements by adding reference to this method to point 3(e) of Chapter V to Annex VIII to that Regulation.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d138e118">
               <num>(6)</num>
               <p>Annex VIII to Regulation (EU) No 142/2011 should therefore be amended accordingly.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d138e124">
               <num>(7)</num>
               <p>The measures provided for in this Regulation are in accordance with the opinion of the Standing Committee on Plants, Animals, Food and Feed,</p>
            </recital>
         </recitals>
         <formula name="enactingFormula">
            <p>HAS ADOPTED THIS REGULATION:</p>
         </formula>
      </preamble>
      <body>
         <article xml:id="art_d138e134" leos:compliant="false">
            <num>Article 1</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>In Article 3 of Regulation (EU) No 142/2011, the following point (k) is added:</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>
                     <mod>
                        <quotedStructure startQuote="" endQuote="">
                           <point>
                              <num>&apos;(k)</num>
                              <content>
                                 <p>renewable diesel, renewable jet fuel, renewable propane and renewable gasoline which fulfil the specific requirements for products from the multi-step catalytic hydro-treatment for the production of renewable fuels set out in point 2(f) of Section 3 of Chapter IV of Annex IV.&apos;</p>
                              </content>
                           </point>
                        </quotedStructure>
                     </mod>
                  </p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <article xml:id="art_d138e148">
            <num>Article 2</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>Annexes IV and VIII to Regulation (EU) No 142/2011 are amended in accordance with the text in the Annex to this Regulation.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <article xml:id="art_d138e153">
            <num>Article 3</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>This Regulation shall enter into force on the twentieth day following that of its publication in the <i>Official Journal of the European Union</i>.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <clause>
            <content>
               <p>This Regulation shall be binding in its entirety and directly applicable in all Member States.</p>
            </content>
         </clause>
      </body>
      <conclusions>
         <p>Done at Brussels, 12 July 2017.</p>
         <block name="signatory">
            <signature>
               <organization refersTo="">For the Commission</organization>
               <role refersTo="">The President</role>
               <person refersTo="">Jean-Claude JUNCKER</person>
            </signature>
         </block>
      </conclusions>
   </bill>
</akomaNtoso>
