<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0"
            xmlns:fmx="http://formex.publications.europa.eu/schema/formex-05.21-20110601.xd"
            xmlns:leos="urn:eu:europa:ec:leos"
            xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema">
   <bill name="">
      <meta xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions">
         <identification source="~COM">
            <FRBRWork>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRcountry value=""/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
         </identification>
      </meta>
      <preface>
         <longTitle>
            <p>
               <docStage/>
               <docType>COUNCIL REGULATION (EU) 2021/2283</docType>of 20 December 2021<docPurpose>opening and providing for the management of autonomous tariff quotas of the Union for certain agricultural and industrial products, and repealing Regulation (EU) No 1388/2013</docPurpose>
            </p>
         </longTitle>
      </preface>
      <preamble>
         <formula name="actingEntity">
            <p>THE COUNCIL OF THE EUROPEAN UNION,</p>
         </formula>
         <citations>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union, and in particular Article 31 thereof,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the proposal from the European Commission,</p>
            </citation>
         </citations>
         <recitals xml:id="recs_d744e59">
            <intro>
               <p>Whereas:</p>
            </intro>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d744e62">
               <num>(1)</num>
               <p>The production of certain agricultural and industrial products in the Union is insufficient to meet the specific requirements of the user industries in the Union. Consequently, Union supplies of those products depend on imports from third countries. The most urgent Union requirements for the products concerned should be met immediately on the most favorable terms. Autonomous tariff quotas of the Union (&apos;quotas&apos;) at preferential quota duty rates should therefore be opened within the limits of appropriate quota volumes, taking account of the need not to disturb the markets for such products or impede the establishment or development of production in the Union.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d744e72">
               <num>(2)</num>
               <p>It is necessary to ensure equal and uninterrupted access to the quotas for all importers in the Union and to ensure the uninterrupted application of the quota duty rates laid down for those quotas to all imports of the products concerned into all Member States until the quotas have been exhausted.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d744e78">
               <num>(3)</num>
               <p>Commission Implementing Regulation (EU) 2015/2447<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="1">
                     <p>Commission Implementing Regulation (EU) 2015/2447 of 24 November 2015 laying down detailed rules for implementing certain provisions of Regulation (EU) No 952/2013 of the European Parliament and of the Council laying down the Union Customs Code (OJ L 343, 29.12.2015, p. 558).</p>
                  </authorialNote> provides for a system of quota management which ensures equal and uninterrupted access to the quotas and uninterrupted application of the quota duty rates, and which follows the chronological order of the dates of acceptance of declarations of release for free circulation. The quotas opened by this Regulation should therefore be managed by the Commission and the Member States in accordance with that system.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d744e94">
               <num>(4)</num>
               <p>The quota volumes are mostly expressed in supplementary units of weight. For certain products for which a quota is opened, the quota volume is set out in another supplementary unit. Where no supplementary unit is specified for those products in the Combined Nomenclature laid down in Annex I to Council Regulation (EEC) No 2658/87<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="2">
                     <p>Council Regulation (EEC) No 2658/87 of 23 July 1987 on the tariff and statistical nomenclature and on the Common Customs Tariff (OJ L 256, 7.9.1987, p. 1).</p>
                  </authorialNote> (&apos;the Combined Nomenclature&apos;), there can be uncertainty in respect of the supplementary unit used. For the sake of clarity and in the interests of better quota management, it is therefore necessary to provide that, in order to benefit from those quotas, the exact quantity of the products imported be entered in the declaration for release for free circulation using the supplementary unit of the quota volume set out for those products in this Regulation.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d744e115">
               <num>(5)</num>
               <p>It is necessary to clarify that any mixtures, preparations or products made up of different components containing products subject to quotas should be excluded from the scope of this Regulation, as only the products as described in this Regulation should be subject to the quotas.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d744e121">
               <num>(6)</num>
               <p>Council Regulation (EU) No 1388/2013<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="3">
                     <p>Council Regulation (EU) No 1388/2013 of 17 December 2013 opening and providing for the management of autonomous tariff quotas of the Union for certain agricultural and industrial products, and repealing Regulation (EU) No 7/2010 (OJ L 354, 28.12.2013, p. 319).</p>
                  </authorialNote> has been amended many times. In addition, as the coding of the Combined Nomenclature has been updated by Commission Implementing Regulation (EU) 2021/1832<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="4">
                     <p>Commission Implementing Regulation (EU) 2021/1832 of 12 October 2021 amending Annex I to Council Regulation (EEC) No 2658/87 on the tariff and statistical nomenclature and on the Common Customs Tariff (OJ L 385, 29.10.2021, p. 1).</p>
                  </authorialNote>, a large number of changes to Regulation (EU) No 1388/2013 would be required. Therefore, in the interests of clarity and transparency, that Regulation should be replaced in its entirety.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d744e147">
               <num>(7)</num>
               <p>In accordance with the principle of proportionality, it is necessary and appropriate for the achievement of the basic objective of promoting trade between Member States and third countries to lay down rules in order to balance the different commercial interests of economic operators in the Union without changing the Union&apos;s World Trade Organization schedule. This Regulation does not go beyond what is necessary in order to achieve the objectives pursued in accordance with Article 5(4) of the Treaty on European Union.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d744e153">
               <num>(8)</num>
               <p>In order to avoid any interruption of the application of the quota scheme and to comply with the guidelines set out in the communication from the Commission of 13 December 2011 concerning autonomous tariff suspensions and quotas, the quotas for the products listed in this Regulation should apply from 1 January 2022. This Regulation should therefore enter into force as a matter of urgency,</p>
            </recital>
         </recitals>
         <formula name="enactingFormula">
            <p>HAS ADOPTED THIS REGULATION:</p>
         </formula>
      </preamble>
      <body>
         <article xml:id="art_d744e168">
            <num>Article 1</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <num>1.</num>
               <content>
                  <p>For the agricultural and industrial products listed in the Annex, autonomous tariff quotas of the Union (&apos;quotas&apos;) shall be opened.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph>
               <num>2.</num>
               <content>
                  <p>Within the quotas referred to in paragraph 1 of this Article, the Common Customs Tariff duties referred to in Article 56(2), point (c), of Regulation (EU) No 952/2013 of the European Parliament and of the Council<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="5">
                        <p>Regulation (EU) No 952/2013 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 9 October 2013 laying down the Union Customs Code (OJ L 269, 10.10.2013, p. 1).</p>
                     </authorialNote> are suspended for the quota periods, at the quota duty rates and up to the quota volumes indicated in the Annex to this Regulation.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph>
               <num>3.</num>
               <content>
                  <p>Paragraphs 1 and 2 do not apply to any mixtures, preparations or products made up of different components containing products listed in the Annex.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <article xml:id="art_d744e200">
            <num>Article 2</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>The quotas referred to in Article 1 of this Regulation shall be managed by the Commission in accordance with Articles 49 to 54 of Implementing Regulation (EU) 2015/2447.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <article xml:id="art_d744e205">
            <num>Article 3</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>Where a customs declaration for release for free circulation is lodged for products for which supplementary units have been provided in the Annex, the exact quantity of the products imported shall be entered in that declaration using the supplementary unit set out in the Annex.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <article xml:id="art_d744e211">
            <num>Article 4</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>Regulation (EU) No 1388/2013 is repealed.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <article xml:id="art_d744e216">
            <num>Article 5</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>This Regulation shall enter into force on the day following that of its publication in the <i>Official Journal of the European Union</i>.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>It shall apply from 1 January 2022.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <clause>
            <content>
               <p>This Regulation shall be binding in its entirety and directly applicable in all Member States.</p>
            </content>
         </clause>
      </body>
      <conclusions>
         <p>Done at Brussels, 20 December 2021.</p>
         <block name="signatory">
            <signature>
               <organization refersTo="">For the Council</organization>
               <role refersTo="">The President</role>
               <person refersTo="">A. VIZJAK</person>
            </signature>
         </block>
      </conclusions>
   </bill>
</akomaNtoso>
