<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0"
            xmlns:fmx="http://formex.publications.europa.eu/schema/formex-05.21-20110601.xd"
            xmlns:leos="urn:eu:europa:ec:leos"
            xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema">
   <bill name="">
      <meta xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions">
         <identification source="~COM">
            <FRBRWork>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRcountry value=""/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
         </identification>
      </meta>
      <preface>
         <longTitle>
            <p>
               <docStage/>
               <docType>COMMISSION REGULATION (EU) 2021/1080</docType>of 28 June 2021<docPurpose>amending Regulation (EC) No 1126/2008 adopting certain international accounting standards in accordance with Regulation (EC) No 1606/2002 of the European Parliament and of the Council as regards International Accounting Standards 16, 37 and 41, and International Financial Reporting Standards 1, 3 and 9</docPurpose>
            </p>
         </longTitle>
         <container name="EEArelevance">
            <p>(Text with EEA relevance)</p>
         </container>
      </preface>
      <preamble>
         <formula name="actingEntity">
            <p>THE EUROPEAN COMMISSION,</p>
         </formula>
         <citations>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to Regulation (EC) No 1606/2002 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 19 July 2002 on the application of international accounting standards<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="1">
                     <p>OJ L 243, 11.9.2002, p. 1.</p>
                  </authorialNote>, and in particular Article 3(1) thereof,</p>
            </citation>
         </citations>
         <recitals xml:id="recs_d276e71">
            <intro>
               <p>Whereas:</p>
            </intro>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d276e74">
               <num>(1)</num>
               <p>By Commission Regulation (EC) No 1126/2008<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="2">
                     <p>Commission Regulation (EC) No 1126/2008 of 3 November 2008 adopting certain international accounting standards in accordance with Regulation (EC) No 1606/2002 of the European Parliament and of the Council (OJ L 320, 29.11.2008, p. 1).</p>
                  </authorialNote> certain international standards and interpretations that were in existence at 15 October 2008 were adopted.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d276e93">
               <num>(2)</num>
               <p>On 14 May 2020, the International Accounting Standards Board (IASB) published several minor amendments to International Accounting Standard (IAS) 16 <i>Property, Plant and Equipment</i>, IAS 37 <i>Provisions, Contingent Liabilities and Contingent Assets</i>, and International Financial Reporting Standards (IFRS) 3 <i>Business Combinations</i>. Those amendments provide further clarifications for a more consistent application of the standards, or update references.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d276e111">
               <num>(3)</num>
               <p>The IASB also issued on 14 May 2020 the <i>Annual Improvements to IFRS Standards 2018&#45;2020 Cycle</i> in the framework of its regular improvement process. The annual improvements aim at streamlining and clarifying existing standards. The objective of the annual improvements is to address non-urgent but necessary issues discussed by the IASB during the project cycle on areas of inconsistency in International Financial Reporting Standards, or where clarification of wording is required. The annual improvements contain amendments to IAS 41 <i>Agriculture,</i> IFRS 1 <i>First-time Adoption of International Financial Reporting Standards</i>, and IFRS 9 <i>Financial Instruments</i>.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d276e132">
               <num>(4)</num>
               <p>Following the consultation with the European Financial Reporting Advisory Group, the Commission concludes that the amendments to IAS 16 <i>Property, Plant and Equipment</i>, IAS 37 <i>Provisions, Contingent Liabilities and Contingent Assets</i>, IAS 41 <i>Agriculture</i>, IFRS 1 <i>First-time Adoption of International Financial Reporting Standards</i>, IFRS 3 <i>Business Combinations</i>, and IFRS 9 <i>Financial Instruments</i> meet the criteria for adoption set out in Article 3(2) of Regulation (EC) No 1606/2002.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d276e157">
               <num>(5)</num>
               <p>Regulation (EC) No 1126/2008 should therefore be amended accordingly.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d276e163">
               <num>(6)</num>
               <p>The measures provided for in this Regulation are in accordance with the opinion of the Accounting Regulatory Committee,</p>
            </recital>
         </recitals>
         <formula name="enactingFormula">
            <p>HAS ADOPTED THIS REGULATION:</p>
         </formula>
      </preamble>
      <body>
         <article xml:id="art_d276e173">
            <num>Article 1</num>
            <heading>The Annex to Regulation (EC) No 1126/2008 is amended as follows:</heading>
            <paragraph>
               <subparagraph>
                  <content>
                     <p/>
                  </content>
               </subparagraph>
               <list>
                  <point>
                     <num>(a)</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>International Accounting Standard (IAS) 16 <i>Property, Plant and Equipment</i> is amended as set out in the Annex to this Regulation;</p>
                     </content>
                  </point>
                  <point>
                     <num>(b)</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>IAS 37 <i>Provisions, Contingent Liabilities and Contingent Assets</i> is amended as set out in the Annex to this Regulation;</p>
                     </content>
                  </point>
                  <point>
                     <num>(c)</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>IAS 41 <i>Agriculture</i> is amended as set out in the Annex to this Regulation;</p>
                     </content>
                  </point>
                  <point>
                     <num>(d)</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>International Financial Reporting Standard (IFRS) 1 <i>First-time Adoption of International Financial Reporting Standards</i> is amended as set out in the Annex to this Regulation;</p>
                     </content>
                  </point>
                  <point>
                     <num>(e)</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>IFRS 3 <i>Business Combinations</i> is amended as set out in the Annex to this Regulation;</p>
                     </content>
                  </point>
                  <point>
                     <num>(f)</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>IFRS 9 <i>Financial Instruments</i> is amended as set out in the Annex to this Regulation;</p>
                     </content>
                  </point>
               </list>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <article xml:id="art_d276e234">
            <num>Article 2</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>Each company shall apply the amendments referred to in Article 1, at the latest, as from the commencement date of its first financial year starting on or after 1 January 2022.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <article xml:id="art_d276e242">
            <num>Article 3</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>This Regulation shall enter into force on the twentieth day following that of its publication in the <i>Official Journal of the European Union</i>.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <clause>
            <content>
               <p>This Regulation shall be binding in its entirety and directly applicable in all Member States.</p>
            </content>
         </clause>
      </body>
      <conclusions>
         <p>Done at Brussels, 28 June 2021.</p>
         <block name="signatory">
            <signature>
               <organization refersTo="">For the Commission</organization>
               <role refersTo="">The President</role>
               <person refersTo="">Ursula VON DER LEYEN</person>
            </signature>
         </block>
      </conclusions>
   </bill>
</akomaNtoso>
