<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0"
            xmlns:fmx="http://formex.publications.europa.eu/schema/formex-05.21-20110601.xd"
            xmlns:leos="urn:eu:europa:ec:leos"
            xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema">
   <bill name="">
      <meta xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions">
         <identification source="~COM">
            <FRBRWork>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRcountry value=""/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
         </identification>
      </meta>
      <preface>
         <longTitle>
            <p>
               <docStage/>
               <docType>COMMISSION REGULATION (EU) 2020/1720</docType>of 17 November 2020<docPurpose>amending Regulation (EU) No 142/2011 as regards imports of petfood from Georgia</docPurpose>
            </p>
         </longTitle>
         <container name="EEArelevance">
            <p>(Text with EEA relevance)</p>
         </container>
      </preface>
      <preamble>
         <formula name="actingEntity">
            <p>THE EUROPEAN COMMISSION,</p>
         </formula>
         <citations>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to Regulation (EC) No 1069/2009 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 21 October 2009 laying down health rules as regards animal by-products and derived products not intended for human consumption and repealing Regulation (EC) No 1774/2002<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="1">
                     <p>OJ L 300, 14.11.2009, p. 1.</p>
                  </authorialNote>, and in particular the first and the third subparagraphs of Article 41(3) and Article 42(2) thereof,</p>
            </citation>
         </citations>
         <recitals xml:id="recs_d236e71">
            <intro>
               <p>Whereas:</p>
            </intro>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d236e74">
               <num>(1)</num>
               <p>Commission Regulation (EU) No 142/2011<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="2">
                     <p>Commission Regulation (EU) No 142/2011 of 25 February 2011 implementing Regulation (EC) No 1069/2009 of the European Parliament and of the Council laying down health rules as regards animal by-products and derived products not intended for human consumption and implementing Council Directive 97/78/EC as regards certain samples and items exempt from veterinary checks at the border under that Directive (OJ L 54, 26.2.2011, p. 1).</p>
                  </authorialNote> lays down rules implementing Regulation (EC) No 1069/2009 including public and animal health conditions for imports of petfood. The requirements for the importation into and transit through the Union of petfood including dogchews are set out in Annex XIV to that Regulation, including the list of third countries.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d236e90">
               <num>(2)</num>
               <p>On 19 March 2019, Georgia asked to be listed in Annex XIV to Regulation (EU) No 142/2011 for the importation into the Union of processed petfood, other than canned petfood.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d236e99">
               <num>(3)</num>
               <p>The Commission carried out on-the spot controls, including an in-depth assessment of the applicant third country&apos;s veterinary legislation and the capacity of the applicant third country&apos;s competent authorities to implement that legislation and perform official controls, with a view to listing the applicant third country in Annex XIV to Regulation (EU) No 142/2011 for the importation into the Union of processed petfood, other than canned petfood. The competent authorities of Georgia provided the Commission with assurances that Georgia can comply with the relevant health conditions and sufficient guarantees for the controls they carry out on the production of processed petfood, other than canned petfood. It is therefore justified to add Georgia to the list of third countries from where processed petfood, other than canned petfood, may be imported into and transit through the Union.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d236e105">
               <num>(4)</num>
               <p>Regulation (EU) No 142/2011 should therefore be amended accordingly.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d236e111">
               <num>(5)</num>
               <p>The measures provided for in this Regulation are in accordance with the opinion of the Standing Committee on Plants, Animals, Food and Feed,</p>
            </recital>
         </recitals>
         <formula name="enactingFormula">
            <p>HAS ADOPTED THIS REGULATION:</p>
         </formula>
      </preamble>
      <body>
         <article xml:id="art_d236e120">
            <num>Article 1</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>Annex XIV to Regulation (EU) No 142/2011 is amended in accordance with the text in the Annex to this Regulation.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <article xml:id="art_d236e125">
            <num>Article 2</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>This Regulation shall enter into force on the twentieth day following the date of publication in the <i>Official Journal of the European Union</i>.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <clause>
            <content>
               <p>This Regulation shall be binding in its entirety and directly applicable in all Member States.</p>
            </content>
         </clause>
      </body>
      <conclusions>
         <p>Done at Brussels, 17 November 2020.</p>
         <block name="signatory">
            <signature>
               <organization refersTo="">For the Commission</organization>
               <role refersTo="">The President</role>
               <person refersTo="">Ursula VON DER LEYEN</person>
            </signature>
         </block>
      </conclusions>
   </bill>
</akomaNtoso>
