<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0"
            xmlns:fmx="http://formex.publications.europa.eu/schema/formex-05.21-20110601.xd"
            xmlns:leos="urn:eu:europa:ec:leos"
            xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema">
   <bill name="">
      <meta xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions">
         <identification source="~COM">
            <FRBRWork>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRcountry value=""/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
         </identification>
      </meta>
      <preface>
         <longTitle>
            <p>
               <docStage/>
               <docType>COUNCIL REGULATION (EU) 2017/2466</docType>of 18 December 2017<docPurpose>amending Regulation (EU) No 1388/2013 opening and providing for the management of autonomous tariff quotas of the Union for certain agricultural and industrial products</docPurpose>
            </p>
         </longTitle>
      </preface>
      <preamble>
         <formula name="actingEntity">
            <p>THE COUNCIL OF THE EUROPEAN UNION,</p>
         </formula>
         <citations>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union, and in particular Article 31 thereof,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the proposal from the European Commission,</p>
            </citation>
         </citations>
         <recitals xml:id="recs_d633e59">
            <intro>
               <p>Whereas:</p>
            </intro>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d633e62">
               <num>(1)</num>
               <p>In order to ensure the sufficient and uninterrupted supply of certain goods insufficiently produced in the Union and to avoid disturbances on the market for certain agricultural and industrial products, autonomous tariff quotas were opened by Council Regulation (EU) No 1388/2013<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="1">
                     <p>Council Regulation (EU) No 1388/2013 of 17 December 2013 opening and providing for the management of autonomous tariff quotas of the Union for certain agricultural and industrial products, and repealing Regulation (EU) No 7/2010 (OJ L 354, 28.12.2013, p. 319).</p>
                  </authorialNote>. Products within those tariff quotas can be imported into the Union at reduced or zero duty rates.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d633e78">
               <num>(2)</num>
               <p>For those reasons, it is necessary to open, with effect from 1 January 2018, tariff quotas at zero duty rates for an appropriate volume as regards 12 new products. In the case of five additional products, the quota volumes should be increased, as an increase is in the interests of economic operators of the Union.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d633e87">
               <num>(3)</num>
               <p>In the case of one additional product, the quota volume should be decreased, as the production capacity of the Union producers has been increased.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d633e93">
               <num>(4)</num>
               <p>In the case of five products, the quota period and the quota volume should be adapted, as they had been opened for a period of 6 months only.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d633e99">
               <num>(5)</num>
               <p>In the case of another product, its description should be amended.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d633e105">
               <num>(6)</num>
               <p>In the case of 12 other products, the autonomous tariff quotas of the Union should be closed with effect from 1 January 2018, as it is not in the Union&apos;s interest to maintain those quotas as from that date.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d633e114">
               <num>(7)</num>
               <p>Regulation (EU) No 1388/2013 should therefore be amended accordingly.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d633e120">
               <num>(8)</num>
               <p>In order to avoid any interruption of the application of the quota scheme and to comply with the guidelines set out in the Communication from the Commission concerning autonomous tariff suspensions and quotas<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="2">
                     <p>OJ C 363, 13.12.2011, p. 6.</p>
                  </authorialNote>, the changes provided for in this Regulation regarding the quotas for the products concerned have to apply from 1 January 2018. This Regulation should therefore enter into force as a matter of urgency,</p>
            </recital>
         </recitals>
         <formula name="enactingFormula">
            <p>HAS ADOPTED THIS REGULATION:</p>
         </formula>
      </preamble>
      <body>
         <article xml:id="art_d633e139">
            <num>Article 1</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <subparagraph>
                  <content>
                     <p>The Annex to Regulation (EU) No 1388/2013 is amended as follows:</p>
                  </content>
               </subparagraph>
               <list>
                  <point>
                     <num>(1)</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>the rows for the tariff quotas with order numbers 09.2872, 09.2874, 09.2878, 09.2880, 09.2886, 09.2876, 09.2888, 09.2866, 09.2906, 09.2909, 09.2910 and 09.2932 set out in Annex I to this Regulation are inserted into the table according to the order of the CN codes indicated in the second column;</p>
                     </content>
                  </point>
                  <point>
                     <num>(2)</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>in the table, the rows for the tariff quotas with order numbers 09.2828, 09.2929, 09.2704, 09.2842, 09.2844, 09.2671, 09.2846, 09.2723, 09.2848, 09.2870, 09.2662, 09.2850 and 09.2868 are replaced by the corresponding rows set out in Annex II to this Regulation;</p>
                     </content>
                  </point>
                  <point>
                     <num>(3)</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>in the table, the rows for the tariff quotas with order numbers 09.2703, 09.2691, 09.2692, 09.2680, 09.2977, 09.2693, 09.2712, 09.2714, 09.2666, 09.2687, 09.2689 and 09.2669 are deleted;</p>
                     </content>
                  </point>
                  <point>
                     <num>(4)</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>endnote (*) containing the text &apos;A newly introduced measure or a measure with amended conditions.&apos; is deleted.</p>
                     </content>
                  </point>
               </list>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <article xml:id="art_d633e174">
            <num>Article 2</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>This Regulation shall enter into force on the day following that of its publication in the <i>Official Journal of the European Union.</i>
                  </p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>It shall apply from 1 January 2018.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <clause>
            <content>
               <p>This Regulation shall be binding in its entirety and directly applicable in all Member States.</p>
            </content>
         </clause>
      </body>
      <conclusions>
         <p>Done at Brussels, 18 December 2017.</p>
         <block name="signatory">
            <signature>
               <organization refersTo="">For the Council</organization>
               <role refersTo="">The President</role>
               <person refersTo="">K. SIMSON</person>
            </signature>
         </block>
      </conclusions>
   </bill>
</akomaNtoso>
