<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0"
            xmlns:fmx="http://formex.publications.europa.eu/schema/formex-05.21-20110601.xd"
            xmlns:leos="urn:eu:europa:ec:leos"
            xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema">
   <bill name="">
      <meta xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions">
         <identification source="~COM">
            <FRBRWork>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRcountry value=""/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
         </identification>
      </meta>
      <preface>
         <longTitle>
            <p>
               <docStage/>
               <docType>COMMISSION REGULATION (EU) 2017/1980</docType>of 31 October 2017<docPurpose>amending Annex III to Regulation (EC) No 2074/2005 as regards paralytic shellfish poison (PSP) detection method</docPurpose>
            </p>
         </longTitle>
         <container name="EEArelevance">
            <p>(Text with EEA relevance)</p>
         </container>
      </preface>
      <preamble>
         <formula name="actingEntity">
            <p>THE EUROPEAN COMMISSION,</p>
         </formula>
         <citations>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to Regulation (EC) No 853/2004 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 29 April 2004 laying down specific hygiene rules for food of animal origin<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="1">
                     <p>OJ L 139, 30.4.2004, p. 55.</p>
                  </authorialNote> and in particular point (4) of Article 11 thereof,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to Regulation (EC) No 854/2004 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 29 April 2004 laying down specific rules for the organisation of official controls on products of animal origin intended for human consumption<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="2">
                     <p>OJ L 139, 30.4.2004, p. 206.</p>
                  </authorialNote>, and in particular point 13(a) of Article 18 thereof,</p>
            </citation>
         </citations>
         <recitals xml:id="recs_d550e82">
            <intro>
               <p>Whereas:</p>
            </intro>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d550e85">
               <num>(1)</num>
               <p>Regulation (EC) No 854/2004 lays down specific rules for the organisation of official controls on products of animal origin and Regulation (EC) No 853/2004 lays down specific requirements concerning hygienic rules for food of animal origin. Implementing measures for those Regulations as regards recognised testing methods for marine biotoxins are set out in Annex III to Commission Regulation (EC) No 2074/2005<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="3">
                     <p>Commission Regulation (EC) No 2074/2005 of 5 December 2005 laying down implementing measures for certain products under Regulation (EC) No 853/2004 of the European Parliament and of the Council and for the organisation of official controls under Regulation (EC) No 854/2004 of the European Parliament and of the Council and Regulation (EC) No 882/2004 of the European Parliament and of the Council, derogating from Regulation (EC) No 852/2004 of the European Parliament and of the Council and amending Regulations (EC) No 853/2004 and (EC) No 854/2004 (OJ L 338, 22.12.2005, p. 27).</p>
                  </authorialNote>.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d550e101">
               <num>(2)</num>
               <p>Point 2 of Chapter I of Annex III to Regulation (EC) No 2074/2005 provides that if the results of the paralytic shellfish pois on (PSP) detection method are challenged, the reference method is to be the biological method.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d550e107">
               <num>(3)</num>
               <p>During the thirty-sixth session of the Codex Alimentarius committee on methods of analysis and sampling (Budapest, Hungary 23&#45;27 February 2015)<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="4">
                     <p>http://www.fao.org/fao-who-codexalimentarius/sh-proxy/en/?lnk=1&amp;url=https%253A%252F%252Fworkspace.fao.org%252Fsites%252Fcodex%252FMeetings%252FCX-715-36%252FREP15_MASe.pdf</p>
                  </authorialNote> it was confirmed to maintain the biological testing method in Section I-8.6.2 of the Codex as Type IV<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="5">
                     <p>Paragraph 56 of the Report.</p>
                  </authorialNote>.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d550e127">
               <num>(4)</num>
               <p>All Codex methods, including Type IV methods, can be used only for control, inspection and regulation (Principles for the establishment of methods of analysis) and when parties so agreed, for resolution of disputes (Guidelines for Settling Disputes on Analytical (Test) Results (CAC/GL 70-2009) but not as reference method.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d550e133">
               <num>(5)</num>
               <p>Considering that a Type IV method cannot be used as reference method, it is important to adapt the current Union rules to the international standards.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d550e139">
               <num>(6)</num>
               <p>Taking into account the so-called Lawrence method as published in AOAC Official Method 2005.06 (Paralytic Shellfish Poisoning Toxins in Shellfish) is currently used for the detection of paralytic shellfish poison (PSP) content of edible parts of molluscs, it is opportune that this method is used as reference method for the detection of those toxins.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d550e145">
               <num>(7)</num>
               <p>Chapter I of Annex III to Regulation (EC) No 2074/2005 should therefore be amended accordingly.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d550e151">
               <num>(8)</num>
               <p>In order to allow the Member States to adapt their methods to the chemical method, the biological testing method may be still used as reference method until 31 December 2018.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d550e160">
               <num>(9)</num>
               <p>The measures provided for in this Regulation are in accordance with the opinion of the Standing Committee on Plants, Animals, Food and Feed,</p>
            </recital>
         </recitals>
         <formula name="enactingFormula">
            <p>HAS ADOPTED THIS REGULATION:</p>
         </formula>
      </preamble>
      <body>
         <article xml:id="art_d550e170" leos:compliant="false">
            <num>Article 1</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>Chapter I of Annex III to Regulation (EC) No 2074/2005 is replaced by the following:</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>
                     <mod>
                        <quotedStructure startQuote="" endQuote=""><!--GR.SEQ is a special position => not treated --></quotedStructure>
                     </mod>
                  </p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <article xml:id="art_d550e197">
            <num>Article 2</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>This Regulation shall enter into force on the third day following that of its publication in the <i>Official Journal of the European Union</i>.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>It shall apply from 1 January 2019.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <clause>
            <content>
               <p>This Regulation shall be binding in its entirety and directly applicable in all Member States.</p>
            </content>
         </clause>
      </body>
      <conclusions>
         <p>Done at Brussels, 31 October 2017.</p>
         <block name="signatory">
            <signature>
               <organization refersTo="">For the Commission</organization>
               <role refersTo="">The President</role>
               <person refersTo="">Jean-Claude JUNCKER</person>
            </signature>
         </block>
      </conclusions>
   </bill>
</akomaNtoso>
