<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0"
            xmlns:fmx="http://formex.publications.europa.eu/schema/formex-05.21-20110601.xd"
            xmlns:leos="urn:eu:europa:ec:leos"
            xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema">
   <bill name="">
      <meta xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions">
         <identification source="~COM">
            <FRBRWork>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRcountry value=""/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
         </identification>
      </meta>
      <preface>
         <longTitle>
            <p>
               <docStage/>
               <docType>COMMISSION REGULATION (EU) 2017/335</docType>of 27 February 2017<docPurpose>amending Annex II to Regulation (EC) No 1333/2008 of the European Parliament and of the Council as regards the use of steviol glycosides (E 960) as a sweetener in certain energy-reduced confectionery products</docPurpose>
            </p>
         </longTitle>
         <container name="EEArelevance">
            <p>(Text with EEA relevance)</p>
         </container>
      </preface>
      <preamble>
         <formula name="actingEntity">
            <p>THE EUROPEAN COMMISSION,</p>
         </formula>
         <citations>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to Regulation (EC) No 1333/2008 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 16 December 2008 on food additives<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="1">
                     <p>OJ L 354, 31.12.2008, p. 16.</p>
                  </authorialNote>, and in particular Article 10(3) thereof,</p>
            </citation>
         </citations>
         <recitals xml:id="recs_d436e71">
            <intro>
               <p>Whereas:</p>
            </intro>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d436e74">
               <num>(1)</num>
               <p>Annex II to Regulation (EC) No 1333/2008 lays down a Union list of food additives approved for use in food and their conditions of use.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d436e80">
               <num>(2)</num>
               <p>That list may be updated in accordance with the common procedure referred to in Article 3(1) of Regulation (EC) No 1331/2008 of the European Parliament and of the Council<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="2">
                     <p>Regulation (EC) No 1331/2008 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 16 December 2008 establishing a common authorisation procedure for food additives, food enzymes and food flavourings (OJ L 354, 31.12.2008, p. 1).</p>
                  </authorialNote> either on the initiative of the Commission or following an application.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d436e96">
               <num>(3)</num>
               <p>On 27 May 2015 an application was submitted for authorisation of the use of steviol glycosides (E 960) as a sweetener in certain energy-reduced confectionery products. The application was subsequently made available to the Member States pursuant to Article 4 of Regulation (EC) No 1331/2008.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d436e105">
               <num>(4)</num>
               <p>Steviol glycosides are non-caloric sweet-tasting constituents and may be used to replace caloric sugars in certain confectionery products, thus reducing their caloric content and offering consumers energy-reduced products, in accordance with Article 7 of Regulation (EC) No 1333/2008. The combined use of steviol glycosides and sugar provide sweetness to products and an improved taste profile compared to products which use only steviol glycosides for sweetening purposes as the sugar masks the aftertaste of steviol glycosides.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d436e111">
               <num>(5)</num>
               <p>Pursuant to Article 3(2) of Regulation (EC) No 1331/2008, the Commission is to seek the opinion of the European Food Safety Authority (&apos;the Authority&apos;) in order to update the Union list of food additives set out in Annex II to Regulation (EC) No 1333/2008.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d436e121">
               <num>(6)</num>
               <p>In 2010 the Authority adopted a scientific opinion<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="3">
                     <p>EFSA Journal 2010;8(4):1537.</p>
                  </authorialNote> on the safety of steviol glycosides for the proposed uses as a food additive (E 960) and established an acceptable daily intake (ADI) of 4 mg/kg body weight/day, expressed as steviol equivalents.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d436e131">
               <num>(7)</num>
               <p>In 2015 the Authority revised the exposure assessment of steviol glycosides and concluded that the exposure estimates are below the ADI for all age groups, except for toddlers at the upper range of the high level (95th percentile) estimates, in one country<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="4">
                     <p>
                        <i>EFSA Journal</i> 2015;13(6):4146.</p>
                  </authorialNote>. Exposure calculations carried out by <i>Rijksinstituut voor Volksgezondheid en Milieu</i> in 2015 showed that the proposed extension of use, assuming a market share of 25 % for steviol glycosides containing products and assuming 100 % brand loyalty, did not affect the 95th percentile of exposure in young children aged two to six years in the Netherlands.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d436e146">
               <num>(8)</num>
               <p>In its opinion of 2015 the Authority indicated that it was not possible within the FoodEx classification system to reflect all the restrictions/exceptions applying to the use of steviol glycosides (E 960) in the foods under food subcategory 05.2. Therefore, the highest maximum level of 2000 mg/kg was assigned to the entire food category resulting in an overestimation of exposure. In addition, foods of category 05.2. &apos;Other confectionery including breath freshening microsweets&apos; were not identified as one of the main food categories contributing to exposure to steviol glycosides (E 960).</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d436e161">
               <num>(9)</num>
               <p>Considering that the exposure estimates are below the ADI for all age groups, the proposed uses and use levels of steviol glycosides (E 960) as a sweetener are not a safety concern.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d436e167">
               <num>(10)</num>
               <p>Therefore, it is appropriate to authorise the use of steviol glycosides (E 960) as a sweetener in certain energy-reduced confectionery products in food subcategory 05.2 &apos;Other confectionery including breath freshening microsweets&apos;: hard confectionery (candies and lollies), soft confectionery (chewing candies, fruit gums and foam sugar products/marshmallows), liquorice, nougat and marzipan (at maximum level of 350 mg/kg); strongly flavoured freshening throat pastilles (at maximum level of 670 mg/kg) and breath-freshening micro-sweets (at maximum level of 2000 mg/kg).</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d436e181">
               <num>(11)</num>
               <p>Annex II to Regulation (EC) No 1333/2008 should be amended accordingly.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d436e187">
               <num>(12)</num>
               <p>The measures provided for in this Regulation are in accordance with the opinion of the Standing Committee on Plants, Animals, Food and Feed,</p>
            </recital>
         </recitals>
         <formula name="enactingFormula">
            <p>HAS ADOPTED THIS REGULATION:</p>
         </formula>
      </preamble>
      <body>
         <article xml:id="art_d436e196">
            <num>Article 1</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>Annex II to Regulation (EC) No 1333/2008 is amended in accordance with the Annex to this Regulation.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <article xml:id="art_d436e201">
            <num>Article 2</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>This Regulation shall enter into force on the twentieth day following that of its publication in the <i>Official Journal of the European Union</i>.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <clause>
            <content>
               <p>This Regulation shall be binding in its entirety and directly applicable in all Member States.</p>
            </content>
         </clause>
      </body>
      <conclusions>
         <p>Done at Brussels, 27 February 2017.</p>
         <block name="signatory">
            <signature>
               <organization refersTo="">For the Commission</organization>
               <role refersTo="">The President</role>
               <person refersTo="">Jean-Claude JUNCKER</person>
            </signature>
         </block>
      </conclusions>
   </bill>
</akomaNtoso>
