<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0"
            xmlns:fmx="http://formex.publications.europa.eu/schema/formex-05.21-20110601.xd"
            xmlns:leos="urn:eu:europa:ec:leos"
            xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema">
   <bill name="">
      <meta xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions">
         <identification source="~COM">
            <FRBRWork>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRcountry value=""/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
         </identification>
      </meta>
      <preface>
         <longTitle>
            <p>
               <docStage/>
               <docType>COMMISSION REGULATION (EU) 2017/269</docType>of 16 February 2017<docPurpose>amending Regulation (EC) No 1185/2009 of the European Parliament and of the Council concerning statistics on pesticides, as regards the list of active substances</docPurpose>
            </p>
         </longTitle>
         <container name="EEArelevance">
            <p>(Text with EEA relevance)</p>
         </container>
      </preface>
      <preamble>
         <formula name="actingEntity">
            <p>THE EUROPEAN COMMISSION,</p>
         </formula>
         <citations>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to Regulation (EC) No 1185/2009 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 25 November 2009 concerning statistics on pesticides<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="1">
                     <p>OJ L 324, 10.12.2009, p. 1.</p>
                  </authorialNote>, and in particular Article 5(3) thereof,</p>
            </citation>
         </citations>
         <recitals xml:id="recs_d58e71">
            <intro>
               <p>Whereas:</p>
            </intro>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d58e74">
               <num>(1)</num>
               <p>Regulation (EC) No 1185/2009 establishes a common framework for producing comparable European statistics on the sales and use of pesticides.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d58e80">
               <num>(2)</num>
               <p>The Commission should adapt, on a regular basis and at least every five years, the list of substances to be covered and their classification in categories of products and chemical classes as set out in Annex III. As the latter was last updated in 2011 by Commission Regulation (EU) No 656/2011<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="2">
                     <p>Commission Regulation (EU) No 656/2011 of 7 July 2011 implementing Regulation (EC) No 1185/2009 of the European Parliament and of the Council concerning statistics on pesticides, as regards definitions and list of active substances (OJ L 180, 8.7.2011, p. 3).</p>
                  </authorialNote>, the list annexed to that Regulation needs to be updated to cover the years from 2016 to 2020.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d58e96">
               <num>(3)</num>
               <p>Given the number of substances concerned and the complex process of identifying and classifying the relevant compounds, it is difficult for the national statistical authorities to acquire the array of tools they need to collect information on use and placing on the market of pesticides. Consequently, only substances assigned an identification number by one or both of the two major internationally recognised institutions that register chemical compounds or pesticides, the Chemical Abstracts Service of the American Chemical Society and the Collaborative International Pesticides Analytical Council, should be included.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d58e102">
               <num>(4)</num>
               <p>The measures provided for in this Regulation are in accordance with the opinion of the European Statistical System Committee,</p>
            </recital>
         </recitals>
         <formula name="enactingFormula">
            <p>HAS ADOPTED THIS REGULATION:</p>
         </formula>
      </preamble>
      <body>
         <article xml:id="art_d58e111">
            <num>Article 1</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>Annex III to Regulation (EC) No 1185/2009 is replaced by the Annex to this Regulation.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <article xml:id="art_d58e116">
            <num>Article 2</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>This Regulation shall enter into force on the twentieth day following that of its publication in the <i>Official Journal of the European Union</i>.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <clause>
            <content>
               <p>This Regulation shall be binding in its entirety and directly applicable in all Member States.</p>
            </content>
         </clause>
      </body>
      <conclusions>
         <p>Done at Brussels, 16 February 2017.</p>
         <block name="signatory">
            <signature>
               <organization refersTo="">For the Commission</organization>
               <role refersTo="">The President</role>
               <person refersTo="">Jean-Claude JUNCKER</person>
            </signature>
         </block>
      </conclusions>
   </bill>
</akomaNtoso>
