<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0"
            xmlns:fmx="http://formex.publications.europa.eu/schema/formex-05.21-20110601.xd"
            xmlns:leos="urn:eu:europa:ec:leos"
            xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema">
   <bill name="">
      <meta xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions">
         <identification source="~COM">
            <FRBRWork>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRcountry value=""/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
         </identification>
      </meta>
      <preface>
         <longTitle>
            <p>
               <docStage/>
               <docType>COMMISSION REGULATION (EU) 2017/1200</docType>of 5 July 2017<docPurpose>refusing to authorise certain health claims made on foods, other than those referring to the reduction of disease risk and to children&apos;s development and health</docPurpose>
            </p>
         </longTitle>
         <container name="EEArelevance">
            <p>(Text with EEA relevance)</p>
         </container>
      </preface>
      <preamble>
         <formula name="actingEntity">
            <p>THE EUROPEAN COMMISSION,</p>
         </formula>
         <citations>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to Regulation (EC) No 1924/2006 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 20 December 2006 on nutrition and health claims made on foods<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="1">
                     <p>OJ L 404, 30.12.2006, p. 9.</p>
                  </authorialNote>, and in particular Article 18(5) thereof,</p>
            </citation>
         </citations>
         <recitals xml:id="recs_d229e71">
            <intro>
               <p>Whereas:</p>
            </intro>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d229e74">
               <num>(1)</num>
               <p>Pursuant to Regulation (EC) No 1924/2006 health claims made on foods, as defined in that Regulation, are prohibited unless they are authorised by the Commission in accordance with that Regulation and included in a list of permitted claims.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d229e80">
               <num>(2)</num>
               <p>Regulation (EC) No 1924/2006 also provides that applications for authorisations of health claims may be submitted by food business operators to the national competent authority of a Member State. The national competent authority is to forward valid applications to the European Food Safety Authority (EFSA), hereinafter referred to as &apos;the Authority&apos;, for a scientific assessment, as well as to the Commission and the Member States for information.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d229e90">
               <num>(3)</num>
               <p>The Authority is to deliver an opinion on the health claim concerned.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d229e96">
               <num>(4)</num>
               <p>The Commission is to decide on the authorisation of health claims taking into account the opinion delivered by the Authority.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d229e102">
               <num>(5)</num>
               <p>Following an application from Ecopharma BVBA, submitted pursuant to Article 13(5) of Regulation (EC) No 1924/2006, the Authority was required to deliver an opinion on a health claim related to Fabenol<sup>®</sup> Max, a standardised aqueous extract from <i>Phaseolus vulgaris</i> L., and the reduction of the absorption of carbohydrates (Question No EFSA-Q-2015-00123<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="2">
                     <p>EFSA Journal 2016;14(2):4401.</p>
                  </authorialNote>). The claim proposed by the applicant was worded as follows: &apos;Fabenol<sup>®</sup> Max reduces the absorption of carbohydrates&apos;.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d229e126">
               <num>(6)</num>
               <p>On 23 February 2016, the Commission and the Member States received the scientific opinion from the Authority, which noted that the claimed effect was not sufficiently defined and that the applicant did not provide any further information as requested by the Authority. Therefore, on the basis of the data presented, the Authority concluded that a cause and effect relationship had not been established between the consumption of Fabenol<sup>®</sup> Max and the claimed effect. Accordingly, as the claim does not comply with the requirements of Regulation (EC) No 1924/2006, it should not be authorised.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d229e139">
               <num>(7)</num>
               <p>Following an application from DSM Nutritional Products, submitted pursuant to Article 13(5) of Regulation (EC) No 1924/2006, the Authority was required to deliver an opinion on a health claim related to docosahexaenoic acid (DHA) and improvement of memory function (Question No EFSA-Q-2015-00456<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="3">
                     <p>EFSA Journal 2016;14(5):4455.</p>
                  </authorialNote>). The claim proposed by the applicant was worded as follows: &apos;DHA contributes to improved memory function&apos;.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d229e153">
               <num>(8)</num>
               <p>On 2 May 2016, the Commission and the Member States received the scientific opinion from the Authority, which concluded that, on the basis of the data presented, a cause and effect relationship had not been established between the consumption of DHA and the claimed effect. Accordingly, as the claim does not comply with the requirements of Regulation (EC) No 1924/2006, it should not be authorised.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d229e162">
               <num>(9)</num>
               <p>Following an application from Tate &amp; Lyle PLC, submitted pursuant to Article 13(5) of Regulation (EC) No 1924/2006, the Authority was required to deliver an opinion on a health claim related to polydextrose and normal defecation (Question No EFSA-Q-2015-00550<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="4">
                     <p>EFSA Journal 2016;14(5):4480.</p>
                  </authorialNote>). The claim proposed by the applicant was worded as follows: &apos;Polydextrose contributes to an improved bowel function by increasing stool bulk&apos;.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d229e177">
               <num>(10)</num>
               <p>On 25 May 2016, the Commission and the Member States received the scientific opinion from the Authority, which concluded that, on the basis of the data presented, a cause and effect relationship had not been established between the consumption of polydextrose and the claimed effect. Accordingly, as the claim does not comply with the requirements of Regulation (EC) No 1924/2006, it should not be authorised.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d229e186">
               <num>(11)</num>
               <p>The measures provided for in this Regulation are in accordance with the opinion of the Standing Committee on Plants, Animals, Food and Feed,</p>
            </recital>
         </recitals>
         <formula name="enactingFormula">
            <p>HAS ADOPTED THIS REGULATION:</p>
         </formula>
      </preamble>
      <body>
         <article xml:id="art_d229e195">
            <num>Article 1</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>The health claims listed in the Annex to this Regulation shall not be included in the Union list of permitted claims as provided for in Article 13(3) of Regulation (EC) No 1924/2006.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <article xml:id="art_d229e200">
            <num>Article 2</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>This Regulation shall enter into force on the twentieth day following that of its publication in the <i>Official Journal of the European Union</i>.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <clause>
            <content>
               <p>This Regulation shall be binding in its entirety and directly applicable in all Member States.</p>
            </content>
         </clause>
      </body>
      <conclusions>
         <p>Done at Brussels, 5 July 2017.</p>
         <block name="signatory">
            <signature>
               <organization refersTo="">For the Commission</organization>
               <role refersTo="">The President</role>
               <person refersTo="">Jean-Claude JUNCKER</person>
            </signature>
         </block>
      </conclusions>
   </bill>
</akomaNtoso>
