<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0"
            xmlns:fmx="http://formex.publications.europa.eu/schema/formex-05.21-20110601.xd"
            xmlns:leos="urn:eu:europa:ec:leos"
            xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema">
   <bill name="">
      <meta xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions">
         <identification source="~COM">
            <FRBRWork>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRcountry value=""/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
         </identification>
      </meta>
      <preface>
         <longTitle>
            <p>
               <docStage/>
               <docType>COMMISSION REGULATION (EU) 2018/781</docType>of 29 May 2018<docPurpose>amending Regulation (EC) No 847/2000 as regards the definition of the concept &apos;similar medicinal product&apos;</docPurpose>
            </p>
         </longTitle>
         <container name="EEArelevance">
            <p>(Text with EEA relevance)</p>
         </container>
      </preface>
      <preamble>
         <formula name="actingEntity">
            <p>THE EUROPEAN COMMISSION,</p>
         </formula>
         <citations>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to Regulation (EC) No 141/2000 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 16 December 1999 on orphan medicinal products<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="1">
                     <p>OJ L 18, 22.1.2000, p. 1.</p>
                  </authorialNote>, and in particular Article 8(4) thereof,</p>
            </citation>
         </citations>
         <recitals xml:id="recs_d70e74">
            <intro>
               <p>Whereas:</p>
            </intro>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d70e77">
               <num>(1)</num>
               <p>Regulation (EC) No 141/2000 was adopted to promote research in the field of rare diseases. It offers undertakings that develop orphan medicinal products the prospect of obtaining market exclusivity for a certain number of years.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d70e83">
               <num>(2)</num>
               <p>Commission Regulation (EC) No 847/2000<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="2">
                     <p>Commission Regulation (EC) No 847/2000 of 27 April 2000 laying down the provisions for implementation of the criteria for designation of a medicinal product as an orphan medicinal product and definitions of the concepts &apos;similar medicinal product&apos; and &apos;clinical superiority&apos; (OJ L 103, 28.4.2000, p. 5).</p>
                  </authorialNote> provides a definition of the concept &apos;similar medicinal product&apos;, which includes specific cases defining what kind of products are to be regarded as similar for the purposes of the application of Article 8 of Regulation (EC) No 141/2000. That definition should be updated in the light of new scientific and technical knowledge, in particular, due to major developments in the field of biological medicines, and especially advanced therapy medicinal products, and in the light of experience gained with regard to the designation and regulation of orphan medicinal products.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d70e112">
               <num>(3)</num>
               <p>In addition, there is a need for a clear definition of the concept &apos;principal molecular structural features&apos;, which is used within the definition of the concept &apos;similar active substance&apos;, which is in turn used within the definition of the concept &apos;similar medicinal product&apos;. As regards the biological medicinal products, the definition of &apos;principal molecular structural features&apos; shall capture certain molecular modifications significantly contributing to the functional characteristics of the active substance that would impact whether or not the products are considered as similar. However, for advanced therapy medicinal products the principal molecular structural features cannot be fully identified. Therefore, in the case of advanced therapy medicinal products the similarity between two active substances should be assessed on the basis of the biological and functional characteristics.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d70e135">
               <num>(4)</num>
               <p>The definition of &apos;active substance&apos; should be deleted as Article 8(4) of Regulation (EC) No 141/2000 does not empower the Commission to define the term &apos;active substance&apos;. The term &apos;active substance&apos; is legally defined in Article 1(3)(a) of Directive 2001/83/EC of the European Parliament and of the Council<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="3">
                     <p>Directive 2001/83/EC of the European Parliament and of the Council of 6 November 2001 on the Community code relating to medicinal products for human use (OJ L 311, 28.11.2001, p. 67).</p>
                  </authorialNote> and the scope and purpose of Article 3(3) of Regulation (EC) No 847/2000 are related to the definitions of the concepts &apos;similar medicinal product&apos; and &apos;clinical superiority&apos;.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d70e173">
               <num>(5)</num>
               <p>The measures provided for in this Regulation are in accordance with the opinion of the Standing Committee on Medicinal Products for Human Use,</p>
            </recital>
         </recitals>
         <formula name="enactingFormula">
            <p>HAS ADOPTED THIS REGULATION:</p>
         </formula>
      </preamble>
      <body>
         <article xml:id="art_d70e182" leos:compliant="false">
            <num>Article 1</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>In Article 3(3) of Regulation (EC) No 847/2000, the introductory sentence and points (a), (b) and (c) are replaced by the following:</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>
                     <mod>
                        <quotedStructure startQuote="" endQuote="">
                           <p><!--default P | TXT -->&apos;For the purposes of the application of Article 8 of Regulation (EC) No 141/2000 on orphan medicinal products, the following definitions shall apply:</p>
                           <alinea>
                              <list>
                                 <point>
                                    <num>(a)</num>
                                    <content>
                                       <p>deleted;</p>
                                    </content>
                                 </point>
                                 <point>
                                    <num>(b)</num>
                                    <content>
                                       <p>&quot;similar medicinal product&quot; means a medicinal product containing a similar active substance or substances as contained in a currently authorised orphan medicinal product, and which is intended for the same therapeutic indication;</p>
                                    </content>
                                 </point>
                                 <point>
                                    <num>(c)</num>
                                    <alinea>
                                       <content>
                                          <p>&quot;similar active substance&quot; means an identical active substance, or an active substance with the same principal molecular structural features (but not necessarily all of the same molecular structural features) and which acts via the same mechanism. However, in the case of advanced therapy medicinal products, for which the principal molecular structural features cannot be fully defined, the similarity between two active substances shall be assessed on the basis of the biological and functional characteristics.</p>
                                       </content>
                                    </alinea>
                                    <alinea>
                                       <content>
                                          <p>For the purpose of application of point (c) above, the following applies for:</p>
                                       </content>
                                    </alinea>
                                    <!--GR.SEQ is a special position => not treated -->
                                    <!--GR.SEQ is a special position => not treated -->
                                    <!--GR.SEQ is a special position => not treated -->
                                    <!--GR.SEQ is a special position => not treated -->
                                 </point>
                              </list>
                           </alinea>
                        </quotedStructure>
                     </mod>
                  </p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <article xml:id="art_d70e333">
            <num>Article 2</num>
            <heading>Entry into force and application</heading>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>This Regulation shall enter into force on the twentieth day following that of its publication in the <i>Official Journal of the European Union</i>.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <clause>
            <content>
               <p>This Regulation shall be binding in its entirety and directly applicable in all Member States.</p>
            </content>
         </clause>
      </body>
      <conclusions>
         <p>Done at Brussels, 29 May 2018.</p>
         <block name="signatory">
            <signature>
               <organization refersTo="">For the Commission</organization>
               <role refersTo="">The President</role>
               <person refersTo="">Jean-Claude JUNCKER</person>
            </signature>
         </block>
      </conclusions>
   </bill>
</akomaNtoso>
