L1742018EN3810120180710EN0007381381<p xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">Corrigendum to Commission Regulation (EU) 2018/683 of 4 May 2018 imposing a provisional anti-dumping duty on imports of certain pneumatic tyres, new or retreaded, of rubber, of a kind used for buses or lorries, with a load index exceeding 121 originating in the People&apos;s Republic of China, and amending Implementing Regulation (EU) 2018/163</p>
<p xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">(Official Journal of the European Union L 116 of 7 May 2018)</p>On page 20, recital 119:<p xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0"><!--default P | TXT -->for:</p>
<mod xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
   <quotedStructure startQuote="" endQuote="">
      <p><!--default P | TXT -->&apos;With respect to one subsidiary of the Aeolus Group, (Pirelli Tyre Co., Ltd), the Commission did not receive within the set deadline the necessary data to establish the export price. On 23 March 2018 the Commission informed the company that questionnaires provided by its related importers were incomplete and it was requested to revise and re-submit the questionnaires replies. The company was informed that failing to provide complete and accurate information within the given deadline, the Commission could revert to the use of facts available in accordance with Article 18 of the basic Regulation. On 4 April 2018 the company in question provided revised replies. However, the Commission considered them still to be incomplete and could not therefore be processed for the purpose of the dumping and injury analysis. As a result, the Commission has established the dumping margin based on the information verified from the other verified companies of the Aeolus Group, namely Aeolus Tyre and Chonche Auto Double Happiness Tyre. The Aeolus Group was invited to update the data concerning Pirelli for the remainder of the proceeding.&apos;,</p>
   </quotedStructure>
</mod>
<p xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0"><!--default P | TXT -->read:</p>
<mod xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
   <quotedStructure startQuote="" endQuote="">
      <p><!--default P | TXT -->&apos;With respect to Pirelli Tyre Co., Ltd, the Commission did not receive within the set deadline the necessary data to establish the export price. On 23 March 2018 the Commission informed the company that questionnaires provided by its related importers were incomplete and it was requested to revise and re-submit the questionnaires replies. The company was informed that failing to provide complete and accurate information within the given deadline, the Commission could revert to the use of facts available in accordance with Article 18 of the basic Regulation. On 4 April 2018 the company in question provided revised replies. However, the Commission considered them still to be incomplete and could not therefore be processed for the purpose of the dumping and injury analysis. As a result, the Commission has established the dumping margin based on the information verified from the other verified companies of the Aeolus Group, namely Aeolus Tyre and Chonche Auto Double Happiness Tyre. The Aeolus Group was invited to update the data concerning Pirelli for the remainder of the proceeding.&apos;;</p>
   </quotedStructure>
</mod>on page 45, in the Annex:<p xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0"><!--default P | TXT -->for:</p>
<mod xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
   <quotedStructure startQuote="" endQuote="">
      <alinea>
         <content>
            <table class="TBL">
               <tr>
                  <td>
                     <p>&apos;Quindao GRT Rubber Co. Ltd</p>
                  </td>
                  <td>
                     <p>C350&apos;</p>
                  </td>
               </tr>
            </table>
         </content>
      </alinea>
   </quotedStructure>
</mod>
<p xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0"><!--default P | TXT -->read:</p>
<mod xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
   <quotedStructure startQuote="" endQuote="">
      <alinea>
         <content>
            <table class="TBL">
               <tr>
                  <td>
                     <p>&apos;Qingdao GRT Rubber Co., Ltd</p>
                  </td>
                  <td>
                     <p>C350&apos;</p>
                  </td>
               </tr>
            </table>
         </content>
      </alinea>
   </quotedStructure>
</mod>
