<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0"
            xmlns:fmx="http://formex.publications.europa.eu/schema/formex-05.21-20110601.xd"
            xmlns:leos="urn:eu:europa:ec:leos"
            xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema">
   <bill name="">
      <meta xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions">
         <identification source="~COM">
            <FRBRWork>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRcountry value=""/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
         </identification>
      </meta>
      <preface>
         <longTitle>
            <p>
               <docStage/>
               <docType>COMMISSION REGULATION (EU) 2021/1901</docType>of 29 October 2021<docPurpose>implementing Regulation (EC) No 1338/2008 of the European Parliament and of the Council as regards statistics on health care expenditure and financing</docPurpose>
            </p>
         </longTitle>
         <container name="EEArelevance">
            <p>(Text with EEA relevance)</p>
         </container>
      </preface>
      <preamble>
         <formula name="actingEntity">
            <p>THE EUROPEAN COMMISSION,</p>
         </formula>
         <citations>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to Regulation (EC) No 1338/2008 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 16 December 2008 on Community statistics on public health and health and safety at work<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="1">
                     <p>OJ L 354, 31.12.2008, p. 70.</p>
                  </authorialNote>, and in particular Article 9(1) and Annex II, point (d), thereof,</p>
            </citation>
         </citations>
         <recitals xml:id="recs_d618e71">
            <intro>
               <p>Whereas:</p>
            </intro>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d618e74">
               <num>(1)</num>
               <p>It follows from Regulation (EC) No 1338/2008 that the data and metadata on health care expenditure and financing should be set out by implementing measures.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d618e80">
               <num>(2)</num>
               <p>In accordance with Article 6(2) of Regulation (EC) No 1338/2008, the Commission carried out a cost-benefit analysis, taking into account the benefits of the availability of data on health care expenditure and financing. Variables on health care expenditure and financing should be collected to ensure the availability of EU-wide data for decisions relating to health and social policy.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d618e86">
               <num>(3)</num>
               <p>The Commission (Eurostat) produced jointly with the Organisation for Economic Cooperation and Development and the World Health Organization a statistical reference manual, the System of Health Accounts 2011<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="2">
                     <p>OECD, Eurostat and World Health Organization, A System of Health Accounts 2011</p>
                  </authorialNote>, to ensure relevance and comparability of the data. This manual, which sets out the concepts, the definitions and the methods for data processing relating to health care expenditure and financing should form the basis for the detailed questionnaire together with the guidelines accompanying the joint annual data collection exercise.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d618e96">
               <num>(4)</num>
               <p>The measures provided for in this Regulation are in accordance with the opinion of the European Statistical System Committee established by Article 7 of Regulation (EC) No 223/2009 of the European Parliament and of the Council<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="3">
                     <p>Regulation (EC) No 223/2009 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 11 March 2009 on European statistics and repealing Regulation (EC, Euratom) No 1101/2008 of the European Parliament and of the Council on the transmission of data subject to statistical confidentiality to the Statistical Office of the European Communities, Council Regulation (EC) No 322/97 on Community Statistics, and Council Decision 89/382/EEC, Euratom establishing a Committee on the Statistical Programmes of the European Communities (OJ L 87, 31.3.2009, p. 164).</p>
                  </authorialNote>,</p>
            </recital>
         </recitals>
         <formula name="enactingFormula">
            <p>HAS ADOPTED THIS REGULATION:</p>
         </formula>
      </preamble>
      <body>
         <article xml:id="art_d618e115">
            <num>Article 1</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>This Regulation lays down rules for the development and production of European statistics in the area of health care expenditure and financing, one of the subjects for statistics on health care listed in Annex II to Regulation (EC) No 1338/2008.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <article xml:id="art_d618e120">
            <num>Article 2</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>For the purpose of this Regulation, the definitions set out in Annex I shall apply.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <article xml:id="art_d618e126">
            <num>Article 3</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>Member States shall provide data for the areas and at the level of aggregation specified in Annex II.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <article xml:id="art_d618e131">
            <num>Article 4</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <num>1.</num>
               <content>
                  <p>Member States shall provide the required data and the associated standard reference metadata on an annual basis. The reference period shall be the calendar year. The first reference year shall be 2021.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph>
               <num>2.</num>
               <content>
                  <p>Data and reference metadata for the reference year N shall be transmitted by 30 April N+2.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph>
               <num>3.</num>
               <content>
                  <p>Data and reference metadata shall be provided to the Commission (Eurostat) using the single entry point services, or be made available for retrieval by the Commission (Eurostat) by electronic means.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <article xml:id="art_d618e149">
            <num>Article 5</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <subparagraph>
                  <content>
                     <p>Member States shall provide the necessary reference metadata, in particular concerning:</p>
                  </content>
               </subparagraph>
               <list>
                  <point>
                     <num>(a)</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>the data sources and their coverage;</p>
                     </content>
                  </point>
                  <point>
                     <num>(b)</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>the compilation methods used;</p>
                     </content>
                  </point>
                  <point>
                     <num>(c)</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>information on features of national health care expenditure and financing specific to the Member States and deviations from the definitions listed in Annex I;</p>
                     </content>
                  </point>
                  <point>
                     <num>(d)</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>references to national legislation where it forms the basis for health care expenditure and financing;</p>
                     </content>
                  </point>
                  <point>
                     <num>(e)</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>information on any changes to the statistical concepts mentioned in Annex I.</p>
                     </content>
                  </point>
               </list>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <article xml:id="art_d618e186">
            <num>Article 6</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>This Regulation shall enter into force on the twentieth day following that of its publication in the <i>Official Journal of the European Union</i>.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <clause>
            <content>
               <p>This Regulation shall be binding in its entirety and directly applicable in all Member States.</p>
            </content>
         </clause>
      </body>
      <conclusions>
         <p>Done at Brussels, 29 October 2021.</p>
         <block name="signatory">
            <signature>
               <organization refersTo="">For the Commission</organization>
               <role refersTo="">The President</role>
               <person refersTo="">Ursula VON DER LEYEN</person>
            </signature>
         </block>
      </conclusions>
   </bill>
</akomaNtoso>
