<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0"
            xmlns:fmx="http://formex.publications.europa.eu/schema/formex-05.21-20110601.xd"
            xmlns:leos="urn:eu:europa:ec:leos"
            xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema">
   <bill name="">
      <meta xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions">
         <identification source="~COM">
            <FRBRWork>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRcountry value=""/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
         </identification>
      </meta>
      <preface>
         <longTitle>
            <p>
               <docStage/>
               <docType>COMMISSION REGULATION (EU) 2018/75</docType>of 17 January 2018<docPurpose>amending the Annex to Regulation (EU) No 231/2012 laying down specifications for food additives listed in Annexes II and III to Regulation (EC) No 1333/2008 of the European Parliament and of the Council as regards specifications for Microcrystalline cellulose (E460(i))</docPurpose>
            </p>
         </longTitle>
         <container name="EEArelevance">
            <p>(Text with EEA relevance)</p>
         </container>
      </preface>
      <preamble>
         <formula name="actingEntity">
            <p>THE EUROPEAN COMMISSION,</p>
         </formula>
         <citations>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to Regulation (EC) No 1333/2008 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 16 December 2008 on food additives<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="1">
                     <p>OJ L 354, 31.12.2008, p. 16.</p>
                  </authorialNote>, and in particular Article 14 thereof,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to Regulation (EC) No 1331/2008 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 16 December 2008 establishing a common authorisation procedure for food additives, food enzymes and food flavourings<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="2">
                     <p>OJ L 354, 31.12.2008, p. 1.</p>
                  </authorialNote>, and in particular Article 7(5) thereof,</p>
            </citation>
         </citations>
         <recitals xml:id="recs_d17e82">
            <intro>
               <p>Whereas:</p>
            </intro>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d17e85">
               <num>(1)</num>
               <p>Commission Regulation (EU) No 231/2012<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="3">
                     <p>Commission Regulation (EU) No 231/2012 of 9 March 2012 laying down specifications for food additives listed in Annexes II and III to Regulation (EC) No 1333/2008 of the European Parliament and of the Council (OJ L 83, 22.3.2012, p. 1).</p>
                  </authorialNote> lays down specifications for food additives listed in Annexes II and III to Regulation (EC) No 1333/2008.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d17e101">
               <num>(2)</num>
               <p>Those specifications may be updated in accordance with the common procedure referred to in Article 3(1) of Regulation (EC) No 1331/2008, either on the initiative of the Commission or following an application.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d17e107">
               <num>(3)</num>
               <p>On 8 February 2016 an application was submitted for the amendment of specifications concerning the food additive microcrystalline cellulose (E 460(i)). The application was made available to the Member States pursuant to Article 4 of Regulation (EC) No 1331/2008.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d17e116">
               <num>(4)</num>
               <p>The current specification as regards the solubility of the food additive microcrystalline cellulose (E 460(i)) states &apos;Insoluble in water, ethanol, ether and dilute mineral acids. Slightly soluble in sodium hydroxide solution&apos;.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d17e126">
               <num>(5)</num>
               <p>The applicant requests that the solubility of this food additive is amended to &apos;Insoluble in water, ethanol, ether and dilute mineral acids. Practically insoluble or insoluble in sodium hydroxide solution&apos;.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d17e136">
               <num>(6)</num>
               <p>In its opinion of 24 January 2017<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="4">
                     <p>EFSA ANS Panel (EFSA Panel on Food Additives and Nutrient Sources added to food), 2017. Safety of the proposed amendment of the specifications for microcrystalline cellulose (E 460(i)) as a food additive. <i>EFSA Journal</i> 2017;15(2):4699, 7 pp. doi:10.2903/j.efsa.2017.4699.</p>
                  </authorialNote> the European Food Safety Authority (&apos;the Authority&apos;) concluded that the amendment to the specifications as regards the solubility of microcrystalline cellulose (E 460(i)) proposed by the applicant is not of a safety concern. However, the Authority recommended that the concentration of sodium hydroxide solution to be used in the solubility test should be indicated in the EU specifications.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d17e155">
               <num>(7)</num>
               <p>Consequently, it is appropriate to amend the description of the solubility of the food additive microcrystalline cellulose (E 460(i)) in sodium hydroxide solution (concentration: 50 g NaOH/L) to &apos;practically insoluble or insoluble&apos;.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d17e165">
               <num>(8)</num>
               <p>Regulation (EU) No 231/2012 should therefore be amended accordingly.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d17e171">
               <num>(9)</num>
               <p>The measures provided for in this Regulation are in accordance with the opinion of the Standing Committee on Plants, Animals, Food and Feed,</p>
            </recital>
         </recitals>
         <formula name="enactingFormula">
            <p>HAS ADOPTED THIS REGULATION:</p>
         </formula>
      </preamble>
      <body>
         <article xml:id="art_d17e180">
            <num>Article 1</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>The Annex to Regulation (EU) No 231/2012 is amended in accordance with the Annex to this Regulation.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <article xml:id="art_d17e186">
            <num>Article 2</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>This Regulation shall enter into force on the twentieth day following that of its publication in the <i>Official Journal of the European Union</i>.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>This Regulation shall be binding in its entirety and directly applicable in all Members States.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
      </body>
      <conclusions>
         <p>Done at Brussels, 17 January 2018.</p>
         <block name="signatory">
            <signature>
               <organization refersTo="">For the Commission</organization>
               <role refersTo="">The President</role>
               <person refersTo="">Jean-Claude JUNCKER</person>
            </signature>
         </block>
      </conclusions>
   </bill>
</akomaNtoso>
