<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0"
            xmlns:fmx="http://formex.publications.europa.eu/schema/formex-05.21-20110601.xd"
            xmlns:leos="urn:eu:europa:ec:leos"
            xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema">
   <bill name="">
      <meta xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions">
         <identification source="~COM">
            <FRBRWork>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRcountry value=""/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
         </identification>
      </meta>
      <preface>
         <longTitle>
            <p>
               <docStage/>
               <docType>COMMISSION REGULATION (EU) 2018/1461</docType>of 28 September 2018<docPurpose>amending Annex II to Regulation (EC) No 1333/2008 of the European Parliament and of the Council and the Annex to Commission Regulation (EU) No 231/2012 as regards the use of Low-substituted hydroxypropyl cellulose (L-HPC) in food supplements</docPurpose>
            </p>
         </longTitle>
         <container name="EEArelevance">
            <p>(Text with EEA relevance)</p>
         </container>
      </preface>
      <preamble>
         <formula name="actingEntity">
            <p>THE EUROPEAN COMMISSION,</p>
         </formula>
         <citations>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to Regulation (EC) No 1333/2008 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 16 December 2008 on food additives<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="1">
                     <p>OJ L 354, 31.12.2008, p. 16.</p>
                  </authorialNote>, and in particular Articles 10(3) and 14 thereof,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to Regulation (EC) No 1331/2008 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 16 December 2008 establishing a common authorisation procedure for food additives, food enzymes and food flavourings<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="2">
                     <p>OJ L 354, 31.12.2008, p. 1.</p>
                  </authorialNote>, and in particular Article 7(5) thereof,</p>
            </citation>
         </citations>
         <recitals xml:id="recs_d375e82">
            <intro>
               <p>Whereas:</p>
            </intro>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d375e85">
               <num>(1)</num>
               <p>Annex II to Regulation (EC) No 1333/2008 lays down a Union list of food additives approved for use in food and their conditions of use.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d375e91">
               <num>(2)</num>
               <p>Only food additives included in the Union list in Annex II to Regulation (EC) No 1333/2008 may be placed on the market as such and used in foods under the conditions of use specified therein.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d375e97">
               <num>(3)</num>
               <p>Commission Regulation (EU) No 231/2012<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="3">
                     <p>Commission Regulation (EU) No 231/2012 of 9 March 2012 laying down specifications for food additives listed in Annexes II and III to Regulation (EC) No 1333/2008 of the European Parliament and of the Council (OJ L 83, 22.3.2012, p. 1).</p>
                  </authorialNote> lays down specifications for food additives listed in Annexes II and III to Regulation (EC) No 1333/2008.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d375e113">
               <num>(4)</num>
               <p>The Union list and the specifications may be updated in accordance with the common procedure referred to in Article 3(1) of Regulation (EC) No 1331/2008, either on the initiative of the Commission or following an application.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d375e119">
               <num>(5)</num>
               <p>On 21 October 2016 an application was submitted for the authorisation of the use of low-substituted hydroxypropyl cellulose (L-HPC) as a food additive in food supplements in tablet form falling under the food category 17.1 &apos;Food supplements supplied in a solid form&apos; in Part E of Annex II to Regulation (EC) No 1333/2008. The application was subsequently made available to the Member States pursuant to Article 4 of Regulation (EC) No 1331/2008.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d375e132">
               <num>(6)</num>
               <p>The European Food Safety Authority evaluated the safety of L-HPC as a food additive and in its opinion<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="4">
                     <p>EFSA Journal 2018;16(1):5062.</p>
                  </authorialNote> of 20 January 2018 concluded that there was no safety concern from the proposed use in food supplements in solid form (tablet), at a maximum use level of 20000 mg/kg and a typical use level of 10000 mg/kg.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d375e152">
               <num>(7)</num>
               <p>Low-substituted hydroxypropyl cellulose (L-HPC) is water insoluble cellulose that facilitates the manufacturing of solid food supplements in tablet form due to its good compressibility and binding properties. Being insoluble in water, it absorbs water while increasing in volume. The increased volume makes the tablet disintegrating rapidly providing a fast release of the nutrients in the stomach.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d375e158">
               <num>(8)</num>
               <p>It is therefore appropriate to include low-substituted hydroxypropyl cellulose (L-HPC) in the Union list of food additives and to assign E 463a as E-number to that additive to enable its authorisation as a glazing agent in food supplements in solid form (tablet) at a maximum use level of 20000 mg/kg.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d375e167">
               <num>(9)</num>
               <p>The specifications for low-substituted hydroxypropyl cellulose (L-HPC) (E 463a) should be included in Regulation (EU) No 231/2012 when it is included in the Union list of food additives laid down in Annex II to Regulation (EC) No 1333/2008 for the first time.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d375e174">
               <num>(10)</num>
               <p>Regulations (EC) No 1333/2008 and (EU) No 231/2012 should therefore be amended accordingly.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d375e180">
               <num>(11)</num>
               <p>The measures provided for in this Regulation are in accordance with the opinion of the Standing Committee on Plants, Animals, Food and Feed,</p>
            </recital>
         </recitals>
         <formula name="enactingFormula">
            <p>HAS ADOPTED THIS REGULATION:</p>
         </formula>
      </preamble>
      <body>
         <article xml:id="art_d375e189">
            <num>Article 1</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>Annex II to Regulation (EC) No 1333/2008 is amended in accordance with Annex I to this Regulation.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <article xml:id="art_d375e194">
            <num>Article 2</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>The Annex to Regulation (EU) No 231/2012 is amended in accordance with Annex II to this Regulation.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <article xml:id="art_d375e199">
            <num>Article 3</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>This Regulation shall enter into force on the twentieth day following that of its publication in the <i>Official Journal of the European Union</i>.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <clause>
            <content>
               <p>This Regulation shall be binding in its entirety and directly applicable in all Member States.</p>
            </content>
         </clause>
      </body>
      <conclusions>
         <p>Done at Brussels, 28 September 2018.</p>
         <block name="signatory">
            <signature>
               <organization refersTo="">For the Commission</organization>
               <role refersTo="">The President</role>
               <person refersTo="">Jean-Claude JUNCKER</person>
            </signature>
         </block>
      </conclusions>
   </bill>
</akomaNtoso>
