<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0"
            xmlns:fmx="http://formex.publications.europa.eu/schema/formex-05.21-20110601.xd"
            xmlns:leos="urn:eu:europa:ec:leos"
            xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema">
   <bill name="">
      <meta xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions">
         <identification source="~COM">
            <FRBRWork>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRcountry value=""/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
         </identification>
      </meta>
      <preface>
         <longTitle>
            <p>
               <docStage/>
               <docType>COMMISSION REGULATION (EU) 2016/440</docType>of 23 March 2016<docPurpose>amending Annexes II, III and V to Regulation (EC) No 396/2005 of the European Parliament and of the Council as regards maximum residue levels for atrazine in or on certain products</docPurpose>
            </p>
         </longTitle>
         <container name="EEArelevance">
            <p>(Text with EEA relevance)</p>
         </container>
      </preface>
      <preamble>
         <formula name="actingEntity">
            <p>THE EUROPEAN COMMISSION,</p>
         </formula>
         <citations>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to Regulation (EC) No 396/2005 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 23 February 2005 on maximum residue levels of pesticides in or on food and feed of plant and animal origin and amending Council Directive 91/414/EEC<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="1">
                     <p>OJ L 70, 16.3.2005, p. 1.</p>
                  </authorialNote>, and in particular Article 14(1)(a) in conjunction with Article 17 and Article 49(2) thereof,</p>
            </citation>
         </citations>
         <recitals xml:id="recs_d601e71">
            <intro>
               <p>Whereas:</p>
            </intro>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d601e74">
               <num>(1)</num>
               <p>For atrazine, maximum residue limits (MRLs) were set in Annex II and Part B of Annex III to Regulation (EC) No 396/2005.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d601e80">
               <num>(2)</num>
               <p>All existing authorisations for plant protection products containing atrazine have been revoked. In accordance with Article 17 of Regulation (EC) No 396/2005, the MRLs set out for that active substance in Annexes II and III should be deleted.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d601e86">
               <num>(3)</num>
               <p>In accordance with Article 43 of Regulation (EC) No 396/2005, the Commission requested the European Food Safety Authority, hereinafter &apos;the Authority&apos;, to provide a scientific opinion on the temporary MRLs, which were set for cereals, following an import tolerance request made by Argentina. Based on residue trials submitted by the applicant in support of the use of atrazine on maize in accordance with Argentinian Good Agricultural Practices, the Authority concluded<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="2">
                     <p>Reasoned opinion on the setting of a new maximum residue level for atrazine in cereals. <i>EFSA Journal</i> 2015;13(6):4126 [21 pp.].</p>
                  </authorialNote> that the MRLs for atrazine in cereals should be lowered to a level of 0,05 mg/kg. Such level corresponds to the existing relevant limit of determination for atrazine in products of plant origin. The proposed MRLs do not pose a consumer health risk for the European consumers.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d601e103">
               <num>(4)</num>
               <p>Through the World Trade Organisation, the trading partners of the Union were consulted on the new MRLs and their comments have been taken into account.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d601e109">
               <num>(5)</num>
               <p>Regulation (EC) No 396/2005 should therefore be amended accordingly.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d601e115">
               <num>(6)</num>
               <p>In order to allow for the normal marketing, processing and consumption of products, this Regulation should provide for a transitional arrangement for products which have been produced before the modification of the MRLs made by this Regulation and for which information shows that a high level of consumer protection is maintained.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d601e121">
               <num>(7)</num>
               <p>A reasonable period should be allowed to elapse before the modified MRLs become applicable in order to permit Member States, third countries and food business operators to prepare themselves to meet the new requirements which will result from the modification of the MRLs.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d601e127">
               <num>(8)</num>
               <p>The measures provided for in this Regulation are in accordance with the opinion of the Standing Committee on Plants, Animals, Food and Feed,</p>
            </recital>
         </recitals>
         <formula name="enactingFormula">
            <p>HAS ADOPTED THIS REGULATION:</p>
         </formula>
      </preamble>
      <body>
         <article xml:id="art_d601e136">
            <num>Article 1</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>Annexes II, III and V to Regulation (EC) No 396/2005 are amended in accordance with the Annex to this Regulation.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <article xml:id="art_d601e142">
            <num>Article 2</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>Regulation (EC) No 396/2005 as it stood before being amended by this Regulation shall continue to apply to products which were produced before 13 October 2016.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <article xml:id="art_d601e150">
            <num>Article 3</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>This Regulation shall enter into force on the twentieth day following that of its publication in the <i>Official Journal of the European Union</i>.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>It shall apply from 13 October 2016.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <clause>
            <content>
               <p>This Regulation shall be binding in its entirety and directly applicable in all Member States.</p>
            </content>
         </clause>
      </body>
      <conclusions>
         <p>Done at Brussels, 23 March 2016.</p>
         <block name="signatory">
            <signature>
               <organization refersTo="">For the Commission</organization>
               <role refersTo="">The President</role>
               <person refersTo="">Jean-Claude JUNCKER</person>
            </signature>
         </block>
      </conclusions>
   </bill>
</akomaNtoso>
