<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0"
            xmlns:fmx="http://formex.publications.europa.eu/schema/formex-05.21-20110601.xd"
            xmlns:leos="urn:eu:europa:ec:leos"
            xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema">
   <bill name="">
      <meta xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions">
         <identification source="~COM">
            <FRBRWork>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRcountry value=""/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
         </identification>
      </meta>
      <preface>
         <longTitle>
            <p>
               <docStage/>
               <docType>REGULATION (EU) 2021/2269 OF THE EUROPEAN PARLIAMENT AND OF THE COUNCIL</docType>of 15 December 2021<docPurpose>amending Regulation (EU) 2018/1091 as regards the Union contribution for integrated farm statistics under Council Regulation (EU, Euratom) 2020/2093 laying down the multiannual financial framework for the years 2021 to 2027</docPurpose>
            </p>
         </longTitle>
         <container name="EEArelevance">
            <p>(Text with EEA relevance)</p>
         </container>
      </preface>
      <preamble>
         <formula name="actingEntity">
            <p>THE EUROPEAN PARLIAMENT AND THE COUNCIL OF THE EUROPEAN UNION,</p>
         </formula>
         <citations>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union, and in particular Article 338(1) thereof,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the proposal from the European Commission,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>After transmission of the draft legislative act to the national parliaments,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>Acting in accordance with the ordinary legislative procedure<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="1">
                     <p>Position of the European Parliament of 23 November 2021 (not yet published in the Official Journal) and decision of the Council of 12 December 2021.</p>
                  </authorialNote>,</p>
            </citation>
         </citations>
         <recitals xml:id="recs_d733e78">
            <intro>
               <p>Whereas:</p>
            </intro>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d733e81">
               <num>(1)</num>
               <p>Regulation (EU) 2018/1091 of the European Parliament and of the Council<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="2">
                     <p>Regulation (EU) 2018/1091 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 18 July 2018 on integrated farm statistics and repealing Regulations (EC) No 1166/2008 and (EU) No 1337/2011 (OJ L 200, 7.8.2018, p. 1).</p>
                  </authorialNote> provides that Member States are to collect and provide core structural data and module data related to agricultural holdings (&apos;core data&apos; and &apos;module data&apos;, respectively) for the reference years 2023 and 2026.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d733e105">
               <num>(2)</num>
               <p>To carry out the farm structure surveys and to satisfy the information requirements of the Union, a considerable amount of funding is required from Member States and from the Union.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d733e111">
               <num>(3)</num>
               <p>Member States are to receive a maximum financial contribution of 75 % from the Union towards the costs of the core data and module data collections for the reference years 2023 and 2026, subject to the maximum amounts specified in Regulation (EU) 2018/1091.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d733e117">
               <num>(4)</num>
               <p>Regulation (EU) 2018/1091 lays down the financial envelope for the entire duration of the relevant multiannual financial framework (MFF) and includes a provision for establishing the amount to be granted for further data collections under the subsequent MFF covering the farm structure surveys for the reference years 2023 and 2026.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d733e123">
               <num>(5)</num>
               <p>That subsequent MFF for the years 2021 to 2027 was laid down by Council Regulation (EU, Euratom) 2020/2093<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="3">
                     <p>Council Regulation (EU, Euratom) 2020/2093 of 17 December 2020 laying down the multiannual financial framework for the years 2021 to 2027 (OJ L 433I, 22.12.2020, p. 11).</p>
                  </authorialNote>.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d733e140">
               <num>(6)</num>
               <p>In accordance with Regulation (EU) 2018/1091, the amount of the Union contribution for integrated farm statistics under the MFF for the years 2021 to 2027 is to be fixed by the European Parliament and the Council, based on a proposal from the Commission following the date of entry into force of Regulation (EU, Euratom) 2020/2093.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d733e146">
               <num>(7)</num>
               <p>The amount proposed for the years 2021 to 2027 should finance the farm structure surveys conducted in 2023 and 2026 only, including the costs related to the management, maintenance and development of the databases used by the Commission to process the data provided by Member States.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d733e152">
               <num>(8)</num>
               <p>In addition, following its withdrawal from the Union, it is appropriate to delete the reference in Regulation (EU) 2018/1091 to the United Kingdom.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d733e158">
               <num>(9)</num>
               <p>Regulation (EU) 2018/1091 should therefore be amended accordingly.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d733e165">
               <num>(10)</num>
               <p>The European Statistical System Committee established by Article 7 of Regulation (EC) No 223/2009 of the European Parliament and of the Council<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="4">
                     <p>Regulation (EC) No 223/2009 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 11 March 2009 on European statistics and repealing Regulation (EC, Euratom) No 1101/2008 of the European Parliament and of the Council on the transmission of data subject to statistical confidentiality to the Statistical Office of the European Communities, Council Regulation (EC) No 322/97 on Community Statistics, and Council Decision 89/382/EEC, Euratom establishing a Committee on the Statistical Programmes of the European Communities (OJ L 87, 31.3.2009, p. 164).</p>
                  </authorialNote> has been consulted.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d733e181">
               <num>(11)</num>
               <p>This Regulation should enter into force as a matter of urgency on the day following that of its publication in the <i>Official Journal of the European Union</i> in order to ensure that the Member States receive financing from the Union in a timely manner to allow their national statistical institutes to prepare the data collection for the reference year 2023,</p>
            </recital>
         </recitals>
         <formula name="enactingFormula">
            <p>HAVE ADOPTED THIS REGULATION:</p>
         </formula>
      </preamble>
      <body>
         <article xml:id="art_d733e193" leos:compliant="false">
            <num>Article 1</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <subparagraph>
                  <content>
                     <p>Regulation (EU) 2018/1091 is amended as follows:</p>
                  </content>
               </subparagraph>
               <list>
                  <point>
                     <num>(1)</num>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>Article 13 is amended as follows:</p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                     <list>
                        <point>
                           <num>(a)</num>
                           <alinea>
                              <content>
                                 <p>paragraph 4 is amended as follows:</p>
                              </content>
                           </alinea>
                           <list>
                              <point>
                                 <num>(i)</num>
                                 <alinea>
                                    <content>
                                       <p>the introductory part is replaced by the following:</p>
                                    </content>
                                 </alinea>
                                 <alinea>
                                    <content>
                                       <p>
                                          <mod>
                                             <quotedStructure startQuote="" endQuote="">
                                                <alinea>
                                                   <content>
                                                      <p>&apos;For the combined costs of the core data and module data collections for the reference years 2023 and 2026, the Union financial contribution shall be limited to the maximum amounts specified below:&apos;;</p>
                                                   </content>
                                                </alinea>
                                             </quotedStructure>
                                          </mod>
                                       </p>
                                    </content>
                                 </alinea>
                              </point>
                              <point>
                                 <num>(ii)</num>
                                 <alinea>
                                    <content>
                                       <p>point (c) is replaced by the following:</p>
                                    </content>
                                 </alinea>
                                 <alinea>
                                    <content>
                                       <p>
                                          <mod>
                                             <quotedStructure startQuote="" endQuote="">
                                                <list>
                                                   <point>
                                                      <num>&apos;(c)</num>
                                                      <content>
                                                         <p>EUR 2000000 each for Bulgaria, Germany, Hungary and Portugal;&apos;;</p>
                                                      </content>
                                                   </point>
                                                </list>
                                             </quotedStructure>
                                          </mod>
                                       </p>
                                    </content>
                                 </alinea>
                              </point>
                           </list>
                        </point>
                        <point>
                           <num>(b)</num>
                           <content>
                              <p>paragraph 5 is deleted;</p>
                           </content>
                        </point>
                        <point>
                           <num>(c)</num>
                           <alinea>
                              <content>
                                 <p>paragraph 7 is replaced by the following:</p>
                              </content>
                           </alinea>
                           <alinea>
                              <content>
                                 <p>
                                    <mod>
                                       <quotedStructure startQuote="" endQuote="">
                                          <paragraph>
                                             <num>&apos;7.</num>
                                             <content>
                                                <p>The Union financial contribution for the grants referred to in paragraph 2 of this Article shall be provided by the European Agricultural Guarantee Fund under Article 4(2), point (d), of Regulation (EU) No 1306/2013 and, as from 1 January 2023, under Article 5(3), point (d), of Regulation (EU) 2021/2116 of the European Parliament and the Council<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="5">
                                                      <p>Regulation (EU) 2021/2116 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 2 December 2021 on the financing, management and monitoring of the common agriculture policy and repealing Regulation (EU) No 1306/2013 (OJ L 435, 6.12.2021, p. 187).&apos;;</p>
                                                   </authorialNote>.</p>
                                             </content>
                                          </paragraph>
                                       </quotedStructure>
                                    </mod>
                                 </p>
                              </content>
                           </alinea>
                        </point>
                     </list>
                  </point>
                  <point>
                     <num>(2)</num>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>in Article 14, paragraph 1 is replaced by the following:</p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>
                              <mod>
                                 <quotedStructure startQuote="" endQuote="">
                                    <paragraph>
                                       <num>&apos;1.</num>
                                       <content>
                                          <p>The Union financial envelope for the implementation of the programme of data collections for the reference years 2023 and 2026, including the appropriations necessary for the management, maintenance and development of the database systems used within the Commission to process the data provided by the Member States under this Regulation, shall be EUR 40000000 for the period covered by Council Regulation (EU, Euratom) 2020/2093<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="6">
                                                <p>Council Regulation (EU, Euratom) 2020/2093 of 17 December 2020 laying down the multiannual financial framework for the years 2021 to 2027 (OJ L 433I, 22.12.2020, p. 11).&apos;.</p>
                                             </authorialNote>.</p>
                                       </content>
                                    </paragraph>
                                 </quotedStructure>
                              </mod>
                           </p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                  </point>
               </list>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <article xml:id="art_d733e315">
            <num>Article 2</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>This Regulation shall enter into force on the day following that of its publication in the <i>Official Journal of the European Union</i>.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <clause>
            <content>
               <p>This Regulation shall be binding in its entirety and directly applicable in all Member States.</p>
            </content>
         </clause>
      </body>
      <conclusions>
         <p>Done at Strasbourg, 15 December 2021.</p>
         <block name="signatory">
            <signature>
               <organization refersTo="">For the European Parliament</organization>
               <role refersTo="">The President</role>
               <person refersTo="">D. M. SASSOLI</person>
            </signature>
            <signature>
               <organization refersTo="">For the Council</organization>
               <role refersTo="">The President</role>
               <person refersTo="">A. LOGAR</person>
            </signature>
         </block>
      </conclusions>
   </bill>
</akomaNtoso>
