<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0"
            xmlns:fmx="http://formex.publications.europa.eu/schema/formex-05.21-20110601.xd"
            xmlns:leos="urn:eu:europa:ec:leos"
            xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema">
   <bill name="">
      <meta xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions">
         <identification source="~COM">
            <FRBRWork>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRcountry value=""/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
         </identification>
      </meta>
      <preface>
         <longTitle>
            <p>
               <docStage/>
               <docType>COMMISSION REGULATION (EU) 2017/294</docType>of 20 February 2017<docPurpose>amending Regulation (EC) No 748/2009 on the list of aircraft operators which performed an aviation activity listed in Annex I to Directive 2003/87/EC of the European Parliament and of the Council on or after 1 January 2006 specifying the administering Member State for each aircraft operator</docPurpose>
            </p>
         </longTitle>
         <container name="EEArelevance">
            <p>(Text with EEA relevance)</p>
         </container>
      </preface>
      <preamble>
         <formula name="actingEntity">
            <p>THE EUROPEAN COMMISSION,</p>
         </formula>
         <citations>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to Directive 2003/87/EC of the European Parliament and of the Council of 13 October 2003 establishing a scheme for greenhouse gas emission allowance trading within the Community and amending Council Directive 96/61/EC<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="1">
                     <p>OJ L 275, 25.10.2003, p. 32.</p>
                  </authorialNote>, and in particular Article 18a(3)(b) thereof,</p>
            </citation>
         </citations>
         <recitals xml:id="recs_d154e74">
            <intro>
               <p>Whereas:</p>
            </intro>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d154e77">
               <num>(1)</num>
               <p>Directive 2008/101/EC of the European Parliament and of the Council<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="2">
                     <p>Directive 2008/101/EC of the European Parliament and of the Council of 19 November 2008 amending Directive 2003/87/EC so as to include aviation activities in the scheme for greenhouse gas emission allowance trading within the Community (OJ L 8, 13.1.2009, p. 3).</p>
                  </authorialNote> amended Directive 2003/87/EC to include aviation activities in the scheme for greenhouse gas emission allowance trading within the Union.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d154e93">
               <num>(2)</num>
               <p>Commission Regulation (EC) No 748/2009<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="3">
                     <p>Commission Regulation (EC) No 748/2009 of 5 August 2009 on the list of aircraft operators which performed an aviation activity listed in Annex I to Directive 2003/87/EC on or after 1 January 2006 specifying the administering Member State for each aircraft operator (OJ L 219, 22.8.2009, p. 1).</p>
                  </authorialNote> establishes a list of aircraft operators which performed an aviation activity listed in Annex I to Directive 2003/87/EC on or after 1 January 2006.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d154e115">
               <num>(3)</num>
               <p>That list aims to reduce the administrative burden on aircraft operators by providing information on which Member State will be regulating a particular aircraft operator.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d154e121">
               <num>(4)</num>
               <p>The inclusion of an aircraft operator in the Union`s emissions trading scheme is dependent upon the performance of an aviation activity listed in Annex I to Directive 2003/87/EC and is not dependent on the inclusion in the list of aircraft operators established by the Commission on the basis of Article 18a(3) of that Directive.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d154e127">
               <num>(5)</num>
               <p>Changes to the list of aircraft operators are based on the latest data provided by Eurocontrol.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d154e133">
               <num>(6)</num>
               <p>This Regulation should enter into force as a matter of urgency in order to meet the deadline for the yearly updating of the list of aircraft operators laid down in Article 18a(3)(b) of Directive 2003/87/EC.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d154e139">
               <num>(7)</num>
               <p>Regulation (EC) No 748/2009 should therefore be amended accordingly,</p>
            </recital>
         </recitals>
         <formula name="enactingFormula">
            <p>HAS ADOPTED THIS REGULATION:</p>
         </formula>
      </preamble>
      <body>
         <article xml:id="art_d154e148">
            <num>Article 1</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>The Annex to Regulation (EC) No 748/2009 is replaced by the text set out in the Annex to this Regulation.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <article xml:id="art_d154e153">
            <num>Article 2</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>This Regulation shall enter into force on the third day following that of its publication in the <i>Official Journal of the European Union</i>.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <clause>
            <content>
               <p>This Regulation shall be binding in its entirety and directly applicable in all Member States.</p>
            </content>
         </clause>
      </body>
      <conclusions>
         <p>Done at Brussels, 20 February 2017.</p>
         <block name="signatory">
            <signature>
               <organization refersTo="">For the Commission</organization>
               <role refersTo="">The President</role>
               <person refersTo="">Jean-Claude JUNCKER</person>
            </signature>
         </block>
      </conclusions>
   </bill>
</akomaNtoso>
