<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0"
            xmlns:fmx="http://formex.publications.europa.eu/schema/formex-05.21-20110601.xd"
            xmlns:leos="urn:eu:europa:ec:leos"
            xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema">
   <bill name="">
      <meta xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions">
         <identification source="~COM">
            <FRBRWork>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRcountry value=""/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
         </identification>
      </meta>
      <preface>
         <longTitle>
            <p>
               <docStage/>
               <docType>COUNCIL REGULATION (EU) 2017/2467</docType>of 21 December 2017<docPurpose>amending Regulation (EU) No 1387/2013 suspending the autonomous Common Customs Tariff duties on certain agricultural and industrial products</docPurpose>
            </p>
         </longTitle>
      </preface>
      <preamble>
         <formula name="actingEntity">
            <p>THE COUNCIL OF THE EUROPEAN UNION,</p>
         </formula>
         <citations>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union, and in particular Article 31 thereof,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the proposal from the European Commission,</p>
            </citation>
         </citations>
         <recitals xml:id="recs_d634e59">
            <intro>
               <p>Whereas:</p>
            </intro>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d634e62">
               <num>(1)</num>
               <p>The Union production of 67 products that are not listed in the Annex to Council Regulation (EU) No 1387/2013<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="1">
                     <p>Council Regulation (EU) No 1387/2013 of 17 December 2013 suspending the autonomous Common Customs Tariff duties on certain agricultural and industrial products and repealing Regulation (EU) No 1344/2011 (OJ L 354, 28.12.2013, p. 201).</p>
                  </authorialNote> is not sufficient to cover the needs of the Union industry. It is therefore in the interest of the Union to suspend the autonomous Common Customs Tariff (&apos;CCT&apos;) duties on those products.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d634e82">
               <num>(2)</num>
               <p>It is necessary to modify the conditions for the suspension of autonomous CCT duties for 49 products listed in the Annex to Regulation (EU) No 1387/2013 in order to take into account technical product developments and economic trends on the market. Certain product classifications have been amended in order to allow industry to fully benefit from the suspensions in force. Moreover, the Annex to Regulation (EU) No 1387/2013 should be updated in order to align or clarify texts in some cases. The modified conditions relate to changes in the product description, classification, duty rates or end-use requirements.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d634e88">
               <num>(3)</num>
               <p>The end dates for the mandatory review provided for in the Annex to Regulation (EU) No 1387/2013 should be revised for 188 suspensions.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d634e94">
               <num>(4)</num>
               <p>It is no longer in the interest of the Union to maintain the suspension of autonomous CCT duties for 92 products listed in the Annex to Regulation (EU) No 1387/2013. Suspensions for those products should therefore be deleted from that Annex.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d634e100">
               <num>(5)</num>
               <p>In the interests of clarity, the entries for the suspensions that are modified or newly introduced by this Regulation should be marked with an asterisk, whereas the asterisk should be removed from the entries for the suspensions that are not modified by this Regulation.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d634e106">
               <num>(6)</num>
               <p>Regulation (EU) No 1387/2013 should therefore be amended accordingly.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d634e112">
               <num>(7)</num>
               <p>In order to avoid any interruption of the application of the autonomous suspension scheme and to comply with the guidelines set out in the Communication from the Commission concerning autonomous tariff suspensions and quotas<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="2">
                     <p>OJ C 363, 13.12.2011, p. 6.</p>
                  </authorialNote>, the changes provided for in this Regulation regarding the suspensions for the products concerned have to apply from 1 January 2018. This Regulation should therefore enter into force as a matter of urgency,</p>
            </recital>
         </recitals>
         <formula name="enactingFormula">
            <p>HAS ADOPTED THIS REGULATION:</p>
         </formula>
      </preamble>
      <body>
         <article xml:id="art_d634e130">
            <num>Article 1</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <subparagraph>
                  <content>
                     <p>The Annex to Regulation (EU) No 1387/2013 is amended as follows:</p>
                  </content>
               </subparagraph>
               <list>
                  <point>
                     <num>(1)</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>in the table, the rows for the products for which the CN and TARIC codes are set out in Annex I to this Regulation are deleted;</p>
                     </content>
                  </point>
                  <point>
                     <num>(2)</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>all asterisks in the table and endnote (*), containing the text &apos;A newly introduced measure or a measure with amended conditions.&apos;, are deleted;</p>
                     </content>
                  </point>
                  <point>
                     <num>(3)</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>the rows for the products listed in Annex II to this Regulation are inserted into the table according to the order of the CN codes indicated in the first column of that table.</p>
                     </content>
                  </point>
               </list>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <article xml:id="art_d634e160">
            <num>Article 2</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>This Regulation shall enter into force on the day following that of its publication in the <i>Official Journal of the European Union</i>.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>It shall apply from 1 January 2018.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <clause>
            <content>
               <p>This Regulation shall be binding in its entirety and directly applicable in all Member States.</p>
            </content>
         </clause>
      </body>
      <conclusions>
         <p>Done at Brussels, 21 December 2017.</p>
         <block name="signatory">
            <signature>
               <organization refersTo="">For the Council</organization>
               <role refersTo="">The President</role>
               <person refersTo="">M. MAASIKAS</person>
            </signature>
         </block>
      </conclusions>
   </bill>
</akomaNtoso>
