<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0"
            xmlns:fmx="http://formex.publications.europa.eu/schema/formex-05.21-20110601.xd"
            xmlns:leos="urn:eu:europa:ec:leos"
            xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema">
   <bill name="">
      <meta xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions">
         <identification source="~COM">
            <FRBRWork>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRcountry value=""/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
         </identification>
      </meta>
      <preface>
         <longTitle>
            <p>
               <docStage/>
               <docType>COMMISSION REGULATION (EU) 2016/621</docType>of 21 April 2016<docPurpose>amending Annex VI to Regulation (EC) No 1223/2009 of the European Parliament and of the Council on cosmetic products</docPurpose>
            </p>
         </longTitle>
         <container name="EEArelevance">
            <p>(Text with EEA relevance)</p>
         </container>
      </preface>
      <preamble>
         <formula name="actingEntity">
            <p>THE EUROPEAN COMMISSION,</p>
         </formula>
         <citations>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to Regulation (EC) No 1223/2009 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 30 November 2009 on cosmetic products<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="1">
                     <p>OJ L 342, 22.12.2009, p. 59.</p>
                  </authorialNote>, and in particular Article 31(2) thereof,</p>
            </citation>
         </citations>
         <recitals xml:id="recs_d674e71">
            <intro>
               <p>Whereas:</p>
            </intro>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d674e74">
               <num>(1)</num>
               <p>The Scientific Committee on Cosmetic Products and Non-Food Products intended for Consumers, subsequently replaced by the Scientific Committee on Consumer Products (&apos;SCCP&apos;), pursuant to Commission Decision 2004/210/EC<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="2">
                     <p>OJ L 66, 4.3.2004, p. 45.</p>
                  </authorialNote>, subsequently replaced by the Scientific Committee on Consumer Safety (&apos;SCCS&apos;), pursuant to Commission Decision 2008/721/EC<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="3">
                     <p>OJ L 241, 10.9.2008, p. 21.</p>
                  </authorialNote>, delivered an opinion on 25 June 2003<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="4">
                     <p>SCCNFP/0649/03, http://ec.europa.eu/health/ph_risk/committees/sccp/documents/out222_en.pdf</p>
                  </authorialNote>, in which it stated that, in general, zinc oxide may be considered as a non-toxic substance, including when used in cosmetic products. However, the potential for absorption by inhalation was not considered and the SCCP expressed concern on the safety of micronised zinc oxide, due to the lack of a reliable safety dossier on that substance. Following requests for clarification by the Commission, the SCCP<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="5">
                     <p>SCCP/0932/05, http://ec.europa.eu/health/ph_risk/committees/04_sccp/docs/sccp_o_00m.pdf SCCP/1147/07, http://ec.europa.eu/health/ph_risk/committees/04_sccp/docs/sccp_o_123.pdf and SCCP/1215/09, http://ec.europa.eu/health/ph_risk/committees/04_sccp/docs/sccp_o_167.pdf</p>
                  </authorialNote> confirmed that the use of the non-nano zinc oxide in cosmetic products was safe up to a maximum concentration of 25 % and that adequate data should be submitted for the risk assessment of zinc oxide in nano form.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d674e111">
               <num>(2)</num>
               <p>The SCCS was requested to perform a safety assessment of zinc oxide in nano form and delivered an opinion on 18 September 2012<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="6">
                     <p>SCCS/1489/2012 Revision of 11 December 2012, http://ec.europa.eu/health/scientific_committees/consumer_safety/docs/sccs_o_103.pdf</p>
                  </authorialNote>, followed by an addendum of 23 July 2013<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="7">
                     <p>SCCS/1518/13 Revision of 22 April 2014, http://ec.europa.eu/health/scientific_committees/consumer_safety/docs/sccs_o_137.pdf</p>
                  </authorialNote>. The SCCS concluded, on the basis of available evidence, that the use of zinc oxide nanoparticles with the characteristics as indicated, at a concentration up to 25 % as a UV filter in sunscreens, can be considered not to pose a risk of adverse effects in humans after dermal application. In addition, the SCCS indicated that there is no evidence for the absorption of zinc oxide nanoparticles through skin and via the oral route. In the Margin of Safety calculation, the calculation of the exposure to zinc oxide nanoparticles results in acceptable Margin of Safety for both the oral and dermal routes. The SCCS later confirmed that zinc oxide nano may be used in cosmetic products other than sunscreens, intended for dermal application.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d674e135">
               <num>(3)</num>
               <p>The characteristics indicated by the SCCS in its opinion concern the physico-chemical properties of the material (such as purity, structure and physical appearance, particle number size distribution and water solubility) and whether it is uncoated or coated with specific chemicals. Other cosmetic ingredients can be used as coatings as long as they are demonstrated to the SCCS to be safe and do not affect the particle properties related to behaviour and/or toxicological effects, compared to the nanomaterials covered in the relevant SCCS opinion. Therefore, the Commission considers that these physico-chemical properties and requirements regarding coatings should be reflected in Regulation (EC) No 1223/2009.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d674e141">
               <num>(4)</num>
               <p>The SCCS also considered that, on the basis of available information, the use of zinc oxide nanoparticles in spray products cannot be considered safe. In addition, the SCCS indicated, in a further opinion of 23 September 2014 for clarification of the meaning of the term &apos;sprayable applications/products&apos; for the nano forms of carbon black CI 77266, titanium dioxide and zinc oxide<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="8">
                     <p>SCCS/1539/14 Revision of 25 June 2015, http://ec.europa.eu/health/scientific_committees/consumer_safety/docs/sccs_o_163.pdf</p>
                  </authorialNote>, that its concern is limited to spray products that could lead to exposure of the consumer&apos;s lungs to nano zinc oxide by inhalation. The SCCS also indicated that non-nano zinc oxide has similar toxic effects to nano zinc oxide, as far as lung toxicity after inhalation is concerned.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d674e163">
               <num>(5)</num>
               <p>In light of the SCCS opinions mentioned above, the Commission considers that zinc oxide in non-nano form should be authorised for use as a UV filter in cosmetic products; zinc oxide in nano form (according to the SCCS&apos;s specifications) should be authorised for use as a UV filter in cosmetic products. Both forms of the substance should be authorised at a maximum concentration of 25 %, except in applications that may lead to exposure of the end-user&apos;s lungs by inhalation.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d674e169">
               <num>(6)</num>
               <p>The Commission considers that Annex VI to Regulation (EC) No 1223/2009 should be amended for the purpose of adapting it to technical and scientific progress.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d674e175">
               <num>(7)</num>
               <p>The measures provided for in this Regulation are in accordance with the opinion of the Standing Committee on Cosmetic Products,</p>
            </recital>
         </recitals>
         <formula name="enactingFormula">
            <p>HAS ADOPTED THIS REGULATION:</p>
         </formula>
      </preamble>
      <body>
         <article xml:id="art_d674e184">
            <num>Article 1</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>Annex VI to Regulation (EC) No 1223/2009 is amended in accordance with the Annex to this Regulation.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <article xml:id="art_d674e189">
            <num>Article 2</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>This Regulation shall enter into force on the twentieth day following that of its publication in the <i>Official Journal of the European Union</i>.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <clause>
            <content>
               <p>This Regulation shall be binding in its entirety and directly applicable in all Member States.</p>
            </content>
         </clause>
      </body>
      <conclusions>
         <p>Done at Brussels, 21 April 2016.</p>
         <block name="signatory">
            <signature>
               <organization refersTo="">For the Commission</organization>
               <role refersTo="">The President</role>
               <person refersTo="">Jean-Claude JUNCKER</person>
            </signature>
         </block>
      </conclusions>
   </bill>
</akomaNtoso>
