<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0"
            xmlns:fmx="http://formex.publications.europa.eu/schema/formex-05.21-20110601.xd"
            xmlns:leos="urn:eu:europa:ec:leos"
            xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema">
   <bill name="">
      <meta xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions">
         <identification source="~COM">
            <FRBRWork>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRcountry value=""/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
         </identification>
      </meta>
      <preface>
         <longTitle>
            <p>
               <docStage/>
               <docType>REGULATION (EU) 2016/2337 OF THE EUROPEAN PARLIAMENT AND OF THE COUNCIL</docType>of 14 December 2016<docPurpose>repealing Regulation (EEC) No 1192/69 of the Council on common rules for the normalisation of the accounts of railway undertakings</docPurpose>
            </p>
         </longTitle>
         <container name="EEArelevance">
            <p>(Text with EEA relevance)</p>
         </container>
      </preface>
      <preamble>
         <formula name="actingEntity">
            <p>THE EUROPEAN PARLIAMENT AND THE COUNCIL OF THE EUROPEAN UNION,</p>
         </formula>
         <citations>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union, and in particular Articles 91 and 109 thereof,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the proposal from the European Commission,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>After transmission of the draft legislative act to the national parliaments,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the opinion of the European Economic and Social Committee<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="1">
                     <p>OJ C 327, 12.11.2013, p. 122.</p>
                  </authorialNote>,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the opinion of the Committee of the Regions<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="2">
                     <p>OJ C 356, 5.12.2013, p. 92.</p>
                  </authorialNote>,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>Acting in accordance with the ordinary legislative procedure<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="3">
                     <p>Position of the European Parliament of 26 February 2014 (not yet published in the Official Journal) and position of the Council at first reading of 17 October 2016 (OJ C 430, 22.11.2016, p. 1). Position of the European Parliament of 14 December 2016 (not yet published in the Official Journal).</p>
                  </authorialNote>,</p>
            </citation>
         </citations>
         <recitals xml:id="recs_d658e100">
            <intro>
               <p>Whereas:</p>
            </intro>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d658e103">
               <num>(1)</num>
               <p>Council Regulation (EEC) No 1192/69<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="4">
                     <p>Regulation (EEC) No 1192/69 of the Council of 26 June 1969 on common rules for the normalisation of the accounts of railway undertakings (OJ L 156, 28.6.1969, p. 8).</p>
                  </authorialNote> allows Member States to compensate 40 enumerated railway undertakings for the payment of obligations which undertakings of other transport modes do not have to support. The correct application of the rules for normalisation results in the exemption of Member States from State aid notification obligations.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d658e119">
               <num>(2)</num>
               <p>A series of Union legal acts has been adopted opening up the rail freight and international rail passenger markets to competition and establishing, in the case of Directive 2012/34/EU of the European Parliament and of the Council<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="5">
                     <p>Directive 2012/34/EU of the European Parliament and of the Council of 21 November 2012 establishing a single European railway area (OJ L 343, 14.12.2012, p. 32).</p>
                  </authorialNote>, certain fundamental principles, which include: that railway undertakings are to be managed in accordance with the principles that apply to commercial companies; that entities responsible for the allocation of capacity and charging for rail infrastructure are to be separate from entities which operate rail services, and that there is to be a separation of accounts; that any railway undertaking licensed in accordance with Union criteria is to have access to railway infrastructure on a fair and non-discriminatory basis; and that infrastructure managers may benefit from State financing.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d658e135">
               <num>(3)</num>
               <p>Regulation (EEC) No 1192/69 is inconsistent and incompatible with legislative measures currently in force. In particular, in the context of a liberalised market, where railway undertakings compete directly with the enumerated railway undertakings, it is no longer appropriate to treat those two groups differently from one another.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d658e141">
               <num>(4)</num>
               <p>In order to eliminate inconsistencies in the Union legal order and with a view to contributing to simplification by eliminating a legal act which has become obsolete, it is therefore appropriate to repeal Regulation (EEC) No 1192/69.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d658e148">
               <num>(5)</num>
               <p>Member States may pay compensation for the costs of crossing facilities on the basis of Article 8 of Directive 2012/34/EU. They may, nevertheless, need time to amend their national law and administrative provisions to take account of the repeal of Regulation (EEC) No 1192/69. As a consequence, this repeal should not take immediate effect for cases covered by Annex IV to Regulation (EEC) No 1192/69,</p>
            </recital>
         </recitals>
         <formula name="enactingFormula">
            <p>HAVE ADOPTED THIS REGULATION:</p>
         </formula>
      </preamble>
      <body>
         <article xml:id="art_d658e157">
            <num>Article 1</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>Regulation (EEC) No 1192/69 is repealed, with the exception of the provisions of that Regulation that apply to the normalisation of accounts for Class IV cases covered by Annex IV to that Regulation. Those provisions shall continue to apply until 31 December 2017.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <article xml:id="art_d658e165">
            <num>Article 2</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>This Regulation shall enter into force on the twentieth day following that of its publication in the <i>Official Journal of the European Union</i>.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <clause>
            <content>
               <p>This Regulation shall be binding in its entirety and directly applicable in all Member States.</p>
            </content>
         </clause>
      </body>
      <conclusions>
         <p>Done at Strasbourg, 14 December 2016.</p>
         <block name="signatory">
            <signature>
               <organization refersTo="">For the European Parliament</organization>
               <role refersTo="">The President</role>
               <person refersTo="">M. SCHULZ</person>
            </signature>
            <signature>
               <organization refersTo="">For the Council</organization>
               <role refersTo="">The President</role>
               <person refersTo="">I. KORČOK</person>
            </signature>
         </block>
      </conclusions>
   </bill>
</akomaNtoso>
