<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0"
            xmlns:fmx="http://formex.publications.europa.eu/schema/formex-05.21-20110601.xd"
            xmlns:leos="urn:eu:europa:ec:leos"
            xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema">
   <bill name="">
      <meta xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions">
         <identification source="~COM">
            <FRBRWork>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRcountry value=""/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
         </identification>
      </meta>
      <preface>
         <longTitle>
            <p>
               <docStage/>
               <docType>COMMISSION REGULATION (EU) 2020/356</docType>of 4 March 2020<docPurpose>amending Annex II to Regulation (EC) No 1333/2008 of the European Parliament and of the Council as regards the use of polysorbates (E 432-436) in carbonated beverages</docPurpose>
            </p>
         </longTitle>
         <container name="EEArelevance">
            <p>(Text with EEA relevance)</p>
         </container>
      </preface>
      <preamble>
         <formula name="actingEntity">
            <p>THE EUROPEAN COMMISSION,</p>
         </formula>
         <citations>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to Regulation (EC) No 1333/2008 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 16 December 2008 on food additives<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="1">
                     <p>OJ L 354, 31.12.2008, p. 16.</p>
                  </authorialNote>, and in particular Article 10(3) thereof,</p>
            </citation>
         </citations>
         <recitals xml:id="recs_d47e71">
            <intro>
               <p>Whereas:</p>
            </intro>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d47e74">
               <num>(1)</num>
               <p>Annex II to Regulation (EC) No 1333/2008 lays down a Union list of food additives approved for use in food and their conditions of use.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d47e80">
               <num>(2)</num>
               <p>That list may be updated in accordance with the common procedure referred to in Article 3(1) of Regulation (EC) No 1331/2008 of the European Parliament and of the Council<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="2">
                     <p>Regulation (EC) No 1331/2008 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 16 December 2008 establishing a common authorisation procedure for food additives, food enzymes and food flavourings (OJ L 354, 31.12.2008, p. 1).</p>
                  </authorialNote>, either on the initiative of the Commission or following an application.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d47e96">
               <num>(3)</num>
               <p>Pursuant to Annex II to Regulation (EC) No 1333/2008, polyoxyethylene sorbitan tristearate (polysorbate 65) (E 436) is currently authorised for use as a food additive in the group &apos;polysorbates&apos; (E 432-436) in a wide variety of foods at maximum levels ranging between 500 and 10000 mg/kg and <i>quantum satis</i> in food supplements.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d47e112">
               <num>(4)</num>
               <p>On 4 July 2018, an application was submitted for the authorisation of the use of polysorbate 65 (E 436) as an anti-foaming agent in several types of beverages. The application was subsequently made available to the Member States pursuant to Article 4 of Regulation (EC) No 1331/2008.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d47e121">
               <num>(5)</num>
               <p>It results from the application that, the proposed use of polysorbate 65 (E 436) is required at the maximum level of 10 mg/kg for containment and inhibition of foam during the manufacture of carbonated beverages by forming a layer around bubbles and stabilising larger bubbles preventing them to coalesce and break. The application shows that, the inhibition of foam is needed to efficiently operate the production equipment, to reduce product waste, to maintain a safe workplace, and to keep facilities clean and in a hygienic state.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d47e127">
               <num>(6)</num>
               <p>Pursuant to Article 3(2) of Regulation (EC) No 1331/2008, the Commission has to seek the opinion of the European Food Safety Authority (&apos;the Authority&apos;) in order to update the Union list of food additives set out in Annex II to Regulation (EC) No 1333/2008, except where the update in question is not liable to have an effect on human health.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d47e137">
               <num>(7)</num>
               <p>The safety of polysorbates (E 432-436) used as food additives was re-evaluated by the Authority in 2015<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="3">
                     <p>EFSA Journal 2015;13(7):4152.</p>
                  </authorialNote>. The Authority concluded that the exposure estimates did not exceed the acceptable daily intake (ADI) of 25 mg/kg body weight/day in the refined non-brand-loyal scenario for all age groups at both the mean exposure level and the high level; although for toddlers at the highest level they were very close to the ADI. The Authority noted that more data were needed to decrease uncertainties in the refined exposure assessment scenario used since no reported uses had been obtained for three food categories and that other dietary sources of exposure to polysorbates could not be considered in the opinion.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d47e148">
               <num>(8)</num>
               <p>In the application the applicant estimated the exposure by using the Food Additives Intake Model<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="4">
                     <p>http://www.efsa.europa.eu/en/applications/foodingredients/tools</p>
                  </authorialNote> developed by the Authority. The estimates provided indicate that the additional exposure due to the requested extension of use is negligible (below 1 % of the ADI).</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d47e158">
               <num>(9)</num>
               <p>The extended use of polysorbate 65 (E 436) at the maximum level of 10 mg/kg in the food categories 14.1.4 &apos;Flavoured drinks&apos;, 14.2.3 &apos;Cider and perry&apos;, 14.2.4 &apos;Fruit wine and made wine&apos; and 14.2.8 &apos;Other alcoholic drinks including mixtures of alcoholic drinks with non-alcoholic drinks and spirits with less than 15 % of alcohol&apos; in Part E of Annex II to Regulation (EC) No 1333/2008 requires an update of the Union list which is not liable to have an effect on human health, since its impact on the overall exposure to polysorbates (E 432-436) is negligible. Consequently, it is not necessary to seek the opinion of the Authority.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d47e182">
               <num>(10)</num>
               <p>For the sake of consistency, it is appropriate to address the requested use of (polysorbate 65) (E 436) by authorising the group polysorbates (E 432-436) in the respective food categories.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d47e188">
               <num>(11)</num>
               <p>Therefore, it is appropriate to authorise the use of polysorbates (E 432-436) at the maximum level of 10 mg/kg in the food categories 14.1.4 &apos;Flavoured drinks&apos;, 14.2.3 &apos;Cider and perry&apos;, 14.2.4 &apos;Fruit wine and made wine&apos; and 14.2.8 &apos;Other alcoholic drinks including mixtures of alcoholic drinks with non-alcoholic drinks and spirits with less than 15 % of alcohol&apos;.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d47e211">
               <num>(12)</num>
               <p>Annex II to Regulation (EC) No 1333/2008 should therefore be amended accordingly.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d47e217">
               <num>(13)</num>
               <p>The measures provided for in this Regulation are in accordance with the opinion of the Standing Committee on Plants, Animals, Food and Feed,</p>
            </recital>
         </recitals>
         <formula name="enactingFormula">
            <p>HAS ADOPTED THIS REGULATION:</p>
         </formula>
      </preamble>
      <body>
         <article xml:id="art_d47e226">
            <num>Article 1</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>Annex II to Regulation (EC) No 1333/2008 is amended in accordance with the Annex to this Regulation.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <article xml:id="art_d47e231">
            <num>Article 2</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>This Regulation shall enter into force on the twentieth day following that of its publication in the <i>Official Journal of the European Union</i>.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <clause>
            <content>
               <p>This Regulation shall be binding in its entirety and directly applicable in all Member States.</p>
            </content>
         </clause>
      </body>
      <conclusions>
         <p>Done at Brussels, 4 March 2020.</p>
         <block name="signatory">
            <signature>
               <organization refersTo="">For the Commission</organization>
               <role refersTo="">The President</role>
               <person refersTo="">Ursula VON DER LEYEN</person>
            </signature>
         </block>
      </conclusions>
   </bill>
</akomaNtoso>
