<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0"
            xmlns:fmx="http://formex.publications.europa.eu/schema/formex-05.21-20110601.xd"
            xmlns:leos="urn:eu:europa:ec:leos"
            xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema">
   <bill name="">
      <meta xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions">
         <identification source="~COM">
            <FRBRWork>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRcountry value=""/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
         </identification>
      </meta>
      <preface>
         <longTitle>
            <p>
               <docStage/>
               <docType>COMMISSION REGULATION (EU) 2019/962</docType>of 12 June 2019<docPurpose>amending Annex I to Regulation (EC) No 1831/2003 of the European Parliament and of the Council as regards the establishment of two new functional groups of feed additives</docPurpose>
            </p>
         </longTitle>
         <container name="EEArelevance">
            <p>(Text with EEA relevance)</p>
         </container>
      </preface>
      <preamble>
         <formula name="actingEntity">
            <p>THE EUROPEAN COMMISSION,</p>
         </formula>
         <citations>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to Regulation (EC) No 1831/2003 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 22 September 2003 on additives for use in animal nutrition<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="1">
                     <p>OJ L 268, 18.10.2003, p. 29.</p>
                  </authorialNote>, and in particular Article 6(3) thereof,</p>
            </citation>
         </citations>
         <recitals xml:id="recs_d323e71">
            <intro>
               <p>Whereas:</p>
            </intro>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d323e74">
               <num>(1)</num>
               <p>Regulation (EC) No 1831/2003 provides for the allocation of feed additives to categories and further to functional groups within those categories according to their functions and properties.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d323e80">
               <num>(2)</num>
               <p>As a result of technological and scientific development, there are various substances that may have a technological effect on feeds which is not described in relation to any already existing functional groups. Therefore it is appropriate to create a new generic functional group within the category &apos;technological additives&apos; to include such substances.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d323e90">
               <num>(3)</num>
               <p>In addition to good farming practices ensuring the wellbeing of animals and the respect of animal welfare provisions in the EU, scientific studies show that some feed additives may help animals in good health to keep a good physiological condition, to contribute to animal welfare, to favourably affect the animal resilience to stress factors or to support their wellbeing in certain situations. Since the main function of these feed additives cannot be allocated to any of the specific functional groups provided for in Regulation (EC) No 1831/2003, it is appropriate to create a new functional group within the category &apos;zootechnical additives&apos;. This should allow to better define the intended purpose for those additives, to establish criteria for the evaluation of the efficacy and to create legal clarity for applicants.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d323e100">
               <num>(4)</num>
               <p>In order to introduce those two new functional groups, Annex I to Regulation (EC) No 1831/2003 should be amended accordingly.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d323e106">
               <num>(5)</num>
               <p>The measures provided for in this Regulation are in accordance with the opinion of the Standing Committee on Plants, Animals, Food and Feed,</p>
            </recital>
         </recitals>
         <formula name="enactingFormula">
            <p>HAS ADOPTED THIS REGULATION:</p>
         </formula>
      </preamble>
      <body>
         <article xml:id="art_d323e115" leos:compliant="false">
            <num>Article 1</num>
            <heading>Amendments to Regulation (EC) No 1831/2003</heading>
            <paragraph>
               <subparagraph>
                  <content>
                     <p>Annex I to Regulation (EC) No 1831/2003 is amended as follows:</p>
                  </content>
               </subparagraph>
               <list>
                  <point>
                     <num>(1)</num>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>in point 1 the following point is added:</p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>
                              <mod>
                                 <quotedStructure startQuote="" endQuote="">
                                    <point>
                                       <num>&apos;(o)</num>
                                       <content>
                                          <p>other technological additives: substances or, when applicable, microorganisms added to feed for a technological purpose and which favourably affect the characteristics of the feed.&apos;;</p>
                                       </content>
                                    </point>
                                 </quotedStructure>
                              </mod>
                           </p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                  </point>
                  <point>
                     <num>(2)</num>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>in point 4 the following point is added:</p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>
                              <mod>
                                 <quotedStructure startQuote="" endQuote="">
                                    <point>
                                       <num>&apos;(e)</num>
                                       <content>
                                          <p>physiological condition stabilisers: substances or, when applicable microorganisms, which, when fed to animals in good health, favourably affect their physiological condition, including their resilience to stress factors.&apos;</p>
                                       </content>
                                    </point>
                                 </quotedStructure>
                              </mod>
                           </p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                  </point>
               </list>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <article xml:id="art_d323e156">
            <num>Article 2</num>
            <heading>Entry into force</heading>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>This Regulation shall enter into force on the twentieth day following that of its publication in the <i>Official Journal of the European Union</i>.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <clause>
            <content>
               <p>This Regulation shall be binding in its entirety and directly applicable in all Member States.</p>
            </content>
         </clause>
      </body>
      <conclusions>
         <p>Done at Brussels, 12 June 2019.</p>
         <block name="signatory">
            <signature>
               <organization refersTo="">For the Commission</organization>
               <role refersTo="">The President</role>
               <person refersTo="">Jean-Claude JUNCKER</person>
            </signature>
         </block>
      </conclusions>
   </bill>
</akomaNtoso>
