<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0"
            xmlns:fmx="http://formex.publications.europa.eu/schema/formex-05.21-20110601.xd"
            xmlns:leos="urn:eu:europa:ec:leos"
            xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema">
   <bill name="">
      <meta xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions">
         <identification source="~COM">
            <FRBRWork>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRcountry value=""/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
         </identification>
      </meta>
      <preface>
         <longTitle>
            <p>
               <docStage/>
               <docType>COMMISSION REGULATION (EU) 2019/636</docType>of 23 April 2019<docPurpose>amending Annexes IV and V to Regulation (EC) No 850/2004 of the European Parliament and of the Council on persistent organic pollutants</docPurpose>
            </p>
         </longTitle>
      </preface>
      <preamble>
         <formula name="actingEntity">
            <p>THE EUROPEAN COMMISSION,</p>
         </formula>
         <citations>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to Regulation (EC) No 850/2004 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 29 April 2004 on persistent organic pollutants and amending Directive 79/117/EEC<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="1">
                     <p>OJ L 158, 30.4.2004, p. 7.</p>
                  </authorialNote>, and in particular Article 7(4)(a) and (5) and Article 14(2) and (4) thereof,</p>
            </citation>
         </citations>
         <recitals xml:id="recs_d322e68">
            <intro>
               <p>Whereas:</p>
            </intro>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d322e71">
               <num>(1)</num>
               <p>Regulation (EC) No 850/2004 implements in the law of the Union the commitments set out in the Stockholm Convention on Persistent Organic Pollutants (hereinafter &apos;the Convention&apos;) approved on behalf of the Community by Council Decision 2006/507/EC<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="2">
                     <p>Council Decision 2006/507/EC of 14 October 2004 concerning the conclusion, on behalf of the European Community, of the Stockholm Convention on Persistent Organic Pollutants (OJ L 209, 31.7.2006, p. 1).</p>
                  </authorialNote>, and in the Protocol to the 1979 Convention on Long-Range Transboundary Air Pollution on Persistent Organic Pollutants approved on behalf of the Community by Council Decision 2004/259/EC<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="3">
                     <p>Council Decision 2004/259/EC of 19 February 2004 concerning the conclusion, on behalf of the European Community, of the Protocol to the 1979 Convention on Long Range Transboundary Air Pollution on Persistent Organic Pollutants (OJ L 81, 19.3.2004, p. 35).</p>
                  </authorialNote>.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d322e101">
               <num>(2)</num>
               <p>At the seventh meeting of the Conference of the Parties to the Convention from 4 to 15 May 2015, it was agreed to include pentachlorophenol and its salts and esters (hereinafter &apos;pentachlorophenol&apos;) in Annex A (elimination) to the Convention.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d322e117">
               <num>(3)</num>
               <p>In view of the amendment of the Convention, it is necessary to amend Annexes IV and V to Regulation (EC) No 850/2004, including pentachlorophenol in the annexes and indicating the corresponding concentration limits, in order to ensure that wastes containing pentachlorophenol are managed in accordance with the provisions of the Convention.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d322e123">
               <num>(4)</num>
               <p>The proposed concentration limits in Annexes IV and V to Regulation (EC) No 850/2004 have been set applying the same methodology that was used for establishing the limit values in previous amendments of Annexes IV and V<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="4">
                     <p>Council Regulation (EC) No 1195/2006 of 18 July 2006 amending Annex IV to Regulation (EC) No 850/2004 of the European Parliament and of the Council on persistent organic pollutants (OJ L 217, 8.8.2006, p. 1), Council Regulation (EC) No 172/2007 of 16 February 2007 amending Annex V to Regulation (EC) No 850/2004 of the European Parliament and of the Council on persistent organic pollutants (OJ L 55, 23.2.2007, p. 1), Commission Regulation (EU) No 756/2010 of 24 August 2010 amending Regulation (EC) No 850/2004 of the European Parliament and of the Council on persistent organic pollutants as regards Annexes IV and V (OJ L 223, 25.8.2010, p. 20), Commission Regulation (EU) No 1342/2014 of 17 December 2014 amending Regulation (EC) No 850/2004 of the European Parliament and of the Council on persistent organic pollutants as regards Annexes IV and V (OJ L 363, 18.12.2014, p. 67) and Commission Regulation (EU) 2016/460 of 30 March 2016 amending Annexes IV and V to Regulation (EC) No 850/2004 of the European Parliament and of the Council on persistent organic pollutants (OJ L 80, 31.3.2016, p. 17).</p>
                  </authorialNote>. The proposed concentration limits are considered the most appropriate to ensure a high level of protection of human health and the environment in view of the destruction or irreversible transformation of pentachlorophenol.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d322e164">
               <num>(5)</num>
               <p>It is appropriate to provide for a sufficient period of time to allow companies and competent authorities to adapt to the new requirements.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d322e170">
               <num>(6)</num>
               <p>The measures provided for in this Regulation are in accordance with the opinion of the committee established by Article 39 of Directive 2008/98/EC of the European Parliament and of the Council<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="5">
                     <p>Directive 2008/98/EC of the European Parliament and of the Council of 19 November 2008 on waste and repealing certain Directives (OJ L 312, 22.11.2008, p. 3).</p>
                  </authorialNote>,</p>
            </recital>
         </recitals>
         <formula name="enactingFormula">
            <p>HAS ADOPTED THIS REGULATION:</p>
         </formula>
      </preamble>
      <body>
         <article xml:id="art_d322e190">
            <num>Article 1</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>Annexes IV and V to Regulation (EC) No 850/2004 are amended in accordance with the Annex to this Regulation.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <article xml:id="art_d322e195">
            <num>Article 2</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>This Regulation shall enter into force on the twentieth day following that of its publication in the <i>Official Journal of the European Union</i>.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>It shall apply from 31 October 2019.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <clause>
            <content>
               <p>This Regulation shall be binding in its entirety and directly applicable in all Member States.</p>
            </content>
         </clause>
      </body>
      <conclusions>
         <p>Done at Brussels, 23 April 2019.</p>
         <block name="signatory">
            <signature>
               <organization refersTo="">For the Commission</organization>
               <role refersTo="">The President</role>
               <person refersTo="">Jean-Claude JUNCKER</person>
            </signature>
         </block>
      </conclusions>
   </bill>
</akomaNtoso>
