<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0"
            xmlns:fmx="http://formex.publications.europa.eu/schema/formex-05.21-20110601.xd"
            xmlns:leos="urn:eu:europa:ec:leos"
            xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema">
   <bill name="">
      <meta xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions">
         <identification source="~COM">
            <FRBRWork>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRcountry value=""/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
         </identification>
      </meta>
      <preface>
         <longTitle>
            <p>
               <docStage/>
               <docType>COUNCIL REGULATION (EU) 2021/2317</docType>of 11 November 2021<docPurpose>on the allocation of fishing opportunities under the Protocol on the implementation of the Sustainable Fisheries Partnership Agreement between the European Union and the Government of the Cook Islands</docPurpose>
            </p>
         </longTitle>
      </preface>
      <preamble>
         <formula name="actingEntity">
            <p>THE COUNCIL OF THE EUROPEAN UNION,</p>
         </formula>
         <citations>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union, and in particular Article 43(3) thereof,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the proposal from the European Commission,</p>
            </citation>
         </citations>
         <recitals xml:id="recs_d726e59">
            <intro>
               <p>Whereas:</p>
            </intro>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d726e62">
               <num>(1)</num>
               <p>The Sustainable Fisheries Partnership Agreement between the European Union and the Government of the Cook Islands<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="1">
                     <p>OJ L 131, 20.5.2016, p. 3.</p>
                  </authorialNote> (&apos;the Agreement&apos;) was concluded by Council Decision (EU) 2017/418<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="2">
                     <p>Council Decision (EU) 2017/418 of 28 February 2017 on the conclusion on behalf of the European Union of the Sustainable Fisheries Partnership Agreement between the European Union and the Government of the Cook Islands and the Implementation Protocol thereto (OJ L 64, 10.3.2017, p. 1).</p>
                  </authorialNote> and entered into force on 10 May 2017. The Protocol on the implementation of the Agreement (&apos;the current Protocol&apos;) was provisionally applied since 14 October 2016<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="3">
                     <p>OJ L 289, 25.10.2016, p. 1.</p>
                  </authorialNote>.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d726e104">
               <num>(2)</num>
               <p>The current Protocol was extended for one year<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="4">
                     <p>OJ L 395, 25.11.2020, p. 1.</p>
                  </authorialNote>, and is due to expire on 13 November 2021.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d726e119">
               <num>(3)</num>
               <p>On 7 July 2020, the Council authorised the Commission to open negotiations with the Government of the Cook Islands for the conclusion of a new Protocol on the implementation of the Agreement (&apos;the Protocol&apos;).</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d726e132">
               <num>(4)</num>
               <p>As a result of those negotiations, the Protocol was initialled on 28 July 2021.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d726e141">
               <num>(5)</num>
               <p>On 11 November 2021, the Council adopted Decision (EU) 2021/2317<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="5">
                     <p>Council Decision (EU) 2021/2317 of 11 November 2021 on the signing, on behalf of the European Union, and provisional application of the Protocol on the implementation of the Sustainable Fisheries Partnership Agreement between the European Union and the Government of the Cook Islands (OJ L 463, 28.12.2021, p. 1).</p>
                  </authorialNote> on the signing and provisional application of the Protocol.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d726e160">
               <num>(6)</num>
               <p>The fishing opportunities set out in the Protocol should be allocated among the Member States for the entire period of its application.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d726e166">
               <num>(7)</num>
               <p>In view of the economic importance of the Union fishing activities in the Cook Islands&apos; fishing areas and in view of the need to avoid interrupting those activities upon the expiration of the current Protocol, this Regulation should enter into force as soon as possible.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d726e173">
               <num>(8)</num>
               <p>The Protocol will apply on a provisional basis as from the date of its signature, in order to allow for the fishing activities of Union vessels. This Regulation should therefore apply from the same date,</p>
            </recital>
         </recitals>
         <formula name="enactingFormula">
            <p>HAS ADOPTED THIS REGULATION:</p>
         </formula>
      </preamble>
      <body>
         <article xml:id="art_d726e182">
            <num>Article 1</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>The fishing opportunities set out in the Protocol on the implementation of the Sustainable Fisheries Partnership Agreement between the European Union and the Government of the Cook Islands (&apos;the Protocol&apos;) shall be allocated among the Member States as follows:</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph>
               <subparagraph>
                  <content>
                     <p>Tuna seiners:</p>
                  </content>
               </subparagraph>
               <list>
                  <indent>
                     <num>-</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>Spain: 3 vessels</p>
                     </content>
                  </indent>
                  <indent>
                     <num>-</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>France: 1 vessel.</p>
                     </content>
                  </indent>
               </list>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <article xml:id="art_d726e201">
            <num>Article 2</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>This Regulation shall enter into force on the day following that of its publication in the <i>Official Journal of the European Union</i>.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>It shall apply from 17 December 2021.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <clause>
            <content>
               <p>This Regulation shall be binding in its entirety and directly applicable in all Member States.</p>
            </content>
         </clause>
      </body>
      <conclusions>
         <p>Done at Brussels, 11 November 2021.</p>
         <block name="signatory">
            <signature>
               <organization refersTo="">For the Council</organization>
               <role refersTo="">The President</role>
               <person refersTo="">Z. POČIVALŠEK</person>
            </signature>
         </block>
      </conclusions>
   </bill>
</akomaNtoso>
