<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0"
            xmlns:fmx="http://formex.publications.europa.eu/schema/formex-05.21-20110601.xd"
            xmlns:leos="urn:eu:europa:ec:leos"
            xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema">
   <bill name="">
      <meta xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions">
         <identification source="~COM">
            <FRBRWork>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRcountry value=""/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
         </identification>
      </meta>
      <preface>
         <longTitle>
            <p>
               <docStage/>
               <docType>COUNCIL REGULATION (EU) 2016/1051</docType>of 24 June 2016<docPurpose>amending Regulation (EU) No 1387/2013 suspending the autonomous Common Customs Tariff duties on certain agricultural and industrial products</docPurpose>
            </p>
         </longTitle>
      </preface>
      <preamble>
         <formula name="actingEntity">
            <p>THE COUNCIL OF THE EUROPEAN UNION,</p>
         </formula>
         <citations>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union, and in particular Article 31 thereof,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the proposal from the European Commission,</p>
            </citation>
         </citations>
         <recitals xml:id="recs_d262e59">
            <intro>
               <p>Whereas:</p>
            </intro>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d262e62">
               <num>(1)</num>
               <p>It is in the interest of the Union to suspend totally the autonomous Common Customs Tariff duties on 140 products that are not currently listed in the Annex to Council Regulation (EU) No 1387/2013<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="1">
                     <p>Council Regulation (EU) No 1387/2013 of 17 December 2013 suspending the autonomous Common Customs Tariff duties on certain agricultural and industrial products and repealing Regulation (EU) No 1344/2011 (OJ L 354, 28.12.2013, p. 201).</p>
                  </authorialNote>.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d262e78">
               <num>(2)</num>
               <p>It is no longer in the interest of the Union to maintain the suspension of autonomous Common Customs Tariff duties on six of the products that are currently listed in the Annex to Regulation (EU) No 1387/2013.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d262e84">
               <num>(3)</num>
               <p>It is necessary to modify the conditions of 46 suspensions, currently listed in the Annex to Regulation (EU) No 1387/2013 in order to take into account technical product developments, economic trends on the market and further scrutiny of classification and to carry out linguistic adaptations. The modified conditions refer to changes of the product description, classification, duty rates or end-use requirement. The suspensions in respect of which modifications are necessary should be deleted from the list of suspensions in the Annex to Regulation (EU) No 1387/2013, and the modified suspensions should be inserted into that list.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d262e90">
               <num>(4)</num>
               <p>In the interest of clarity, the endnote indicating a newly introduced measure or a measure with amended conditions listed in the Annex to Regulation (EU) No 1387/2013 should be deleted and the entries modified by this Regulation should be marked with an asterisk.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d262e96">
               <num>(5)</num>
               <p>Regulation (EU) No 1387/2013 should therefore be amended accordingly.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d262e102">
               <num>(6)</num>
               <p>As the changes regarding the suspensions for the products concerned provided for in this Regulation have to apply from 1 July 2016, this Regulation should enter into force as a matter of urgency. In addition, in order to adequately ensure the benefit of the suspension classified under TARIC code 7616991030, the newly inserted TARIC code 8708999750 should apply from 1 January 2016,</p>
            </recital>
         </recitals>
         <formula name="enactingFormula">
            <p>HAS ADOPTED THIS REGULATION:</p>
         </formula>
      </preamble>
      <body>
         <article xml:id="art_d262e123" leos:compliant="false">
            <num>Article 1</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <subparagraph>
                  <content>
                     <p>The Annex to Regulation (EU) No 1387/2013 is amended as follows:</p>
                  </content>
               </subparagraph>
               <list>
                  <point>
                     <num>(1)</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>the rows for the products listed in Annex I to this Regulation are inserted following the order of the CN codes indicated in the first column of the table in the Annex to Regulation (EU) No 1387/2013;</p>
                     </content>
                  </point>
                  <point>
                     <num>(2)</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>the rows for the products for which the CN and TARIC codes are set out in Annex II to this Regulation are deleted;</p>
                     </content>
                  </point>
                  <point>
                     <num>(3)</num>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>endnote 1 is replaced by the following:</p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>
                              <mod>
                                 <quotedStructure startQuote="" endQuote="">
                                    <point>
                                       <num>&apos;(<sup>1</sup>)</num>
                                       <content>
                                          <p>Suspension of duties is subject to end-use customs supervision in accordance with Article 254 of Regulation (EU) No 952/2013 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 9 October 2013 laying down the Union Customs Code (OJ L 269, 10.10.2013, p. 1).&apos;;</p>
                                       </content>
                                    </point>
                                 </quotedStructure>
                              </mod>
                           </p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                  </point>
                  <point>
                     <num>(4)</num>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>endnote 4 is replaced by the following:</p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>
                              <mod>
                                 <quotedStructure startQuote="" endQuote="">
                                    <point>
                                       <num>&apos;(<sup>4</sup>)</num>
                                       <content>
                                          <p>A surveillance of imports of goods covered by this tariff suspension shall be established in accordance with the procedure laid down in Articles 55 and 56 of Commission Implementing Regulation (EU) 2015/2447 of 24 November 2015 laying down detailed rules for implementing certain provisions of Regulation (EU) No 952/2013 of the European Parliament and of the Council laying down the Union Customs Code (OJ L 343, 29.12.2015, p. 558).&apos;;</p>
                                       </content>
                                    </point>
                                 </quotedStructure>
                              </mod>
                           </p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                  </point>
                  <point>
                     <num>(5)</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>endnote 7 is deleted;</p>
                     </content>
                  </point>
                  <point>
                     <num>(6)</num>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>the following endnote marked with an asterisk is added:</p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>
                              <mod>
                                 <quotedStructure startQuote="" endQuote="">
                                    <point>
                                       <num>&apos;*</num>
                                       <content>
                                          <p>Suspension relating to a product in the Annex to Regulation (EU) No 1344/2011 for which the CN or TARIC code or the product description is modified by this Regulation.&apos;.</p>
                                       </content>
                                    </point>
                                 </quotedStructure>
                              </mod>
                           </p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                  </point>
               </list>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <article xml:id="art_d262e215">
            <num>Article 2</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>This Regulation shall enter into force on the date of its publication in the <i>Official Journal of the European Union</i>.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>It shall apply from 1 July 2016.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>However, TARIC code &apos;ex 8708999750&apos; shall apply from 1 January 2016.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <clause>
            <content>
               <p>This Regulation shall be binding in its entirety and directly applicable in all Member States.</p>
            </content>
         </clause>
      </body>
      <conclusions>
         <p>Done at Luxembourg, 24 June 2016.</p>
         <block name="signatory">
            <signature>
               <organization refersTo="">For the Council</organization>
               <role refersTo="">The President</role>
               <person refersTo="">A.G. KOENDERS</person>
            </signature>
         </block>
      </conclusions>
   </bill>
</akomaNtoso>
