<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0"
            xmlns:fmx="http://formex.publications.europa.eu/schema/formex-05.21-20110601.xd"
            xmlns:leos="urn:eu:europa:ec:leos"
            xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema">
   <bill name="">
      <meta xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions">
         <identification source="~COM">
            <FRBRWork>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRcountry value=""/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
         </identification>
      </meta>
      <preface>
         <longTitle>
            <p>
               <docStage/>
               <docType>COMMISSION REGULATION (EU) 2016/1004</docType>of 22 June 2016<docPurpose>amending Regulation (EC) No 661/2009 of the European Parliament and of the Council</docPurpose>
            </p>
         </longTitle>
         <container name="EEArelevance">
            <p>(Text with EEA relevance)</p>
         </container>
      </preface>
      <preamble>
         <formula name="actingEntity">
            <p>THE EUROPEAN COMMISSION,</p>
         </formula>
         <citations>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to Directive 2007/46/EC of the European Parliament and of the Council of 5 September 2007 establishing a framework for the approval of motor vehicles and their trailers, and of systems, components and separate technical units intended for such vehicles (Framework Directive)<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="1">
                     <p>OJ L 263, 9.10.2007, p. 1.</p>
                  </authorialNote>, and in particular Article 39(2) thereof,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to Regulation (EC) No 661/2009 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 13 July 2009 concerning type-approval requirements for the general safety of motor vehicles, their trailers and systems, components and separate technical units intended therefor<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="2">
                     <p>OJ L 200, 31.7.2009, p. 1.</p>
                  </authorialNote>, and in particular Article 14(1)(a) and (f) thereof,</p>
            </citation>
         </citations>
         <recitals xml:id="recs_d391e82">
            <intro>
               <p>Whereas:</p>
            </intro>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d391e85">
               <num>(1)</num>
               <p>Annex IV to Regulation (EC) No 661/2009 lists the UNECE regulations annexed to the &apos;Revised 1958 Agreement&apos;<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="3">
                     <p>Council Decision 97/836/EC of 27 November 1997 with a view to accession by the European Community to the Agreement of the United Nations Economic Commission for Europe concerning the adoption of uniform technical prescriptions for wheeled vehicles, equipment and parts which can be fitted to and/or be used on wheeled vehicles and the conditions for reciprocal recognition of approvals granted on the basis of these prescriptions (&apos;Revised 1958 Agreement&apos;) (OJ L 346, 17.12.1997, p. 78).</p>
                  </authorialNote> which apply on a compulsory basis. This list should be updated to reflect the application at EU level of new requirements in the respective UNECE regulations.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d391e108">
               <num>(2)</num>
               <p>In accordance with Article 13(14) of Regulation (EC) No 661/2009, the Appendix to its Annex IV lists the repealed Directives under which type-approvals granted before 1 November 2012 should continue to be valid unless new requirements become applicable. As new requirements become applicable at EU level with the update of Annex IV, it is also necessary to update the Appendix to Annex IV to the regulation.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d391e117">
               <num>(3)</num>
               <p>Since the new requirements of UNECE Regulations No 107 and 118 will require manufacturers to adapt their vehicles, sufficient time should be provided for the application of those requirements.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d391e123">
               <num>(4)</num>
               <p>The measures provided for in this Regulation are in accordance with the opinion of the Technical Committee &#45; Motor Vehicles,</p>
            </recital>
         </recitals>
         <formula name="enactingFormula">
            <p>HAS ADOPTED THIS REGULATION:</p>
         </formula>
      </preamble>
      <body>
         <article xml:id="art_d391e133">
            <num>Article 1</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>Annex IV to Regulation (EC) No 661/2009 is amended in accordance with the Annex to this Regulation.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <article xml:id="art_d391e138">
            <num>Article 2</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>With effect from 1 July 2016, national authorities shall, on grounds relating to indirect vision, consider the certificates of conformity of new vehicles of categories N<sub>2</sub> and N<sub>3</sub> approved to Directive 2003/97/EC of the European Parliament and of the Council<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="4">
                        <p>Directive 2003/97/EC of the European Parliament and of the Council of 10 November 2003 on the approximation of the laws of the Member States relating to the type-approval of devices for indirect vision and of vehicles equipped with these devices, amending Directive 70/156/EEC and repealing Directive 71/127/EEC (OJ L 25, 29.1.2004, p. 1).</p>
                     </authorialNote> to be no longer valid for the purposes of Article 26 of Directive 2007/46/EC, and shall prohibit the registration, sale and entry into service of such vehicles.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <article xml:id="art_d391e162">
            <num>Article 3</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>With effect from 1 July 2016, national authorities shall, on grounds relating to their general construction, consider the certificates of conformity of new vehicles of categories M<sub>2</sub> and M<sub>3</sub> to be no longer valid for the purposes of Article 26 of Directive 2007/46/EC, and shall prohibit the registration, sale and entry into service of such vehicles where they do not comply with the provisions of UNECE Regulation No 107 as amended by the 05 series of amendments.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <article xml:id="art_d391e176">
            <num>Article 4</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>With effect from 1 July 2016, national authorities shall, on grounds relating to the burning behaviour and/or the capability to repel fuel or lubricant of materials used in the construction, consider the certificates of conformity of new vehicles of category M<sub>3</sub> Classes II and III to be no longer valid for the purposes of Article 26 of Directive 2007/46/EC, and shall prohibit the registration, sale and entry into service of such vehicles where they do not comply with the provisions of UNECE Regulation No 118 as amended by the 01 series of amendments.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <article xml:id="art_d391e187">
            <num>Article 5</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>This Regulation shall enter into force on the twentieth day following that of its publication in the <i>Official Journal of the European Union</i>.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>It shall apply from 1 July 2016.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <clause>
            <content>
               <p>This Regulation shall be binding in its entirety and directly applicable in all Member States.</p>
            </content>
         </clause>
      </body>
      <conclusions>
         <p>Done at Brussels, 22 June 2016.</p>
         <block name="signatory">
            <signature>
               <organization refersTo="">For the Commission</organization>
               <role refersTo="">The President</role>
               <person refersTo="">Jean-Claude JUNCKER</person>
            </signature>
         </block>
      </conclusions>
   </bill>
</akomaNtoso>
