<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0"
            xmlns:fmx="http://formex.publications.europa.eu/schema/formex-05.21-20110601.xd"
            xmlns:leos="urn:eu:europa:ec:leos"
            xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema">
   <bill name="">
      <meta xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions">
         <identification source="~COM">
            <FRBRWork>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRcountry value=""/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
         </identification>
      </meta>
      <preface>
         <longTitle>
            <p>
               <docStage/>
               <docType>COMMISSION REGULATION (EU) 2017/1973</docType>of 30 October 2017<docPurpose>amending Regulation (EC) No 2074/2005 as regards official controls on fishery products caught by vessels flying the flag of a Member State and introduced into Union after being transferred in third countries and establishing a model health certificate for those products</docPurpose>
            </p>
         </longTitle>
         <container name="EEArelevance">
            <p>(Text with EEA relevance)</p>
         </container>
      </preface>
      <preamble>
         <formula name="actingEntity">
            <p>THE EUROPEAN COMMISSION,</p>
         </formula>
         <citations>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to Regulation (EC) No 853/2004 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 29 April 2004 laying down specific hygiene rules for food of animal origin<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="1">
                     <p>OJ L 139, 30.4.2004, p. 55.</p>
                  </authorialNote>, and in particular the second paragraph of Article 9 thereof,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to Regulation (EC) No 854/2004 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 29 April 2004 laying down specific rules for the organisation of official controls on products of animal origin intended for human consumption<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="2">
                     <p>OJ L 139, 30.4.2004, p. 206.</p>
                  </authorialNote>, and in particular the second paragraph of Article 16 thereof,</p>
            </citation>
         </citations>
         <recitals xml:id="recs_d520e82">
            <intro>
               <p>Whereas:</p>
            </intro>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d520e85">
               <num>(1)</num>
               <p>In order to safeguard public and animal health, products from the Union which are transferred, with or without storage, through third countries are regarded as no longer complying with the requirements for those products laid down in Union legislation. Consequently, Council Directive 97/78/EC<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="3">
                     <p>Council Directive 97/78/EC of 18 December 1997 laying down the principles governing the organisation of veterinary checks on products entering the Community from third countries (OJ L 24, 30.1.1998, p. 9).</p>
                  </authorialNote> provides that Member States are required to ensure that veterinary checks are carried out on consignments of these products introduced into the Union from third countries.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d520e101">
               <num>(2)</num>
               <p>Regulation (EC) No 853/2004 lays down specific rules on the hygiene of food of animal origin for food business operators, including rules for fishery products. In addition, Regulation (EC) No 854/2004 lays down rules for official controls to be carried out on products of animal origin intended for human consumption. Regulation (EC) No 854/2004 provides that a document meeting certain requirements is to accompany consignments of products of animal origin when they enter the Union and official controls of those products are to take place in accordance with that Regulation.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d520e107">
               <num>(3)</num>
               <p>Commission Regulation (EC) No 2074/2005<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="4">
                     <p>Commission Regulation (EC) No 2074/2005 of 5 December 2005 laying down implementing measures for certain products under Regulation (EC) No 853/2004 of the European Parliament and of the Council and for the organisation of official controls under Regulation (EC) No 854/2004 of the European Parliament and of the Council and Regulation (EC) No 882/2004 of the European Parliament and of the Council, derogating from Regulation (EC) No 852/2004 of the European Parliament and of the Council and amending Regulations (EC) No 853/2004 and (EC) No 854/2004 (OJ L 338, 22.12.2005, p. 27).</p>
                  </authorialNote> sets out model health certificates and documents for imports of certain products of animal origin for the purposes of Regulations (EC) Nos 853/2004 and 854/2004, including one for imports of fishery products in Annex VI thereto.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d520e123">
               <num>(4)</num>
               <p>Member States and stakeholder organisations have requested the Commission to establish a model health certificate for consignments of fishery products intended for human consumption caught by vessels flying the flag of a Member State and transferred in third countries, with or without storage, to be signed by the competent authority in the third country in order to harmonise the information to be provided when such consignments are entering the Union territory.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d520e129">
               <num>(5)</num>
               <p>The model of health certificate should specifically refer to the relevant provisions concerning the landing, unloading and storing of fishery products laid down in Chapters II and VII of Section VIII of Annex III to Regulation (EC) No 853/2004.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d520e136">
               <num>(6)</num>
               <p>The model of health certificate should also be compatible for use with the electronic trade control and expert system (TRACES)<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="5">
                     <p>Commission Decision 2004/292/EC (OJ L 94, 31.3.2004, p. 63).</p>
                  </authorialNote> used for the exchange of health certificates between the third countries and the Member States.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d520e149">
               <num>(7)</num>
               <p>It is therefore appropriate to establish a harmonised model of health certificate to be signed by the competent authority in the third country through which the fishery products are transferred, before they are dispatched to the Union.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d520e155">
               <num>(8)</num>
               <p>Regulation (EC) No 2074/2005 should be amended accordingly.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d520e161">
               <num>(9)</num>
               <p>The measures provided for in this Regulation are in accordance with the opinion of the Standing Committee on Plants, Animals, Food and Feed,</p>
            </recital>
         </recitals>
         <formula name="enactingFormula">
            <p>HAS ADOPTED THIS REGULATION:</p>
         </formula>
      </preamble>
      <body>
         <article xml:id="art_d520e170" leos:compliant="false">
            <num>Article 1</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <subparagraph>
                  <content>
                     <p>Regulation (EC) No 2074/2005 is amended as follows:</p>
                  </content>
               </subparagraph>
               <list>
                  <point>
                     <num>(a)</num>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>the following Article 6c is inserted:</p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>
                              <mod>
                                 <quotedStructure startQuote="" endQuote="">
                                    <article xml:id="art_d520e185">
                                       <num>&apos;Article 6c</num>
                                       <heading>Requirements concerning the official controls on fishery products caught by vessels flying the flag of Member States entering the Union after being transferred in third countries with or without storage</heading>
                                       <paragraph>
                                          <num>1.</num>
                                          <content>
                                             <p>Fishery products intended for human consumption caught by vessels flying the flag of a Member State, unloaded, with or without storage, in third countries before entering the Union by a different means of transportation, must be accompanied by a health certificate issued by the competent authority of that third country and completed in accordance with the model health certificate set out in Appendix VIII to Annex VI.</p>
                                          </content>
                                       </paragraph>
                                       <paragraph>
                                          <num>2.</num>
                                          <content>
                                             <p>The third country where the transfer takes place must be listed as provided for in Article 11(1) of Regulation (EC) No 854/2004.</p>
                                          </content>
                                       </paragraph>
                                       <paragraph>
                                          <num>3.</num>
                                          <content>
                                             <p>If the fishery products referred to in paragraph 1 are unloaded and transported to storage facility located in the third country referred to in that paragraph, that storage facility shall appear in a list as provided for in Article 12 of Regulation (EC) No 854/2004.</p>
                                          </content>
                                       </paragraph>
                                       <paragraph>
                                          <num>4.</num>
                                          <subparagraph>
                                             <content>
                                                <p>If the fishery products referred to in paragraph 1 are loaded in a vessel flying the flag of a third country, that third country must be listed as provided for in Article 11(1) of Regulation (EC) No 854/2004 and the vessel must appear in a list as provided for in Article 12 of Regulation (EC) No 854/2004.</p>
                                             </content>
                                          </subparagraph>
                                          <subparagraph>
                                             <content>
                                                <p>Container vessels used to transport containerised fishery products are excluded from this requirement&apos;;</p>
                                             </content>
                                          </subparagraph>
                                       </paragraph>
                                    </article>
                                 </quotedStructure>
                              </mod>
                           </p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                  </point>
                  <point>
                     <num>(b)</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>Annex VI is amended in accordance with the Annex to this Regulation.</p>
                     </content>
                  </point>
               </list>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <article xml:id="art_d520e221">
            <num>Article 2</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>This Regulation shall enter into force on the third day following that of its publication in the <i>Official Journal of the European Union</i>.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>It shall apply from 1 July 2018.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <clause>
            <content>
               <p>This Regulation shall be binding in its entirety and directly applicable in all Member States.</p>
            </content>
         </clause>
      </body>
      <conclusions>
         <p>Done at Brussels, 30 October 2017.</p>
         <block name="signatory">
            <signature>
               <organization refersTo="">For the Commission</organization>
               <role refersTo="">The President</role>
               <person refersTo="">Jean-Claude JUNCKER</person>
            </signature>
         </block>
      </conclusions>
   </bill>
</akomaNtoso>
