<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0"
            xmlns:fmx="http://formex.publications.europa.eu/schema/formex-05.21-20110601.xd"
            xmlns:leos="urn:eu:europa:ec:leos"
            xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema">
   <bill name="">
      <meta xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions">
         <identification source="~COM">
            <FRBRWork>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRcountry value=""/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
         </identification>
      </meta>
      <preface>
         <longTitle>
            <p>
               <docStage/>
               <docType>COUNCIL REGULATION (EU) 2019/2220</docType>of 19 December 2019<docPurpose>amending Regulation (EU) No 1388/2013 opening and providing for the management of autonomous tariff quotas of the Union for certain agricultural and industrial products</docPurpose>
            </p>
         </longTitle>
      </preface>
      <preamble>
         <formula name="actingEntity">
            <p>THE COUNCIL OF THE EUROPEAN UNION,</p>
         </formula>
         <citations>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union, and in particular Article 31 thereof,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the proposal from the European Commission,</p>
            </citation>
         </citations>
         <recitals xml:id="recs_d656e59">
            <intro>
               <p>Whereas:</p>
            </intro>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d656e62">
               <num>(1)</num>
               <p>In order to ensure a sufficient and uninterrupted supply of certain agricultural and industrial products which are produced in insufficient quantities in the Union and thereby avoid any disturbances on the market for those products, autonomous tariff quotas were opened by Council Regulation (EU) No 1388/2013<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="1">
                     <p>Council Regulation (EU) No 1388/2013 of 17 December 2013 opening and providing for the management of autonomous tariff quotas of the Union for certain agricultural and industrial products, and repealing Regulation (EU) No 7/2010 (OJ L 354, 28.12.2013, p. 319).</p>
                  </authorialNote>. Within those tariff quotas, products can be imported into the Union at reduced or zero duty rates.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d656e78">
               <num>(2)</num>
               <p>As it is in the Union&apos;s interest to ensure an adequate supply of certain industrial products and having regard to the fact that identical, equivalent or substitute products are not produced in sufficient quantities within the Union, it is necessary to open new tariff quotas with order numbers 09.2586 to 09.2593 inclusive at zero duty rates for appropriate quantities of those products.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d656e84">
               <num>(3)</num>
               <p>In the case of tariff quotas with order numbers 09.2594, 09.2595, 09.2596, 09.2597, 09.2598, 09.2599, 09.2738, 09.2742 and 09.2872, the quota volumes should be increased, as an increase is in the interest of the Union.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d656e90">
               <num>(4)</num>
               <p>For the tariff quota with order number 09.2738, the reference to &apos;tin&apos; in the product description should be replaced with &apos;zinc&apos;.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d656e104">
               <num>(5)</num>
               <p>For the tariff quotas with order numbers 09.2595, 09.2596, 09.2597, 09.2598 and 09.2599, the quota period should be prolonged from six months to one year.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d656e110">
               <num>(6)</num>
               <p>As the scope of the tariff quota with order number 09.2652 has become inadequate to fulfil the needs of the economic operators in the Union, the description of the product covered by this quota should be amended.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d656e116">
               <num>(7)</num>
               <p>The products covered by the tariff quota with order number 09.2740 are classifiable under TARIC code 2309903187 and not under TARIC code 2309909697. The indication of the applicable CN code and TARIC subheading for those products should therefore be amended.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d656e128">
               <num>(8)</num>
               <p>As it is no longer in the Union&apos;s interest to maintain the tariff quotas with order numbers 09.2690, 09.2850, 09.2878, 09.2906, 09.2909, 09.2929 and 09.2932, they should be closed with effect from 1 January 2020.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d656e137">
               <num>(9)</num>
               <p>For the tariff quota with order number 09.2828, it is in the interest of the Union to apply the quota only from 1 April to 31 October of each year, which are the months with the highest demand for the products concerned, and to reduce the volume by half.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d656e143">
               <num>(10)</num>
               <p>The tariff quota with order number 09.2722 has been applied simultaneously with a suspension of tariff duties in accordance with Council Regulation (EU) No 1387/2013<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="2">
                     <p>Council Regulation (EU) No 1387/2013 of 17 December 2013 suspending the autonomous Common Customs Tariff duties on certain agricultural and industrial products and repealing Regulation (EU) No 1344/2011 (OJ L 354, 28.12.2013, p. 201).</p>
                  </authorialNote> from 1 July 2019 to 31 December 2019. As that suspension should be closed with effect from 1 January 2020, it is in the interest of the Union to increase the quota volume.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d656e170">
               <num>(11)</num>
               <p>The substances Dimethyl Sulphate (CAS RN 77-78-1), 2‐Methylaniline (CAS RN 95‐53‐4) and 4,4&apos;-Methanediyldianiline (CAS RN 101-77-9) are included on the candidate list referred to in Article 59 of Regulation (EC) No 1907/2006 of the European Parliament and of the Council<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="3">
                     <p>Regulation (EC) No 1907/2006 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 18 December 2006 concerning the Registration, Evaluation, Authorisation and Restriction of Chemicals (REACH), establishing a European Chemicals Agency, amending Directive 1999/45/EC and repealing Council Regulation (EEC) No 793/93 and Commission Regulation (EC) No 1488/94 as well as Council Directive 76/769/EEC and Commission Directives 91/155/EEC, 93/67/EEC, 93/105/EC and 2000/21/EC (OJ L 396, 30.12.2006, p. 1).</p>
                  </authorialNote> and the substance with CAS RN 101-77-9 is included in Annex XIV to that Regulation. For that reason, existing tariff quotas for such products will be progressively closed and any newly opened tariff quotas will apply for a limited period. Therefore, the tariff quotas with order numbers 09.2648 and 09.2730 should apply only from 1 January 2020 to 30 June 2020 and the relevant quota volumes should be reduced in proportion. The tariff quota with order number 09.2590 should only be opened for the same period.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d656e192">
               <num>(12)</num>
               <p>The early exhaustion of the tariff quota with order number 09.2872 indicated that demand for the product covered by this tariff quota is high and that the production capacity in the Union is insufficient to cover that demand. To enhance the competitive capacity of Union enterprises, the quota volume should be increased with a retroactive effect to cover the period from 1 January 2019 to 31 December 2019.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d656e204">
               <num>(13)</num>
               <p>Taking into account the amendments to be made and for the sake of clarity, the Annex to Regulation (EU) No 1388/2013 should be replaced.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d656e210">
               <num>(14)</num>
               <p>In order to avoid any interruption of the application of the tariff quota scheme and to comply with the guidelines set out in the communication from the Commission of 13 December 2011 concerning autonomous tariff suspensions and quotas, the changes provided for in this Regulation regarding the tariff quotas for the products concerned should apply from 1 January 2020 and, for the tariff quota with order number 09.2872, from 1 January 2019. This Regulation should therefore enter into force as a matter of urgency,</p>
            </recital>
         </recitals>
         <formula name="enactingFormula">
            <p>HAS ADOPTED THIS REGULATION:</p>
         </formula>
      </preamble>
      <body>
         <article xml:id="art_d656e228" leos:compliant="false">
            <num>Article 1</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <subparagraph>
                  <content>
                     <p>The Annex to Regulation (EU) No 1388/2013 is amended as follows:</p>
                  </content>
               </subparagraph>
               <list>
                  <point>
                     <num>(1)</num>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>the row for the tariff quota with order number 09.2872 is replaced by the following:</p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>
                              <mod>
                                 <quotedStructure startQuote="" endQuote="">
                                    <alinea>
                                       <content>
                                          <table class="TBL">
                                             <tr>
                                                <td>
                                                   <p>&apos;09.2872</p>
                                                </td>
                                                <td>
                                                   <p>ex28332980</p>
                                                </td>
                                                <td>
                                                   <p>40</p>
                                                </td>
                                                <td>
                                                   <p>Caesium sulphate (CAS RN 10294-54-9) in solid form or as aqueous solution containing by weight 48 % or more but not more than 52 % of caesium sulphate</p>
                                                </td>
                                                <td>
                                                   <p>1.1.-31.12.</p>
                                                </td>
                                                <td>
                                                   <p>200 tonnes</p>
                                                </td>
                                                <td>
                                                   <p>0 %&apos;</p>
                                                </td>
                                             </tr>
                                          </table>
                                       </content>
                                    </alinea>
                                 </quotedStructure>
                              </mod>
                           </p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                  </point>
                  <point>
                     <num>(2)</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>it is replaced by the text set out in the Annex to this Regulation.</p>
                     </content>
                  </point>
               </list>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <article xml:id="art_d656e269">
            <num>Article 2</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>This Regulation shall enter into force on the day following that of its publication in the <i>Official Journal of the European Union</i>.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>It shall apply from 1 January 2020. However, point (1) of Article 1 shall apply from 1 January 2019 to 31 December 2019.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <clause>
            <content>
               <p>This Regulation shall be binding in its entirety and directly applicable in all Member States.</p>
            </content>
         </clause>
      </body>
      <conclusions>
         <p>Done at Brussels, 19 December 2019.</p>
         <block name="signatory">
            <signature>
               <organization refersTo="">For the Council</organization>
               <role refersTo="">The President</role>
               <person refersTo="">K. MIKKONEN</person>
            </signature>
         </block>
      </conclusions>
   </bill>
</akomaNtoso>
