<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0"
            xmlns:fmx="http://formex.publications.europa.eu/schema/formex-05.21-20110601.xd"
            xmlns:leos="urn:eu:europa:ec:leos"
            xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema">
   <bill name="">
      <meta xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions">
         <identification source="~COM">
            <FRBRWork>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRcountry value=""/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
         </identification>
      </meta>
      <preface>
         <longTitle>
            <p>
               <docStage/>
               <docType>REGULATION (EU) 2018/976 OF THE EUROPEAN PARLIAMENT AND OF THE COUNCIL</docType>of 4 July 2018<docPurpose>amending Regulation (EU) 2016/1139 as regards fishing mortality ranges and safeguard levels for certain herring stocks in the Baltic Sea</docPurpose>
            </p>
         </longTitle>
      </preface>
      <preamble>
         <formula name="actingEntity">
            <p>THE EUROPEAN PARLIAMENT AND THE COUNCIL OF THE EUROPEAN UNION,</p>
         </formula>
         <citations>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union, and in particular Article 43(2) thereof,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the proposal from the European Commission,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>After transmission of the draft legislative act to the national parliaments,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the opinion of the European Economic and Social Committee<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="1">
                     <p>Opinion of 14 February 2018 (not yet published in the Official Journal).</p>
                  </authorialNote>,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>Acting in accordance with the ordinary legislative procedure<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="2">
                     <p>Position of the European Parliament of 29 May 2018 (not yet published in the Official Journal) and decision of the Council of 18 June 2018.</p>
                  </authorialNote>,</p>
            </citation>
         </citations>
         <recitals xml:id="recs_d267e84">
            <intro>
               <p>Whereas:</p>
            </intro>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d267e87">
               <num>(1)</num>
               <p>Regulation (EU) 2016/1139 of the European Parliament and of the Council<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="3">
                     <p>Regulation (EU) 2016/1139 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 6 July 2016 establishing a multiannual plan for the stocks of cod, herring and sprat in the Baltic Sea and the fisheries exploiting those stocks, amending Council Regulation (EC) No 2187/2005 and repealing Council Regulation (EC) No 1098/2007 (OJ L 191, 15.7.2016, p. 1).</p>
                  </authorialNote> establishes a multiannual plan for the stocks of cod, herring and sprat in the Baltic Sea (&apos;the plan&apos;). The purpose of the plan is to contribute to the achievement of the objectives of the common fisheries policy and, in particular, to ensure that the exploitation of living marine biological resources restores and maintains populations of harvested species above levels which can produce maximum sustainable yield (MSY).</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d267e107">
               <num>(2)</num>
               <p>Article 1 of Regulation (EU) 2016/1139 sets out the Baltic fish stocks concerned, including the Bothnian Sea herring stock and the Bothnian Bay herring stock. In order to safeguard the full reproductive capacity of those stocks, Annexes I and II to that Regulation establish certain conservation reference points, including fishing mortality ranges and spawning stock biomass reference points.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d267e113">
               <num>(3)</num>
               <p>The scientific evaluation of the Bothnian Sea herring stock and the Bothnian Bay herring stock conducted in 2017 by the International Council for the Exploration of the Sea (ICES) showed that those two stocks are similar. As a consequence, ICES combined the two stocks into one, changed the boundaries of its geographic distribution area and re-estimated the MSY fishing mortality ranges, as well as the relevant conservation reference points. This led to different stock definition and numerical values than the ones established in Article 1 of, and Annexes I and II to, Regulation (EU) 2016/1139.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d267e119">
               <num>(4)</num>
               <p>Article 5(6) of Regulation (EU) 2016/1139 provides that where, on the basis of scientific advice, the Commission considers that the conservation reference points set out in Annex II to that Regulation no longer correctly express the objectives of the plan, those points may, as a matter of urgency, be submitted for revision to the European Parliament and to the Council.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d267e125">
               <num>(5)</num>
               <p>It is appropriate to amend urgently points (e) and (f) of Article 1(1) of, and Annexes I and II to, Regulation (EU) 2016/1139 in order to ensure that the fishing opportunities for the relevant stocks are fixed in accordance with updated conservation reference points.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d267e131">
               <num>(6)</num>
               <p>Regulation (EU) 2016/1139 should therefore be amended accordingly,</p>
            </recital>
         </recitals>
         <formula name="enactingFormula">
            <p>HAVE ADOPTED THIS REGULATION:</p>
         </formula>
      </preamble>
      <body>
         <article xml:id="art_d267e141" leos:compliant="false">
            <num>Article 1</num>
            <heading>Amendments to Regulation (EU) 2016/1139</heading>
            <paragraph>
               <subparagraph>
                  <content>
                     <p>Regulation (EU) 2016/1139 is amended as follows:</p>
                  </content>
               </subparagraph>
               <list>
                  <point>
                     <num>(1)</num>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>Article 1(1) is amended as follows:</p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                     <list>
                        <point>
                           <num>(a)</num>
                           <alinea>
                              <content>
                                 <p>point (e) is replaced by the following:</p>
                              </content>
                           </alinea>
                           <alinea>
                              <content>
                                 <p>
                                    <mod>
                                       <quotedStructure startQuote="" endQuote="">
                                          <point>
                                             <num>&apos;(e)</num>
                                             <content>
                                                <p>herring (<i>Clupea harengus</i>) in ICES subdivisions 30-31 (Gulf of Bothnia herring);&apos;;</p>
                                             </content>
                                          </point>
                                       </quotedStructure>
                                    </mod>
                                 </p>
                              </content>
                           </alinea>
                        </point>
                        <point>
                           <num>(b)</num>
                           <content>
                              <p>point (f) is deleted;</p>
                           </content>
                        </point>
                     </list>
                  </point>
                  <point>
                     <num>(2)</num>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>in Annex I, the entries concerning the Bothnian Sea herring stock and Bothnian Bay herring stock are replaced by the following entry:</p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <table class="TBL">
                              <tr>
                                 <td>
                                    <p>&apos;Gulf of Bothnia herring</p>
                                 </td>
                                 <td>
                                    <p>0,15-0,21</p>
                                 </td>
                                 <td>
                                    <p>0,21-0,21&apos;</p>
                                 </td>
                              </tr>
                           </table>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                  </point>
                  <point>
                     <num>(3)</num>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>in Annex II, the entries concerning the Bothnian Sea herring stock and the Bothnian Bay herring stock are replaced by the following entry:</p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <table class="TBL">
                              <tr>
                                 <td>
                                    <p>&apos;Gulf of Bothnia herring</p>
                                 </td>
                                 <td>
                                    <p>283180</p>
                                 </td>
                                 <td>
                                    <p>202272&apos;</p>
                                 </td>
                              </tr>
                           </table>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                  </point>
               </list>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <article xml:id="art_d267e221">
            <num>Article 2</num>
            <heading>Entry into force</heading>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>This Regulation shall enter into force on the day following that of its publication in the <i>Official Journal of the European Union</i>.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <clause>
            <content>
               <p>This Regulation shall be binding in its entirety and directly applicable in all Member States.</p>
            </content>
         </clause>
      </body>
      <conclusions>
         <p>Done at Strasbourg, 4 July 2018.</p>
         <block name="signatory">
            <signature>
               <organization refersTo="">For the European Parliament</organization>
               <role refersTo="">The President</role>
               <person refersTo="">A. TAJANI</person>
            </signature>
            <signature>
               <organization refersTo="">For the Council</organization>
               <role refersTo="">The President</role>
               <person refersTo="">K. EDTSTADLER</person>
            </signature>
         </block>
      </conclusions>
   </bill>
</akomaNtoso>
