<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0"
            xmlns:fmx="http://formex.publications.europa.eu/schema/formex-05.21-20110601.xd"
            xmlns:leos="urn:eu:europa:ec:leos"
            xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema">
   <bill name="">
      <meta xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions">
         <identification source="~COM">
            <FRBRWork>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRcountry value=""/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
         </identification>
      </meta>
      <preface>
         <longTitle>
            <p>
               <docStage/>
               <docType>COMMISSION REGULATION (EU) 2021/1917</docType>of 3 November 2021<docPurpose>amending Annex I to Regulation (EC) No 1334/2008 of the European Parliament and of the Council as regards the inclusion of 2-(4-methylphenoxy)-N-(1H-pyrazol-3-yl)-N-(thiophen-2-ylmethyl)acetamide in the Union list of flavourings</docPurpose>
            </p>
         </longTitle>
         <container name="EEArelevance">
            <p>(Text with EEA relevance)</p>
         </container>
      </preface>
      <preamble>
         <formula name="actingEntity">
            <p>THE EUROPEAN COMMISSION,</p>
         </formula>
         <citations>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to Regulation (EC) No 1334/2008 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 16 December 2008 on flavourings and certain food ingredients with flavouring properties for use in and on foods and amending Council Regulation (EEC) No 1601/91, Regulations (EC) No 2232/96 and (EC) No 110/2008 and Directive 2000/13/EC<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="1">
                     <p>OJ L 354, 31.12.2008, p. 34.</p>
                  </authorialNote>, and in particular Article 11(3) thereof,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to Regulation (EC) No 1331/2008 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 16 December 2008 establishing a common authorisation procedure for food additives, food enzymes and food flavourings<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="2">
                     <p>OJ L 354, 31.12.2008, p. 1.</p>
                  </authorialNote>, and in particular Article 7(5) thereof,</p>
            </citation>
         </citations>
         <recitals xml:id="recs_d621e91">
            <intro>
               <p>Whereas:</p>
            </intro>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d621e94">
               <num>(1)</num>
               <p>Annex I to Regulation (EC) No 1334/2008 lays down a Union list of flavourings and source materials approved for use in and on foods and their conditions of use.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d621e100">
               <num>(2)</num>
               <p>Commission Implementing Regulation (EU) No 872/2012<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="3">
                     <p>Commission Implementing Regulation (EU) No 872/2012 of 1 October 2012 adopting the list of flavouring substances provided for by Regulation (EC) No 2232/96 of the European Parliament and of the Council, introducing it in Annex I to Regulation (EC) No 1334/2008 of the European Parliament and of the Council and repealing Commission Regulation (EC) No 1565/2000 and Commission Decision 1999/217/EC (OJ L 267, 2.10.2012, p. 1).</p>
                  </authorialNote> adopted the list of flavouring substances and introduced that list in Part A of Annex I to Regulation (EC) No 1334/2008.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d621e116">
               <num>(3)</num>
               <p>That list may be updated in accordance with the common procedure referred to in Article 3(1) of Regulation (EC) No 1331/2008, either on the initiative of the Commission or following an application submitted by a Member State or by an interested party.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d621e122">
               <num>(4)</num>
               <p>On 7 December 2015, an application was submitted to the Commission for the authorisation of the use of 2-(4-methylphenoxy)-<i>N</i>-(1<i>H</i>-pyrazol-3-yl)-<i>N</i>-(thiophen-2-ylmethyl)acetamide (FL No 16.133), as a flavouring substance in various foods falling, in substance, under a number of food categories referred to in the Union list of flavourings and source materials. The application was notified to the European Food Safety Authority (&apos;the Authority&apos;) for its opinion. The Commission also made the application available to the Member States pursuant to Article 4 of Regulation (EC) No 1331/2008.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d621e145">
               <num>(5)</num>
               <p>The Authority in its opinion, adopted on 12 September 2018<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="4">
                     <p>
                        <i>EFSA Journal</i> 2018;16(10):5421.</p>
                  </authorialNote>, evaluated the safety of the substance FL No 16.133 when used as a flavouring substance and concluded that its use does not give rise to safety concerns when limited to levels up to those specified for various foods in different food categories. The Authority also indicated that its conclusion on the safety of the substance does not apply to the potential addition of the substance to non-opaque beverages where the substance can be subject to photo-transformation. This flavouring should only be added to opaque foods and packed in containers protected from light.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d621e160">
               <num>(6)</num>
               <p>In accordance with Article 15(1), point (c), of Regulation (EC) No 1334/2008, the information on the special conditions for storage and of use should be provided in the labelling to the customer of the flavouring substance and/or preparations to which that flavouring substance has been added. An indication on the containers such as &apos;keep away from light&apos; should be included in the labelling.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d621e170">
               <num>(7)</num>
               <p>The Authority also noted that substance FL No 16.133 is a substance with flavouring modifying properties.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d621e176">
               <num>(8)</num>
               <p>This flavouring substance is not intended for sale to the final consumer and therefore it should be placed on the market ensuring that this purpose is avoided.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d621e182">
               <num>(9)</num>
               <p>In light of the opinion of the Authority, since the use of the substance FL No 16.133 as a flavouring substance does not give rise to safety concerns with the specified conditions of use and it is not expected to mislead the consumer, it is appropriate to authorise such use.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d621e189">
               <num>(10)</num>
               <p>Part A of Annex I to Regulation (EC) No 1334/2008 should therefore be amended accordingly to include 2-(4-methylphenoxy)-<i>N</i>-(1<i>H</i>-pyrazol-3-yl)-<i>N</i>-(thiophen-2-ylmethyl)acetamide in the Union list of flavourings.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d621e204">
               <num>(11)</num>
               <p>The measures provided for in this Regulation are in accordance with the opinion of the Standing Committee on Plants, Animals, Food and Feed,</p>
            </recital>
         </recitals>
         <formula name="enactingFormula">
            <p>HAS ADOPTED THIS REGULATION:</p>
         </formula>
      </preamble>
      <body>
         <article xml:id="art_d621e213">
            <num>Article 1</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>Annex I, Part A to Regulation (EC) No 1334/2008 is amended in accordance with the Annex to this Regulation.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <article xml:id="art_d621e218">
            <num>Article 2</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>The flavouring substance 2-(4-methylphenoxy)-<i>N</i>-(1<i>H</i>-pyrazol-3-yl)-<i>N</i>-(thiophen-2-ylmethyl)acetamide is not authorised for sale to the final consumer.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <article xml:id="art_d621e232">
            <num>Article 3</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <subparagraph>
                  <content>
                     <p>In addition to the labelling requirements for flavourings not intended for sale to the final consumer in accordance with Article 15(1), point (c), of Regulation (EC) No 1334/2008, the following additional information shall be provided in the labelling of the packages or containers:</p>
                  </content>
               </subparagraph>
               <list>
                  <indent>
                     <num>-</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>&apos;Contains substance FL 16.133. Protect from light to avoid its photo-transformation.&apos;,</p>
                     </content>
                  </indent>
                  <indent>
                     <num>-</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>an indication such as &apos;keep away from light&apos;.</p>
                     </content>
                  </indent>
               </list>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <article xml:id="art_d621e252">
            <num>Article 4</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>This Regulation shall enter into force on the twentieth day following that of its publication in the <i>Official Journal of the European Union</i>.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <clause>
            <content>
               <p>This Regulation shall be binding in its entirety and directly applicable in all Member States.</p>
            </content>
         </clause>
      </body>
      <conclusions>
         <p>Done at Brussels, 3 November 2021.</p>
         <block name="signatory">
            <signature>
               <organization refersTo="">For the Commission</organization>
               <role refersTo="">The President</role>
               <person refersTo="">Ursula VON DER LEYEN</person>
            </signature>
         </block>
      </conclusions>
   </bill>
</akomaNtoso>
