<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0"
            xmlns:fmx="http://formex.publications.europa.eu/schema/formex-05.21-20110601.xd"
            xmlns:leos="urn:eu:europa:ec:leos"
            xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema">
   <bill name="">
      <meta xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions">
         <identification source="~COM">
            <FRBRWork>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRcountry value=""/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
         </identification>
      </meta>
      <preface>
         <longTitle>
            <p>
               <docStage/>
               <docType>REGULATION (EU) 2021/557 OF THE EUROPEAN PARLIAMENT AND OF THE COUNCIL</docType>of 31 March 2021<docPurpose>amending Regulation (EU) 2017/2402 laying down a general framework for securitisation and creating a specific framework for simple, transparent and standardised securitisation to help the recovery from the COVID-19 crisis</docPurpose>
               <p><!--default P | TXT -->(Text with EEA relevance)</p>
            </p>
         </longTitle>
      </preface>
      <preamble>
         <formula name="actingEntity">
            <p>THE EUROPEAN PARLIAMENT AND THE COUNCIL OF THE EUROPEAN UNION,</p>
         </formula>
         <citations>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union, and in particular Article 114 thereof,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the proposal from the European Commission,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>After transmission of the draft legislative act to the national parliaments,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the opinion of the European Central Bank<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="1">
                     <p>OJ C 377, 9.11.2020, p. 1.</p>
                  </authorialNote>,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the opinion of the European Economic and Social Committee<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="2">
                     <p>OJ C 10, 11.1.2021, p. 30.</p>
                  </authorialNote>,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>Acting in accordance with the ordinary legislative procedure<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="3">
                     <p>Position of the European Parliament of 25 March 2021 (not yet published in the Official Journal) and decision of the Council of 30 March 2021.</p>
                  </authorialNote>,</p>
            </citation>
         </citations>
         <recitals xml:id="recs_d106e94">
            <intro>
               <p>Whereas:</p>
            </intro>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d106e97">
               <num>(1)</num>
               <p>The COVID-19 crisis is severely affecting people, companies, health systems and the economies of Member States. In its Communication of 27 May 2020 entitled &apos;Europe&apos;s Moment: Repair and Prepare for the Next Generation&apos;, the Commission stressed that liquidity and access to finance will continue to be a challenge in the months to come. It is therefore crucial to support the recovery from the severe economic shock caused by the COVID-19 pandemic by introducing targeted amendments to existing pieces of financial legislation.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d106e110">
               <num>(2)</num>
               <p>The severe economic shock caused by the COVID-19 pandemic and the exceptional containment measures required are having a far-reaching impact on the economy. Businesses are facing disruption to supply chains, temporary closures and reduced demand, while households are confronted with unemployment and a fall in income. Public authorities at Union and Member State level have taken far-reaching action to support households and solvent undertakings in withstanding the severe but temporary slowdown in economic activity and the resulting liquidity shortages.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d106e117">
               <num>(3)</num>
               <p>It is important that credit institutions and investment firms (institutions) employ their capital where it is most needed and the Union regulatory framework facilitates their doing so while ensuring that institutions act prudently. In addition to the flexibility provided for by the existing rules, targeted changes to Regulation (EU) 2017/2402 of the European Parliament and of the Council<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="4">
                     <p>Regulation (EU) 2017/2402 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 12 December 2017 laying down a general framework for securitisation and creating a specific framework for simple, transparent and standardised securitisation, and amending Directives 2009/65/EC, 2009/138/EC and 2011/61/EU and Regulations (EC) No 1060/2009 and (EU) No 648/2012 (OJ L 347, 28.12.2017, p. 35).</p>
                  </authorialNote> would ensure that the Union securitisation framework provides for an additional tool to foster economic recovery in the aftermath of the COVID-19 crisis.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d106e133">
               <num>(4)</num>
               <p>The extraordinary circumstances of the COVID-19 crisis and the unprecedented magnitude of the attendant challenges triggered a call for immediate action to ensure that institutions have the ability to channel sufficient funds to businesses, so as to help them absorb the economic shock caused by the COVID-19 pandemic.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d106e139">
               <num>(5)</num>
               <p>The COVID-19 crisis risks increasing the number of non-performing exposures (NPEs), and increases the need for institutions to manage and deal with their NPEs. One way for institutions to do so is to trade their NPEs on the market through securitisation. Additionally, in the current context, it is vital that risks are moved away from the systemically important parts of the financial system and that lenders strengthen their capital positions. Synthetic securitisation is one way of achieving this, as well as, for example, raising new own funds.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d106e145">
               <num>(6)</num>
               <p>Securitisation special purpose entities (SSPEs) should only be established in third countries that are not listed by the Union<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="5">
                     <p>See in particular: Council Conclusions of 8 November 2016 on the criteria for and process leading to the establishment of the EU list of non-cooperative jurisdictions for tax purposes and the Annex thereto (OJ C 461, 10.12.2016, p. 2) and Council conclusions on the revised EU list of non-cooperative jurisdictions for tax purposes and the Annexes thereto (OJ C 66, 26.2.2021, p. 40).</p>
                  </authorialNote> on the EU list of non-cooperative jurisdictions for tax purposes, and updates thereto (Annex I), or in the list of high-risk third countries which have strategic deficiencies in their regimes on anti-money laundering and counter terrorist financing. Annex II on the State of play of the cooperation with the EU with respect to commitments taken by cooperative jurisdictions to implement tax good governance principles reports on the state of play of discussions with certain cooperating third countries, some of which currently maintain harmful tax practices. Such discussions should lead to a timely termination of such harmful tax practices to avoid future restrictions on the establishment of SSPEs.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d106e164">
               <num>(7)</num>
               <p>To reinforce the capability of national authorities in countering tax avoidance, an investor should notify the competent tax authorities of the Member State in which it is resident for tax purposes whenever it is due to invest in an SSPE established, after the date of application of this Regulation, in a jurisdiction mentioned in Annex II for the reason of operating a harmful tax regime. This information may be used to assess whether the investor derives a tax benefit.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d106e170">
               <num>(8)</num>
               <p>As pointed out by the European Supervisory Authority (European Banking Authority) (EBA), established by Regulation (EU) No 1093/2010 of the European Parliament and of the Council<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="6">
                     <p>Regulation (EU) No 1093/2010 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 24 November 2010 establishing a European Supervisory Authority (European Banking Authority), amending Decision No 716/2009/EC and repealing Commission Decision 2009/78/EC (OJ L 331, 15.12.2010, p. 12).</p>
                  </authorialNote>, in its Opinion on the Regulatory Treatment of Non-Performing Exposure Securitisation<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="7">
                     <p>Opinion of the European Banking Authority to the European Commission on the Regulatory Treatment of Non-Performing Exposure Securitisations, EBA-OP-2019-13, published on 23 October 2019.</p>
                  </authorialNote>, the risks associated with the assets backing NPE securitisations are economically distinct from those of securitisations of performing assets. NPEs are securitised at a discount on their nominal or outstanding value and reflect the market&apos;s assessment of, inter alia, the likelihood of the debt workout generating sufficient cash flow and asset recovery. The risk for investors is, therefore, that the debt workout for the assets does not generate sufficient cash flow and asset recovery to cover the net value at which the NPEs have been purchased. The actual risk of loss for investors does, therefore, not represent the nominal value of the portfolio, but the discounted value, namely, net of the price discount at which the underlying assets are transferred. It is therefore appropriate, in the case of NPE securitisations, to calculate the amount of the risk retention on the basis of that discounted value.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d106e195">
               <num>(9)</num>
               <p>The risk-retention requirement aligns the interests of originators, sponsors and original lenders that are involved in a securitisation with those of investors. Typically, in securitisations of performing assets, the prevalent interest on the sell-side is that of the originator, who is often also the original lender. In NPE securitisations, however, originators seek to offload the defaulted assets from their balance sheets, as they might no longer wish to be associated with them in any way. In such cases, the servicer of the assets has a greater interest in the debt workout for the assets and in value recovery.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d106e201">
               <num>(10)</num>
               <p>Before the 2008 financial crisis, some securitisation activities followed an &apos;originate to distribute&apos; model. In that model, assets of inferior quality were selected for securitisation to the detriment of investors, who ended up with more risk then they might have intended to undertake. The requirement to verify the credit granting standards used in the creation of securitised assets was introduced to prevent such practices in the future. For NPE securitisations, however, the credit granting standards applicable at the origination of the securitised assets are of minor importance due to the specific circumstances including the purchase of those non-performing assets and the type of securitisation. Instead, the application of sound standards in the selection and pricing of the exposures is a more important factor with respect to investments in NPE securitisations. It is therefore necessary to amend the verification of credit granting standards to enable the investor to carry out a due diligence on the quality and performance of the non-performing assets in order to make a sensible and well-informed investment decision, while ensuring that the derogation is not abused. Therefore, for NPE securitisation, the competent authorities should review the application of sound standards for selection and pricing of the exposures.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d106e211">
               <num>(11)</num>
               <p>Synthetic securitisations involve transferring the credit risk of a set of loans, typically large corporate loans or loans to small and medium-sized enterprises (SMEs), by means of a credit protection agreement where the originator buys credit protection from the investor. Such credit protection is achieved by the use of financial guarantees or credit derivatives while the ownership of the assets remains with the originator and is not transferred to a SSPE, as is the case in traditional securitisations. The originator, as protection buyer, commits to pay a credit protection premium, which generates the return for investors. In turn, the investor, as protection seller, commits to a specified credit protection payment when a pre-determined credit event occurs.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d106e217">
               <num>(12)</num>
               <p>The overall complexity of the securitisation structures and associated risks should be appropriately mitigated and no regulatory incentives should be provided to originators which would cause them to prefer synthetic securitisations over traditional securitisations. The requirements for simple, transparent and standardised (STS) on-balance-sheet securitisations should therefore be highly consistent with the STS criteria for traditional true sale securitisations.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d106e223">
               <num>(13)</num>
               <p>There are certain requirements for STS traditional securitisations that are not appropriate for STS on-balance-sheet securitisations due to inherent differences between both types of securitisation, in particular due to the fact that, in synthetic securitisations, the risk transfer is achieved via a credit protection agreement instead of a sale of the underlying assets. Therefore, the STS criteria should be adapted, where necessary, in order to take those differences into account. Furthermore, it is necessary to introduce a set of new requirements, specific to synthetic securitisations, to ensure that the STS framework targets only on-balance-sheet synthetic securitisations and that the credit protection agreement is structured to adequately protect the position of both the originator and the investor. That new set of requirements should seek to address counterparty credit risk for both the originator and the investor.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d106e229">
               <num>(14)</num>
               <p>The object of a credit risk transfer should be exposures originated or purchased by a Union regulated institution within its core lending business activity and held on its balance sheet or, in the case of a group structure, on its consolidated balance sheet at the closing date of the transaction. The requirement for an originator to hold the securitised exposures on the balance sheet should exclude arbitrage securitisations from the scope of the STS label.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d106e235">
               <num>(15)</num>
               <p>It is important that the interests of originators, sponsors, and original lenders that are involved in a securitisation are aligned. The risk-retention requirement set out in Regulation (EU) 2017/2402, which applies to all types of securitisations, works to align those interests. Such a requirement should also apply to STS on-balance-sheet securitisations. As a minimum, the originator, sponsor or original lender should retain, on an ongoing basis, a material net economic interest in the securitisation of not less than 5 %. Higher risk retention ratios might be justifiable and have already been observed in the market.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d106e243">
               <num>(16)</num>
               <p>The originator should make sure that it does not hedge the same credit risk more than once by obtaining credit protection in addition to the credit protection provided by the STS on-balance-sheet securitisation. In order to ensure the robustness of the credit protection agreement, it should meet the credit risk mitigation requirements laid down in Article 249 of Regulation (EU) No 575/2013 of the European Parliament and of the Council<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="8">
                     <p>Regulation (EU) No 575/2013 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 26 June 2013 on prudential requirements for credit institutions and investment firms and amending Regulation (EU) No 648/2012 (OJ L 176, 27.6.2013, p. 1).</p>
                  </authorialNote> that have to be met by institutions seeking significant risk transfer through a synthetic securitisation.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d106e259">
               <num>(17)</num>
               <p>STS on-balance-sheet securitisation might feature non-sequential amortisation in order to avoid disproportionate costs for protecting the underlying exposures and the evolution of the portfolio. Certain performance-related triggers should determine the application of sequential amortisation in order to ensure that tranches providing credit protection have not already been amortised when significant losses occur at the end of the transaction, thereby ensuring that significant risk transfer is not undermined.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d106e265">
               <num>(18)</num>
               <p>To avoid conflicts between the originator and the investor, and to ensure legal certainty in terms of the scope of the credit protection purchased for underlying exposures, such credit protection should reference clearly identified reference obligations, giving rise to the underlying exposures, of clearly identified entities or obligors. Therefore, the reference obligations on which protection is purchased should be clearly identified at all times, via a reference register, and kept up to date. That requirement should also be indirectly part of the criteria defining the STS on-balance-sheet securitisation and excluding arbitrage securitisation from the STS framework.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d106e271">
               <num>(19)</num>
               <p>Credit events that trigger payments under the credit protection agreement should include at least those referred to in Chapter 4 of Title II of Part Three of Regulation (EU) No 575/2013. Such events are well-known and recognisable from a market perspective and should serve to ensure consistency with the prudential framework. Forbearance measures, which consist of concessions towards a debtor that is experiencing or about to experience difficulties in meeting its financial commitments, should not preclude the triggering of the credit event.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d106e278">
               <num>(20)</num>
               <p>The right of the originator, as protection buyer, to receive timely payments on actual losses, should be adequately protected. Accordingly, the transaction documentation should provide for a sound and transparent settlement process for the determination of actual losses in the reference portfolio, to prevent the originator from being underpaid. As working out the losses might be a lengthy process and to ensure timely payments to the originator, interim payments should be made at the latest six months after a credit event has occurred. Furthermore, there should be a final adjustment mechanism to ensure that interim payments cover actual losses and to prevent those interim losses from overpaying, which would be to the detriment of investors. The loss settlement mechanism should also clearly specify the maximum extension period that should apply to the workout process for those exposures and such extension period should be no longer than two years. That loss settlement mechanism should ensure the effectiveness of the credit protection agreement from the originator&apos;s perspective, and give investors legal certainty on the termination date of their obligation to make payments, and therefore contribute to a well-functioning market.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d106e284">
               <num>(21)</num>
               <p>Having a third-party verification agent is a widespread market practice that enhances legal certainty for all parties involved in a transaction, thereby decreasing the likelihood of disputes and litigation that could arise as a result of the loss allocation process. To enhance the soundness of the transaction&apos;s loss settlement mechanism, a third-party verification agent should be appointed to carry out a review of the correctness and accuracy of certain aspects of the credit protection when a credit event has been triggered.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d106e291">
               <num>(22)</num>
               <p>Credit protection premiums should depend only on the outstanding size and credit risk of the protected tranche. Non-contingent premiums should not be permitted in STS on-balance-sheet securitisations as they could be used to undermine the effective risk transfer from the originator as protection buyer to the protection sellers. Other arrangements, such as upfront premium payments, rebate mechanisms or overly complex premium structures, should also be prohibited for STS on-balance-sheet securitisations.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d106e297">
               <num>(23)</num>
               <p>To ensure the stability and continuity of credit protection, the early termination of an STS on-balance-sheet securitisation by the originator should only be possible in certain limited, well-defined circumstances. Although the originator should be entitled to close out the credit protection early upon the occurrence of certain specified regulatory events, those events should involve actual changes in legislation or taxation that could not have been reasonably anticipated at the time of entering into the transaction and that have a material adverse effect on the originator&apos;s capital requirements or the economics of the transaction relative to the parties&apos; expectations at that time. STS on-balance-sheet securitisations should not feature complex call clauses for the originator, in particular very short-dated time calls with the aim of temporarily changing the representation of their capital position on a case-by-case basis.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d106e303">
               <num>(24)</num>
               <p>Synthetic excess spread is widely present in certain types of transactions and is a helpful mechanism for both investors and originators, in order to reduce the cost of the credit protection and the exposure at risk respectively. In that regard, synthetic excess spread is essential for some specific retail asset classes, such as SMEs and consumer lending, that show both higher yield and credit losses than other asset classes, and for which the securitised exposures generate excess spread to cover those losses. However, where the amount of synthetic excess spread subordinated to the investor position is too high, it is possible that there is no realistic scenario in which the investor in the securitisation positions will experience any losses, resulting in no effective risk transfer. To mitigate supervisory concerns and further standardise that structural feature, it is important to specify strict criteria for STS on-balance-sheet securitisations and to ensure full disclosure on the use of synthetic excess spread.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d106e309">
               <num>(25)</num>
               <p>Only high quality credit protection agreements should be eligible for STS on-balance-sheet securitisations. Unfunded credit protection should be ensured by restricting the scope of eligible protection providers to those entities that are eligible providers in accordance with Regulation (EU) No 575/2013 and are recognised as counterparties with a 0 % risk-weight in accordance with Chapter 2 of Title II of Part Three of that Regulation. In the case of funded credit protection, the originator as protection buyer and the investors as protection sellers should have recourse to high quality collateral, which should refer to collateral of any form which may be assigned a 0 % risk weight under that Chapter, subject to appropriate deposit or custody arrangements. When the collateral provided is in the form of cash, it should be held either with a third-party credit institution or on deposit with the protection buyer, subject in both cases to a minimum credit quality standing.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d106e315">
               <num>(26)</num>
               <p>Member States should designate the competent authorities responsible for supervising the requirements that the synthetic securitisation has to meet in order to qualify for the STS designation. The competent authority could be the same as the one designated to supervise the compliance of originators, sponsors and SSPEs with the requirements that traditional securitisations have to meet in order to acquire the STS designation. As in the case of traditional securitisations, such competent authority could be different from the competent authority responsible for supervising the compliance of originators, original lenders, SSPEs, sponsors and investors with the prudential obligations laid down in Articles 5 to 9 of Regulation (EU) 2017/2402, the compliance with which was specifically entrusted to the competent authorities in charge of the prudential supervision of the relevant financial institutions, due to the prudential dimension of those obligations.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d106e321">
               <num>(27)</num>
               <p>In order to avoid negative consequences for financial stability, the introduction of a specific framework for STS on-balance-sheet securitisations should be accompanied by an appropriate macroprudential oversight. In particular, the European Systemic Risk Board (ESRB), established by Regulation (EU) No 1092/2010 of the European Parliament and of the Council<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="9">
                     <p>Regulation (EU) No 1092/2010 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 24 November 2010 on European Union macro-prudential oversight of the financial system and establishing a European Systemic Risk Board (OJ L 331, 15.12.2010, p. 1).</p>
                  </authorialNote> should monitor macroprudential risks associated with synthetic securitisation and assess whether they are sufficiently removed from the systemic part of the financial system.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d106e338">
               <num>(28)</num>
               <p>For the purpose of integrating sustainability-related transparency requirements in Regulation (EU) 2017/2402, EBA, in close cooperation with the European Supervisory Authority (European Securities and Markets Authority) (ESMA), established by Regulation (EU) No 1095/2010 of the European Parliament and of the Council<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="10">
                     <p>Regulation (EU) No 1095/2010 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 24 November 2010 establishing a European Supervisory Authority (European Securities and Markets Authority), amending Decision No 716/2009/EC and repealing Commission Decision 2009/77/EC (OJ L 331, 15.12.2010, p. 84).</p>
                  </authorialNote>, and the European Supervisory Authority (European Insurance and Occupational Pensions Authority) (EIOPA), established by Regulation (EU) No 1094/2010 of the European Parliament and of the Council<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="11">
                     <p>Regulation (EU) No 1094/2010 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 24 November 2010 establishing a European Supervisory Authority (European Insurance and Occupational Pensions Authority), amending Decision No 716/2009/EC and repealing Commission Decision 2009/79/EC (OJ L 331, 15.12.2010, p. 48).</p>
                  </authorialNote>, should be mandated to publish a report on developing a specific sustainable securitisation framework. That report should duly assess, in particular, the introduction of sustainability factors, the implementation of proportionate disclosure and due diligence requirements, the content, methodologies and presentation of information in relation to environmental, social and governance-related adverse impacts, and any potential effects on financial stability and on the scaling up of the Union securitisation market and of bank lending capacity. Based on that report, the Commission should submit a report to the European Parliament and to the Council on the creation of a specific sustainable securitisation framework, together with a legislative proposal, if appropriate.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d106e365">
               <num>(29)</num>
               <p>Disclosures of the integration of sustainability risks and the consideration of adverse sustainability impacts on investment decision-making to investors are insufficiently developed because such disclosures are not yet subject to harmonised requirements. Pursuant to Regulation (EU) 2019/2088 of the European Parliament and of the Council<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="12">
                     <p>Regulation (EU) 2019/2088 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 27 November 2019 on sustainability-related disclosures in the financial services sector (OJ L 317, 9.12.2019, p. 1).</p>
                  </authorialNote>, manufacturers of financial products and financial advisers to end-investors are obliged to consider the principal adverse impacts of investment decisions on sustainability factors, and to disclose how their due diligence policies take those principal adverse impacts into account. The disclosures of adverse sustainability impacts are accompanied by regulatory technical standards, which are jointly developed by EBA, ESMA and EIOPA (collectively, the &apos;European Supervisory Authorities&apos;) on the content, methodologies and presentation of the relevant information to be disclosed under Regulation (EU) 2019/2088. Originators of STS securitisations should also have the option to disclose specific information regarding the consideration of adverse impacts on sustainability factors, giving particular attention to climate and other environmental, social and governance-related impacts. To harmonise information disclosure and to ensure consistency between Regulation (EU) 2019/2088 and Regulation (EU) 2017/2402, the Joint Committee of the European Supervisory Authorities should develop regulatory technical standards, building as much as possible on their work in the context of Regulation (EU) 2019/2088 and adapting it, where necessary and relevant, to the specificities of securitisations.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d106e385">
               <num>(30)</num>
               <p>Since the objectives of this Regulation, namely to extend the STS securitisation framework to synthetic securitisation and to remove regulatory obstacles to securitisation of NPEs to further increase lending capacities without lowering the prudential standards for bank lending, cannot be sufficiently achieved by the Member States but can rather, by reason of their scale and effects, be better achieved at Union level, the Union may adopt measures, in accordance with the principle of subsidiarity set out in Article 5 of the Treaty on European Union. In accordance with the principle of proportionality as set out in that Article, this Regulation does not go beyond what is necessary in order to achieve those objectives.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d106e391">
               <num>(31)</num>
               <p>Regulation (EU) 2017/2402 should therefore be amended accordingly.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d106e397">
               <num>(32)</num>
               <p>In view of the need to introduce targeted measures to support economic recovery from the COVID-19 crisis as quickly as possible, this Regulation should enter into force as a matter of urgency on the third day following that of its publication in the <i>Official Journal of the European Union</i>,</p>
            </recital>
         </recitals>
         <formula name="enactingFormula">
            <p>HAVE ADOPTED THIS REGULATION:</p>
         </formula>
      </preamble>
      <body>
         <article xml:id="art_d106e410" leos:compliant="false">
            <num>Article 1</num>
            <heading>Amendments to Regulation (EU) 2017/2402</heading>
            <paragraph>
               <subparagraph>
                  <content>
                     <p>Regulation (EU) 2017/2402 is amended as follows:</p>
                  </content>
               </subparagraph>
               <list>
                  <point>
                     <num>(1)</num>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>in Article 2, the following points are added:</p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>
                              <mod>
                                 <quotedStructure startQuote="" endQuote="">
                                    <list>
                                       <point>
                                          <num>&apos;(24)</num>
                                          <content>
                                             <p>&quot;non-performing exposure&quot; or &quot;NPE&quot; means an exposure that meets any of the conditions set out in Article 47a(3) of Regulation (EU) No 575/2013;</p>
                                          </content>
                                       </point>
                                       <point>
                                          <num>(25)</num>
                                          <content>
                                             <p>&quot;NPE securitisation&quot; means a securitisation backed by a pool of non-performing exposures the nominal value of which makes up not less than 90 % of the entire pool&apos;s nominal value at the time of origination and at any later time where assets are added to or removed from the underlying pool due to replenishment, restructuring or any other relevant reason;</p>
                                          </content>
                                       </point>
                                       <point>
                                          <num>(26)</num>
                                          <content>
                                             <p>&quot;credit protection agreement&quot; means an agreement concluded between the originator and the investor to transfer the credit risk of securitised exposures from the originator to the investor by means of credit derivatives or guarantees, whereby the originator commits to pay an amount, known as a credit protection premium, to the investor and the investor commits to pay an amount, known as a credit protection payment, to the originator in the event that one of the contractually defined credit events occurs;</p>
                                          </content>
                                       </point>
                                       <point>
                                          <num>(27)</num>
                                          <content>
                                             <p>&quot;credit protection premium&quot; means the amount the originator has committed to pay to the investor under the credit protection agreement for the credit protection promised by the investor;</p>
                                          </content>
                                       </point>
                                       <point>
                                          <num>(28)</num>
                                          <content>
                                             <p>&quot;credit protection payment&quot; means the amount the investor has committed to pay to the originator under the credit protection agreement in the event that a credit event defined in the credit protection agreement occurs;</p>
                                          </content>
                                       </point>
                                       <point>
                                          <num>(29)</num>
                                          <content>
                                             <p>&quot;synthetic excess spread&quot; means the amount that, according to the documentation of a synthetic securitisation, is contractually designated by the originator to absorb losses of the securitised exposures that might occur before the maturity date of the transaction;</p>
                                          </content>
                                       </point>
                                       <point>
                                          <num>(30)</num>
                                          <content>
                                             <p>&quot;sustainability factors&quot; mean sustainability factors as defined in point (24) of Article 2 of Regulation (EU) 2019/2088 of the European Parliament and of the Council<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="13">
                                                   <p>Regulation (EU) 2019/2088 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 27 November 2019 on sustainability-related disclosures in the financial services sector (OJ L 317, 9.12.2019, p. 1).&apos;;</p>
                                                </authorialNote>;</p>
                                          </content>
                                       </point>
                                       <point>
                                          <num>(31)</num>
                                          <content>
                                             <p>&quot;non-refundable purchase price discount&quot; means the difference between the outstanding balance of the exposures in the underlying pool and the price at which those exposures are sold by the originator to the SSPE, where neither the originator nor the original lender are reimbursed for that difference.</p>
                                          </content>
                                       </point>
                                    </list>
                                 </quotedStructure>
                              </mod>
                           </p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                  </point>
                  <point>
                     <num>(2)</num>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>Article 4 is amended as follows:</p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                     <list>
                        <point>
                           <num>(a)</num>
                           <alinea>
                              <content>
                                 <p>point (a) is replaced by the following:</p>
                              </content>
                           </alinea>
                           <alinea>
                              <content>
                                 <p>
                                    <mod>
                                       <quotedStructure startQuote="" endQuote="">
                                          <list>
                                             <point>
                                                <num>&apos;(a)</num>
                                                <content>
                                                   <p>the third country is listed as a high-risk third country that has strategic deficiencies in its regime on anti-money laundering and counter terrorist financing, in accordance with Article 9 of Directive (EU) 2015/849 of the European Parliament and of the Council<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="14">
                                                         <p>Directive (EU) 2015/849 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 20 May 2015 on the prevention of the use of the financial system for the purposes of money laundering or terrorist financing, amending Regulation (EU) No 648/2012 of the European Parliament and of the Council, and repealing Directive 2005/60/EC of the European Parliament and of the Council and Commission Directive 2006/70/EC (OJ L 141, 5.6.2015, p. 73).&apos;;</p>
                                                      </authorialNote>;</p>
                                                </content>
                                             </point>
                                          </list>
                                       </quotedStructure>
                                    </mod>
                                 </p>
                              </content>
                           </alinea>
                        </point>
                        <point>
                           <num>(b)</num>
                           <alinea>
                              <content>
                                 <p>the following point is inserted:</p>
                              </content>
                           </alinea>
                           <alinea>
                              <content>
                                 <p>
                                    <mod>
                                       <quotedStructure startQuote="" endQuote="">
                                          <list>
                                             <point>
                                                <num>&apos;(aa)</num>
                                                <content>
                                                   <p>the third country is listed in Annex I of the EU list of non-cooperative jurisdictions for tax purposes;&apos;;</p>
                                                </content>
                                             </point>
                                          </list>
                                       </quotedStructure>
                                    </mod>
                                 </p>
                              </content>
                           </alinea>
                        </point>
                        <point>
                           <num>(c)</num>
                           <alinea>
                              <content>
                                 <p>the following paragraph is added:</p>
                              </content>
                           </alinea>
                           <alinea>
                              <content>
                                 <p>&apos;For an SSPE established, after 9 April 2021, in a jurisdiction mentioned in Annex II for the reason of operating a harmful tax regime, the investor shall notify the investment in securities issued by that SSPE to the competent tax authorities of the Member State in which the investor is resident for tax purposes.&apos;;</p>
                              </content>
                           </alinea>
                        </point>
                     </list>
                  </point>
                  <point>
                     <num>(3)</num>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>in Article 5(1), the following point is added:</p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>
                              <mod>
                                 <quotedStructure startQuote="" endQuote="">
                                    <list>
                                       <point>
                                          <num>&apos;(f)</num>
                                          <content>
                                             <p>in the case of non-performing exposures, sound standards are applied in the selection and pricing of the exposures.&apos;;</p>
                                          </content>
                                       </point>
                                    </list>
                                 </quotedStructure>
                              </mod>
                           </p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                  </point>
                  <point>
                     <num>(4)</num>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>Article 6 is amended as follows:</p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                     <list>
                        <point>
                           <num>(a)</num>
                           <alinea>
                              <content>
                                 <p>in paragraph 1, the following subparagraphs are added:</p>
                              </content>
                           </alinea>
                           <alinea>
                              <content>
                                 <p>
                                    <mod>
                                       <quotedStructure startQuote="" endQuote="">
                                          <alinea>
                                             <content>
                                                <p>&apos;When measuring the material net economic interest, the retainer shall take into account any fees that may in practice be used to reduce the effective material net economic interest.</p>
                                             </content>
                                          </alinea>
                                          <alinea>
                                             <content>
                                                <p>In the case of traditional NPE securitisations, the requirement of this paragraph may also be fulfilled by the servicer provided that the servicer can demonstrate that it has expertise in servicing exposures of a similar nature to those securitised and that it has well-documented and adequate policies, procedures and risk-management controls in place relating to the servicing of exposures.&apos;;</p>
                                             </content>
                                          </alinea>
                                       </quotedStructure>
                                    </mod>
                                 </p>
                              </content>
                           </alinea>
                        </point>
                        <point>
                           <num>(b)</num>
                           <alinea>
                              <content>
                                 <p>the following paragraph is inserted:</p>
                              </content>
                           </alinea>
                           <alinea>
                              <content>
                                 <p>
                                    <mod>
                                       <quotedStructure startQuote="" endQuote="">
                                          <paragraph>
                                             <num>&apos;3a.</num>
                                             <subparagraph>
                                                <content>
                                                   <p>By way of derogation from paragraph 3, in the case of NPE securitisations, where a non-refundable purchase price discount has been agreed, the retention of a material net economic interest for the purposes of that paragraph shall not be less than 5 % of the sum of the net value of the securitised exposures that qualify as non-performing exposures and, if applicable, the nominal value of any performing securitised exposures.</p>
                                                </content>
                                             </subparagraph>
                                             <subparagraph>
                                                <content>
                                                   <p>The net value of a non-performing exposure shall be calculated by deducting the non-refundable purchase price discount agreed at the level of the individual securitised exposure at the time of origination or, where applicable, a corresponding share of the non-refundable purchase price discount agreed at the level of the pool of underlying exposures at the time of origination from the exposure&apos;s nominal value or, where applicable, its outstanding value at the time of origination. In addition, for the purpose of determining the net value of the securitised non-performing exposures, the non-refundable purchase price discount may include the difference between the nominal amount of the tranches of the NPE securitisation underwritten by the originator for subsequent sale and the price at which these tranches are first sold to unrelated third parties.&apos;;</p>
                                                </content>
                                             </subparagraph>
                                          </paragraph>
                                       </quotedStructure>
                                    </mod>
                                 </p>
                              </content>
                           </alinea>
                        </point>
                        <point>
                           <num>(c)</num>
                           <alinea>
                              <content>
                                 <p>paragraph 7 is amended as follows:</p>
                              </content>
                           </alinea>
                           <list>
                              <point>
                                 <num>(i)</num>
                                 <alinea>
                                    <content>
                                       <p>in the first subparagraph, the following points are added:</p>
                                    </content>
                                 </alinea>
                                 <alinea>
                                    <content>
                                       <p>
                                          <mod>
                                             <quotedStructure startQuote="" endQuote="">
                                                <list>
                                                   <point>
                                                      <num>&apos;(f)</num>
                                                      <content>
                                                         <p>the modalities of retaining risk pursuant to paragraphs 3 and 3a in the case of NPE securitisations;</p>
                                                      </content>
                                                   </point>
                                                   <point>
                                                      <num>(g)</num>
                                                      <content>
                                                         <p>the impact of fees paid to the retainer on the effective material net economic interest within the meaning of paragraph 1.&apos;;</p>
                                                      </content>
                                                   </point>
                                                </list>
                                             </quotedStructure>
                                          </mod>
                                       </p>
                                    </content>
                                 </alinea>
                              </point>
                              <point>
                                 <num>(ii)</num>
                                 <alinea>
                                    <content>
                                       <p>the second subparagraph is replaced by the following:</p>
                                    </content>
                                 </alinea>
                                 <alinea>
                                    <content>
                                       <p>&apos;EBA shall submit those draft regulatory technical standards to the Commission by 10 October 2021.&apos;;</p>
                                    </content>
                                 </alinea>
                              </point>
                           </list>
                        </point>
                     </list>
                  </point>
                  <point>
                     <num>(5)</num>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>in Article 9(1), the following subparagraph is added:</p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>
                              <mod>
                                 <quotedStructure startQuote="" endQuote="">
                                    <alinea>
                                       <content>
                                          <p>&apos;By way of derogation from the first subparagraph, with regard to underlying exposures that were non-performing exposures at the time the originator purchased them from the relevant third party, sound standards shall apply in the selection and pricing of the exposures.&apos;;</p>
                                       </content>
                                    </alinea>
                                 </quotedStructure>
                              </mod>
                           </p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                  </point>
                  <point>
                     <num>(6)</num>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>in Article 18, point (a) is replaced by the following:</p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>
                              <mod>
                                 <quotedStructure startQuote="" endQuote="">
                                    <list>
                                       <point>
                                          <num>&apos;(a)</num>
                                          <content>
                                             <p>the securitisation meets all the requirements set out in Section 1, 2 or 2a of this Chapter, and ESMA has been notified pursuant to Article 27(1); and&apos;;</p>
                                          </content>
                                       </point>
                                    </list>
                                 </quotedStructure>
                              </mod>
                           </p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                  </point>
                  <point>
                     <num>(7)</num>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>the title of Section 1 of Chapter 4 is replaced by the following:</p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>
                              <mod>
                                 <quotedStructure startQuote="" endQuote="">
                                    <alinea>
                                       <content>
                                          <p>&apos;Requirements for simple, transparent and standardised non-ABCP traditional securitisation&apos;</p>
                                       </content>
                                    </alinea>
                                 </quotedStructure>
                              </mod>
                           </p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                  </point>
                  <point>
                     <num>(8)</num>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>Article 19 is amended as follows:</p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                     <list>
                        <point>
                           <num>(a)</num>
                           <alinea>
                              <content>
                                 <p>the title of the Article is replaced by the following:</p>
                              </content>
                           </alinea>
                           <alinea>
                              <content>
                                 <p>
                                    <mod>
                                       <quotedStructure startQuote="" endQuote="">
                                          <alinea>
                                             <content>
                                                <p>&apos;Simple, transparent and standardised non-ABCP traditional securitisation&apos;;</p>
                                             </content>
                                          </alinea>
                                       </quotedStructure>
                                    </mod>
                                 </p>
                              </content>
                           </alinea>
                        </point>
                        <point>
                           <num>(b)</num>
                           <alinea>
                              <content>
                                 <p>paragraph 1 is replaced by the following:</p>
                              </content>
                           </alinea>
                           <alinea>
                              <content>
                                 <p>
                                    <mod>
                                       <quotedStructure startQuote="" endQuote="">
                                          <paragraph>
                                             <num>&apos;1.</num>
                                             <content>
                                                <p>Traditional securitisations, except for ABCP programmes and ABCP transactions, that meet the requirements set out in Articles 20, 21 and 22, shall be considered to be STS.&apos;;</p>
                                             </content>
                                          </paragraph>
                                       </quotedStructure>
                                    </mod>
                                 </p>
                              </content>
                           </alinea>
                        </point>
                     </list>
                  </point>
                  <point>
                     <num>(9)</num>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>Article 22 is amended as follows:</p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                     <list>
                        <point>
                           <num>(a)</num>
                           <alinea>
                              <content>
                                 <p>in paragraph 4, the following subparagraph is added:</p>
                              </content>
                           </alinea>
                           <alinea>
                              <content>
                                 <p>
                                    <mod>
                                       <quotedStructure startQuote="" endQuote="">
                                          <alinea>
                                             <content>
                                                <p>&apos;By way of derogation from the first subparagraph, originators may, from 1 June 2021, decide to publish the available information related to the principal adverse impacts of the assets financed by underlying exposures on sustainability factors.&apos;;</p>
                                             </content>
                                          </alinea>
                                       </quotedStructure>
                                    </mod>
                                 </p>
                              </content>
                           </alinea>
                        </point>
                        <point>
                           <num>(b)</num>
                           <alinea>
                              <content>
                                 <p>the following paragraph is added:</p>
                              </content>
                           </alinea>
                           <alinea>
                              <content>
                                 <p>
                                    <mod>
                                       <quotedStructure startQuote="" endQuote="">
                                          <paragraph>
                                             <num>&apos;6.</num>
                                             <subparagraph>
                                                <content>
                                                   <p>By 10 July 2021, the ESAs shall develop, through the Joint Committee of the European Supervisory Authorities, draft regulatory technical standards in accordance with Articles 10 to 14 of Regulations (EU) No 1093/2010, (EU) No 1094/2010 and (EU) No 1095/2010 on the content, methodologies and presentation of information referred to in the second subparagraph of paragraph 4 of this Article, in respect of the sustainability indicators in relation to adverse impacts on the climate and other environmental, social and governance-related adverse impacts.</p>
                                                </content>
                                             </subparagraph>
                                             <subparagraph>
                                                <content>
                                                   <p>Where relevant, the draft regulatory technical standards referred to in the first subparagraph shall mirror or draw upon the regulatory technical standards developed pursuant to the mandate given to the ESAs in Regulation (EU) 2019/2088, in particular in Article 2a and Article 4(6) and (7) thereof.</p>
                                                </content>
                                             </subparagraph>
                                             <subparagraph>
                                                <content>
                                                   <p>The Commission is empowered to supplement this Regulation by adopting the regulatory technical standards referred to in the first subparagraph in accordance with Articles 10 to 14 of Regulations (EU) No 1093/2010, (EU) No 1094/2010 and (EU) No 1095/2010.&apos;;</p>
                                                </content>
                                             </subparagraph>
                                          </paragraph>
                                       </quotedStructure>
                                    </mod>
                                 </p>
                              </content>
                           </alinea>
                        </point>
                     </list>
                  </point>
                  <point>
                     <num>(10)</num>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>the following Section is inserted:</p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>
                              <mod>
                                 <quotedStructure startQuote="" endQuote=""><!--GR.SEQ is a special position => not treated --></quotedStructure>
                              </mod>
                           </p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                  </point>
                  <point>
                     <num>(11)</num>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>Article 27 is amended as follows:</p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                     <list>
                        <point>
                           <num>(a)</num>
                           <alinea>
                              <content>
                                 <p>in paragraph 1, the first and second subparagraphs are replaced by the following:</p>
                              </content>
                           </alinea>
                           <alinea>
                              <content>
                                 <p>
                                    <mod>
                                       <quotedStructure startQuote="" endQuote="">
                                          <alinea>
                                             <content>
                                                <p>&apos;Originators and sponsors shall jointly notify ESMA by means of the template referred to in paragraph 7 of this Article where a securitisation meets the requirements set out in Articles 19 to 22, Articles 23 to 26 or Articles 26a to 26e (&quot;STS notification&quot;). In the case of an ABCP programme, only the sponsor shall be responsible for the notification of that programme and, within that programme, of the ABCP transactions complying with Article 24. In the case of synthetic securitisation, only the originator shall be responsible for the notification.</p>
                                             </content>
                                          </alinea>
                                          <alinea>
                                             <content>
                                                <p>The STS notification shall include an explanation by the originator and sponsor of how the STS criteria set out in Articles 20 to 22, Articles 24 to 26 or Articles 26b to 26e have been complied with.&apos;;</p>
                                             </content>
                                          </alinea>
                                       </quotedStructure>
                                    </mod>
                                 </p>
                              </content>
                           </alinea>
                        </point>
                        <point>
                           <num>(b)</num>
                           <alinea>
                              <content>
                                 <p>paragraph 2 is amended as follows:</p>
                              </content>
                           </alinea>
                           <list>
                              <point>
                                 <num>(i)</num>
                                 <alinea>
                                    <content>
                                       <p>in the first subparagraph, the first sentence is replaced by the following:</p>
                                    </content>
                                 </alinea>
                                 <alinea>
                                    <content>
                                       <p>
                                          <mod>
                                             <quotedStructure startQuote="" endQuote="">
                                                <alinea>
                                                   <content>
                                                      <p>&apos;The originator, sponsor or SSPE may use the service of a third party authorised under Article 28 to assess whether a securitisation complies with Articles 19 to 22, Articles 23 to 26 or Articles 26a to 26e.&apos;;</p>
                                                   </content>
                                                </alinea>
                                             </quotedStructure>
                                          </mod>
                                       </p>
                                    </content>
                                 </alinea>
                              </point>
                              <point>
                                 <num>(ii)</num>
                                 <alinea>
                                    <content>
                                       <p>in the second subparagraph, the first sentence is replaced by the following:</p>
                                    </content>
                                 </alinea>
                                 <alinea>
                                    <content>
                                       <p>
                                          <mod>
                                             <quotedStructure startQuote="" endQuote="">
                                                <alinea>
                                                   <content>
                                                      <p>&apos;Where the originator, sponsor or SSPE uses the service of a third party authorised pursuant to Article 28 to assess whether a securitisation complies with Articles 19 to 22, Articles 23 to 26 or Articles 26a to 26e, the STS notification shall include a statement that compliance with the STS criteria was confirmed by that authorised third party.&apos;;</p>
                                                   </content>
                                                </alinea>
                                             </quotedStructure>
                                          </mod>
                                       </p>
                                    </content>
                                 </alinea>
                              </point>
                           </list>
                        </point>
                        <point>
                           <num>(c)</num>
                           <alinea>
                              <content>
                                 <p>paragraph 4 is replaced by the following:</p>
                              </content>
                           </alinea>
                           <alinea>
                              <content>
                                 <p>
                                    <mod>
                                       <quotedStructure startQuote="" endQuote="">
                                          <paragraph>
                                             <num>&apos;4.</num>
                                             <content>
                                                <p>The originator and, where applicable, sponsor, shall immediately notify ESMA and inform their competent authority when a securitisation no longer meets the requirements set out in Articles 19 to 22, Articles 23 to 26, or Articles 26a to 26e.&apos;;</p>
                                             </content>
                                          </paragraph>
                                       </quotedStructure>
                                    </mod>
                                 </p>
                              </content>
                           </alinea>
                        </point>
                        <point>
                           <num>(d)</num>
                           <alinea>
                              <content>
                                 <p>in paragraph 5, the first sentence is replaced by the following:</p>
                              </content>
                           </alinea>
                           <alinea>
                              <content>
                                 <p>
                                    <mod>
                                       <quotedStructure startQuote="" endQuote="">
                                          <alinea>
                                             <content>
                                                <p>&apos;ESMA shall maintain, on its official website, a list of all securitisations which the originators and sponsors have notified it of meeting the requirements set out in Articles 19 to 22, Articles 23 to 26, or Articles 26a to 26e.&apos;;</p>
                                             </content>
                                          </alinea>
                                       </quotedStructure>
                                    </mod>
                                 </p>
                              </content>
                           </alinea>
                        </point>
                        <point>
                           <num>(e)</num>
                           <alinea>
                              <content>
                                 <p>in paragraph 6, the second subparagraph is replaced by the following:</p>
                              </content>
                           </alinea>
                           <alinea>
                              <content>
                                 <p>
                                    <mod>
                                       <quotedStructure startQuote="" endQuote="">
                                          <alinea>
                                             <content>
                                                <p>&apos;ESMA shall submit those draft regulatory technical standards to the Commission by 10 October 2021.&apos;;</p>
                                             </content>
                                          </alinea>
                                       </quotedStructure>
                                    </mod>
                                 </p>
                              </content>
                           </alinea>
                        </point>
                        <point>
                           <num>(f)</num>
                           <alinea>
                              <content>
                                 <p>in paragraph 7, the second subparagraph is replaced by the following:</p>
                              </content>
                           </alinea>
                           <alinea>
                              <content>
                                 <p>
                                    <mod>
                                       <quotedStructure startQuote="" endQuote="">
                                          <alinea>
                                             <content>
                                                <p>&apos;ESMA shall submit those draft implementing technical standards to the Commission by 10 October 2021.&apos;;</p>
                                             </content>
                                          </alinea>
                                       </quotedStructure>
                                    </mod>
                                 </p>
                              </content>
                           </alinea>
                        </point>
                     </list>
                  </point>
                  <point>
                     <num>(12)</num>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>in Article 28(1), the first sentence is replaced by the following:</p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>
                              <mod>
                                 <quotedStructure startQuote="" endQuote="">
                                    <paragraph>
                                       <num>&apos;1.</num>
                                       <content>
                                          <p>A third party as referred to in Article 27(2) shall be authorised by the competent authority to assess the compliance of securitisations with the STS criteria provided for in Articles 19 to 22, Articles 23 to 26, or Articles 26a to 26e.&apos;;</p>
                                       </content>
                                    </paragraph>
                                 </quotedStructure>
                              </mod>
                           </p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                  </point>
                  <point>
                     <num>(13)</num>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>in Article 29(5), the second sentence is replaced by the following:</p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>
                              <mod>
                                 <quotedStructure startQuote="" endQuote="">
                                    <alinea>
                                       <content>
                                          <p>&apos;Member States shall inform the Commission and ESMA of the designation of competent authorities pursuant to this paragraph by 10 October 2021. Until the designation of a competent authority to supervise the compliance with the requirements set out in Articles 26a to 26e, the competent authority designated to supervise the compliance with the requirements set out in Articles 18 to 27 applicable at 8 April 2021 shall also supervise the compliance with the requirements set out in Articles 26a to 26e.&apos;;</p>
                                       </content>
                                    </alinea>
                                 </quotedStructure>
                              </mod>
                           </p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                  </point>
                  <point>
                     <num>(14)</num>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>Article 30(2) is amended as follows:</p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                     <list>
                        <point>
                           <num>(a)</num>
                           <alinea>
                              <content>
                                 <p>point (a) is replaced by the following:</p>
                              </content>
                           </alinea>
                           <alinea>
                              <content>
                                 <p>
                                    <mod>
                                       <quotedStructure startQuote="" endQuote="">
                                          <list>
                                             <point>
                                                <num>&apos;(a)</num>
                                                <content>
                                                   <p>the processes and mechanisms to correctly measure and retain the material net economic interest on an ongoing basis in accordance with Article 6(1) and the gathering and timely disclosure of all information to be made available in accordance with Article 7;&apos;;</p>
                                                </content>
                                             </point>
                                          </list>
                                       </quotedStructure>
                                    </mod>
                                 </p>
                              </content>
                           </alinea>
                        </point>
                        <point>
                           <num>(b)</num>
                           <alinea>
                              <content>
                                 <p>the following point is inserted:</p>
                              </content>
                           </alinea>
                           <alinea>
                              <content>
                                 <p>
                                    <mod>
                                       <quotedStructure startQuote="" endQuote="">
                                          <list>
                                             <point>
                                                <num>&apos;(aa)</num>
                                                <alinea>
                                                   <content>
                                                      <p>for exposures that are not part of an NPE Securitisation:</p>
                                                   </content>
                                                </alinea>
                                                <list>
                                                   <point>
                                                      <num>(i)</num>
                                                      <content>
                                                         <p>the credit-granting criteria applied to performing exposures in accordance with Article 9;</p>
                                                      </content>
                                                   </point>
                                                   <point>
                                                      <num>(ii)</num>
                                                      <content>
                                                         <p>the sound standards for selection and pricing applied to underlying exposures that are non-performing exposures as referred to in the second subparagraph of Article 9(1);&apos;;</p>
                                                      </content>
                                                   </point>
                                                </list>
                                             </point>
                                          </list>
                                       </quotedStructure>
                                    </mod>
                                 </p>
                              </content>
                           </alinea>
                        </point>
                        <point>
                           <num>(c)</num>
                           <alinea>
                              <content>
                                 <p>the following points are added:</p>
                              </content>
                           </alinea>
                           <alinea>
                              <content>
                                 <p>
                                    <mod>
                                       <quotedStructure startQuote="" endQuote="">
                                          <list>
                                             <point>
                                                <num>&apos;(d)</num>
                                                <content>
                                                   <p>for NPE securitisations, the processes and mechanisms to ensure compliance with Article 9(1) preventing any abuse of the derogation provided for in the second subparagraph of Article 9(1);</p>
                                                </content>
                                             </point>
                                             <point>
                                                <num>(e)</num>
                                                <content>
                                                   <p>for STS on-balance-sheet securitisations, the processes and mechanisms to ensure compliance with Articles 26b to 26e;&apos;;</p>
                                                </content>
                                             </point>
                                          </list>
                                       </quotedStructure>
                                    </mod>
                                 </p>
                              </content>
                           </alinea>
                        </point>
                     </list>
                  </point>
                  <point>
                     <num>(15)</num>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>Article 31 is replaced by the following:</p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>
                              <mod>
                                 <quotedStructure startQuote="" endQuote="">
                                    <article xml:id="art_d106e1908">
                                       <num>&apos;Article 31</num>
                                       <heading>Macroprudential oversight of the securitisation market</heading>
                                       <paragraph>
                                          <num>1.</num>
                                          <content>
                                             <p>Within the limits of its mandate, the ESRB shall be responsible for the macroprudential oversight of the Union&apos;s securitisation market.</p>
                                          </content>
                                       </paragraph>
                                       <paragraph>
                                          <num>2.</num>
                                          <content>
                                             <p>In order to contribute to the prevention or mitigation of systemic risks to financial stability in the Union that arise from developments within the financial system and taking into account macroeconomic developments, so as to avoid periods of widespread financial distress, the ESRB shall continuously monitor developments in the securitisation markets. Where the ESRB considers it necessary, and at least every three years, the ESRB shall, in cooperation with EBA, publish a report on the financial stability implications of the securitisation market in order to highlight financial stability risks.</p>
                                          </content>
                                       </paragraph>
                                       <paragraph>
                                          <num>3.</num>
                                          <subparagraph>
                                             <content>
                                                <p>Without prejudice to paragraph 2 of this Article and to the report referred to in Article 44, the ESRB shall, in close cooperation with the ESAs, publish by 31 December 2022 a report assessing the impact of the introduction of STS on-balance-sheet securitisations on financial stability, and any potential systemic risks, such as risks created by concentration and inter-connectedness among non-public credit protection sellers.</p>
                                             </content>
                                          </subparagraph>
                                          <subparagraph>
                                             <content>
                                                <p>The ESRB report referred to in the first subparagraph shall take into account the specific features of synthetic securitisation, namely its typical bespoke and private character in financial markets, and examine whether the treatment of STS on-balance-sheet securitisation is conducive to overall risk reduction in the financial system and to better financing of the real economy.</p>
                                             </content>
                                          </subparagraph>
                                          <subparagraph>
                                             <content>
                                                <p>When preparing its report, the ESRB shall use a variety of relevant data sources, such as:</p>
                                             </content>
                                          </subparagraph>
                                          <list>
                                             <point>
                                                <num>(a)</num>
                                                <content>
                                                   <p>data collected by competent authorities in accordance with Article 7(1);</p>
                                                </content>
                                             </point>
                                             <point>
                                                <num>(b)</num>
                                                <content>
                                                   <p>the outcome of reviews carried out by competent authorities in accordance with Article 30(2); and</p>
                                                </content>
                                             </point>
                                             <point>
                                                <num>(c)</num>
                                                <content>
                                                   <p>data held in securitisation repositories in accordance with Article 10.</p>
                                                </content>
                                             </point>
                                          </list>
                                       </paragraph>
                                       <paragraph>
                                          <num>4.</num>
                                          <subparagraph>
                                             <content>
                                                <p>In accordance with Article 16 of Regulation (EU) No 1092/2010, the ESRB shall provide warnings and, where appropriate, issue recommendations for remedial action in response to the risks referred to in paragraphs 2 and 3 of this Article, including on the appropriateness of modifying the risk-retention levels, or other macroprudential measures.</p>
                                             </content>
                                          </subparagraph>
                                          <subparagraph>
                                             <content>
                                                <p>Within three months of the date of transmission of the recommendation, the addressee of the recommendation shall, in accordance with Article 17 of Regulation (EU) No 1092/2010, communicate to the European Parliament, the Council, the Commission and the ESRB the actions it has taken in response to the recommendation and shall provide adequate justification for any inaction.&apos;;</p>
                                             </content>
                                          </subparagraph>
                                       </paragraph>
                                    </article>
                                 </quotedStructure>
                              </mod>
                           </p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                  </point>
                  <point>
                     <num>(16)</num>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>Article 32 is amended as follows:</p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                     <list>
                        <point>
                           <num>(a)</num>
                           <alinea>
                              <content>
                                 <p>in paragraph 1, point (e) is replaced by the following:</p>
                              </content>
                           </alinea>
                           <alinea>
                              <content>
                                 <p>
                                    <mod>
                                       <quotedStructure startQuote="" endQuote="">
                                          <list>
                                             <point>
                                                <num>&apos;(e)</num>
                                                <content>
                                                   <p>a securitisation is designated as STS and an originator, sponsor or SSPE of that securitisation has failed to meet the requirements provided for in Articles 19 to 22, Articles 23 to 26 or Articles 26a to 26e;&apos;;</p>
                                                </content>
                                             </point>
                                          </list>
                                       </quotedStructure>
                                    </mod>
                                 </p>
                              </content>
                           </alinea>
                        </point>
                        <point>
                           <num>(b)</num>
                           <alinea>
                              <content>
                                 <p>paragraph 2 is amended as follows:</p>
                              </content>
                           </alinea>
                           <list>
                              <point>
                                 <num>(i)</num>
                                 <alinea>
                                    <content>
                                       <p>point (d) is replaced by the following:</p>
                                    </content>
                                 </alinea>
                                 <alinea>
                                    <content>
                                       <p>
                                          <mod>
                                             <quotedStructure startQuote="" endQuote="">
                                                <list>
                                                   <point>
                                                      <num>&apos;(d)</num>
                                                      <content>
                                                         <p>in the case of an infringement as referred to in point (e) or (f) of the first subparagraph of paragraph 1 of this Article, a temporary ban preventing the originator and sponsor from notifying under Article 27(1) that a securitisation meets the requirements set out in Articles 19 to 22, Articles 23 to 26 or Articles 26a to 26e.&apos;;</p>
                                                      </content>
                                                   </point>
                                                </list>
                                             </quotedStructure>
                                          </mod>
                                       </p>
                                    </content>
                                 </alinea>
                              </point>
                              <point>
                                 <num>(ii)</num>
                                 <alinea>
                                    <content>
                                       <p>point (h) is replaced by the following:</p>
                                    </content>
                                 </alinea>
                                 <alinea>
                                    <content>
                                       <p>
                                          <mod>
                                             <quotedStructure startQuote="" endQuote="">
                                                <list>
                                                   <point>
                                                      <num>&apos;(h)</num>
                                                      <content>
                                                         <p>in the case of an infringement as referred to in point (h) of the first subparagraph of paragraph 1 of this Article, a temporary withdrawal of the authorisation referred to in Article 28 for the third party authorised to assess the compliance of a securitisation with Articles 19 to 22, Articles 23 to 26 or Articles 26a to 26e.&apos;;</p>
                                                      </content>
                                                   </point>
                                                </list>
                                             </quotedStructure>
                                          </mod>
                                       </p>
                                    </content>
                                 </alinea>
                              </point>
                           </list>
                        </point>
                     </list>
                  </point>
                  <point>
                     <num>(17)</num>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>the following article is inserted:</p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>
                              <mod>
                                 <quotedStructure startQuote="" endQuote="">
                                    <article xml:id="art_d106e2044">
                                       <num>&apos;Article 43a</num>
                                       <heading>Transitional provisions for STS on-balance-sheet securitisations</heading>
                                       <paragraph>
                                          <num>1.</num>
                                          <content>
                                             <p>In respect of synthetic securitisations for which the credit protection agreement has become effective before 9 April 2021, originators and SSPEs may use the designation &quot;STS&quot; or &quot;simple, transparent and standardised&quot;, or a designation that refers directly or indirectly to those terms, only where the requirements set out in Article 18 and the conditions set out in paragraph 3 of this Article are complied with at the time of the notification referred to in Article 27(1).</p>
                                          </content>
                                       </paragraph>
                                       <paragraph>
                                          <num>2.</num>
                                          <content>
                                             <p>Until the date of application of the regulatory technical standards referred to in Article 27(6), originators shall, for the purposes of the obligation set out in Article 27(1), make the necessary information available to ESMA in writing.</p>
                                          </content>
                                       </paragraph>
                                       <paragraph>
                                          <num>3.</num>
                                          <subparagraph>
                                             <content>
                                                <p>Securitisations the initial securitisation positions of which were created before 9 April 2021 shall be considered to be STS provided that:</p>
                                             </content>
                                          </subparagraph>
                                          <list>
                                             <point>
                                                <num>(a)</num>
                                                <content>
                                                   <p>they met, at the time of the creation of the initial securitisation positions, the requirements set out in Articles 26b(1) to (5), (7) to (9) and (11) and (12), Articles 26c(1) and (3), Article 26e(1), the first subparagraph of Article 26e(2), the third and fourth subparagraph of Article 26e(3), and Articles 26e(6) to (9); and</p>
                                                </content>
                                             </point>
                                             <point>
                                                <num>(b)</num>
                                                <content>
                                                   <p>they meet, as of the time of notification pursuant to Article 27(1), the requirements set out in Articles 26b(6) and (10), Articles 26c(2) and (4) to (10), Articles 26d(1) to (5) and the second to seventh subparagraph of Article 26e(2), the first, second and fifth subparagraph of Article 26e(3) and Articles 26e(4) and (5).</p>
                                                </content>
                                             </point>
                                          </list>
                                       </paragraph>
                                       <paragraph>
                                          <num>4.</num>
                                          <subparagraph>
                                             <content>
                                                <p>For the purposes of point (b) of paragraph 3 of this Article, the following shall apply:</p>
                                             </content>
                                          </subparagraph>
                                          <list>
                                             <point>
                                                <num>(a)</num>
                                                <content>
                                                   <p>in Article 26d(2), &quot;prior to the closing of the transaction&quot; shall be deemed to read &quot;prior to notification under Article 27(1)&quot;;</p>
                                                </content>
                                             </point>
                                             <point>
                                                <num>(b)</num>
                                                <content>
                                                   <p>in Article 26d(3), &quot;before the pricing of the securitisation&quot; shall be deemed to read &quot;prior to notification under Article 27(1)&quot;;</p>
                                                </content>
                                             </point>
                                             <point>
                                                <num>(c)</num>
                                                <alinea>
                                                   <content>
                                                      <p>in Article 26d(5):</p>
                                                   </content>
                                                </alinea>
                                                <list>
                                                   <point>
                                                      <num>(i)</num>
                                                      <content>
                                                         <p>in the second sentence, &quot;before pricing&quot; shall be deemed to read &quot;prior to notification under Article 27(1)&quot;;</p>
                                                      </content>
                                                   </point>
                                                   <point>
                                                      <num>(ii)</num>
                                                      <content>
                                                         <p>in the third sentence, &quot;before pricing at least in draft or initial form&quot; shall be deemed to read &quot;prior to notification under Article 27(1)&quot;;</p>
                                                      </content>
                                                   </point>
                                                   <point>
                                                      <num>(iii)</num>
                                                      <content>
                                                         <p>the requirement set out in the fourth sentence shall not apply;</p>
                                                      </content>
                                                   </point>
                                                   <point>
                                                      <num>(iv)</num>
                                                      <content>
                                                         <p>references to compliance with Article 7 shall be construed as if Article 7 applied to those securitisations notwithstanding Article 43(1).&apos;;</p>
                                                      </content>
                                                   </point>
                                                </list>
                                             </point>
                                          </list>
                                       </paragraph>
                                    </article>
                                 </quotedStructure>
                              </mod>
                           </p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                  </point>
                  <point>
                     <num>(18)</num>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>Article 44 is amended as follows:</p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                     <list>
                        <point>
                           <num>(a)</num>
                           <alinea>
                              <content>
                                 <p>in the first paragraph, the following point is added:</p>
                              </content>
                           </alinea>
                           <alinea>
                              <content>
                                 <p>
                                    <mod>
                                       <quotedStructure startQuote="" endQuote="">
                                          <list>
                                             <point>
                                                <num>&apos;(e)</num>
                                                <content>
                                                   <p>the geographical location of SSPEs.&apos;;</p>
                                                </content>
                                             </point>
                                          </list>
                                       </quotedStructure>
                                    </mod>
                                 </p>
                              </content>
                           </alinea>
                        </point>
                        <point>
                           <num>(b)</num>
                           <alinea>
                              <content>
                                 <p>the following paragraph is added:</p>
                              </content>
                           </alinea>
                           <alinea>
                              <content>
                                 <p>
                                    <mod>
                                       <quotedStructure startQuote="" endQuote="">
                                          <alinea>
                                             <content>
                                                <p>&apos;Based on the information provided to it every three years under point (e), the Commission shall provide an assessment of the reasons behind the location choice, including, subject to the availability and accessibility of information, to what extent the existence of a favourable tax and regulatory regime plays a critical role.&apos;;</p>
                                             </content>
                                          </alinea>
                                       </quotedStructure>
                                    </mod>
                                 </p>
                              </content>
                           </alinea>
                        </point>
                     </list>
                  </point>
                  <point>
                     <num>(19)</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>Article 45 is deleted.</p>
                     </content>
                  </point>
                  <point>
                     <num>(20)</num>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>the following article is inserted:</p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>
                              <mod>
                                 <quotedStructure startQuote="" endQuote="">
                                    <article xml:id="art_d106e2232">
                                       <num>&apos;Article 45a</num>
                                       <heading>Development of a sustainable securitisation framework</heading>
                                       <paragraph>
                                          <num>1.</num>
                                          <subparagraph>
                                             <content>
                                                <p>By 1 November 2021, EBA, in close cooperation with ESMA and EIOPA, shall publish a report on developing a specific sustainable securitisation framework for the purpose of integrating sustainability-related transparency requirements into this Regulation. That report shall duly assess in particular:</p>
                                             </content>
                                          </subparagraph>
                                          <list>
                                             <point>
                                                <num>(a)</num>
                                                <content>
                                                   <p>the implementation of proportionate disclosure and due diligence requirements relating to potential positive and adverse impacts of the assets financed by the underlying exposures on sustainability factors;</p>
                                                </content>
                                             </point>
                                             <point>
                                                <num>(b)</num>
                                                <content>
                                                   <p>the content, methodologies and presentation of information in respect of sustainability factors in relation to positive and adverse impacts on environmental, social and governance-related matters;</p>
                                                </content>
                                             </point>
                                             <point>
                                                <num>(c)</num>
                                                <content>
                                                   <p>how to establish a specific sustainable securitisation framework that mirrors or draws upon financial products covered under Articles 8 and 9 of Regulation (EU) 2019/2088 and takes into account, where appropriate, Regulation (EU) 2020/852 of the European Parliament and of the Council<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="15">
                                                         <p>Regulation (EU) 2020/852 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 18 June 2020 on the establishment of a framework to facilitate sustainable investment, and amending Regulation (EU) 2019/2088 (OJ L 198, 22.6.2020, p. 13).&apos;;</p>
                                                      </authorialNote>;</p>
                                                </content>
                                             </point>
                                             <point>
                                                <num>(d)</num>
                                                <content>
                                                   <p>possible effects of a sustainable securitisation framework on financial stability, the scaling up of the Union securitisation market and of bank lending capacity.</p>
                                                </content>
                                             </point>
                                          </list>
                                       </paragraph>
                                       <paragraph>
                                          <num>2.</num>
                                          <content>
                                             <p>In drafting the report referred to in paragraph 1 of this Article, EBA shall where relevant, mirror or draw upon the transparency requirements set out in Articles 3, 4, 7, 8 and 9 of Regulation (EU) 2019/2088 and seek input from the European Environment Agency and the Joint Research Centre of the European Commission.</p>
                                          </content>
                                       </paragraph>
                                       <paragraph>
                                          <num>3.</num>
                                          <content>
                                             <p>In conjunction with the review report under Article 46, the Commission shall, based on the EBA report referred to in paragraph 1 of this Article, submit a report to the European Parliament and to the Council on the creation of a specific sustainable securitisation framework. The Commission&apos;s report shall, where appropriate, be accompanied by a legislative proposal.</p>
                                          </content>
                                       </paragraph>
                                    </article>
                                 </quotedStructure>
                              </mod>
                           </p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                  </point>
                  <point>
                     <num>(21)</num>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>in Article 46, the second paragraph is amended as follows:</p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                     <list>
                        <point>
                           <num>(a)</num>
                           <alinea>
                              <content>
                                 <p>point (f) is replaced by the following:</p>
                              </content>
                           </alinea>
                           <alinea>
                              <content>
                                 <p>
                                    <mod>
                                       <quotedStructure startQuote="" endQuote="">
                                          <list>
                                             <point>
                                                <num>&apos;(f)</num>
                                                <content>
                                                   <p>the implementation of the requirements set out in Articles 22(4) and 26d(4) and whether they may be extended to securitisation where the underlying exposures are not residential loans or auto loans or leases, with a view to mainstreaming environmental, social and governance disclosure;&apos;;</p>
                                                </content>
                                             </point>
                                          </list>
                                       </quotedStructure>
                                    </mod>
                                 </p>
                              </content>
                           </alinea>
                        </point>
                        <point>
                           <num>(b)</num>
                           <alinea>
                              <content>
                                 <p>the following point is added:</p>
                              </content>
                           </alinea>
                           <alinea>
                              <content>
                                 <p>
                                    <mod>
                                       <quotedStructure startQuote="" endQuote="">
                                          <list>
                                             <point>
                                                <num>&apos;(i)</num>
                                                <content>
                                                   <p>the possibility for further standardisation and disclosure requirements in view of evolving market practices, namely through the use of templates, for both traditional and synthetic securitisations, including for bespoke private securitisations where no prospectus has to be drawn up in compliance with Regulation (EU) 2017/1129 of the European Parliament and of the Council<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="16">
                                                         <p>Regulation (EU) 2017/1129 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 14 June 2017 on the prospectus to be published when securities are offered to the public or admitted to trading on a regulated market, and repealing Directive 2003/71/EC (OJ L 168, 30.6.2017, p. 12).&apos;.</p>
                                                      </authorialNote>.</p>
                                                </content>
                                             </point>
                                          </list>
                                       </quotedStructure>
                                    </mod>
                                 </p>
                              </content>
                           </alinea>
                        </point>
                     </list>
                  </point>
               </list>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <article xml:id="art_d106e2350">
            <num>Article 2</num>
            <heading>Entry into force</heading>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>This Regulation shall enter into force on the third day following that of its publication in the <i>Official Journal of the European Union</i>.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <clause>
            <content>
               <p>This Regulation shall be binding in its entirety and directly applicable in all Member States.</p>
            </content>
         </clause>
      </body>
      <conclusions>
         <p>Done at Brussels, 31 March 2021.</p>
         <block name="signatory">
            <signature>
               <organization refersTo="">For the European Parliament</organization>
               <role refersTo="">The President</role>
               <person refersTo="">D. M. SASSOLI</person>
            </signature>
            <signature>
               <organization refersTo="">For the Council</organization>
               <role refersTo="">The President</role>
               <person refersTo="">A. P. ZACARIAS</person>
            </signature>
         </block>
      </conclusions>
   </bill>
</akomaNtoso>
