<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0"
            xmlns:fmx="http://formex.publications.europa.eu/schema/formex-05.21-20110601.xd"
            xmlns:leos="urn:eu:europa:ec:leos"
            xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema">
   <bill name="">
      <meta xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions">
         <identification source="~COM">
            <FRBRWork>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRcountry value=""/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
         </identification>
      </meta>
      <preface>
         <longTitle>
            <p>
               <docStage/>
               <docType>COMMISSION REGULATION (EU) 2021/1099</docType>of 5 July 2021<docPurpose>amending Annexes II and III to Regulation (EC) No 1223/2009 of the European Parliament and of the Council on cosmetic products</docPurpose>
            </p>
         </longTitle>
         <container name="EEArelevance">
            <p>(Text with EEA relevance)</p>
         </container>
      </preface>
      <preamble>
         <formula name="actingEntity">
            <p>THE EUROPEAN COMMISSION,</p>
         </formula>
         <citations>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to Regulation (EC) No 1223/2009 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 30 November 2009 on cosmetic products<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="1">
                     <p>OJ L 342, 22.12.2009, p. 59.</p>
                  </authorialNote>, and in particular Article 31(1) thereof,</p>
            </citation>
         </citations>
         <recitals xml:id="recs_d240e71">
            <intro>
               <p>Whereas:</p>
            </intro>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d240e74">
               <num>(1)</num>
               <p>The substance 4-[(tetrahydro-2H-pyran-2-yl)oxy]phenol (common name: deoxyarbutin, INCI name: Tetrahydropyranyloxy Phenol), currently not regulated in Regulation (EC) No 1223/2009, results in the release of 1,4-Dihydroxybenzene (INCI name: Hydroquinone). Hydroquinone is included among the substances prohibited for use in cosmetic products, listed under entry 1339 of Annex II to Regulation (EC) No 1223/2009, with the exception of entry 14 of Annex III to that Regulation.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d240e80">
               <num>(2)</num>
               <p>The use of deoxyarbutin in cosmetic products was assessed by the Scientific Committee on Consumer Safety (SCCS). In its opinion adopted on 25 June 2015<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="2">
                     <p>SCCS (Scientific Committee on Consumer Safety), Opinion on deoxyarbutin &#45; Tetrahydropyranyloxy Phenol, 25 June 2015, SCCS/1554/15.</p>
                  </authorialNote>, the SCCS concluded that due to safety concerns raised with regard to the life-cycle of products containing that substance, the use of deoxyarbutin up to 3 % in face creams cannot be considered as safe<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="3">
                     <p>See point 4 of the opinion.</p>
                  </authorialNote>.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d240e99">
               <num>(3)</num>
               <p>Based on that opinion, deoxyarbutin should be prohibited for use in cosmetic products and added to the list of prohibited substances in Annex II to Regulation (EC) No 1223/2009.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d240e105">
               <num>(4)</num>
               <p>The substance 1,3-Dihydroxy-2-propanone (INCI name: Dihydroxyacetone) is a cosmetic ingredient with the reported functions of skin conditioning and tanning. Dihydroxyacetone is currently not regulated under Regulation (EC) No 1223/2009.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d240e111">
               <num>(5)</num>
               <p>In its opinion adopted on 3-4 March 2020<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="4">
                     <p>SCCS (Scientific Committee on Consumer Safety), Opinion on Dihydroxyacetone &#45; DHA, 3-4 March 2020, SCCS/1612/19.</p>
                  </authorialNote>,the SCCS considered Dihydroxyacetone safe when used as a hair colouring ingredient in leave-on applications (non-oxidative) up to a maximum concentration of 6,25 %. Furthermore, the SCCS concluded in that opinion that the use of Dihydroxyacetone as a hair colouring ingredient in leave-on applications (non-oxidative) up to a maximum concentration of 6,25 % together with the use of self-tanning lotion and face cream containing up to a maximum concentration of 10 % Dihydroxyacetone is also considered safe.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d240e132">
               <num>(6)</num>
               <p>Based on those conclusions, it is necessary to add a new entry in Annex III to Regulation (EC) No 1223/2009 that will allow for a restricted use of Dihydroxyacetone in non-oxidative hair dye products and in self-tanning products only, in a maximum concentration of up to 6,25 % and 10 % respectively.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d240e138">
               <num>(7)</num>
               <p>Regulation (EC) No 1223/2009 should therefore be amended accordingly.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d240e144">
               <num>(8)</num>
               <p>It is appropriate to provide for reasonable periods of time in order for the industry to adapt to the new requirements on the use of Dihydroxyacetone in cosmetic products and to phase out the placing and making available on the market of cosmetic products which do not comply with those requirements.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d240e150">
               <num>(9)</num>
               <p>The measures provided for in this Regulation are in accordance with the opinion of the Standing Committee on Cosmetic Products,</p>
            </recital>
         </recitals>
         <formula name="enactingFormula">
            <p>HAS ADOPTED THIS REGULATION:</p>
         </formula>
      </preamble>
      <body>
         <article xml:id="art_d240e160">
            <num>Article 1</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>Regulation (EC) No 1223/2009 is amended in accordance with the Annex to this Regulation.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <article xml:id="art_d240e165">
            <num>Article 2</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>This Regulation shall enter into force on the twentieth day following that of its publication in the <i>Official Journal of the European Union</i>.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <clause>
            <content>
               <p>This Regulation shall be binding in its entirety and directly applicable in all Member States.</p>
            </content>
         </clause>
      </body>
      <conclusions>
         <p>Done at Brussels, 5 July 2021.</p>
         <block name="signatory">
            <signature>
               <organization refersTo="">For the Commission</organization>
               <role refersTo="">The President</role>
               <person refersTo="">Ursula VON DER LEYEN</person>
            </signature>
         </block>
      </conclusions>
   </bill>
</akomaNtoso>
