<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0"
            xmlns:fmx="http://formex.publications.europa.eu/schema/formex-05.21-20110601.xd"
            xmlns:leos="urn:eu:europa:ec:leos"
            xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema">
   <bill name="">
      <meta xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions">
         <identification source="~COM">
            <FRBRWork>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRcountry value=""/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
         </identification>
      </meta>
      <preface>
         <longTitle>
            <p>
               <docStage/>
               <docType>COUNCIL REGULATION (EU) 2021/1819</docType>of 18 October 2021<docPurpose>amending Regulation (EU) No 224/2014 concerning restrictive measures in view of the situation in the Central African Republic</docPurpose>
            </p>
         </longTitle>
      </preface>
      <preamble>
         <formula name="actingEntity">
            <p>THE COUNCIL OF THE EUROPEAN UNION,</p>
         </formula>
         <citations>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union, and in particular Article 215 thereof,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to Council Decision 2013/798/CFSP of 23 December 2013 concerning restrictive measures against the Central African Republic<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="1">
                     <p>OJ L 352, 24.12.2013, p. 51.</p>
                  </authorialNote>,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the joint proposal from the High Representative of the Union for Foreign Affairs and Security Policy and the European Commission,</p>
            </citation>
         </citations>
         <recitals xml:id="recs_d651e70">
            <intro>
               <p>Whereas:</p>
            </intro>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d651e73">
               <num>(1)</num>
               <p>On 10 March 2014, the Council adopted Regulation (EU) No 224/2014<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="2">
                     <p>Council Regulation (EU) No 224/2014 of 10 March 2014 concerning restrictive measures in view of the situation in the Central African Republic (OJ L 70, 11.3.2014, p. 1).</p>
                  </authorialNote> in order to give effect to certain measures provided for in Decision 2013/798/CFSP.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d651e92">
               <num>(2)</num>
               <p>On 29 July 2021, the United Nations Security Council (UNSC) adopted Resolution 2588 (2021). That Resolution extends the exemptions to the arms embargo and broadens the scope of the restrictive measures.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d651e101">
               <num>(3)</num>
               <p>On 18 October 2021, the Council adopted Decision (CFSP) 2021/1823<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="3">
                     <p>Council Decision (CFSP) 2021/1823 of 18 October 2021 amending Decision 2013/798/CFSP concerning restrictive measures against the Central African Republic (see page 11 of this Official Journal).</p>
                  </authorialNote>, which amends Decision 2013/798/CFSP in accordance with UNSC Resolution 2588 (2021).</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d651e117">
               <num>(4)</num>
               <p>Certain of those amendments fall within the scope of the Treaty and regulatory action at the level of the Union is therefore necessary in order to implement them together with technical adjustments in light of previous UNSC Resolutions, in particular with a view to ensuring their uniform application by economic operators in all Member States.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d651e123">
               <num>(5)</num>
               <p>Regulation (EU) No 224/2014 should therefore be amended accordingly,</p>
            </recital>
         </recitals>
         <formula name="enactingFormula">
            <p>HAS ADOPTED THIS REGULATION:</p>
         </formula>
      </preamble>
      <body>
         <article xml:id="art_d651e133" leos:compliant="false">
            <num>Article 1</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <subparagraph>
                  <content>
                     <p>Regulation (EU) No 224/2014 is amended as follows:</p>
                  </content>
               </subparagraph>
               <list>
                  <point>
                     <num>(1)</num>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>in Article 3, point (e) is replaced by the following:</p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>
                              <mod>
                                 <quotedStructure startQuote="" endQuote="">
                                    <list>
                                       <point>
                                          <num>&apos;(e)</num>
                                          <content>
                                             <p>related to weapons with a calibre of 14,5 mm or less and ammunition and components specially designed for such weapons, and to unarmed ground military vehicles and ground military vehicles mounted with weapons with a calibre of 14,5 mm or less, and their spare parts, and to rocket-propelled grenades, and ammunition specially designed for such weapons, and of mortars with a calibre of 60 mm and 82 mm, and ammunition specially designed for such weapons, to the CAR security forces, including state civilian law enforcement institutions, where such weapons, ammunition, components and vehicles are intended solely for support of, or use in, the CAR process of SSR, provided that the provision of such assistance or services has been notified at least 20 days in advance to the Sanctions Committee;&apos;;</p>
                                          </content>
                                       </point>
                                    </list>
                                 </quotedStructure>
                              </mod>
                           </p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                  </point>
                  <point>
                     <num>(2)</num>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>in Article 5(3), the following point is added:</p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>
                              <mod>
                                 <quotedStructure startQuote="" endQuote="">
                                    <list>
                                       <point>
                                          <num>&apos;(k)</num>
                                          <content>
                                             <p>involved in planning, directing, sponsoring or committing acts in the CAR that violate international humanitarian law, including attacks against medical personnel or humanitarian personnel.&apos;.</p>
                                          </content>
                                       </point>
                                    </list>
                                 </quotedStructure>
                              </mod>
                           </p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                  </point>
               </list>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <article xml:id="art_d651e176">
            <num>Article 2</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>This Regulation shall enter into force on the day following that of its publication in the <i>Official Journal of the European Union</i>.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <clause>
            <content>
               <p>This Regulation shall be binding in its entirety and directly applicable in all Member States.</p>
            </content>
         </clause>
      </body>
      <conclusions>
         <p>Done at Luxembourg, 18 October 2021.</p>
         <block name="signatory">
            <signature>
               <organization refersTo="">For the Council</organization>
               <role refersTo="">The President</role>
               <person refersTo="">J. BORRELL FONTELLES</person>
            </signature>
         </block>
      </conclusions>
   </bill>
</akomaNtoso>
