<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0"
            xmlns:fmx="http://formex.publications.europa.eu/schema/formex-05.21-20110601.xd"
            xmlns:leos="urn:eu:europa:ec:leos"
            xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema">
   <bill name="">
      <meta xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions">
         <identification source="~COM">
            <FRBRWork>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRcountry value=""/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
         </identification>
      </meta>
      <preface>
         <longTitle>
            <p>
               <docStage/>
               <docType>REGULATION (EU) 2018/946 OF THE EUROPEAN PARLIAMENT AND OF THE COUNCIL</docType>of 4 July 2018<docPurpose>replacing Annexes A and B to Regulation (EU) 2015/848 on insolvency proceedings</docPurpose>
            </p>
         </longTitle>
      </preface>
      <preamble>
         <formula name="actingEntity">
            <p>THE EUROPEAN PARLIAMENT AND THE COUNCIL OF THE EUROPEAN UNION,</p>
         </formula>
         <citations>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union, and in particular Article 81 thereof,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the proposal from the European Commission,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>After transmission of the draft legislative act to the national parliaments,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>Acting in accordance with the ordinary legislative procedure<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="1">
                     <p>Position of the European Parliament of 13 June 2018 (not yet published in the Official Journal) and decision of the Council of 26 June 2018.</p>
                  </authorialNote>,</p>
            </citation>
         </citations>
         <recitals xml:id="recs_d224e75">
            <intro>
               <p>Whereas:</p>
            </intro>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d224e78">
               <num>(1)</num>
               <p>Annexes A and B to Regulation (EU) 2015/848 of the European Parliament and of the Council<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="2">
                     <p>Regulation (EU) 2015/848 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 20 May 2015 on insolvency proceedings (OJ L 141, 5.6.2015, p. 19).</p>
                  </authorialNote> list the designations given in the national law of the Member States to the insolvency proceedings and to the insolvency practitioners to which that Regulation applies. Annex A lists the insolvency proceedings referred to in point (4) of Article 2 of Regulation (EU) 2015/848 and Annex B lists the insolvency practitioners referred to in point (5) of that Article.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d224e94">
               <num>(2)</num>
               <p>On 3 January 2017, the Republic of Croatia notified the Commission of recent changes in its domestic insolvency law that introduce new types of insolvency proceedings. Those new types of insolvency proceedings are consistent with the definition of insolvency proceedings under Regulation (EU) 2015/848.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d224e103">
               <num>(3)</num>
               <p>After the Commission presented its proposal, it received further notifications from the Republic of Bulgaria, the Republic of Croatia, the Republic of Latvia and the Portuguese Republic relating to recent changes to their domestic law that introduce new types of insolvency proceedings or insolvency practitioners. Furthermore, the Kingdom of Belgium notified the Commission of the adoption of a new law that introduces changes to its domestic insolvency law. That new law entered into force on 1 May 2018. Those new types of insolvency proceedings and insolvency practitioners comply with the requirements set out in Regulation (EU) 2015/848 and make it necessary to amend Annexes A and B to that Regulation.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d224e112">
               <num>(4)</num>
               <p>In accordance with Article 3 and Article 4a(1) of Protocol No 21 on the position of the United Kingdom and Ireland in respect of the area of freedom, security and justice, annexed to the Treaty on European Union and to the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union, the United Kingdom has notified, by letter of 15 November 2017, its wish to take part in the adoption and application of this Regulation.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d224e121">
               <num>(5)</num>
               <p>In accordance with Articles 1 and 2 and Article 4a(1) of Protocol No 21 on the position of the United Kingdom and Ireland in respect of the area of freedom, security and justice, annexed to the Treaty on European Union and to the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union, and without prejudice to Article 4 of that Protocol, Ireland is not taking part in the adoption of this Regulation and is not bound by it or subject to its application.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d224e128">
               <num>(6)</num>
               <p>In accordance with Articles 1 and 2 of Protocol No 22 on the position of Denmark, annexed to the Treaty on European Union and to the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union, Denmark is not taking part in the adoption of this Regulation and is not bound by it or subject to its application.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d224e134">
               <num>(7)</num>
               <p>Annexes A and B to Regulation (EU) 2015/848 should therefore be amended accordingly,</p>
            </recital>
         </recitals>
         <formula name="enactingFormula">
            <p>HAVE ADOPTED THIS REGULATION:</p>
         </formula>
      </preamble>
      <body>
         <article xml:id="art_d224e143">
            <num>Article 1</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>Annexes A and B to Regulation (EU) 2015/848 are replaced by the text set out in the Annex to this Regulation.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <article xml:id="art_d224e148">
            <num>Article 2</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>This Regulation shall enter into force on the twentieth day following that of its publication in the <i>Official Journal of the European Union</i>.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <clause>
            <content>
               <p>This Regulation shall be binding in its entirety and directly applicable in the Member States in accordance with the Treaties.</p>
            </content>
         </clause>
      </body>
      <conclusions>
         <p>Done at Strasbourg, 4 July 2018.</p>
         <block name="signatory">
            <signature>
               <organization refersTo="">For the European Parliament</organization>
               <role refersTo="">The President</role>
               <person refersTo="">A. TAJANI</person>
            </signature>
            <signature>
               <organization refersTo="">For the Council</organization>
               <role refersTo="">The President</role>
               <person refersTo="">K. EDTSTADLER</person>
            </signature>
         </block>
      </conclusions>
   </bill>
</akomaNtoso>
