<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0"
            xmlns:fmx="http://formex.publications.europa.eu/schema/formex-05.21-20110601.xd"
            xmlns:leos="urn:eu:europa:ec:leos"
            xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema">
   <bill name="">
      <meta xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions">
         <identification source="~COM">
            <FRBRWork>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRcountry value=""/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
         </identification>
      </meta>
      <preface>
         <longTitle>
            <p>
               <docStage/>
               <docType>COMMISSION REGULATION (EU) 2018/1514</docType>of 10 October 2018<docPurpose>amending Annexes II, III and IV to Regulation (EC) No 396/2005 of the European Parliament and of the Council as regards maximum residue levels for abamectin, acibenzolar-S-methyl, clopyralid, emamectin, fenhexamid, fenpyrazamine, fluazifop-P, isofetamid, Pasteuria nishizawae Pn1, talc E553B and tebuconazole in or on certain products</docPurpose>
            </p>
         </longTitle>
         <container name="EEArelevance">
            <p>(Text with EEA relevance)</p>
         </container>
      </preface>
      <preamble>
         <formula name="actingEntity">
            <p>THE EUROPEAN COMMISSION,</p>
         </formula>
         <citations>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to Regulation (EC) No 396/2005 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 23 February 2005 on maximum residue levels of pesticides in or on food and feed of plant and animal origin and amending Council Directive 91/414/EEC<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="1">
                     <p>OJ L 70, 16.3.2005, p. 1.</p>
                  </authorialNote>, and in particular Article 5(1) and Article 14(1)(a) thereof,</p>
            </citation>
         </citations>
         <recitals xml:id="recs_d277e74">
            <intro>
               <p>Whereas:</p>
            </intro>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d277e77">
               <num>(1)</num>
               <p>For abamectin, acibenzolar-S-methyl, fenhexamid, fluazifop-P, isofetamid and tebuconazole, maximum residue levels (MRLs) were set in Annex II to Regulation (EC) No 396/2005. For clopyralid, emamectin and fenpyrazamine, MRLs were set in Part A of Annex III to that Regulation. For <i>Pasteuria nishizawae</i> Pn1 and talc E553B, no specific MRLs were set nor were those substance included in Annex IV to that Regulation, so the default value of 0,01 mg/kg laid down in Article 18(1)(b) thereof applies.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d277e86">
               <num>(2)</num>
               <p>In the context of a procedure for the authorisation of the use of a plant protection product containing the active substance abamectin on citrus fruits, an application was submitted in accordance with Article 6(1) of Regulation (EC) No 396/2005 for modification of the existing MRLs.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d277e92">
               <num>(3)</num>
               <p>As regards acibenzolar-S-methyl, such an application was submitted for aubergines and cucurbits. As regards clopyralid, such an application was submitted for spring onions and leeks. As regards emamectin, such an application was submitted for leafy brassica, beans (with pods) and peas (with pods). As regards fenhexamid, such an application was submitted for plums, blueberries, cranberries, currants, gooseberries and beans (with pods). As regards fenpyrazamine, such an application was submitted for lettuces, salad plants, spinaches and similar leaves. As regards fluazifop-P, such an application was submitted for tomatoes. As regards isofetamid, such an application was submitted for tomatoes, peppers, aubergines, okra and cucurbits (with edible peel). As regards tebuconazole, such an application was submitted for olives, rice, &apos;herbs and edible flowers&apos; and herbal infusions from flowers, leaves and herbs.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d277e102">
               <num>(4)</num>
               <p>In accordance with Article 8 of Regulation (EC) No 396/2005, those applications were evaluated by the Member States concerned and the evaluation reports were forwarded to the Commission.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d277e108">
               <num>(5)</num>
               <p>The European Food Safety Authority (&apos;the Authority&apos;) assessed the applications and the evaluation reports, examining in particular the risks to the consumer and, where relevant, to animals and gave reasoned opinions on the proposed MRLs<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="2">
                     <p>EFSA scientific reports available online: http://www.efsa.europa.eu:</p>
                     <alinea>
                        <list>
                           <indent>
                              <num> </num>
                              <content>
                                 <p>Reasoned opinion on the modification of the existing maximum residue level for abamectin in citrus fruits. <i>EFSA Journal</i> 2018;16(4):5254.</p>
                              </content>
                           </indent>
                           <indent>
                              <num> </num>
                              <content>
                                 <p>Reasoned opinion on the modification of the existing maximum residue levels for acibenzolar-S-methyl in aubergines and cucurbits with edible and inedible peel. <i>EFSA Journal</i> 2018;16(4):5256.</p>
                              </content>
                           </indent>
                           <indent>
                              <num> </num>
                              <content>
                                 <p>Reasoned opinion on the modification of the existing maximum residue levels for clopyralid in spring/green/Welsh onions and leeks. <i>EFSA Journal</i> 2018;16(1):5149.</p>
                              </content>
                           </indent>
                           <indent>
                              <num> </num>
                              <content>
                                 <p>Reasoned opinion on the modification of the existing maximum residue levels for emamectin in leafy brassica and beans and peas with pods. <i>EFSA Journal</i> 2018;16(4):5255.</p>
                              </content>
                           </indent>
                           <indent>
                              <num> </num>
                              <content>
                                 <p>Reasoned opinion on the modification of the existing maximum residue levels for fenhexamid in various crops. <i>EFSA Journal</i> 2018;16(1):5158.</p>
                              </content>
                           </indent>
                           <indent>
                              <num> </num>
                              <content>
                                 <p>Reasoned opinion on the modification of the existing maximum residue levels for fenpyrazamine in lettuces, salad plants, spinaches and similar leaves. <i>EFSA Journal</i> 2018;16(3):5231</p>
                              </content>
                           </indent>
                           <indent>
                              <num> </num>
                              <content>
                                 <p>Reasoned opinion on the modification of the existing maximum residue level for fluazifop-P in tomato. <i>EFSA Journal</i> 2018;16(4):5253.</p>
                              </content>
                           </indent>
                           <indent>
                              <num> </num>
                              <content>
                                 <p>Reasoned opinion on the modification of the existing maximum residue levels for isofetamid in tomatoes, peppers, aubergines, okra and cucurbits with edible peel. <i>EFSA Journal</i> 2018;16(5):5264.</p>
                              </content>
                           </indent>
                           <indent>
                              <num> </num>
                              <content>
                                 <p>Reasoned opinion on the Modification of the existing maximum residue levels for tebuconazole in olives, rice, herbs and herbal infusions (dried). <i>EFSA Journal</i> 2018;16(5):5257.</p>
                              </content>
                           </indent>
                        </list>
                     </alinea>
                  </authorialNote>. The Authority forwarded those opinions to the applicants, the Commission and the Member States and made them available to the public.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d277e177">
               <num>(6)</num>
               <p>As regards all applications, the Authority concluded that all requirements with respect to data were met and that the modifications to the MRLs requested by the applicants were acceptable with regard to consumer safety on the basis of a consumer exposure assessment for 27 specific European consumer groups. The Authority took into account the most recent information on the toxicological properties of the substances. Neither the lifetime exposure to these substances via consumption of all food products that may contain them, nor the short-term exposure due to high consumption of the relevant products showed that there is a risk that the acceptable daily intake or the acute reference dose is exceeded.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d277e183">
               <num>(7)</num>
               <p>As regards abamectin, the applicant also submitted validated analytical methods for crop matrices with high acid and water content. As regards tebuconazole, the applicant also submitted validated analytical methods for all crop matrices. The relevant footnotes should therefore be deleted from Annex II to Regulation (EC) No 396/2005.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d277e189">
               <num>(8)</num>
               <p>In the context of the approval of the active substance <i>Pasteuria nishizawae</i> Pn1, an MRL application was included in the summary dossier in accordance with Article 8(1)(g) of Regulation (EC) No 1107/2009 of the European Parliament and of the Council<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="3">
                     <p>Regulation (EC) No 1107/2009 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 21 October 2009 concerning the placing of plant protection products on the market and repealing Council Directives 79/117/EEC and 91/414/EEC (OJ L 309, 24.11.2009, p. 1).</p>
                  </authorialNote>. Such application was evaluated by the Member State concerned in accordance with Article 11(2) of that Regulation. The Authority assessed the application and delivered a conclusion on the peer review of the pesticide risk assessment of the active substance, where it recommended the inclusion of <i>Pasteuria nishizawae</i> Pn1 in Annex IV to Regulation (EC) No 396/2005.<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="4">
                     <p>Conclusion on the peer review of the pesticide risk assessment of the active substance Pasteuria nishizawae Pn1. <i>EFSA Journal</i> 2018;16(2):5159.</p>
                  </authorialNote>.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d277e220">
               <num>(9)</num>
               <p>Talc E553B is approved as basic substance by Commission Implementing Regulation (EU) 2018/691<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="5">
                     <p>Commission Implementing Regulation (EU) 2018/691 of 7 May 2018 approving the basic substance talc E553B in accordance with Regulation (EC) No 1107/2009 of the European Parliament and of the Council concerning the placing of plant protection products on the market, and amending the Annex to Commission Implementing Regulation (EU) No 540/2011 (OJ L 117, 8.5.2018, p. 6).</p>
                  </authorialNote>. The conditions of use of that substance are not expected to lead to the presence of residues in food or feed commodities that may pose a risk to the consumer. It is therefore appropriate to include that substance in Annex IV to Regulation (EC) No 396/2005.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d277e236">
               <num>(10)</num>
               <p>Based on the reasoned opinions and the conclusions of the Authority and taking into account the factors relevant to the matter under consideration, the appropriate modifications to the MRLs fulfil the requirements of Article 14(2) of Regulation (EC) No 396/2005.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d277e243">
               <num>(11)</num>
               <p>Regulation (EC) No 396/2005 should therefore be amended accordingly.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d277e249">
               <num>(12)</num>
               <p>The measures provided for in this Regulation are in accordance with the opinion of the Standing Committee on Plants, Animals, Food and Feed,</p>
            </recital>
         </recitals>
         <formula name="enactingFormula">
            <p>HAS ADOPTED THIS REGULATION:</p>
         </formula>
      </preamble>
      <body>
         <article xml:id="art_d277e258">
            <num>Article 1</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>Annexes II, III and IV to Regulation (EC) No 396/2005 are amended in accordance with the Annex to this Regulation.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <article xml:id="art_d277e263">
            <num>Article 2</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>This Regulation shall enter into force on the twentieth day following that of its publication in the <i>Official Journal of the European Union</i>.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <clause>
            <content>
               <p>This Regulation shall be binding in its entirety and directly applicable in all Member States.</p>
            </content>
         </clause>
      </body>
      <conclusions>
         <p>Done at Brussels, 10 October 2018.</p>
         <block name="signatory">
            <signature>
               <organization refersTo="">For the Commission</organization>
               <role refersTo="">The President</role>
               <person refersTo="">Jean-Claude JUNCKER</person>
            </signature>
         </block>
      </conclusions>
   </bill>
</akomaNtoso>
