<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0"
            xmlns:fmx="http://formex.publications.europa.eu/schema/formex-05.21-20110601.xd"
            xmlns:leos="urn:eu:europa:ec:leos"
            xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema">
   <bill name="">
      <meta xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions">
         <identification source="~COM">
            <FRBRWork>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRcountry value=""/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
         </identification>
      </meta>
      <preface>
         <longTitle>
            <p>
               <docStage/>
               <docType>COUNCIL REGULATION (EU) 2017/719</docType>of 7 April 2017<docPurpose>amending Regulation (EU) 2015/2192 on the allocation of the fishing opportunities under the Protocol setting out the fishing opportunities and financial contribution provided for in the Fisheries Partnership Agreement between the European Community and the Islamic Republic of Mauritania for a period of four years</docPurpose>
            </p>
         </longTitle>
      </preface>
      <preamble>
         <formula name="actingEntity">
            <p>THE COUNCIL OF THE EUROPEAN UNION,</p>
         </formula>
         <citations>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union, and in particular Article 43(3) thereof,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the proposal from the European Commission,</p>
            </citation>
         </citations>
         <recitals xml:id="recs_d34e59">
            <intro>
               <p>Whereas:</p>
            </intro>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d34e62">
               <num>(1)</num>
               <p>On 30 November 2006, the Council adopted Regulation (EC) No 1801/2006 on the conclusion of the Fisheries Partnership Agreement between the European Community and the Islamic Republic of Mauritania<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="1">
                     <p>OJ L 343, 8.12.2006, p. 1.</p>
                  </authorialNote> (&apos;the Partnership Agreement&apos;).</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d34e81">
               <num>(2)</num>
               <p>On 24 May 2016, the Council adopted Decision (EU) 2016/870<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="2">
                     <p>Council Decision (EU) 2016/870 of 24 May 2016 on the conclusion, on behalf of the European Union, of the Protocol setting out the fishing opportunities and financial contribution provided for in the Fisheries Partnership Agreement between the European Community and the Islamic Republic of Mauritania for a period of four years (OJ L 145, 2.6.2016, p. 1).</p>
                  </authorialNote> on the conclusion of the Protocol setting out the fishing opportunities and financial contribution provided for in the Partnership Agreement for a period of four years from 16 November 2015 (&apos;the Protocol&apos;).</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d34e107">
               <num>(3)</num>
               <p>Council Regulation (EU) 2015/2192<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="3">
                     <p>Council Regulation (EU) 2015/2192 of 10 November 2015 on the allocation of the fishing opportunities under the Protocol setting out the fishing opportunities and financial contribution provided for in the Fisheries Partnership Agreement between the European Community and the Islamic Republic of Mauritania for a period of four years (OJ L 315, 1.12.2015, p. 72).</p>
                  </authorialNote> allocates among the Member States the fishing opportunities fixed under the Protocol.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d34e123">
               <num>(4)</num>
               <p>Scientific advice by the Independent Joint Scientific Committee established under Article 4 of the Protocol identified a surplus of black hake and took note of the 2014 scientific advice of the IMROP (Institut Mauritanien de Recherches Océanographiques et des Pêches) confirming a surplus of squid and cuttlefish.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d34e129">
               <num>(5)</num>
               <p>In accordance with Article 6(1)(a) of the Protocol, the Joint Committee established under Article 10 of the Partnership Agreement decided, at its meeting in Nouakchott on 15 and 16 November 2016, to modify the Protocol by introducing new fishing opportunities, within the available surplus, for freezer trawlers targeting black hake as a primary species and squid and cuttlefish as secondary species.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d34e141">
               <num>(6)</num>
               <p>It is appropriate to allocate these new fishing opportunities among the Member States for the remainder of the period of application of the Protocol.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d34e147">
               <num>(7)</num>
               <p>Since the introduction of new fishing opportunities has an impact on Union vessels&apos; economic activities and planning of their fishing seasons, this Regulation should enter into force immediately after its publication.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d34e153">
               <num>(8)</num>
               <p>Regulation (EU) 2015/2192 should be modified accordingly,</p>
            </recital>
         </recitals>
         <formula name="enactingFormula">
            <p>HAS ADOPTED THIS REGULATION:</p>
         </formula>
      </preamble>
      <body>
         <article xml:id="art_d34e163" leos:compliant="false">
            <num>Article 1</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>In Article 1(1) of Regulation (EU) 2015/2192, the following point is added:</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>
                     <mod>
                        <quotedStructure startQuote="" endQuote="">
                           <point>
                              <num>&apos;(h)</num>
                              <alinea>
                                 <content>
                                    <p>Category 2a &#45; Black hake (freezer) trawlers:</p>
                                 </content>
                              </alinea>
                              <alinea>
                                 <content>
                                    <table class="TBL">
                                       <tr>
                                          <td rowspan="3">
                                             <p>Spain:</p>
                                          </td>
                                          <td>
                                             <p>Black hake</p>
                                          </td>
                                          <td>
                                             <p>3500 tonnes</p>
                                          </td>
                                       </tr>
                                       <tr>
                                          <td>
                                             <p>Squid</p>
                                          </td>
                                          <td>
                                             <p>1450 tonnes</p>
                                          </td>
                                       </tr>
                                       <tr>
                                          <td>
                                             <p>Cuttlefish</p>
                                          </td>
                                          <td>
                                             <p>600 tonnes</p>
                                          </td>
                                       </tr>
                                    </table>
                                 </content>
                              </alinea>
                              <alinea>
                                 <content>
                                    <p>Within this category, a maximum of 6 vessels may be deployed in Mauritanian waters at any one time.&apos;.</p>
                                 </content>
                              </alinea>
                           </point>
                        </quotedStructure>
                     </mod>
                  </p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <article xml:id="art_d34e204">
            <num>Article 2</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>This Regulation shall enter into force on the day following that of its publication in the <i>Official Journal of the European Union</i>.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <clause>
            <content>
               <p>This Regulation shall be binding in its entirety and directly applicable in all Member States.</p>
            </content>
         </clause>
      </body>
      <conclusions>
         <p>Done at Brussels, 7 April 2017.</p>
         <block name="signatory">
            <signature>
               <organization refersTo="">For the Council</organization>
               <role refersTo="">The President</role>
               <person refersTo="">L. GRECH</person>
            </signature>
         </block>
      </conclusions>
   </bill>
</akomaNtoso>
