<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0"
            xmlns:fmx="http://formex.publications.europa.eu/schema/formex-05.21-20110601.xd"
            xmlns:leos="urn:eu:europa:ec:leos"
            xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema">
   <bill name="">
      <meta xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions">
         <identification source="~COM">
            <FRBRWork>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRcountry value=""/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
         </identification>
      </meta>
      <preface>
         <longTitle>
            <p>
               <docStage/>
               <docType>COUNCIL REGULATION (EU) 2020/1108</docType>of 20 July 2020<docPurpose>amending Regulation (EU) 2017/2454 as regards the dates of application in response to the COVID‐19 pandemic</docPurpose>
            </p>
         </longTitle>
      </preface>
      <preamble>
         <formula name="actingEntity">
            <p>THE COUNCIL OF THE EUROPEAN UNION,</p>
         </formula>
         <citations>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union, and in particular Article 113 thereof,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the proposal from the European Commission,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>After transmission of the draft legislative act to the national parliaments,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the opinion of the European Parliament<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="1">
                     <p>Opinion of 10 July 2020 (not yet published in the Official Journal).</p>
                  </authorialNote>,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the opinion of the European Economic and Social Committee<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="2">
                     <p>Opinion of 10 June 2020 (not yet published in the Official Journal).</p>
                  </authorialNote>,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>Acting in accordance with a special legislative procedure,</p>
            </citation>
         </citations>
         <recitals xml:id="recs_d142e81">
            <intro>
               <p>Whereas:</p>
            </intro>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d142e84">
               <num>(1)</num>
               <p>Council Regulation (EU) No 904/2010<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="3">
                     <p>Council Regulation (EU) No 904/2010 of 7 October 2010 on administrative cooperation and combating fraud in the field of value added tax (OJ L 268, 12.10.2010, p. 1).</p>
                  </authorialNote> lays down rules on the exchange and storage of information by Member States in order to establish the special schemes provided for by Chapter 6 of Title XII of Council Directive 2006/112/EC<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="4">
                     <p>Council Directive 2006/112/EC of 28 November 2006 on the common system of value added tax (OJ L 347, 11.12.2006, p. 1).</p>
                  </authorialNote>.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d142e110">
               <num>(2)</num>
               <p>Council Regulation (EU) 2017/2454<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="5">
                     <p>Council Regulation (EU) 2017/2454 of 5 December 2017 amending Regulation (EU) No 904/2010 on administrative cooperation and combating fraud in the field of value added tax (OJ L 348, 29.12.2017, p. 1).</p>
                  </authorialNote> amends those provisions to extend the scope of those special schemes and introduce a new scheme. Those amendments are to be applied from 1 January 2021.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d142e129">
               <num>(3)</num>
               <p>On 30 January 2020, the World Health Organization (WHO) declared the COVID‐19 outbreak a public health emergency of international concern. On 11 March 2020, the WHO declared the COVID-19 outbreak a pandemic. The COVID-19 pandemic has affected all Member States. Due to the alarming increase in the number of cases and the lack of efficient means immediately available to deal with the COVID-19 pandemic, numerous Member States have declared a national state of emergency.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d142e141">
               <num>(4)</num>
               <p>The COVID-19 pandemic constitutes an unexpected and unprecedented emergency that deeply affects all Member States and obliges them to take immediate action at national level to deal with the ongoing crisis as a priority by reallocating resources reserved for other issues. As a result of this crisis, several Member States are encountering difficulties in finalising the development of IT systems necessary for the application of Regulation (EU) 2017/2454 as of 1 January 2021. Some Member States have therefore asked for the postponement of the dates of application of Regulation (EU) 2017/2454.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d142e151">
               <num>(5)</num>
               <p>Taking into consideration the challenges that Member States face in tackling the COVID‐19 crisis and the fact that the new provisions are based on the principle that all Member States have to update their IT systems in order to be able to apply Regulation (EU) 2017/2454, and ensure the collection and transmission of information and payments under the modified schemes, it is necessary to postpone the dates of application of that Regulation by six months. A postponement of six months is appropriate, as the delay should be kept as short as possible in order to minimise additional budgetary losses for Member States.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d142e157">
               <num>(6)</num>
               <p>In view of the significant impact of the economic disturbances and possible additional difficulties resulting from the COVID-19 pandemic and in order to support the correct and timely application of the new VAT e-commerce rules, the Commission could work closely with the Member States concerned to monitor the adaptation of the national IT systems and to provide technical assistance whenever needed.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d142e163">
               <num>(7)</num>
               <p>Regulation (EU) 2017/2454 should therefore be amended accordingly,</p>
            </recital>
         </recitals>
         <formula name="enactingFormula">
            <p>HAS ADOPTED THIS REGULATION:</p>
         </formula>
      </preamble>
      <body>
         <article xml:id="art_d142e172" leos:compliant="false">
            <num>Article 1</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <subparagraph>
                  <content>
                     <p>Regulation (EU) 2017/2454 is amended as follows:</p>
                  </content>
               </subparagraph>
               <list>
                  <point>
                     <num>(1)</num>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>in Article 1, point (7) is amended as follows:</p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                     <list>
                        <point>
                           <num>(a)</num>
                           <alinea>
                              <content>
                                 <p>in point (a), the heading of Section 2 is replaced by the following:</p>
                              </content>
                           </alinea>
                           <alinea>
                              <content>
                                 <p>
                                    <mod>
                                       <quotedStructure startQuote="" endQuote="">
                                          <alinea>
                                             <content>
                                                <p>&apos;<b><!--!!! HT is implicitely treated !!!-->Provisions applicable from 1 January 2015 until 30 June 2021</b>&apos;;</p>
                                             </content>
                                          </alinea>
                                       </quotedStructure>
                                    </mod>
                                 </p>
                              </content>
                           </alinea>
                        </point>
                        <point>
                           <num>(b)</num>
                           <alinea>
                              <content>
                                 <p>point (b) is amended as follows:</p>
                              </content>
                           </alinea>
                           <list>
                              <point>
                                 <num>(i)</num>
                                 <alinea>
                                    <content>
                                       <p>the heading of Section 3 is replaced by the following:</p>
                                    </content>
                                 </alinea>
                                 <alinea>
                                    <content>
                                       <p>
                                          <mod>
                                             <quotedStructure startQuote="" endQuote="">
                                                <alinea>
                                                   <content>
                                                      <p>&apos;<b>
                                                            <i>Provisions applicable from 1 July 2021</i>
                                                         </b>&apos;;</p>
                                                   </content>
                                                </alinea>
                                             </quotedStructure>
                                          </mod>
                                       </p>
                                    </content>
                                 </alinea>
                              </point>
                              <point>
                                 <num>(ii)</num>
                                 <alinea>
                                    <content>
                                       <p>Article 47a is replaced by the following:</p>
                                    </content>
                                 </alinea>
                                 <alinea>
                                    <content>
                                       <p>
                                          <mod>
                                             <quotedStructure startQuote="" endQuote="">
                                                <article xml:id="art_d142e240">
                                                   <num>&apos;<!--!!! HT is implicitely treated !!!--><b>Article 47a</b>
                                                   </num>
                                                   <heading/>
                                                   <paragraph>
                                                      <content>
                                                         <p>The provisions of this Section shall apply from 1 July 2021.&apos;;</p>
                                                      </content>
                                                   </paragraph>
                                                </article>
                                             </quotedStructure>
                                          </mod>
                                       </p>
                                    </content>
                                 </alinea>
                              </point>
                           </list>
                        </point>
                     </list>
                  </point>
                  <point>
                     <num>(2)</num>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>in Article 2, the second paragraph is replaced by the following:</p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>
                              <mod>
                                 <quotedStructure startQuote="" endQuote="">
                                    <alinea>
                                       <content>
                                          <p>&apos;It shall apply from 1 July 2021.&apos;.</p>
                                       </content>
                                    </alinea>
                                 </quotedStructure>
                              </mod>
                           </p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                  </point>
               </list>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <article xml:id="art_d142e270">
            <num>Article 2</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>This Regulation shall enter into force on the twentieth day following that of its publication in the <i>Official Journal of the European Union</i>.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <clause>
            <content>
               <p>This Regulation shall be binding in its entirety and directly applicable in all Member States.</p>
            </content>
         </clause>
      </body>
      <conclusions>
         <p>Done at Brussels, 20 July 2020.</p>
         <block name="signatory">
            <signature>
               <organization refersTo="">For the Council</organization>
               <role refersTo="">The President</role>
               <person refersTo="">M. ROTH</person>
            </signature>
         </block>
      </conclusions>
   </bill>
</akomaNtoso>
