<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0"
            xmlns:fmx="http://formex.publications.europa.eu/schema/formex-05.21-20110601.xd"
            xmlns:leos="urn:eu:europa:ec:leos"
            xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema">
   <bill name="">
      <meta xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions">
         <identification source="~COM">
            <FRBRWork>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRcountry value=""/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
         </identification>
      </meta>
      <preface>
         <longTitle>
            <p>
               <docStage/>
               <docType>COUNCIL REGULATION (EU) 2020/900</docType>of 25 June 2020<docPurpose>amending Regulation (EU) 2019/1838 as regards certain fishing opportunities for 2020 in the Baltic Sea and amending Regulation (EU) 2020/123 as regards certain fishing opportunities in 2020 in Union and non-Union waters</docPurpose>
            </p>
         </longTitle>
      </preface>
      <preamble>
         <formula name="actingEntity">
            <p>THE COUNCIL OF THE EUROPEAN UNION,</p>
         </formula>
         <citations>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union, and in particular Article 43(3) thereof,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the proposal from the European Commission,</p>
            </citation>
         </citations>
         <recitals xml:id="recs_d90e59">
            <intro>
               <p>Whereas:</p>
            </intro>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d90e62">
               <num>(1)</num>
               <p>Council Regulation (EU) 2019/1838<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="1">
                     <p>Council Regulation (EU) 2019/1838 of 30 October 2019 fixing for 2020 the fishing opportunities for certain fish stocks and groups of fish stocks applicable in the Baltic Sea and amending Regulation (EU) 2019/124 as regards certain fishing opportunities in other waters (OJ L 281, 31.10.2019, p. 1).</p>
                  </authorialNote> fixes the fishing opportunities for certain fish stocks and groups of fish stocks applicable in the Baltic Sea for 2020. It establishes spawning closure periods for the two Baltic cod stocks with a derogation for fishing vessels of less than 12 meters length overall that fish with certain passive gears. Fishing with drifting lines is excluded from the derogation. However, it is considered that the use of drifting lines should be allowed and should thus be included in the derogation, as in the previous fishing opportunities regulations. Regulation (EU) 2019/1838 should therefore be amended accordingly.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d90e78">
               <num>(2)</num>
               <p>Council Regulation (EU) 2020/123<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="2">
                     <p>Council Regulation (EU) 2020/123 of 27 January 2020 fixing for 2020 the fishing opportunities for certain fish stocks and groups of fish stocks, applicable in Union waters and, for Union fishing vessels, in certain non-Union waters (OJ L 25, 30.1.2020, p. 1).</p>
                  </authorialNote> fixes for 2020 the fishing opportunities for certain fish stocks and groups of fish stocks applicable in Union waters and, for Union vessels, in certain non-Union waters.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d90e94">
               <num>(3)</num>
               <p>In the report of its plenary session of 16-20 March 2020, the Scientific, Technical and Economic Committee for Fisheries (STECF) concluded that, for whiting (<i>Merlangius merlangus</i>) by-catches in the Celtic Sea, the 100 mm diamond mesh cod-end with a 160 mm square mesh panel is the most selective of the four different cod-end designs listed in the remedial measures set out in point (a) of Article 13(1) of Regulation (EU) 2020/123 fixing fishing opportunities for 2020. The STECF did not have any reliable estimates for cod (<i>Gadus morhua</i>) selectivity in the 100 mm diamond mesh cod-end with a 160 mm square mesh panel. Therefore, to ensure the recovery of the whiting stock concerned, it is appropriate to continue to allow the use of this cod-end and square mesh panel combination. In order to ensure the recovery of Celtic Sea cod, the 100 mm diamond mesh cod-end with a 160 mm square mesh panel should continue being used with the raised fishing line.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d90e112">
               <num>(4)</num>
               <p>The fishing mortality (F) for North sea cod (<i>Gadus morhua</i>) has increased since 2016 and is now estimated to be above the fishing mortality reference point (F<sub>lim</sub>), i.e. a reference point which in the long term will result in an average stock size at biomass limit reference point (B<sub>lim</sub>). Fishing at levels above F<sub>lim</sub> will result in a decline in the stock to levels below B<sub>lim</sub>. Consequently, the spawning-stock biomass (SSB) has decreased since 2015 and is estimated to be below B<sub>lim</sub>. B<sub>lim</sub> is the reference point provided for in the best available scientific advice, in particular by International Council for the Exploration of the Sea (ICES), below which there may be reduced reproductive capacity. Moreover, recruitment has remained poor since 1998, and was exceptionally poor in 2016 and 2018.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d90e141">
               <num>(5)</num>
               <p>In accordance with Article 7(2) of Regulation (EU) 2018/973 of the European Parliament and of the Council<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="3">
                     <p>Regulation (EU) 2018/973 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 4 July 2018 establishing a multiannual plan for demersal stocks in the North Sea and the fisheries exploiting those stocks, specifying details of the implementation of the landing obligation in the North Sea and repealing Council Regulations (EC) No 676/2007 and (EC) No 1342/2008 (OJ L 179, 16.7.2018, p. 1).</p>
                  </authorialNote> establishing the North Sea multiannual plan, where scientific advice indicates that the SSB of any of the stocks referred to in Article 1(1) of that Regulation is below the B<sub>lim</sub>, further remedial measures are to be adopted to ensure rapid return of the stock to levels above the level capable of producing maximum sustainable yield (MSY). In particular, those remedial measures may include the suspension of the targeted fishery for the stock concerned and the adequate reduction of fishing opportunities for those stocks or other stocks in the fisheries having by-catches of cod, or both.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d90e160">
               <num>(6)</num>
               <p>In the absence of a Joint Recommendation from the regional group of the North Sea Member States for longer term measures, the Commission is proposing to introduce additional technical measures functionally linked to the 2020 fishing opportunities in accordance with commitments made between the European Union and Norway, which are consistent with the joint statement of the European Commission and the Council.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d90e166">
               <num>(7)</num>
               <p>In order to reduce catches of the stocks for which by-catch total allowable catch (TAC) are set, fishing opportunities for the fisheries in which fish from those stocks are caught should be set at levels that help the biomass of vulnerable stocks to recover to sustainable levels. Technical measures that are functionally linked to fishing opportunities should also be established. In its mixed fisheries overview for the North Sea, the ICES estimates that in the absence of any changes to fishing patterns and in light of illegal discarding, catches of cod are estimated to be approximately 40000 tonnes. In order to minimise the risk of catches significantly exceeding the agreed TAC, additional measures to further limit catches are required.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d90e175">
               <num>(8)</num>
               <p>In accordance with the procedure provided for in the agreements or protocols on fisheries relations with Norway<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="4">
                     <p>Agreement on fisheries between the European Economic Community and the Kingdom of Norway (OJ L 226, 29.8.1980, p. 48).</p>
                  </authorialNote> the Union has held consultations on fishing rights with Norway. The Parties have agreed to recommend to their respective authorities the introduction of additional remedial measures to supplement the TAC already agreed in December 2019, so as to provide additional protection for both juvenile and adult cod on a temporary basis during 2020. Those measures should include seasonal closures for the protection of juveniles, restricted areas with specific access conditions and the introduction of new fishing gear-based measures.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d90e188">
               <num>(9)</num>
               <p>On 9 March 2020, ICES issued advice for catches of Northern prawn (<i>Pandalus borealis</i>) in ICES divisions 3a and 4a East (Skagerrak, Kattegat, and the northern North Sea in the Norwegian Deep). On the basis of that advice and following consultations with Norway, it is appropriate to fix the Union quota for Northern prawn in ICES division 3a at 3266 tonnes, in line with the MSY.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d90e204">
               <num>(10)</num>
               <p>According to the ICES advice of 14 April 2020, catches of sprat (<i>Sprattus sprattus</i>) in Union waters of ICES subarea 4 (the North Sea) and in ICES division 3a (Skagerrak and Kattegatt) should be no more than 207807 tonnes for the period from 1 July 2020 to 30 June 2021. The fishing opportunities for sprat should therefore be set at 169778 tonnes in Union waters of ICES division 2a and ICES subarea 4, and at 38029 tonnes in ICES division 3a for that period, in line with the MSY.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d90e232">
               <num>(11)</num>
               <p>The TAC for anchovy (<i>Engraulis encrasicolus</i>) in ICES subareas 9 and 10 and Union waters of the Fishery Committee for the Eastern Central Atlantic (CECAF) 34.1.1 for the period from 1 July 2020 to 30 June 2021 has been set at zero, pending the scientific advice for that period. ICES will issue its advice for that stock at the end of June 2020. In order to ensure that fishing activity may continue until the TAC is set on the basis of the latest scientific advice, a provisional TAC of 4018 tonnes, based on the catches in the third quarter of 2019, should be established. That provisional TAC should be amended in line with the ICES scientific advice.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d90e250">
               <num>(12)</num>
               <p>In the Agreed Record of Fisheries Consultations between Norway and the European Union for 2020 of 19 December 2019, the Parties agreed that, in addition to the agreed 50000 tonnes of herring (<i>Clupea harengus</i>) that Norway is allowed to fish from its quota in Union waters of 4a and 4b and that the Union can fish from its quota in Norwegian waters south of 62° N, an additional quantity of maximum 10000 tonnes will be granted if such an increase is called for by Norway or by the Union. That agreement should be implemented in Union law.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d90e269">
               <num>(13)</num>
               <p>At its 2020 annual meeting held from 14 to 18 February 2020, the South Pacific Regional Fisheries Management Organisation (SPRFMO) reviewed the conservation measure for jack mackerel (<i>Trachurus murphyi</i>), for which the fishing opportunities had not yet been determined in Regulation (EU) 2020/123. The applicable measures should be implemented in Union law.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d90e284">
               <num>(14)</num>
               <p>At its annual meeting held from 23 to 27 September 2019, the Northwest Atlantic Fisheries Organisation (NAFO), decided to close the fishery for splendid alfonsino (<i>Beryx splendens</i>) in NAFO subarea 6 due to a possible depletion of the stock. That measure should therefore be implemented in Union law and the list of prohibited species should therefore be amended accordingly.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d90e299">
               <num>(15)</num>
               <p>The International Commission for the Conservation of Atlantic Tunas (ICCAT) Recommendation 16-05, which decreased the TAC for Mediterranean swordfish (<i>Xiphias gladius</i>) in 2020, has already been implemented in Union law. However, in January 2020, the ICCAT Secretariat issued guidelines for the calculation of the TAC for Mediterranean swordfish. As a result, the Union quota needs to be updated accordingly.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d90e308">
               <num>(16)</num>
               <p>At its 2019 annual meeting held from 17 to 21 June 2019, the Indian Ocean Tuna Commission (IOTC) adopted new catch limits for yellowfin tuna (<i>Thunnus albacares</i>) that do not affect the Union catch limits in the framework of IOTC. However, it reduced possibilities for using fish aggregating devices (FADs), supply vessels as well as instrumented buoys. Therefore, further changes should be made to Regulation (EU) 2020/123 to ensure that the implementing rules properly reflect the decisions taken by the Contracting Parties to the IOTC.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d90e323">
               <num>(17)</num>
               <p>In July 2019, the 6th Meeting of the Parties of the Southern Indian Ocean Fisheries Agreement (SIOFA) decided on bottom fishing measures and effort limitations in the Agreement area. Those measures were implemented in Union law by Regulation (EU) 2020/123. However, further changes should be made to ensure that the implementing rules properly reflect the decisions taken by SIOFA regarding limits to bottom fishing.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d90e329">
               <num>(18)</num>
               <p>Fishing licenses are granted by the Commission to vessels flying the Venezuelan flag in order to allow them to fish for snapper in European waters off the coast of French Guiana. Regulation (EU) 2020/123 provides for granting of 45 licenses. In order to issue those authorisations, proof is to be provided that a valid contract has been concluded between the shipowner and a processing company located in the Department of French Guiana. During the authorisation process in between two years, continuity of fishing operations should be allowed under certain conditions.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d90e335">
               <num>(19)</num>
               <p>Vessels fishing for sandeels using certain gears in ICES subdivisions 2a, 3a and 4 should be subject to prohibition periods from 1 August to 31 December 2020 and from 1 January to 31 March 2021.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d90e354">
               <num>(20)</num>
               <p>Regulation (EU) 2020/123 should therefore be amended accordingly.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d90e360">
               <num>(21)</num>
               <p>The catch limits provided for in Regulation (EU) 2019/1838 and Regulation (EU) 2020/123 apply from 1 January 2020. The provisions introduced by this Regulation concerning catch limits should therefore enter into force as soon as possible. With respect to changes in the TAC levels, the additional derogation in the Baltic Sea and the continued permission of the use of a gear in the Celtic Sea, the provisions should apply from 1 January 2020. Since the fishing opportunities concerned have not yet been exhausted or are increased and more permissive rules are introduced by this Regulation, the principles of legal certainty and protection of legitimate expectations are not affected by the retroactive application of this Regulation.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d90e372">
               <num>(22)</num>
               <p>The United Kingdom has been consulted in accordance with Article 130(1) of the Agreement on the withdrawal of the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland from the European Union and the European Atomic Energy Community<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="5">
                     <p>OJ L 29, 31.1.2020, p. 7.</p>
                  </authorialNote>,</p>
            </recital>
         </recitals>
         <formula name="enactingFormula">
            <p>HAS ADOPTED THIS REGULATION:</p>
         </formula>
      </preamble>
      <body>
         <article xml:id="art_d90e387">
            <num>Article 1</num>
            <heading>Amendment of Regulation (EU) 2019/1838</heading>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>The Annex to Regulation (EU) 2019/1838 is amended in accordance with Annex I to this Regulation.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <article xml:id="art_d90e395" leos:compliant="false">
            <num>Article 2</num>
            <heading>Amendment of Regulation (EU) 2020/123</heading>
            <paragraph>
               <subparagraph>
                  <content>
                     <p>Regulation (EU) 2020/123 is amended as follows:</p>
                  </content>
               </subparagraph>
               <list>
                  <point>
                     <num>(1)</num>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>In Article 3, the following points are added:</p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>
                              <mod>
                                 <quotedStructure startQuote="" endQuote="">
                                    <list>
                                       <point>
                                          <num>&apos;(j)</num>
                                          <content>
                                             <p>&quot;instrumented buoy&quot; means a buoy clearly marked with a unique reference number allowing identification of its owner and equipped with a satellite tracking system to monitor its position;</p>
                                          </content>
                                       </point>
                                       <point>
                                          <num>(k)</num>
                                          <content>
                                             <p>&quot;operational buoy&quot; means any instrumented buoy, previously activated, switched on and deployed at sea on a drifting FAD or log, which transmits positions and any other available information such as echo-sounder estimates.&apos;.</p>
                                          </content>
                                       </point>
                                    </list>
                                 </quotedStructure>
                              </mod>
                           </p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                  </point>
                  <point>
                     <num>(2)</num>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>The following Article is inserted:</p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>
                              <mod>
                                 <quotedStructure startQuote="" endQuote="">
                                    <article xml:id="art_d90e442">
                                       <num>&apos;Article 12a</num>
                                       <heading>Closed fishing seasons for sandeels</heading>
                                       <paragraph>
                                          <content>
                                             <p>Commercial fishing for sandeels with demersal trawl, seine or similar towed gears with a mesh size of less than 16 mm shall be prohibited in ICES divisions 2a, 3a and ICES subarea 4 from 1 August to 31 December 2020 and from 1 January to 31 March 2021.&apos;.</p>
                                          </content>
                                       </paragraph>
                                    </article>
                                 </quotedStructure>
                              </mod>
                           </p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                  </point>
                  <point>
                     <num>(3)</num>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>The fourth indent of point (a) of Article 13(1) is replaced by the following:</p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>
                              <mod>
                                 <quotedStructure startQuote="" endQuote="">
                                    <list>
                                       <num>&apos;&#45;</num>
                                       <content>
                                          <p>100 mm with 160 mm square-mesh panel;&apos;.</p>
                                       </content>
                                    </list>
                                 </quotedStructure>
                              </mod>
                           </p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                  </point>
                  <point>
                     <num>(4)</num>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>Article 14 is replaced by the following:</p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>
                              <mod>
                                 <quotedStructure startQuote="" endQuote="">
                                    <article xml:id="art_d90e490">
                                       <num>&apos;Article 14</num>
                                       <heading>Remedial measures for cod in the North Sea</heading>
                                       <paragraph>
                                          <num>1.</num>
                                          <content>
                                             <p>The closed areas to fishing, except with pelagic gear (purse seines and trawls), and the periods during which the closures apply are set out in Annex IV.</p>
                                          </content>
                                       </paragraph>
                                       <paragraph>
                                          <num>2.</num>
                                          <content>
                                             <p>Vessels fishing with bottom trawls and seines with minimum mesh size of at least 70 mm in 4a and 4b or at least 90 mm in 3a, and longlines<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="6">
                                                   <p>Gear codes: OTB, OTT, OT, TBN, TBS, TB, TX, PTB, SDN, SSC, SX, LL, LLS.&apos;.</p>
                                                </authorialNote> shall be prohibited from fishing in Union waters of ICES division 4a, North of latitude 58° 30′ 00″ N and South of latitude 61° 30′ 00″ N and in Union waters of ICES divisions 3a.20 (Skagerrak), 4a and 4b, North of latitude 57° 00′ 00″ N and East of longitude 5° 00′ 00″ E.</p>
                                          </content>
                                       </paragraph>
                                       <paragraph>
                                          <num>3.</num>
                                          <subparagraph>
                                             <content>
                                                <p>By way of derogation from paragraph 2, fishing vessels referred to in paragraph 2 may fish in the areas referred to in paragraph 1 provided that they fulfil at least one of the following criteria:</p>
                                             </content>
                                          </subparagraph>
                                          <list>
                                             <point>
                                                <num>(a)</num>
                                                <content>
                                                   <p>the percentage of cod catches does not exceed 5 % of the total catches per fishing trip; vessels with cod catches that have not exceeded 5 % of their total catches in the period 2017-2019 are presumed to comply with this criterion provided that they continue to use the same gear which they used in that period; this presumption may be rebutted;</p>
                                                </content>
                                             </point>
                                             <point>
                                                <num>(b)</num>
                                                <content>
                                                   <p>a regulated and highly selective bottom trawl or seine is used, which results, according to a scientific study, in at least a 30 % reduction of cod catches compared to vessels fishing with the baseline mesh size for towed gears as specified in point 1.1 of Part B of Annex V of Regulation (EU) 2019/1241; such studies may be evaluated by STECF; in the case of a negative evaluation by STECF, these gears shall no longer be considered as valid for use in the areas defined in paragraph 2 of this Article;</p>
                                                </content>
                                             </point>
                                             <point>
                                                <num>(c)</num>
                                                <alinea>
                                                   <content>
                                                      <p>for vessels operating with bottom trawls and seines with mesh sizes equal to or larger than 100 mm (TR1), the following highly selective gears are used:</p>
                                                   </content>
                                                </alinea>
                                                <list>
                                                   <indent>
                                                      <num>-</num>
                                                      <content>
                                                         <p>belly trawls with a minimum belly mesh size of 600 mm;</p>
                                                      </content>
                                                   </indent>
                                                   <indent>
                                                      <num>-</num>
                                                      <content>
                                                         <p>raised fishing line (0,6 m);</p>
                                                      </content>
                                                   </indent>
                                                   <indent>
                                                      <num>-</num>
                                                      <content>
                                                         <p>horizontal separating panel with large mesh escape panel;</p>
                                                      </content>
                                                   </indent>
                                                </list>
                                             </point>
                                             <point>
                                                <num>(d)</num>
                                                <alinea>
                                                   <content>
                                                      <p>for vessels operating with bottom trawls and seines with mesh sizes equal to or larger than 70 mm in 4a and 90 mm in 3a and less than 100 mm (TR2), the following highly selective gears are used:</p>
                                                   </content>
                                                </alinea>
                                                <list>
                                                   <indent>
                                                      <num>-</num>
                                                      <content>
                                                         <p>horizontal sorting grid with maximum 50 mm bar spacing separating flatfish and roundfish, with an unblocked fish outlet for roundfish;</p>
                                                      </content>
                                                   </indent>
                                                   <indent>
                                                      <num>-</num>
                                                      <content>
                                                         <p>seltra panel with 300 mm square-mesh size;</p>
                                                      </content>
                                                   </indent>
                                                   <indent>
                                                      <num>-</num>
                                                      <content>
                                                         <p>sorting grid with maximum 35 mm bar spacing, with an unblocked fish outlet;</p>
                                                      </content>
                                                   </indent>
                                                </list>
                                             </point>
                                             <point>
                                                <num>(e)</num>
                                                <content>
                                                   <p>vessels are subject to a national cod avoidance plan to sustain cod catches in line with the fishing mortality corresponding to the fishing opportunities set, based on scientific advice levels, through spatial or technical measures, or a combination thereof; such plans should be assessed no later than two months following implementation, by STECF in the case of Member States, and by their relevant national scientific body for third countries and where deemed necessary, further revised if such assessments consider that the objective of the plan will not be met.</p>
                                                </content>
                                             </point>
                                          </list>
                                       </paragraph>
                                       <paragraph>
                                          <num>4.</num>
                                          <subparagraph>
                                             <content>
                                                <p>Member States shall enhance monitoring, control and surveillance of vessels referred to in paragraph 2 to control compliance with the conditions specified in points (a) to (e) of paragraph 3.</p>
                                             </content>
                                          </subparagraph>
                                       </paragraph>
                                    </article>
                                 </quotedStructure>
                              </mod>
                           </p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                  </point>
                  <point>
                     <num>(5)</num>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>In Article 16(1) the following point is inserted:</p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>
                              <mod>
                                 <quotedStructure startQuote="" endQuote="">
                                    <list>
                                       <point>
                                          <num>&apos;(o)</num>
                                          <content>
                                             <p>splendid alfonsino (<i>Beryx splendens</i>) in NAFO subarea 6.&apos;.</p>
                                          </content>
                                       </point>
                                    </list>
                                 </quotedStructure>
                              </mod>
                           </p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                  </point>
                  <point>
                     <num>(6)</num>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>Article 27 is replaced by the following:</p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>
                              <mod>
                                 <quotedStructure startQuote="" endQuote="">
                                    <article xml:id="art_d90e607">
                                       <num>&apos;Article 27</num>
                                       <heading>Drifting FADs and supply vessels</heading>
                                       <paragraph>
                                          <num>1.</num>
                                          <content>
                                             <p>Drifting FADs shall be equipped with instrumented buoys. The use of any other buoys, such as radio buoys is prohibited.</p>
                                          </content>
                                       </paragraph>
                                       <paragraph>
                                          <num>2.</num>
                                          <content>
                                             <p>A purse seiner shall not follow more than 300 operational buoys at any one time.</p>
                                          </content>
                                       </paragraph>
                                       <paragraph>
                                          <num>3.</num>
                                          <content>
                                             <p>The maximum number of instrumented buoys that may be acquired annually for each purse seine vessel is 500. No purse seine vessel shall have more than 500 instrumented buoys (buoy in stock and operational buoy) at any time.</p>
                                          </content>
                                       </paragraph>
                                       <paragraph>
                                          <num>4.</num>
                                          <content>
                                             <p>The maximum number of supply vessels shall be two supply vessels in support of not less than five purse seiners, all flying the flag of a Member State. This provision shall not apply to Member States using only one supply vessel.</p>
                                          </content>
                                       </paragraph>
                                       <paragraph>
                                          <num>5.</num>
                                          <content>
                                             <p>A single purse seiner shall not be supported by more than one single supply vessel flying the flag of a Member State at any time.</p>
                                          </content>
                                       </paragraph>
                                       <paragraph>
                                          <num>6.</num>
                                          <content>
                                             <p>The Union shall not register new or additional supply vessels in the IOTC record of authorised vessels.&apos;.</p>
                                          </content>
                                       </paragraph>
                                    </article>
                                 </quotedStructure>
                              </mod>
                           </p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                  </point>
                  <point>
                     <num>(7)</num>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>Article 46 is replaced by the following:</p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>
                              <mod>
                                 <quotedStructure startQuote="" endQuote="">
                                    <article xml:id="art_d90e653">
                                       <num>&apos;Article 46</num>
                                       <heading>Limits to bottom fishing</heading>
                                       <paragraph>
                                          <subparagraph>
                                             <content>
                                                <p>Member States shall ensure that vessels flying their flag that are fishing in the SIOFA Agreement Area:</p>
                                             </content>
                                          </subparagraph>
                                          <list>
                                             <point>
                                                <num>(a)</num>
                                                <content>
                                                   <p>limit their annual bottom fishing effort and catch to their average annual level for those years where their vessels were active in the SIOFA Agreement Area, over a representative period for which data declared to the Commission exists;</p>
                                                </content>
                                             </point>
                                             <point>
                                                <num>(b)</num>
                                                <content>
                                                   <p>do not expand the spatial distribution of bottom fishing effort, excluding line and trap methods, beyond areas fished in recent years;</p>
                                                </content>
                                             </point>
                                             <point>
                                                <num>(c)</num>
                                                <content>
                                                   <p>are not authorised to fish in the interim protected areas of Atlantis Bank, Coral, Fools Flat, Middle of What, Walter&apos;s Shoal, as defined in Annex IK, except with line and traps methods and on condition of having a scientific observer on board at all times while fishing in those areas.&apos;.</p>
                                                </content>
                                             </point>
                                          </list>
                                       </paragraph>
                                    </article>
                                 </quotedStructure>
                              </mod>
                           </p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                  </point>
                  <point>
                     <num>(8)</num>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>Article 51 is replaced by the following:</p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>
                              <mod>
                                 <quotedStructure startQuote="" endQuote="">
                                    <article xml:id="art_d90e692">
                                       <num>&apos;<i>Article 51</i>
                                       </num>
                                       <heading>Closed fishing seasons</heading>
                                       <paragraph>
                                          <subparagraph>
                                             <content>
                                                <p>Third-country vessels which are authorised to fish for sandeels and associated by-catches in Union waters of ICES subarea 4 shall not fish for sandeels in that subarea with demersal trawl, seine or similar towed gear with a mesh size of less than 16 mm in the following periods:</p>
                                             </content>
                                          </subparagraph>
                                          <list>
                                             <point>
                                                <num>(a)</num>
                                                <content>
                                                   <p>from 1 August to 31 December 2020;</p>
                                                </content>
                                             </point>
                                             <point>
                                                <num>(b)</num>
                                                <content>
                                                   <p>from 1 January to 31 March 2021.&apos;.</p>
                                                </content>
                                             </point>
                                          </list>
                                       </paragraph>
                                    </article>
                                 </quotedStructure>
                              </mod>
                           </p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                  </point>
                  <point>
                     <num>(9)</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>Annexes IA, ID, IH, and V are amended in accordance with Annex II to this Regulation.</p>
                     </content>
                  </point>
               </list>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <article xml:id="art_d90e735">
            <num>Article 3</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>This Regulation shall enter into force on the day following that of its publication in the <i>Official Journal of the European Union</i>.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>Article 1 and point (3) of Article 2 and point (9) of Article 2 in conjunction with points 1(a) and (e) and points 2 and 3 of Annex II shall apply from 1 January 2020.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>Points (1), (2) and (5) to (8) of Article 2 and point (9) of Article 2 in conjunction with points 1(b), (c) and (d) and point 4 of Annex II shall apply from 1 July 2020.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>Point (4) of Article 2 shall apply from 15 August 2020.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <clause>
            <content>
               <p>This Regulation shall be binding in its entirety and directly applicable in all Member States.</p>
            </content>
         </clause>
      </body>
      <conclusions>
         <p>Done at Brussels, 25 June 2020.</p>
         <block name="signatory">
            <signature>
               <organization refersTo="">For the Council</organization>
               <role refersTo="">The President</role>
               <person refersTo="">A. METELKO-ZGOMBIĆ</person>
            </signature>
         </block>
      </conclusions>
   </bill>
</akomaNtoso>
