<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0"
            xmlns:fmx="http://formex.publications.europa.eu/schema/formex-05.21-20110601.xd"
            xmlns:leos="urn:eu:europa:ec:leos"
            xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema">
   <bill name="">
      <meta xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions">
         <identification source="~COM">
            <FRBRWork>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRcountry value=""/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
         </identification>
      </meta>
      <preface>
         <longTitle>
            <p>
               <docStage/>
               <docType>COMMISSION REGULATION (EU) 2016/441</docType>of 23 March 2016<docPurpose>amending Annex II to Regulation (EC) No 1333/2008 of the European Parliament and of the Council as regards the use of Steviol glycosides (E 960) as a sweetener in mustard</docPurpose>
            </p>
         </longTitle>
         <container name="EEArelevance">
            <p>(Text with EEA relevance)</p>
         </container>
      </preface>
      <preamble>
         <formula name="actingEntity">
            <p>THE EUROPEAN COMMISSION,</p>
         </formula>
         <citations>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to Regulation (EC) No 1333/2008<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="1">
                     <p>OJ L 354, 31.12.2008, p. 16.</p>
                  </authorialNote> of the European Parliament and of the Council of 16 December 2008 on food additives, and in particular Article 10(3) thereof,</p>
            </citation>
         </citations>
         <recitals xml:id="recs_d144e71">
            <intro>
               <p>Whereas:</p>
            </intro>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d144e74">
               <num>(1)</num>
               <p>Annex II to Regulation (EC) No 1333/2008 lays down a Union list of food additives approved for use in food and their conditions of use.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d144e80">
               <num>(2)</num>
               <p>That list may be updated in accordance with the common procedure referred to in Article 3(1) of Regulation (EC) No 1331/2008 of the European Parliament and of the Council<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="2">
                     <p>Regulation (EC) No 1331/2008 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 16 December 2008 establishing a common authorisation procedure for food additives, food enzymes and food flavourings (OJ L 354, 31.12.2008, p. 1).</p>
                  </authorialNote> either on the initiative of the Commission or following an application.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d144e96">
               <num>(3)</num>
               <p>On 23 January 2015 an application was submitted for authorisation of the use of steviol glycosides (E 960) as a sweetener in mustard. The application was subsequently made available to the Member States pursuant to Article 4 of Regulation (EC) No 1331/2008.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d144e105">
               <num>(4)</num>
               <p>Steviol glycosides are non-caloric sweet-tasting constituents which may be used to replace sucrose in the production of mustard thus allowing for an extension of its shelf life and its microbiological stability (decreasing the content of sugar prevents the process of fermentation for which sugar is a substrate) whilst retaining the demanded organoleptic properties of the product. Permitting steviol glycosides in mustard will make it possible to widen the assortment of this product by means of a product containing a sweetener different than those applied hitherto and having slightly other flavour properties.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d144e111">
               <num>(5)</num>
               <p>The European Food Safety Authority (&apos;the Authority&apos;) evaluated the safety of steviol glycosides, extracted from the leaves of the <i>Stevia rebaudiana</i> Bertoni plant, as a sweetener and expressed its opinion on 14 April 2010<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="3">
                     <p>EFSA Journal 2010;8(4):1537.</p>
                  </authorialNote>. The Authority established an Acceptable Daily Intake (ADI) for steviol glycosides, expressed as steviol equivalents, of 4 mg/kg body weight/day.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d144e130">
               <num>(6)</num>
               <p>Authorising this sweetener in mustard at 120 mg/kg (as steviol equivalents) would lead to an increase in the intake of E960 within the following limits: between 0 up to 0,133 % of the ADI in the case of mean consumption and between 0 up to 1,143 % of the ADI in the case of high level consumption. This is considered to be an additional negligible exposure of the consumer and therefore is not of safety concern.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d144e136">
               <num>(7)</num>
               <p>Pursuant to Article 3(2) of Regulation (EC) No 1331/2008, the Commission is to seek the opinion of &apos;the Authority&apos; in order to update the Union list of food additives set out in Annex II to Regulation (EC) No 1333/2008, except where that update is not liable to have an effect on human health. Since the authorisation of use of steviol glycosides (E 960) as a sweetener in mustard constitutes an update of that list which is not liable to have an effect on human health, it is not necessary to seek the opinion of the Authority.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d144e146">
               <num>(8)</num>
               <p>Therefore, it is appropriate to authorise the use of steviol glycosides (E 960) as a sweetener added to mustard (food subcategory 12.4) at maximum level of 120 mg/kg.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d144e153">
               <num>(9)</num>
               <p>Therefore, Annex II to Regulation (EC) No 1333/2008 should be amended accordingly.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d144e160">
               <num>(10)</num>
               <p>The measures provided for in this Regulation are in accordance with the opinion of the Standing Committee on Plants, Animals, Food and Feed,</p>
            </recital>
         </recitals>
         <formula name="enactingFormula">
            <p>HAS ADOPTED THIS REGULATION:</p>
         </formula>
      </preamble>
      <body>
         <article xml:id="art_d144e169">
            <num>Article 1</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>Annex II to Regulation (EC) No 1333/2008 is amended in accordance with the Annex to this Regulation.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <article xml:id="art_d144e174">
            <num>Article 2</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>This Regulation shall enter into force on the twentieth day following that of its publication in the <i>Official Journal of the European Union</i>.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <clause>
            <content>
               <p>This Regulation shall be binding in its entirety and directly applicable in all Member States.</p>
            </content>
         </clause>
      </body>
      <conclusions>
         <p>Done at Brussels, 23 March 2016.</p>
         <block name="signatory">
            <signature>
               <organization refersTo="">For the Commission</organization>
               <role refersTo="">The President</role>
               <person refersTo="">Jean-Claude JUNCKER</person>
            </signature>
         </block>
      </conclusions>
   </bill>
</akomaNtoso>
