<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0"
            xmlns:fmx="http://formex.publications.europa.eu/schema/formex-05.21-20110601.xd"
            xmlns:leos="urn:eu:europa:ec:leos"
            xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema">
   <bill name="">
      <meta xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions">
         <identification source="~COM">
            <FRBRWork>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRcountry value=""/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
         </identification>
      </meta>
      <preface>
         <longTitle>
            <p>
               <docStage/>
               <docType>COMMISSION REGULATION (EU) 2020/1085</docType>of 23 July 2020<docPurpose>amending Annexes II and V to Regulation (EC) No 396/2005 of the European Parliament and of the Council as regards maximum residue levels for chlorpyrifos and chlorpyrifos-methyl in or on certain products</docPurpose>
            </p>
         </longTitle>
         <container name="EEArelevance">
            <p>(Text with EEA relevance)</p>
         </container>
      </preface>
      <preamble>
         <formula name="actingEntity">
            <p>THE EUROPEAN COMMISSION,</p>
         </formula>
         <citations>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to Regulation (EC) No 396/2005 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 23 February 2005 on maximum residue levels of pesticides in or on food and feed of plant and animal origin and amending Council Directive 91/414/EEC<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="1">
                     <p>OJ L 70, 16.3.2005, p. 1.</p>
                  </authorialNote>, and in particular Article 14(1)(a) and Article 18(1)(b) thereof,</p>
            </citation>
         </citations>
         <recitals xml:id="recs_d130e71">
            <intro>
               <p>Whereas:</p>
            </intro>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d130e74">
               <num>(1)</num>
               <p>For chlorpyrifos and chlorpyrifos-methyl, maximum residue levels (MRLs) were set in Annex II to Regulation (EC) No 396/2005.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d130e80">
               <num>(2)</num>
               <p>The approvals of the active substances chlorpyrifos and chlorpyrifos-methyl were not renewed by Commission Implementing Regulation (EU) 2020/18<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="2">
                     <p>Commission Implementing Regulation (EU) 2020/18 of 10 January 2020 concerning the non-renewal of approval of the active substance chlorpyrifos, in accordance with Regulation (EC) No 1107/2009 of the European Parliament and of the Council concerning the placing of plant protection products on the market, and amending Commission Implementing Regulation (EU) No 540/2011 (OJ L 7, 13.1.2020, p. 14).</p>
                  </authorialNote> and Commission Implementing Regulation (EU) 2020/17<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="3">
                     <p>Commission Implementing Regulation (EU) 2020/17 of 10 January 2020 concerning the non-renewal of approval of the active substance chlorpyrifos-methyl, in accordance with Regulation (EC) No 1107/2009 of the European Parliament and of the Council concerning the placing of plant protection products on the market, and amending Commission Implementing Regulation (EU) No 540/2011 (OJ L 7, 13.1.2020, p. 11).</p>
                  </authorialNote>, respectively.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d130e106">
               <num>(3)</num>
               <p>All existing authorisations for plant protection products containing chlorpyrifos and chlorpyrifos-methyl have been revoked. It is therefore appropriate to delete the MRLs set out for these substances in Annex II to Regulation (EC) No 396/2005 in accordance with Article 17 of Regulation (EC) No 396/2005 in conjunction with Article 14(1)(a) thereof.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d130e112">
               <num>(4)</num>
               <p>The Commission consulted the European Union reference laboratories as regards the need to adapt certain limits of determination (LODs) for the two substances. Those laboratories concluded that technical development permits the setting of LODs at 0,01 mg/kg for chlorpyrifos and chlorpyrifos-methyl in all products. Those default values should be listed in Annex V in accordance with Article 18(1)(b) of Regulation (EC) No 396/2005.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d130e118">
               <num>(5)</num>
               <p>In the context of the non-renewal of the approval of chlorpyrifos and chlorpyrifos-methyl, the European Food Safety Authority (&apos;the Authority&apos;) published statements on the human health assessment for those active substances<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="4">
                     <p>Statement on the available outcomes of the human health assessment in the context of the pesticides peer review of the active substance chlorpyrifos. <i>EFSA Journal</i> 2019;17(5):5809.</p>
                  </authorialNote>
                  <authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="5">
                     <p>Updated statement on the available outcomes of the human health assessment in the context of the pesticides peer review of the active substance chlorpyrifos-methyl. <i>EFSA Journal</i> 2019;17(11):5908.</p>
                  </authorialNote>. In those statements the Authority confirmed developmental neurotoxicity of both active substances in children and could not exclude a genotoxic potential due to the exposure to residues of the two substances in food.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d130e141">
               <num>(6)</num>
               <p>Through the World Trade Organisation, the trading partners of the Union were consulted on the new MRLs and their comments have been taken into account.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d130e147">
               <num>(7)</num>
               <p>Regulation (EC) No 396/2005 should therefore be amended accordingly.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d130e154">
               <num>(8)</num>
               <p>A reasonable period should be allowed to elapse before the modified MRLs become applicable in order to permit Member States, third countries and food business operators to prepare themselves to meet the new requirements which will result from the modification of the MRLs.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d130e160">
               <num>(9)</num>
               <p>The measures provided for in this Regulation are in accordance with the opinion of the Standing Committee on Plants, Animals, Food and Feed,</p>
            </recital>
         </recitals>
         <formula name="enactingFormula">
            <p>HAS ADOPTED THIS REGULATION:</p>
         </formula>
      </preamble>
      <body>
         <article xml:id="art_d130e169">
            <num>Article 1</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>Annexes II and V to Regulation (EC) No 396/2005 are amended in accordance with the Annex to this Regulation.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <article xml:id="art_d130e174">
            <num>Article 2</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>This Regulation shall enter into force on the twentieth day following that of its publication in the <i>Official Journal of the European Union</i>.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>It shall apply from 6 August 2020.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <clause>
            <content>
               <p>This Regulation shall be binding in its entirety and directly applicable in all Member States.</p>
            </content>
         </clause>
      </body>
      <conclusions>
         <p>Done at Brussels, 23 July 2020.</p>
         <block name="signatory">
            <signature>
               <organization refersTo="">For the Commission</organization>
               <role refersTo="">The President</role>
               <person refersTo="">Ursula VON DER LEYEN</person>
            </signature>
         </block>
      </conclusions>
   </bill>
</akomaNtoso>
