<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0"
            xmlns:fmx="http://formex.publications.europa.eu/schema/formex-05.21-20110601.xd"
            xmlns:leos="urn:eu:europa:ec:leos"
            xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema">
   <bill name="">
      <meta xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions">
         <identification source="~COM">
            <FRBRWork>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRcountry value=""/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
         </identification>
      </meta>
      <preface>
         <longTitle>
            <p>
               <docStage/>
               <docType>COMMISSION REGULATION (EU) 2019/1892</docType>of 31 October 2019<docPurpose>amending Regulation (EU) No 1230/2012 as regards type-approval requirements for certain motor vehicles fitted with elongated cabs and for aerodynamic devices and equipment for motor vehicles and their trailers</docPurpose>
            </p>
         </longTitle>
         <container name="EEArelevance">
            <p>(Text with EEA relevance)</p>
         </container>
      </preface>
      <preamble>
         <formula name="actingEntity">
            <p>THE EUROPEAN COMMISSION,</p>
         </formula>
         <citations>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to Regulation (EC) No 661/2009 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 13 July 2009 concerning type-approval requirements for the general safety of motor vehicles, their trailers and systems, components and separate technical units intended therefor<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="1">
                     <p>OJ L 200, 31.7.2009, p. 1.</p>
                  </authorialNote>, and in particular Article 14(1)(a) thereof,</p>
            </citation>
         </citations>
         <recitals xml:id="recs_d607e71">
            <intro>
               <p>Whereas:</p>
            </intro>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d607e74">
               <num>(1)</num>
               <p>Commission Regulation (EU) No 1230/2012<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="2">
                     <p>Commission Regulation (EU) No 1230/2012 of 12 December 2012 implementing Regulation (EC) No 661/2009 of the European Parliament and of the Council with regard to type-approval requirements for masses and dimensions of motor vehicles and their trailers and amending Directive 2007/46/EC of the European Parliament and of the Council (OJ L 353, 21.12.2012, p. 31).</p>
                  </authorialNote> implements Regulation (EC) No 661/2009 through laying down requirements for the EC type-approval of motor vehicles and their trailers with regard to their masses and dimensions.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d607e90">
               <num>(2)</num>
               <p>Aerodynamic devices and equipment, such as for instance retractable or foldable flaps attached to the rear of trucks and their trailers, as well as aerodynamic devices and equipment for cabs are currently available technology with a potential for improving the aerodynamic performance of vehicles. However, due to their design, those devices and equipment may project beyond the outermost part at the front, back or laterally of the vehicles on which they are fitted. Therefore, vehicles fitted with such devices and equipment should be exempted from the requirements relating to the standard dimensions.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d607e96">
               <num>(3)</num>
               <p>Council Directive 96/53/EC<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="3">
                     <p>Council Directive 96/53/EC of 25 July 1996 laying down for certain road vehicles circulating within the Community the maximum authorised dimensions in national and international traffic and the maximum authorised weights in international traffic (OJ L 235, 17.9.1996, p. 59).</p>
                  </authorialNote> was amended by Directive (EU) 2015/719 of the European Parliament and of the Council<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="4">
                     <p>Directive (EU) 2015/719 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 29 April 2015 amending Council Directive 96/53/EC laying down for certain road vehicles circulating within the Community the maximum authorised dimensions in national and international traffic and the maximum authorised weights in international traffic (OJ L 115, 6.5.2015, p. 1).</p>
                  </authorialNote> and by Regulation (EU) 2019/1242 of the European Parliament and of the Council<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="5">
                     <p>Regulation (EU) 2019/1242 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 20 June 2019 setting CO<sub>2</sub> emission performance standards for new heavy-duty vehicles and amending Regulations (EC) No 595/2009 and (EU) 2018/956 of the European Parliament and of the Council and Council Directive 96/53/EC (OJ L 198, 25.7.2019, p. 202).</p>
                  </authorialNote> to provide for a derogation from the maximum length and weight restrictions in order to allow the use of motor vehicles with improved aerodynamic characteristics and alternatively fuelled or zero-emission motor vehicles, respectively, in cross-border traffic.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d607e136">
               <num>(4)</num>
               <p>With a view to ensuring coherence between EC type-approval legislation and the harmonised rules for road vehicles circulating within the Union, it is necessary to lay down type-approval requirements for motor vehicles with elongated cabs and for aerodynamic equipment or devices in order to ensure that they provide benefits in terms of energy performance, better visibility for drivers, safety to other road users as well as safety and comfort for drivers.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d607e142">
               <num>(5)</num>
               <p>It is not possible for an approval authority to certify that a type of aerodynamic device and equipment satisfies the relevant technical requirements independently of a vehicle. Such aerodynamic devices and equipment should therefore be type-approved in relation to one or more specified types of vehicles or in relation to generic vehicles for which the precise dimensions and material specifications at the installation location are defined. For that reason, they should be type-approved as separate technical units and the specific requirements for their approval before being placed on the market should be set out. Elongated cabs should be subject to a vehicle type-approval, respectively, as required by Directive 96/53/EC.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d607e148">
               <num>(6)</num>
               <p>Compliance with the upcoming CO<sub>2</sub> emission standards for heavy duty vehicles will require the application of various technologies to improve energy efficiency. One of the most efficient measures to improve energy efficiency is to reduce air drag of motor vehicles.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d607e157">
               <num>(7)</num>
               <p>Retractable or foldable aerodynamic devices attached to the rear of trucks and their trailers and aerodynamic devices and equipment of cabs should be constructed in such a way to ensure that they do not impair the capability of the vehicle to be used for intermodal transport. Therefore, the maximum width of 2,60 m should apply to all vehicles, including the refrigerated ones. In addition, the aerodynamic devices should be able to resist the displacement of air generated by operational circumstances in intermodal transport.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d607e163">
               <num>(8)</num>
               <p>Alternatively fuelled or zero-emission motor vehicles should benefit from extra weight allowance. The additional weight required for the alternative fuel or zero-emission technology should be clearly indicated on the manufacturer&apos;s statutory plate.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d607e169">
               <num>(9)</num>
               <p>Regulation (EU) No 1230/2012 should therefore be amended accordingly.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d607e176">
               <num>(10)</num>
               <p>The measures provided for in this Regulation are in accordance with the opinion of the Technical Committee &#45; Motor Vehicles,</p>
            </recital>
         </recitals>
         <formula name="enactingFormula">
            <p>HAS ADOPTED THIS REGULATION:</p>
         </formula>
      </preamble>
      <body>
         <article xml:id="art_d607e185" leos:compliant="false">
            <num>Article 1</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <subparagraph>
                  <content>
                     <p>Regulation (EU) No 1230/2012 is amended as follows:</p>
                  </content>
               </subparagraph>
               <list>
                  <point>
                     <num>(1)</num>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>in Article 1, paragraph 1 is replaced by the following:</p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>
                              <mod>
                                 <quotedStructure startQuote="" endQuote="">
                                    <paragraph>
                                       <num>&apos;1.</num>
                                       <content>
                                          <p>This Regulation lays down the requirements for the EC type-approval of motor vehicles and their trailers with regard to their masses and dimensions as well as of certain separate technical units intended for those vehicles.&apos;;</p>
                                       </content>
                                    </paragraph>
                                 </quotedStructure>
                              </mod>
                           </p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                  </point>
                  <point>
                     <num>(2)</num>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>Article 2 is amended as follows:</p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                     <list>
                        <point>
                           <num>(a)</num>
                           <alinea>
                              <content>
                                 <p>points (25) and (26) are replaced by the following:</p>
                              </content>
                           </alinea>
                           <alinea>
                              <content>
                                 <p>
                                    <mod>
                                       <quotedStructure startQuote="" endQuote="">
                                          <list>
                                             <point>
                                                <num>&apos;(25)</num>
                                                <alinea>
                                                   <content>
                                                      <p>&quot;wheelbase&quot; means the following:</p>
                                                   </content>
                                                </alinea>
                                                <list>
                                                   <point>
                                                      <num>(a)</num>
                                                      <content>
                                                         <p>for motor vehicles and drawbar trailers, the horizontal distance between the centre of the first and the last axle;</p>
                                                      </content>
                                                   </point>
                                                   <point>
                                                      <num>(b)</num>
                                                      <content>
                                                         <p>for centre-axle trailers, semi-trailers and rigid drawbar trailers, the distance between the vertical axis of the coupling and the centre of the last axle;</p>
                                                      </content>
                                                   </point>
                                                </list>
                                             </point>
                                             <point>
                                                <num>(26)</num>
                                                <content>
                                                   <p>&quot;axle spacing&quot; means the distance between two consecutive axles; for centre axle trailers, semi-trailers and rigid drawbar trailers, the first axle spacing is the horizontal distance between the vertical axis of the front coupling and the centre of the first axle;&apos;;</p>
                                                </content>
                                             </point>
                                          </list>
                                       </quotedStructure>
                                    </mod>
                                 </p>
                              </content>
                           </alinea>
                        </point>
                        <point>
                           <num>(b)</num>
                           <alinea>
                              <content>
                                 <p>point (33) is replaced by the following:</p>
                              </content>
                           </alinea>
                           <alinea>
                              <content>
                                 <p>
                                    <mod>
                                       <quotedStructure startQuote="" endQuote="">
                                          <list>
                                             <point>
                                                <num>&apos;(33)</num>
                                                <content>
                                                   <p>&quot;rear swing-out&quot; means the distance between the initial point and the actual extreme point reached by the rear end of a vehicle when manoeuvring in the conditions specified in Section 8 of Part B of Annex I or in Section 7 of Part C of that Annex;&apos;;</p>
                                                </content>
                                             </point>
                                          </list>
                                       </quotedStructure>
                                    </mod>
                                 </p>
                              </content>
                           </alinea>
                        </point>
                        <point>
                           <num>(c)</num>
                           <alinea>
                              <content>
                                 <p>the following point (41) is added:</p>
                              </content>
                           </alinea>
                           <alinea>
                              <content>
                                 <p>
                                    <mod>
                                       <quotedStructure startQuote="" endQuote="">
                                          <list>
                                             <point>
                                                <num>&apos;(41)</num>
                                                <content>
                                                   <p>&quot;aerodynamic devices and equipment&quot; mean devices or equipment that are designed to reduce the aerodynamic drag of road vehicles, with the exception of elongated cabs.&apos;;</p>
                                                </content>
                                             </point>
                                          </list>
                                       </quotedStructure>
                                    </mod>
                                 </p>
                              </content>
                           </alinea>
                        </point>
                     </list>
                  </point>
                  <point>
                     <num>(3)</num>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>the following Articles 4a and 4b are inserted:</p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>
                              <mod>
                                 <quotedStructure startQuote="" endQuote="">
                                    <article xml:id="art_d607e311">
                                       <num>&apos;Article 4a</num>
                                       <heading>EC separate technical unit type-approval of aerodynamic devices and equipment</heading>
                                       <paragraph>
                                          <num>1.</num>
                                          <subparagraph>
                                             <content>
                                                <p>The manufacturer or his representative shall submit to the type-approval authority the application for EC type-approval of an aerodynamic device or equipment as a separate technical unit.</p>
                                             </content>
                                          </subparagraph>
                                          <subparagraph>
                                             <content>
                                                <p>The application shall be drawn up in accordance with the model of the information document set out in Part C of Annex V.</p>
                                             </content>
                                          </subparagraph>
                                       </paragraph>
                                       <paragraph>
                                          <num>2.</num>
                                          <subparagraph>
                                             <content>
                                                <p>If the relevant requirements set out in this Regulation are met, the approval authority shall grant an EC separate technical unit type-approval and issue a type-approval number in accordance with the numbering system set out in Annex VII to Directive 2007/46/EC</p>
                                             </content>
                                          </subparagraph>
                                          <subparagraph>
                                             <content>
                                                <p>A Member State shall not assign the same number to another type of separate technical unit.</p>
                                             </content>
                                          </subparagraph>
                                       </paragraph>
                                       <paragraph>
                                          <num>3.</num>
                                          <content>
                                             <p>For the purposes of paragraph 2, the type-approval authority shall deliver an EC type-approval certificate established in accordance with the model set out in Part D of Annex V.</p>
                                          </content>
                                       </paragraph>
                                    </article>
                                    <article xml:id="art_d607e336">
                                       <num>Article 4b</num>
                                       <heading>EC separate technical unit type-approval mark</heading>
                                       <paragraph>
                                          <content>
                                             <p>Every separate technical unit conforming to a type in respect of which EC separate technical unit type-approval has been granted pursuant to this Regulation shall bear an EC separate technical unit type-approval mark as set out in Part E of Annex V.&apos;;</p>
                                          </content>
                                       </paragraph>
                                    </article>
                                 </quotedStructure>
                              </mod>
                           </p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                  </point>
                  <point>
                     <num>(4)</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>Annex I is amended in accordance with Annex I to this Regulation;</p>
                     </content>
                  </point>
                  <point>
                     <num>(5)</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>Annex V is amended in accordance with Annex II to this Regulation.</p>
                     </content>
                  </point>
               </list>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <article xml:id="art_d607e357">
            <num>Article 2</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>This Regulation shall enter into force on the twentieth day following that of its publication in the <i>Official Journal of the European Union</i>.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <clause>
            <content>
               <p>This Regulation shall be binding in its entirety and directly applicable in all Member States.</p>
            </content>
         </clause>
      </body>
      <conclusions>
         <p>Done at Brussels, 31 October 2019.</p>
         <block name="signatory">
            <signature>
               <organization refersTo="">For the Commission</organization>
               <role refersTo="">The President</role>
               <person refersTo="">Jean-Claude JUNCKER</person>
            </signature>
         </block>
      </conclusions>
   </bill>
</akomaNtoso>
