<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0"
            xmlns:fmx="http://formex.publications.europa.eu/schema/formex-05.21-20110601.xd"
            xmlns:leos="urn:eu:europa:ec:leos"
            xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema">
   <bill name="">
      <meta xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions">
         <identification source="~COM">
            <FRBRWork>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRcountry value=""/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
         </identification>
      </meta>
      <preface>
         <longTitle>
            <p>
               <docStage/>
               <docType>COMMISSION REGULATION (EU) 2021/1881</docType>of 26 October 2021<docPurpose>amending Annexes II and III to Regulation (EC) No 396/2005 of the European Parliament and of the Council as regards maximum residue levels for imidacloprid in or on certain products</docPurpose>
            </p>
         </longTitle>
         <container name="EEArelevance">
            <p>(Text with EEA relevance)</p>
         </container>
      </preface>
      <preamble>
         <formula name="actingEntity">
            <p>THE EUROPEAN COMMISSION,</p>
         </formula>
         <citations>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to Regulation (EC) No 396/2005 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 23 February 2005 on maximum residue levels of pesticides in or on food and feed of plant and animal origin and amending Council Directive 91/414/EEC<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="1">
                     <p>OJ L 070, 16.3.2005, p. 1.</p>
                  </authorialNote>, and in particular Article 14(1)(a) and Article 49(2) thereof,</p>
            </citation>
         </citations>
         <recitals xml:id="recs_d606e71">
            <intro>
               <p>Whereas:</p>
            </intro>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d606e74">
               <num>(1)</num>
               <p>Maximum residue levels (MRLs) for imidacloprid were set in Part A of Annex III to Regulation (EC) No 396/2005.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d606e80">
               <num>(2)</num>
               <p>The European Food Safety Authority (&apos;the Authority&apos;) submitted a reasoned opinion on the review of the existing MRLs for imidacloprid in accordance with Article 12(1) of Regulation (EC) No 396/2005<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="2">
                     <p>European Food Safety Authority; Reasoned opinion on the review of the existing maximum residue levels for imidacloprid according to Article 12 of Regulation (EC) No 396/2005. <i>EFSA Journal</i> 2019;17(1):5570.</p>
                  </authorialNote>. The Authority recommended setting the residue definition as imidacloprid only. It identified a risk for consumers concerning the MRLs for escaroles/broad-leaved endives. It is therefore appropriate to lower this MRL to the specific limit of determination (LOD). The Authority recommended lowering the MRLs for pecans, bananas, tomatoes, sweet peppers/bell peppers, aubergines/eggplants, cucumbers, gherkins, courgettes and products of animal origin. The MRLs for those products should be set in Annex II to Regulation (EC) No 396/2005 at the level identified by the Authority.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d606e97">
               <num>(3)</num>
               <p>The Authority concluded that concerning the MRLs for citrus fruits, grapes, blueberries, cranberries, okra/lady&apos;s fingers, cucurbits with inedible peel, beans (with and without pods), peas (with and without pods), beans, peanuts/groundnuts, coffee beans and hops, some information was not available and that further consideration by risk managers was required. As there is no risk for consumers, the MRLs for those products should also be set in Annex II to Regulation (EC) No 396/2005 at the level identified by the Authority. These MRLs will be reviewed; the review will take into account the information available within one year from the publication of this Regulation.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d606e103">
               <num>(4)</num>
               <p>Existing Codex maximum residue limits (CXLs) were taken into account in the reasoned opinions of the Authority. Concerning the CXLs, the Authority concluded that they are not compatible with the EU residue definition and recommended not to include the existing CXLs in Annex II to Regulation (EC) No 396/2005. It is therefore appropriate to set those MRLs to the level identified by the Authority.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d606e109">
               <num>(5)</num>
               <p>As regards products on which the use of the plant protection product concerned is not authorised, and for which no import tolerances or CXLs exist, MRLs should be set at the specific LOD or the default MRL should apply, as provided for in Article 18(1)(b) of Regulation (EC) No 396/2005.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d606e116">
               <num>(6)</num>
               <p>The Commission consulted the European Union reference laboratories for residues of pesticides as regards the need to adapt certain limits of determination. Those laboratories concluded that for certain commodities technical development requires the setting of specific LODs.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d606e122">
               <num>(7)</num>
               <p>Based on the reasoned opinions of the Authority and taking into account the factors relevant to the matter under consideration, the appropriate modifications to the MRLs fulfil the requirements of Article 14(2) of Regulation (EC) No 396/2005.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d606e128">
               <num>(8)</num>
               <p>Through the World Trade Organisation, the trading partners of the Union were consulted on the new MRLs and their comments have been taken into account.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d606e134">
               <num>(9)</num>
               <p>Regulation (EC) No 396/2005 should therefore be amended accordingly.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d606e141">
               <num>(10)</num>
               <p>In order to allow for the normal marketing, processing and consumption of products, this Regulation should provide for a transitional arrangement for products which have been produced before the modification of the MRLs and for which information shows that a high level of consumer protection is maintained.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d606e147">
               <num>(11)</num>
               <p>A reasonable period should be allowed to elapse before the modified MRLs become applicable in order to permit Member States, third countries and food business operators to prepare themselves to meet the new requirements which will result from the modification of the MRLs.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d606e153">
               <num>(12)</num>
               <p>The approval of imidacloprid expired on 1 December 2020<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="3">
                     <p>OJ L 370, 6.11.2020, p. 18.</p>
                  </authorialNote>. Any grace periods that may have been granted by Member States will expire on 1 June 2022. A further review of maximum residue levels is envisaged after that date.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d606e170">
               <num>(13)</num>
               <p>The measures provided for in this Regulation are in accordance with the opinion of the Standing Committee on Plants, Animals, Food and Feed,</p>
            </recital>
         </recitals>
         <formula name="enactingFormula">
            <p>HAS ADOPTED THIS REGULATION:</p>
         </formula>
      </preamble>
      <body>
         <article xml:id="art_d606e179">
            <num>Article 1</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>Annexes II and III to Regulation (EC) No 396/2005 are amended in accordance with the Annex to this Regulation.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <article xml:id="art_d606e184">
            <num>Article 2</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>As regards the active substance imidacloprid in and on all products except escaroles, Regulation (EC) No 396/2005 as it stood before being amended by this Regulation shall continue to apply to products, which were produced in the Union or imported into the Union before 16 May 2022.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <article xml:id="art_d606e192">
            <num>Article 3</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>This Regulation shall enter into force on the twentieth day following that of its publication in the <i>Official Journal of the European Union</i>.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>It shall apply from 16 May 2022.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <clause>
            <content>
               <p>This Regulation shall be binding in its entirety and directly applicable in all Member States.</p>
            </content>
         </clause>
      </body>
      <conclusions>
         <p>Done at Brussels, 26 October 2021.</p>
         <block name="signatory">
            <signature>
               <organization refersTo="">For the Commission</organization>
               <role refersTo="">The President</role>
               <person refersTo="">Ursula VON DER LEYEN</person>
            </signature>
         </block>
      </conclusions>
   </bill>
</akomaNtoso>
