<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0"
            xmlns:fmx="http://formex.publications.europa.eu/schema/formex-05.21-20110601.xd"
            xmlns:leos="urn:eu:europa:ec:leos"
            xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema">
   <bill name="">
      <meta xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions">
         <identification source="~COM">
            <FRBRWork>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRcountry value=""/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
         </identification>
      </meta>
      <preface>
         <longTitle>
            <p>
               <docStage/>
               <docType>COUNCIL REGULATION (EU) 2019/998</docType>of 13 June 2019<docPurpose>amending Regulation (EU) No 1388/2013 opening and providing for the management of autonomous tariff quotas of the Union for certain agricultural and industrial products</docPurpose>
            </p>
         </longTitle>
      </preface>
      <preamble>
         <formula name="actingEntity">
            <p>THE COUNCIL OF THE EUROPEAN UNION,</p>
         </formula>
         <citations>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union, and in particular Article 31 thereof,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the proposal from the European Commission,</p>
            </citation>
         </citations>
         <recitals xml:id="recs_d286e59">
            <intro>
               <p>Whereas:</p>
            </intro>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d286e62">
               <num>(1)</num>
               <p>In order to ensure the sufficient and uninterrupted supply of certain agricultural and industrial products which are produced in insufficient quantities in the Union and thereby avoid any disturbances on the market for those products, autonomous tariff quotas were opened by Council Regulation (EU) No 1388/2013<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="1">
                     <p>Council Regulation (EU) No 1388/2013 of 17 December 2013 opening and providing for the management of autonomous tariff quotas of the Union for certain agricultural and industrial products, and repealing Regulation (EU) No 7/2010 (OJ L 354, 28.12.2013, p. 319).</p>
                  </authorialNote>. Within those tariff quotas, products can be imported into the Union at reduced or zero duty rates.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d286e78">
               <num>(2)</num>
               <p>As it is in the Union&apos;s interest to ensure an adequate supply of certain industrial products and having regard to the fact that identical, equivalent or substitute products are not produced in sufficient quantities within the Union, it is necessary to open new tariff quotas with order numbers 09.2594, 09.2595, 09.2596, 09.2597, 09.2598 and 09.2599 at zero duty rates for appropriate quantities of those products.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d286e84">
               <num>(3)</num>
               <p>In the case of the tariff quotas with order numbers 09.2679, 09.2683 and 09.2888, the quota volumes should be increased, as an increase is in the interest of the Union. In the case of the tariff quota bearing order number 09.2723, the quota volume should be increased retroactively for the period from 1 January to 31 December 2018.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d286e96">
               <num>(4)</num>
               <p>For the tariff quota with order number 09.2740, the products covered by that tariff quota are covered not only by CN code 23099096 but also by CN code 23099031. The indication of the CN code for that tariff quota should therefore be adapted.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d286e108">
               <num>(5)</num>
               <p>As it is no longer in the Union&apos;s interest to maintain the tariff quota with order number 09.2870, it should be closed with effect from 1 July 2019.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d286e117">
               <num>(6)</num>
               <p>The tariff quotas with order numbers 09.2633, 09.2643, 09.2620 and 09.2932 should be closed as a result of the implementation of the agreement in the form of the Declaration on the Expansion of Trade in Information Technology Products<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="2">
                     <p>OJ L 161, 18.6.2016, p. 4.</p>
                  </authorialNote>, which reduced the duty rate for the products concerned to zero.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d286e129">
               <num>(7)</num>
               <p>Taking into account the amendments to be made and for the sake of clarity, the Annex to Regulation (EU) No 1388/2013 should be replaced.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d286e136">
               <num>(8)</num>
               <p>In order to avoid any interruption of the application of the tariff quota scheme and to comply with the guidelines set out in the communication from the Commission concerning autonomous tariff suspensions and quotas<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="3">
                     <p>OJ C 363, 13.12.2011, p. 6.</p>
                  </authorialNote>, the changes provided for in this Regulation regarding the tariff quotas for the products concerned should apply from 1 July 2019 and, for the tariff quota with order number 09.2723, from 1 January 2018. This Regulation should therefore enter into force as a matter of urgency,</p>
            </recital>
         </recitals>
         <formula name="enactingFormula">
            <p>HAS ADOPTED THIS REGULATION:</p>
         </formula>
      </preamble>
      <body>
         <article xml:id="art_d286e157" leos:compliant="false">
            <num>Article 1</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <subparagraph>
                  <content>
                     <p>The Annex to Regulation (EU) No 1388/2013 is amended as follows:</p>
                  </content>
               </subparagraph>
               <list>
                  <point>
                     <num>(1)</num>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>the row for tariff quota with order number 09.2723 is replaced by the following:</p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>
                              <mod>
                                 <quotedStructure startQuote="" endQuote="">
                                    <alinea>
                                       <content>
                                          <table class="TBL">
                                             <tr>
                                                <td>
                                                   <p>&apos;09.2723</p>
                                                </td>
                                                <td>
                                                   <p>ex39119019</p>
                                                </td>
                                                <td>
                                                   <p>10</p>
                                                </td>
                                                <td>
                                                   <p>Poly(oxy-1,4-phenylenesulphonyl-1,4-phenyleneoxy-4,4′-biphenylene)</p>
                                                </td>
                                                <td>
                                                   <p>1.1.-31.12.</p>
                                                </td>
                                                <td>
                                                   <p>5000 tonnes</p>
                                                </td>
                                                <td>
                                                   <p>0 %&apos;</p>
                                                </td>
                                             </tr>
                                          </table>
                                       </content>
                                    </alinea>
                                 </quotedStructure>
                              </mod>
                           </p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                  </point>
                  <point>
                     <num>(2)</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>it is replaced by the text set out in the Annex to this Regulation.</p>
                     </content>
                  </point>
               </list>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <article xml:id="art_d286e201">
            <num>Article 2</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>This Regulation shall enter into force on the day following that of its publication in the <i>Official Journal of the European Union</i>.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>It shall apply from 1 July 2019. However, point (1) of Article 1 shall apply from 1 January 2018.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <clause>
            <content>
               <p>This Regulation shall be binding in its entirety and directly applicable in all Member States.</p>
            </content>
         </clause>
      </body>
      <conclusions>
         <p>Done at Luxembourg, 13 June 2019.</p>
         <block name="signatory">
            <signature>
               <organization refersTo="">For the Council</organization>
               <role refersTo="">The President</role>
               <person refersTo="">M.C. BUDĂI</person>
            </signature>
         </block>
      </conclusions>
   </bill>
</akomaNtoso>
