<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0"
            xmlns:fmx="http://formex.publications.europa.eu/schema/formex-05.21-20110601.xd"
            xmlns:leos="urn:eu:europa:ec:leos"
            xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema">
   <bill name="">
      <meta xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions">
         <identification source="~COM">
            <FRBRWork>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRcountry value=""/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
         </identification>
      </meta>
      <preface>
         <longTitle>
            <p>
               <docStage/>
               <docType>COUNCIL REGULATION (EU) 2021/2048</docType>of 23 November 2021<docPurpose>temporarily suspending autonomous Common Customs Tariff duties on imports of certain industrial products into the Canary Islands</docPurpose>
            </p>
         </longTitle>
      </preface>
      <preamble>
         <formula name="actingEntity">
            <p>THE COUNCIL OF THE EUROPEAN UNION,</p>
         </formula>
         <citations>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union, and in particular Article 349 thereof,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the proposal from the European Commission,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>After transmission of the draft legislative act to the national parliaments,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the opinion of the European Parliament<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="1">
                     <p>Opinion of 5 October 2021 (not yet published in the Official Journal).</p>
                  </authorialNote>,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the opinion of the European Economic and Social Committee<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="2">
                     <p>Opinion of 20 October 2021 (not yet published in the Official Journal).</p>
                  </authorialNote>,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>Acting in accordance with a special legislative procedure,</p>
            </citation>
         </citations>
         <recitals xml:id="recs_d625e81">
            <intro>
               <p>Whereas:</p>
            </intro>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d625e84">
               <num>(1)</num>
               <p>In accordance with Council Regulation (EU) No 1386/2011<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="3">
                     <p>Council Regulation (EU) No 1386/2011 of 19 December 2011 temporarily suspending autonomous Common Customs Tariff duties on imports of certain industrial products into the Canary Islands (OJ L 345, 29.12.2011, p. 1).</p>
                  </authorialNote>, the duty suspension for certain capital goods for commercial or industrial use, imported into the Canary Islands, is to expire on 31 December 2021.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d625e103">
               <num>(2)</num>
               <p>In April 2021, the Government of Spain requested the prolongation of the suspension of the autonomous Common Customs Tariff duties for a number of products in accordance with Article 349 of the Treaty. Measures established by Regulation (EU) No 1386/2011 positively contributed to the development of the Canary Islands&apos; economy, in particular in industry and construction, thus reducing the severe impact of economic and commercial disadvantages caused by the remoteness, insularity and small size of those islands.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d625e109">
               <num>(3)</num>
               <p>The Canary Islands&apos; economy continues to be negatively affected by the small size of the islands&apos; market, its fragmentation and remoteness from continental Europe, a particularly high level of unemployment and higher production and distribution costs than those of economic operators in continental Europe. While the Canary Islands&apos; unemployment rate showed some improvement up to 2019, unemployment increased from 20,5 % in 2019 to 22,6 % in 2020, well above an average unemployement rate in 2020 of 15,5 % in Spain and of 7,1 % in the Member States collectively (Eurostat, 2021).</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d625e115">
               <num>(4)</num>
               <p>Moreover, the COVID-19 pandemic halted tourism activity in the Canary Islands which, in 2020, led to an estimated drop of around 20 % in the GDP. In addition, there was a contraction in the construction and industrial activity with an estimated decline of 13 %, in comparison to 2019.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d625e122">
               <num>(5)</num>
               <p>It is therefore appropriate to prolong the suspension of the Common Customs Tariff duties for certain goods as listed in Annexes I and II to Regulation (EU) No 1386/2011 in order to ensure sustainability of the positive effects of Regulation (EU) No 1386/2011, contribute to the diversification of the economy, ensure constant growth and the creation of jobs in industry and construction, enhance innovation, reduce the dependence of the local economy on the service sector and complement other measures dedicated to the stabilisation of the economic and social environment in the Canary Islands.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d625e128">
               <num>(6)</num>
               <p>In addition to the product categories covered by Regulation (EU) No 1386/2011, the Government of Spain has requested the suspension of the Common Customs Tariff duties for seven new product categories falling under CN codes 390319, 560394, 560410, 732690, 760720, 844140 and 847990. That request should be accepted as those suspensions, which include suspensions for machines for industrial purposes and raw materials, would strengthen the economy of the Canary Islands.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d625e156">
               <num>(7)</num>
               <p>In order to ensure that only economic operators located on the territory of the Canary Islands benefit from those tariff measures, the suspensions should be made conditional on the end-use of the products, in accordance with Regulation (EU) No 952/2013 of the European Parliament and of the Council<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="4">
                     <p>Regulation (EU) No 952/2013 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 9 October 2013 laying down the Union Customs Code (OJ L 269, 10.10.2013, p. 1).</p>
                  </authorialNote> and Commission Implementing Regulation (EU) 2015/2447<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="5">
                     <p>Commission Implementing Regulation (EU) 2015/2447 of 24 November 2015 laying down detailed rules for implementing certain provisions of Regulation (EU) No 952/2013 of the European Parliament and of the Council laying down the Union Customs Code (OJ L 343, 29.12.2015, p. 558).</p>
                  </authorialNote>.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d625e182">
               <num>(8)</num>
               <p>In case of a deflection of trade and in order to ensure uniform conditions for the implementation of this Regulation, implementing powers should be conferred on the Commission allowing the Commission to temporarily withdraw the suspension. Those powers should be exercised in accordance with Regulation (EU) No 182/2011 of the European Parliament and of the Council<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="6">
                     <p>Regulation (EU) No 182/2011 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 16 February 2011 laying down the rules and general principles concerning mechanisms for control by Member States of the Commission&apos;s exercise of implementing powers (OJ L 55, 28.2.2011, p. 13).</p>
                  </authorialNote>.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d625e198">
               <num>(9)</num>
               <p>In order to ensure continuity after the expiration of the provisions of Regulation (EU) No 1386/2011, it is appropriate to apply the measures provided in this Regulation from 1 January 2022 until 31 December 2031,</p>
            </recital>
         </recitals>
         <formula name="enactingFormula">
            <p>HAS ADOPTED THIS REGULATION:</p>
         </formula>
      </preamble>
      <body>
         <article xml:id="art_d625e213">
            <num>Article 1</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>From 1 January 2022 to 31 December 2031, the Common Customs Tariff duties referred to in Article 56(2), point (c), of Regulation (EU) No 952/2013, applicable to imports into the Canary Islands of capital goods for commercial or industrial use, currently falling under the CN codes listed in Annex I to this Regulation, shall be suspended in full.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>Those capital goods shall be used in accordance with the relevant provisions of Regulation (EU) No 952/2013 and of Regulation (EU) 2015/2447 for a period of at least 24 months after their release into free circulation by economic operators located in the Canary Islands.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <article xml:id="art_d625e226">
            <num>Article 2</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>From 1 January 2022 to 31 December 2031, the Common Customs Tariff duties referred to in Article 56(2), point (c), of Regulation (EU) No 952/2013, applicable to imports into the Canary Islands of raw materials, parts and components, currently falling under the CN codes listed in Annex II to this Regulation, and used for industrial transformation or maintenance in the Canary Islands, shall be suspended in full.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <article xml:id="art_d625e238">
            <num>Article 3</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>The suspension of duties referred to in Articles 1 and 2 shall be subject to end-use customs supervision in accordance with Article 254 of Regulation (EU) No 952/2013.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <article xml:id="art_d625e243">
            <num>Article 4</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <num>1.</num>
               <subparagraph>
                  <content>
                     <p>Where the Commission has reason to believe that any suspension laid down in this Regulation has led to a deflection of trade for a specific product, it shall be empowered to adopt implementing acts in order to temporarily withdraw the suspension with regard to that product for a period not longer than 12 months. Such implementing acts shall be adopted in accordance with the examination procedure referred to in Article 5(2).</p>
                  </content>
               </subparagraph>
               <subparagraph>
                  <content>
                     <p>Import duties for products for which the suspension has been temporarily withdrawn shall be secured by a guarantee, and the release of the products concerned for free circulation in the Canary Islands shall be conditional upon the provision of such guarantee.</p>
                  </content>
               </subparagraph>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph>
               <num>2.</num>
               <content>
                  <p>Where the Council decides, in accordance with the procedure laid down in the Treaty, within the 12-month period referred to in paragraph 1, that the suspension is to be definitively withdrawn, the amounts of duties secured by guarantees shall be collected definitively.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph>
               <num>3.</num>
               <content>
                  <p>Where the Council has not adopted a decision that the suspension should definitively be withdrawn within the 12-month period referred to in paragraph 2, the guarantees shall be released.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <article xml:id="art_d625e263">
            <num>Article 5</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <num>1.</num>
               <content>
                  <p>The Commission shall be assisted by the Customs Code Committee, established by Article 285(1) of Regulation (EU) No 952/2013.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph>
               <num>2.</num>
               <content>
                  <p>Where reference is made to this paragraph, Article 5 of Regulation (EU) No 182/2011 shall apply.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <article xml:id="art_d625e276">
            <num>Article 6</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>This Regulation shall enter into force on the third day following that of its publication in the <i>Official Journal of the European Union</i>.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>It shall apply from 1 January 2022.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <clause>
            <content>
               <p>This Regulation shall be binding in its entirety and directly applicable in all Member States.</p>
            </content>
         </clause>
      </body>
      <conclusions>
         <p>Done at Brussels, 23 November 2021.</p>
         <block name="signatory">
            <signature>
               <organization refersTo="">For the Council</organization>
               <role refersTo="">The President</role>
               <person refersTo="">G. DOVŽAN</person>
            </signature>
         </block>
      </conclusions>
   </bill>
</akomaNtoso>
