<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0"
            xmlns:fmx="http://formex.publications.europa.eu/schema/formex-05.21-20110601.xd"
            xmlns:leos="urn:eu:europa:ec:leos"
            xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema">
   <bill name="">
      <meta xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions">
         <identification source="~COM">
            <FRBRWork>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRcountry value=""/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
         </identification>
      </meta>
      <preface>
         <longTitle>
            <p>
               <docStage/>
               <docType>COMMISSION REGULATION (EU) 2020/351</docType>of 28 February 2020<docPurpose>amending Annex II to Regulation (EC) No 1333/2008 of the European Parliament and of the Council as regards the use of citric acid (E 330) in cocoa and chocolate products</docPurpose>
            </p>
         </longTitle>
         <container name="EEArelevance">
            <p>(Text with EEA relevance)</p>
         </container>
      </preface>
      <preamble>
         <formula name="actingEntity">
            <p>THE EUROPEAN COMMISSION,</p>
         </formula>
         <citations>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to Regulation (EC) No 1333/2008 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 16 December 2008 on food additives<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="1">
                     <p>OJ L 354, 31.12.2008, p. 16.</p>
                  </authorialNote>, and in particular Article 10(3) thereof,</p>
            </citation>
         </citations>
         <recitals xml:id="recs_d44e71">
            <intro>
               <p>Whereas:</p>
            </intro>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d44e74">
               <num>(1)</num>
               <p>Annex II to Regulation (EC) No 1333/2008 lays down a Union list of food additives approved for use in food and their conditions of use.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d44e80">
               <num>(2)</num>
               <p>That list may be updated in accordance with the common procedure referred to in Article 3(1) of Regulation (EC) No 1331/2008 of the European Parliament and of the Council<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="2">
                     <p>Regulation (EC) No 1331/2008 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 16 December 2008 establishing a common authorisation procedure for food additives, food enzymes and food flavourings (OJ L 354, 31.12.2008, p. 1).</p>
                  </authorialNote>, either on the initiative of the Commission or following an application.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d44e96">
               <num>(3)</num>
               <p>Pursuant to Annex II to Regulation (EC) No 1333/2008, citric acid (E 330) is an authorised food additive in food category 05.1 &apos;Cocoa and Chocolate products as covered by Directive 2000/36/EC&apos; at a maximum level of 5000 mg/kg.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d44e109">
               <num>(4)</num>
               <p>On 6 March 2018, an application was submitted for the modification of the conditions of use of citric acid (E 330) contained in food category 05.1 &apos;Cocoa and Chocolate products as covered by Directive 2000/36/EC&apos;, by increasing its maximum level of use to 10000 mg/kg for milk chocolate. The application was subsequently made available to the Member States pursuant to Article 4 of Regulation (EC) No 1331/2008.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d44e125">
               <num>(5)</num>
               <p>Citric acid (E 330), when used as a stabiliser in cocoa mass containing high levels of polyphenols, lowers pH and reacts with a part of polyphenols intensifying cocoa mass colour into characteristic pink shades accompanied by a berry-fruit sour taste. Both, pink shades and a berry-fruit sour taste are still apparent in the final product, i.e. in chocolate. The application shows that, the currently authorised maximum level of 5000 mg/kg is not sufficient to obtain the desired pink shades and a berry-fruit sour taste, which is achievable with the maximum level of 10000 mg/kg. As for the reaction between citric acid (E 330) and polyphenols, a constant ratio of citric acid (E 330) relative to cocoa mass is needed, thus the higher use level of citric acid (E 330) implies an increase in total dry cocoa solids in the final product. This final product would therefore comply with the definition of milk chocolate as laid down in Annex I to Directive 2000/36/EC of the European Parliament and of the Council<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="3">
                     <p>Directive 2000/36/EC of the European Parliament and of the Council of 23 June 2000 relating to cocoa and chocolate products intended for human consumption (OJ L 197, 3.8.2000, p. 19).</p>
                  </authorialNote>.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d44e148">
               <num>(6)</num>
               <p>Pursuant to Article 3(2) of Regulation (EC) No 1331/2008, the Commission has to seek the opinion of the European Food Safety Authority in order to update the Union list of food additives set out in Annex II to Regulation (EC) No 1333/2008, except where the update in question is not liable to have an effect on human health.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d44e154">
               <num>(7)</num>
               <p>The safety of citric acid (E 330) was evaluated in 1990 by the Scientific Committee for Food, which established its acceptable daily intake as &apos;not specified&apos;<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="4">
                     <p>Reports of the Scientific Committee for Food, Twenty-fifth series, 1991, p. 13 (https://ec.europa.eu/food/sites/food/files/safety/docs/sci-com_scf_reports_25.pdf).</p>
                  </authorialNote>. The term &apos;not specified&apos; is used when, on the basis of the available toxicological, biochemical and clinical data, the total daily intake of the substance, arising from its natural occurrence and its present use or uses in food at the levels necessary to achieve the desired technological effect, will not present a hazard to health.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d44e171">
               <num>(8)</num>
               <p>Citric acid (E 330) is a food additive authorised in a variety of foods in accordance with Annex II to Regulation (EC) No 1333/2008. It is not expected that the increase of its maximum level to 10000 mg/kg for milk chocolate will have a significant impact on the overall exposure.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d44e180">
               <num>(9)</num>
               <p>Since the authorisation of the use of citric acid (E 330) in milk chocolate at 10000 mg/kg requires an update of the Union list which is not liable to have an effect on human health, it is not necessary to seek the opinion of the Authority.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d44e190">
               <num>(10)</num>
               <p>Therefore, it is appropriate to authorise the use of citric acid (E 330) in milk chocolate at 10000 mg/kg.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d44e199">
               <num>(11)</num>
               <p>Annex II to Regulation (EC) No 1333/2008 should therefore be amended accordingly.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d44e205">
               <num>(12)</num>
               <p>The measures provided for in this Regulation are in accordance with the opinion of the Standing Committee on Plants, Animals, Food and Feed,</p>
            </recital>
         </recitals>
         <formula name="enactingFormula">
            <p>HAS ADOPTED THIS REGULATION:</p>
         </formula>
      </preamble>
      <body>
         <article xml:id="art_d44e214">
            <num>Article 1</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>Annex II to Regulation (EC) No 1333/2008 is amended in accordance with the Annex to this Regulation.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <article xml:id="art_d44e219">
            <num>Article 2</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>This Regulation shall enter into force on the twentieth day following that of its publication in the <i>Official Journal of the European Union</i>.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <clause>
            <content>
               <p>This Regulation shall be binding in its entirety and directly applicable in all Member States.</p>
            </content>
         </clause>
      </body>
      <conclusions>
         <p>Done at Brussels, 28 February 2020.</p>
         <block name="signatory">
            <signature>
               <organization refersTo="">For the Commission</organization>
               <role refersTo="">The President</role>
               <person refersTo="">Ursula VON DER LEYEN</person>
            </signature>
         </block>
      </conclusions>
   </bill>
</akomaNtoso>
