L2832019EN7210120191105EN000772177618502019---<p xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0"><!--default P | TXT -->Only the original UN/ECE texts have legal effect under international public law. The status and date of entry into force of this Regulation should be checked in the latest version of the UN/ECE status document TRANS/WP.29/343, available at:</p>
<p xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0"><!--default P | TXT -->http://www.unece.org/trans/main/wp29/wp29wgs/wp29gen/wp29fdocstts.html</p>
<p xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">Regulation No 29 of the Economic Commission for Europe of the United Nations (UN/ECE) &#45; Uniform provisions concerning the approval of vehicles with regard to the protection of the occupants of the cab of a commercial vehicle [2019/1850]</p>
<p xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0"><!--default P | TXT -->Incorporating all valid text up to:</p>
<p xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0"><!--default P | TXT -->Supplement 4 to the 03 series of amendments &#45; Date of entry into force: 28 May 2019</p>
<num xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">1.</num>
<p xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">SCOPE</p>
<p xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0"><!--default P | TXT -->This Regulation applies to vehicles of category N<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="1">
      <p>As defined in the Consolidated Resolution on the Construction of Vehicles (R.E.3.), document ECE/TRANS/WP.29/78/Rev.6, para. 2.</p>
   </authorialNote> with regard to the protection of the occupants of the cab.</p>
<num xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">2.</num>
<p xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">DEFINITIONS</p>
<p xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0"><!--default P | TXT -->For the purposes of this Regulation:</p>
<num xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">2.1.</num>
<p xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">&apos;Approval of a vehicle&apos; means the approval of a vehicle type pursuant to the requirements of this Regulation, with regard to the protection of the occupants of the cab of a vehicle in the event of head-on impact or of overturning.</p>
<num xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">2.2.</num>
<p xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">&apos;Vehicle type&apos; means a category of motor vehicle which does not differ in such essential respects as:</p>
<num xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">2.2.1.</num>
<p xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">The dimensions, shapes and materials of the components of the vehicle cab; or</p>
<num xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">2.2.2.</num>
<p xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">The manner of attachment of the cab to the chassis frame;</p>
<num xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">2.3.</num>
<p xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">&apos;Transverse plane&apos; means a vertical plane perpendicular to the longitudinal plane of the vehicle;</p>
<num xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">2.4.</num>
<p xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">&apos;Longitudinal plane&apos; means a plane parallel to the median longitudinal plane of the vehicle;</p>
<num xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">2.5.</num>
<p xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">&apos;Cab-over-engine vehicle&apos; means a vehicle where more than half of the engine length is rearward of the foremost point of the windshield base and the steering wheel hub is in the forward quarter of the vehicle length.</p>
<num xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">2.6.</num>
<p xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">&apos;R point&apos; means the seating reference point as defined in Annex 4, paragraph 2.4.</p>
<num xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">2.7.</num>
<p xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">&apos;H-point&apos; means the point defined in Annex 4, paragraph 2.3.</p>
<num xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">2.8.</num>
<p xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">&apos;Test A&apos; means a frontal impact test intended to evaluate the resistance of a cab in frontal impact accident.</p>
<num xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">2.9.</num>
<p xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">&apos;Test B&apos; means an impact test to the A-pillars of the cab intended to evaluate the resistance of a cab in a 90° rollover accident with subsequent impact.</p>
<num xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">2.10.</num>
<p xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">&apos;Test C&apos; means a cab roof strength test intended to evaluate the resistance of a cab in a 180° rollover accident.</p>
<num xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">2.11.</num>
<p xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">&apos;A-pillar&apos; means the foremost and outermost roof support.</p>
<num xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">2.12.</num>
<p xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">&apos;Windscreen&apos; means the frontal glazing of the vehicle situated between the A-pillars.</p>
<num xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">2.13.</num>
<p xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">&apos;Vehicles of category N<sub>1</sub> derived from M<sub>1</sub>&apos;&apos;means those vehicles of N<sub>1</sub> category which, forward of the A-pillars, have the same general structure and shape as a pre-existing M<sub>1</sub> category vehicle.&apos;</p>
<num xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">2.14.</num>
<p xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">&apos;Separate cab&apos; means a cab attached to the vehicle&apos;s frame by specific links and which has no common part with the cargo area.</p>
<num xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">3.</num>
<p xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">APPLICATION FOR APPROVAL</p>
<num xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">3.1.</num>
<p xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">The application for approval of a vehicle type with regard to the protection of the occupants of the cab of a vehicle shall be submitted by the vehicle manufacturer or by his duly accredited representative.</p>
<num xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">3.2.</num>
<p xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">It shall be accompanied by drawings of the vehicle, showing the position of the cab on the vehicle and the manner of its attachment, and by sufficiently detailed drawings relating to the structure of the cab, all the said drawings being submitted in triplicate. A model for the information document relating to the construction features is given in Annex 1, Part 1.</p>
<num xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">4.</num>
<p xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">APPROVAL</p>
<num xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">4.1.</num>
<p xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">If the vehicle type submitted for approval pursuant to this Regulation meets the requirements of paragraph 5 hereof, approval of that vehicle type shall be granted.</p>
<num xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">4.2.</num>
<p xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">An approval number shall be assigned to each type approved. Its first two digits (at present 03 corresponding to the 03 series of amendments) shall indicate the series of amendments incorporating the most recent major technical amendments made to the Regulation at the time of issue of the approval. The same Contracting Party may not assign the same number to another vehicle type within the meaning of paragraph 2.2 above.</p>
<num xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">4.3.</num>
<p xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">Notice of approval or of extension or of refusal or of withdrawal of approval or production definitely discontinued of a vehicle type pursuant to this Regulation shall be communicated by the Parties to the Agreement which apply this Regulation by means of a form conforming to the model in annex 1 to this Regulation.</p>
<num xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">4.4.</num>
<p xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">There shall be affixed, conspicuously and in a readily accessible place specified on the approval form, to every vehicle conforming to a vehicle type approved under this Regulation, an international approval mark consisting of:</p>
<num xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">4.4.1.</num>
<p xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">A circle surrounding the letter &apos;E&apos; followed by the distinguishing number of the country which has granted the approval<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="2">
      <p>The distinguishing numbers of the Contracting Parties to the 1958 Agreement are reproduced in Annex 3 to the Consolidated Resolution on the Construction of Vehicles (R.E.3), document ECE/TRANS/WP.29/78/Rev. 6 &#45; http://www.unece.org/trans/main/wp29/wp29wgs/wp29gen/wp29resolutions.html</p>
   </authorialNote> and</p>
<num xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">4.4.2.</num>
<p xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">the number of this Regulation, followed by the letter &apos;R&apos;, a dash and the approval number, to the right of the circle prescribed in paragraph 4.4.1;</p>
<num xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">4.5.</num>
<p xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">If the vehicle conforms to a vehicle type approved, under one or more other Regulations annexed to the Agreement, in the country which has granted approval under this Regulation, the symbol prescribed in paragraph 4.4.1 need not be repeated; in such a case the additional numbers and symbols of all the Regulations under which approval has been granted in the country which has granted approval under this Regulation shall be placed in vertical columns to the right of the symbol prescribed in paragraph 4.4.1.</p>
<num xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">4.6.</num>
<p xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">The approval mark shall be clearly legible and be indelible.</p>
<num xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">4.7.</num>
<p xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">The approval mark shall be placed close to or on the vehicle data plate.</p>
<num xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">4.8.</num>
<p xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">Annex 2 to this Regulation gives examples of arrangements of approval marks.</p>
<num xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">5.</num>
<p xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">REQUIREMENTS</p>
<num xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">5.1.</num>
<p xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">General requirements</p>
<num xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">5.1.1.</num>
<p xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">The cab of the vehicle shall be so designed and so attached to the vehicle as to eliminate to the greatest possible extent the risk of injury to the occupants in the event of an accident.</p>
<num xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">5.1.2.</num>
<p xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">Vehicles of categories N<sub>1</sub> and vehicles of categories N<sub>2</sub> with a gross vehicle mass not exceeding 7,5 t shall be subjected to the tests A and C, as described in Annex 3, paragraphs 5 and 7.</p>
<p xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0"><!--default P | TXT -->However a vehicle type which meets the frontal impact requirements of Regulation No 12 or Regulation No 33 or Regulation No 94, and vehicles of category N<sub>1</sub>, derived from M<sub>1</sub> approved to Regulation No 94, may be considered to have satisfied the requirements on frontal impact (test A).</p>
<p xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0"><!--default P | TXT -->Test C shall only be conducted on vehicles which have a separate cab.</p>
<num xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">5.1.3.</num>
<p xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">Vehicles of categories N<sub>3</sub> and vehicles of categories N<sub>2</sub> with a gross vehicle mass exceeding 7,5 t shall be subjected to the tests A, B, and C, as described in Annex 3, paragraphs 5, 6, and 7.</p>
<p xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0"><!--default P | TXT -->Test C shall only be conducted on vehicles which have a separate cab.</p>
<num xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">5.1.4.</num>
<p xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">Test A (frontal impact) shall only be conducted on cab-over-engine vehicles.</p>
<num xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">5.1.5.</num>
<p xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">One, two or three cabs, at the manufacturer&apos;s choice, may be used for the purpose of demonstrating compliance with paragraphs 5.1.2 or 5.1.3 above. However both phases in test C, if applicable, shall be conducted on the same cab.</p>
<num xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">5.1.6.</num>
<p xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">None of the tests A, B, C, need be carried out if the manufacturer can show by computer simulation or calculations of the strength of the component parts of the cab or by other means to the satisfaction of the Technical Service that the cab will not undergo deformation dangerous to the occupants (penetration into the survival space) if subjected to the conditions of the tests.</p>
<num xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">5.2.</num>
<p xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">Survival space required after the test or tests</p>
<num xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">5.2.1.</num>
<p xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">After undergoing each of the tests referred to in paragraphs 5.1.2 or 5.1.3, the cab of the vehicle shall exhibit a survival space allowing accommodation of the manikin defined in Annex 3, Appendix 2, on the seat, when the latter is in its median position, without contact between the test manikin and non-resilient parts with a Shore-Hardness of 50 or more. No account shall be taken of non-resilient parts which can be moved away without any tools from the test manikin by using a force of less than 100 N. To facilitate installation, the manikin may be inserted in dismantled form and assembled in the cab. For this purpose, the seat shall be adjusted to its most rearward position and the manikin completely assembled and so placed that its H point coincides with the R point. The seat shall then be moved forward to its median position for the assessment of the survival space. As an alternative to the test manikin defined in Annex 3, Appendix 2, a fiftieth percentile Hybrid II or III male dummy, with or without measuring instrumentation, the description of which is given in Regulation No 94, may be used.</p>
<num xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">5.2.2.</num>
<p xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">The space so defined shall be verified for every seat provided by the manufacturer.</p>
<num xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">5.3.</num>
<p xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">Other conditions</p>
<num xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">5.3.1.</num>
<p xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">During the tests the components by which the cab is secured to the chassis frame may be distorted or broken, provided that the cab remains attached to the chassis frame by standard fixture attachments and does not unintentionally move, shift or rotate about the attachment points.</p>
<num xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">5.3.2.</num>
<p xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">None of the doors shall open during the tests, but the doors shall not be required to open after testing.</p>
<num xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">6.</num>
<p xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">MODIFICATION AND EXTENSION OF APPROVAL OF THE VEHICLE TYPE</p>
<num xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">6.1.</num>
<p xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">Every modification of the vehicle type shall be notified to the Type Approval Authority which approved the vehicle type. The Type Approval Authority may then either:</p>
<num xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">6.1.1.</num>
<p xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">Consider that the modifications made are unlikely to have an appreciable adverse effect, and that in any case the vehicle still complies with the requirements;</p>
<num xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">6.1.2.</num>
<p xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">Or require a further test report from the Technical Service responsible for conducting the tests.</p>
<num xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">6.2.</num>
<p xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">Confirmation or refusal of approval, specifying the alterations, shall be communicated by the procedure specified in paragraph 4.3 above to the Contracting Parties to the Agreement which apply this Regulation.</p>
<num xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">6.3.</num>
<p xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">The competent authority issuing an extension of approval shall assign a series number for such an extension and inform thereof the other Parties to the 1958 Agreement applying this Regulation by means of a communication form conforming to the model in Annex 1 to this Regulation.</p>
<num xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">7.</num>
<p xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">CONFORMITY OF PRODUCTION</p>
<p xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0"><!--default P | TXT -->The conformity of production procedures shall comply with those set out in the Agreement, (Schedule 1, E/ECE/TRANS/505/Rev.3), with the following requirements:</p>
<num xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">7.1.</num>
<p xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">A vehicle approved pursuant to this Regulation shall be so manufactured as to conform to the type approved by meeting the requirements of paragraph 5 above.</p>
<num xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">7.2.</num>
<p xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">The Competent Authority which has granted approval may at any time verify the conformity of control methods applicable to each production unit. The normal frequency of such inspections shall be once every two years.</p>
<num xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">8.</num>
<p xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">PENALTIES FOR NON-CONFORMITY OF PRODUCTION</p>
<num xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">8.1.</num>
<p xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">The approval granted in respect of a vehicle type, pursuant to this Regulation, may be withdrawn if the requirement laid down in paragraph 7.1 above is not complied with.</p>
<num xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">8.2.</num>
<p xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">If a Party to the Agreement which applies this Regulation withdraws an approval it has previously granted, it shall forthwith so notify the other Contracting Parties applying this Regulation by means of a communication form conforming to the model in Annex 1 to this Regulation.</p>
<num xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">9.</num>
<p xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">PRODUCTION DEFINITELY DISCONTINUED</p>
<p xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0"><!--default P | TXT -->If the holder of the approval completely ceases to manufacture a type of vehicle approved in accordance with this Regulation, he shall so inform the authority which granted the approval. Upon receiving the relevant communication, that authority shall inform thereof the other Parties to the 1958 Agreement which apply this Regulation by means of a communication form conforming to the model in Annex 1 to this Regulation.</p>
<num xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">10.</num>
<p xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">TRANSITIONAL PROVISIONS</p>
<num xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">10.1.</num>
<p xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">As from the official date of entry into force of the 02 series of amendments, no Contracting Party applying this Regulation shall refuse to grant ECE approval under this Regulation as amended by the 02 series of amendments.</p>
<num xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">10.2.</num>
<p xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">As from 1 October 2002 Contracting Party applying this Regulation shall grant ECE approvals only if the requirements of this Regulation, as amended by the 02 series of amendments are satisfied.</p>
<num xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">10.3.</num>
<p xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">As from 1 October 2006 Contracting Party applying this Regulation may refuse to recognise approvals which were not granted in accordance with the 02 series of amendments to this Regulation.</p>
<num xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">10.4.</num>
<p xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">As from the official date of entry into force of the 03 series of amendments, no Contracting Party applying this Regulation shall refuse to grant ECE approval under this Regulation as amended by the 03 series of amendments.</p>
<num xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">10.5.</num>
<p xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">As from 72 months after the date of entry into force of the 03 series of amendments Contracting Parties applying this Regulation shall grant ECE approval under this Regulation to the new types of cabs only if the requirements of this Regulation, as amended by the 03 series of amendments, are satisfied.</p>
<num xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">10.6.</num>
<p xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">Contracting Parties applying this Regulation shall not refuse to grant extensions of approval to the preceding series of amendments to this Regulation.</p>
<num xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">10.7.</num>
<p xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">Contracting Parties applying this Regulation shall continue to grant approvals to those types of vehicles which comply with the requirements of this Regulation as amended by the preceding series of amendments during the 72 months&apos; period which follows the date of entry into force of the 03 series of amendments.</p>
<num xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">10.8.</num>
<p xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">No Contracting Party applying this Regulation shall refuse national or regional type approval of a vehicle type approved to the 03 series of amendments to this Regulation.</p>
<num xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">10.9.</num>
<p xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">Even after the entry into force of the 03 series of amendments to this Regulation, approvals of the vehicles to the preceding series of amendments to this Regulation shall remain valid and Contracting Parties applying this Regulation shall continue to accept them.</p>
<num xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">11.</num>
<p xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">NAMES AND ADDRESSES OF TECHNICAL SERVICES RESPONSIBLE FOR CONDUCTING APPROVAL TESTS AND OF TYPE APPROVAL AUTHORITIES</p>
<p xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0"><!--default P | TXT -->The Parties to the Agreement which apply this Regulation shall communicate to the Secretariat of the United Nations the names and addresses of the Technical Services conducting approval tests, and of the Type Approval Authorities which grant approval and to which forms certifying approval or extension, or refusal or withdrawal of approval, issued in other countries, are to be sent.</p>
