<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0"
            xmlns:fmx="http://formex.publications.europa.eu/schema/formex-05.21-20110601.xd"
            xmlns:leos="urn:eu:europa:ec:leos"
            xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema">
   <bill name="">
      <meta xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions">
         <identification source="~COM">
            <FRBRWork>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRcountry value=""/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
         </identification>
      </meta>
      <preface>
         <longTitle>
            <p>
               <docStage/>
               <docType>COMMISSION REGULATION (EU) 2020/703</docType>of 26 May 2020<docPurpose>amending Annex II to Regulation (EC) No 396/2005 of the European Parliament and of the Council as regards maximum residue levels for dimethoate and omethoate in or on cherries</docPurpose>
            </p>
         </longTitle>
         <container name="EEArelevance">
            <p>(Text with EEA relevance)</p>
         </container>
      </preface>
      <preamble>
         <formula name="actingEntity">
            <p>THE EUROPEAN COMMISSION,</p>
         </formula>
         <citations>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to Regulation (EC) No 396/2005 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 23 February 2005 on maximum residue levels of pesticides in or on food and feed of plant and animal origin and amending Council Directive 91/414/EEC<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="1">
                     <p>OJ L 70, 16.3.2005, p. 1.</p>
                  </authorialNote>, and in particular Article 14(1)(a) thereof,</p>
            </citation>
         </citations>
         <recitals xml:id="recs_d71e71">
            <intro>
               <p>Whereas:</p>
            </intro>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d71e74">
               <num>(1)</num>
               <p>For dimethoate and omethoate, maximum residue levels (MRLs) were set in Annex II to Regulation (EC) No 396/2005.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d71e80">
               <num>(2)</num>
               <p>The approval of the active substance dimethoate was not renewed by Commission Implementing Regulation (EU) 2019/1090<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="2">
                     <p>Commission Implementing Regulation (EU) 2019/1090 of 26 June 2019 concerning the non-renewal of approval of the active substance dimethoate, in accordance with Regulation (EC) No 1107/2009 of the European Parliament and of the Council concerning the placing of plant protection products on the market, and amending the Annex to Commission Implementing Regulation (EU) No 540/2011 (OJ L 173, 27.6.2019, p. 39).</p>
                  </authorialNote>.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d71e96">
               <num>(3)</num>
               <p>All existing authorisations for plant protection products containing dimethoate have been revoked in relation to uses on cherries. It is therefore appropriate to delete the MRLs for cherries set out for dimethoate and omethoate in Annex II of Regulation (EC) No 396/2005 in accordance with Article 17 of Regulation (EC) No 396/2005 in conjunction with Article 14(1)(a) thereof.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d71e102">
               <num>(4)</num>
               <p>In the context of the non-renewal of the approval of dimethoate, the European Food Safety Authority (&apos;the Authority&apos;) delivered a conclusion on the peer review of the pesticide risk assessment of that active substance<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="3">
                     <p>EFSA (European Food Safety Authority), 2018. Conclusion on the peer review of the pesticide risk assessment of the active substance dimethoate, EFSA Journal 2018;16(10):5454. https://www.efsa.europa.eu/en/efsajournal/pub/5454.</p>
                  </authorialNote>. In that framework, the Authority could not exclude a risk to consumers due to the exposure to residues of dimethoate, for which the genotoxic potential could not be excluded, and to its main metabolite omethoate which was concluded to be an in vivo mutagenic agent.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d71e116">
               <num>(5)</num>
               <p>Through the World Trade Organisation, the trading partners of the Union were consulted on the new MRLs and their comments have been taken into account.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d71e122">
               <num>(6)</num>
               <p>Regulation (EC) No 396/2005 should therefore be amended accordingly.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d71e129">
               <num>(7)</num>
               <p>A reasonable period should be allowed to elapse before the modified MRLs become applicable in order to permit Member States, third countries and food business operators to prepare themselves to meet the new requirements which will result from the modification of the MRLs.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d71e135">
               <num>(8)</num>
               <p>The measures provided for in this Regulation are in accordance with the opinion of the Standing Committee on Plants, Animals, Food and Feed,</p>
            </recital>
         </recitals>
         <formula name="enactingFormula">
            <p>HAS ADOPTED THIS REGULATION:</p>
         </formula>
      </preamble>
      <body>
         <article xml:id="art_d71e144">
            <num>Article 1</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>Annex II to Regulation (EC) No 396/2005 is amended in accordance with the Annex to this Regulation.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <article xml:id="art_d71e149">
            <num>Article 2</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>This Regulation shall enter into force on the twentieth day following that of its publication in the <i>Official Journal of the European Union</i>.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>It shall apply from 16 December 2020.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <clause>
            <content>
               <p>This Regulation shall be binding in its entirety and directly applicable in all Member States.</p>
            </content>
         </clause>
      </body>
      <conclusions>
         <p>Done at Brussels, 26 May 2020.</p>
         <block name="signatory">
            <signature>
               <organization refersTo="">For the Commission</organization>
               <role refersTo="">The President</role>
               <person refersTo="">Ursula VON DER LEYEN</person>
            </signature>
         </block>
      </conclusions>
   </bill>
</akomaNtoso>
