<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0"
            xmlns:fmx="http://formex.publications.europa.eu/schema/formex-05.21-20110601.xd"
            xmlns:leos="urn:eu:europa:ec:leos"
            xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema">
   <bill name="">
      <meta xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions">
         <identification source="~COM">
            <FRBRWork>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRcountry value=""/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
         </identification>
      </meta>
      <preface>
         <longTitle>
            <p>
               <docStage/>
               <docType>COMMISSION REGULATION (EU) 2020/1593</docType>of 29 October 2020<docPurpose>amending Annex X to Regulation (EC) No 999/2001 of the European Parliament and of the Council as regards further examination of positive cases of transmissible spongiform encephalopathies in ovine and caprine animals</docPurpose>
            </p>
         </longTitle>
         <container name="EEArelevance">
            <p>(Text with EEA relevance)</p>
         </container>
      </preface>
      <preamble>
         <formula name="actingEntity">
            <p>THE EUROPEAN COMMISSION,</p>
         </formula>
         <citations>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to Regulation (EC) No 999/2001 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 22 May 2001 laying down rules for the prevention, control and eradication of certain transmissible spongiform encephalopathies<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="1">
                     <p>OJ L 147, 31.5.2001, p. 1.</p>
                  </authorialNote>, and in particular the first paragraph of Article 23 and Article 23a(m) thereof,</p>
            </citation>
         </citations>
         <recitals xml:id="recs_d259e71">
            <intro>
               <p>Whereas:</p>
            </intro>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d259e74">
               <num>(1)</num>
               <p>Regulation (EC) No 999/2001 lays down rules for the prevention, control and eradication of transmissible spongiform encephalopathies (&apos;TSEs&apos;) in animals. It applies to the production and placing on the market of live animals and products of animal origin and in certain specific cases to exports thereof.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d259e84">
               <num>(2)</num>
               <p>Annex X to Regulation (EC) No 999/2001 lays down the sampling and laboratory methods for detection of TSEs.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d259e90">
               <num>(3)</num>
               <p>Point 3.2(a) and (b) of Chapter C of Annex X to Regulation (EC) No 999/2001 requests further examination of samples from suspect cases and samples from TSE monitoring that resulted positive in the confirmatory examination. This requirement was introduced by Commission Regulation (EC) No 36/2005<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="2">
                     <p>Commission Regulation (EC) No 36/2005 of 12 January 2005 amending Annexes III and X to Regulation (EC) No 999/2001 of the European Parliament and of the Council as regards epidemio-surveillance for transmissible spongiform encephalopathies in bovine, ovine and caprine animals (OJ L 10, 13.1.2005, p. 9).</p>
                  </authorialNote> to investigate the possible presence of BSE in small ruminants.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d259e106">
               <num>(4)</num>
               <p>On 28 January 2005, the first case of BSE in a small ruminant under natural conditions was confirmed in a goat slaughtered in France. Consequently, Commission Regulation (EC) No 214/2005<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="3">
                     <p>Commission Regulations (EC) No 214/2005 of 9 February 2005 amending Annex III to Regulation (EC) No 999/2001 of the European Parliament and of the Council as regards monitoring of transmissible spongiform encephalopathies in caprine animals (OJ L 37, 10.2.2005, p. 9).</p>
                  </authorialNote> increased the testing requirements for goats.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d259e125">
               <num>(5)</num>
               <p>Due to the identification of two possible BSE-like cases in sheep in France and one in Cyprus in 2006, Commission Regulation (EC) No 1041/2006<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="4">
                     <p>Commission Regulation (EC) No 1041/2006 of 7 July 2006 amending Annex III to Regulation (EC) No 999/2001 of the European Parliament and of the Council as regards monitoring of transmissible spongiform encephalopathies in ovine animals (OJ L 187, 8.7.2006, p. 10).</p>
                  </authorialNote> extended the monitoring programme in sheep based on a statistically valid survey in order to determine the likely prevalence of BSE in sheep. These cases were subsequently confirmed to be scrapie and not BSE.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d259e141">
               <num>(6)</num>
               <p>These monitoring programmes were reviewed by Commission Regulation (EC) No 727/2007<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="5">
                     <p>Commission Regulation (EC) No 727/2007 of 26 June 2007 amending Annexes I, III, VII and X to Regulation (EC) No 999/2001 of the European Parliament and of the Council laying down rules for the prevention, control and eradication of certain transmissible spongiform encephalopathies (OJ L 165, 27.6.2007, p. 8).</p>
                  </authorialNote> in the light of the results of two years of intensified testing which led to the detection of no additional BSE cases in ovine or caprine animals.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d259e157">
               <num>(7)</num>
               <p>After further systematic examination of positive TSE cases in ovine and caprine animals since 2005, no more BSE positive or suspicious cases have been detected.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d259e164">
               <num>(8)</num>
               <p>In view of the absence of BSE positive or suspicious cases in ovine and caprine animals since 2005, it is appropriate that the discriminatory testing in case of positive TSE cases in ovine and caprine animals is limited to the &apos;index case&apos; as defined in point 2(c) of Annex I to Regulation (EC) No 999/2001.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d259e174">
               <num>(9)</num>
               <p>Furthermore, point 3.2(c)(ii) of Chapter C of Annex X to Regulation (EC) No 999/2001 requests that the TSE cases in which BSE cannot be excluded by the primary molecular testing should be submitted to a secondary molecular test in one of the three laboratories listed in that point.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d259e181">
               <num>(10)</num>
               <p>This list was established by Regulation (EC) No 36/2005 based on the methods and laboratory expertise available in 2005. It has never been updated since then.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d259e187">
               <num>(11)</num>
               <p>It is appropriate to ensure more flexibility as regards the method of secondary molecular testing, the design of which should be approved on a case-by-case basis by the EU reference laboratory taking into account the latest scientific knowledge. The choice of the performing laboratory should also be more flexible in order to make the best use of the latest scientific knowledge and laboratory expertise</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d259e193">
               <num>(12)</num>
               <p>Point 3.2 (a), (b) and (c) of Chapter C of Annex X to Regulation (EC) No 999/2001 should therefore be amended accordingly.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d259e199">
               <num>(13)</num>
               <p>The measures provided for in this Regulation are in accordance with the opinion of the Standing Committee on Plants, Animals, Food and Feed,</p>
            </recital>
         </recitals>
         <formula name="enactingFormula">
            <p>HAS ADOPTED THIS REGULATION:</p>
         </formula>
      </preamble>
      <body>
         <article xml:id="art_d259e208">
            <num>Article 1</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>Annex X to Regulation (EC) No 999/2001 is amended in accordance with the Annex to this Regulation.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <article xml:id="art_d259e213">
            <num>Article 2</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>This Regulation shall enter into force on the twentieth day following that of its publication in the <i>Official Journal of the European Union</i>.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <clause>
            <content>
               <p>This Regulation shall be binding in its entirety and directly applicable in all Member States.</p>
            </content>
         </clause>
      </body>
      <conclusions>
         <p>Done at Brussels, 29 October 2020.</p>
         <block name="signatory">
            <signature>
               <organization refersTo="">For the Commission</organization>
               <role refersTo="">The President</role>
               <person refersTo="">Ursula VON DER LEYEN</person>
            </signature>
         </block>
      </conclusions>
   </bill>
</akomaNtoso>
