<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0"
            xmlns:fmx="http://formex.publications.europa.eu/schema/formex-05.21-20110601.xd"
            xmlns:leos="urn:eu:europa:ec:leos"
            xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema">
   <bill name="">
      <meta xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions">
         <identification source="~COM">
            <FRBRWork>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRcountry value=""/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
         </identification>
      </meta>
      <preface>
         <longTitle>
            <p>
               <docStage/>
               <docType>COMMISSION REGULATION (EU) 2019/543</docType>of 3 April 2019<docPurpose>amending Annex IV to Regulation (EC) No 661/2009 of the European Parliament and of the Council and Annexes I, III and IV to Directive 2007/46/EC of the European Parliament and of the Council as regards updating the references to and including certain Regulations of the United Nations Economic Commission for Europe on the type-approval of motor vehicles</docPurpose>
            </p>
         </longTitle>
         <container name="EEArelevance">
            <p>(Text with EEA relevance)</p>
         </container>
      </preface>
      <preamble>
         <formula name="actingEntity">
            <p>THE EUROPEAN COMMISSION,</p>
         </formula>
         <citations>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to Directive 2007/46/EC of the European Parliament and of the Council of 5 September 2007 establishing a framework for the approval of motor vehicles and their trailers, and of systems, components and separate technical units intended for such vehicles (Framework Directive)<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="1">
                     <p>OJ L 263, 9.10.2007, p. 1.</p>
                  </authorialNote>, and in particular Article 39(2) thereof,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to Regulation (EC) No 661/2009 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 13 July 2009 concerning type-approval requirements for the general safety of motor vehicles, their trailers and systems, components and separate technical units intended therefor<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="2">
                     <p>OJ L 200, 31.7.2009, p. 1.</p>
                  </authorialNote>, and in particular Article 14(1)(a) and (f) thereof,</p>
            </citation>
         </citations>
         <recitals xml:id="recs_d159e82">
            <intro>
               <p>Whereas:</p>
            </intro>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d159e85">
               <num>(1)</num>
               <p>Annex IV of Directive 2007/46/EC lists the requirements applicable for the purpose of EC type-approval of motor vehicles. Those requirements include Union legislation and in some cases UN Regulations adopted in the context of the United Nations Economic Commission for Europe, which apply either on a compulsory basis or as an alternative to the Union requirements.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d159e91">
               <num>(2)</num>
               <p>Annex IV to Regulation (EC) No 661/2009 lists the UN Regulations which apply on a compulsory basis in the context of the general safety of vehicles.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d159e97">
               <num>(3)</num>
               <p>The lists of requirements applicable for the purpose of EC type-approval in Annex IV of Directive 2007/46/EC and the list of UN Regulations which apply on a compulsory basis in Annex IV to Regulation (EC) No 661/2009 are updated frequently to reflect the application at Union level of new requirements in the respective UN Regulations.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d159e103">
               <num>(4)</num>
               <p>UN Regulation No 0 on the International Whole Vehicle Type Approval<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="3">
                     <p>OJ L 135, 31.5.2018, p. 1.</p>
                  </authorialNote> was recently adopted in the context of the United Nations Economic Commission for Europe in order to reduce barriers to trade between the Contracting Parties applying that UN Regulation, which include the Union and its Member States, and to provide an increased level of certainty for vehicle manufacturers seeking recognition of their type-approval in those Contracting Parties.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d159e116">
               <num>(5)</num>
               <p>It is appropriate to update the lists of requirements which apply for the purpose of EC type-approval of vehicles included in Annex IV of Directive 2007/46/EC, as well as the list of UN regulations which apply on a compulsory basis set out in Annex IV to Regulation (EC) No 661/2009 in order to reflect the changes introduced by UN Regulation No 0.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d159e122">
               <num>(6)</num>
               <p>The table in Part II of Annex IV to Directive 2007/46/EC is outdated. For this reason, it is necessary to update the list of UN Regulations the requirements of which are considered as equivalent to the Union requirements for the purposes of EC type-approval.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d159e128">
               <num>(7)</num>
               <p>It is also necessary to update the list of information for the purposes of EC type-approval of vehicles contained in Annex I and the information document in Section A of Part I of Annex III to Directive 2007/46/EC with references to Acoustic Vehicle Alerting System to be approved in accordance with the provisions either of Regulation (EU) No 540/2014 of the European Parliament and of the Council<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="4">
                     <p>Regulation (EU) No 540/2014 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 16 April 2014 on the sound level of motor vehicles and of replacement silencing systems, and amending Directive 2007/46/EC and repealing Directive 70/157/EEC (OJ L 158, 27.5.2014, p. 131).</p>
                  </authorialNote> or of UN Regulation No 138<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="5">
                     <p>OJ L 9, 13.1.2017, p. 33.</p>
                  </authorialNote>.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d159e150">
               <num>(8)</num>
               <p>From 1 September 2018 new UN Regulations No 140<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="6">
                     <p>OJ L 269, 26.10.2018, p. 17.</p>
                  </authorialNote> and No 141<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="7">
                     <p>OJ L 269, 26.10.2018, p. 36.</p>
                  </authorialNote> became applicable. Sufficient time should be provided for manufacturers to adapt their vehicles to the new requirements. Therefore, it should be clarified that for the purposes of EC type-approval those requirements apply only to new types of vehicles with regard to their electronic stability control and tyre pressure monitoring systems.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d159e171">
               <num>(9)</num>
               <p>The measures provided for in this Regulation are in accordance with the opinion of the Technical Committee &#45; Motor Vehicles,</p>
            </recital>
         </recitals>
         <formula name="enactingFormula">
            <p>HAS ADOPTED THIS REGULATION:</p>
         </formula>
      </preamble>
      <body>
         <article xml:id="art_d159e180">
            <num>Article 1</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>Annex IV to Regulation (EC) No 661/2009 is amended in accordance with Annex I to this Regulation.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <article xml:id="art_d159e185">
            <num>Article 2</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>Annexes I, III and IV to Directive 2007/46/EC are amended in accordance with Annex II to this Regulation.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <article xml:id="art_d159e190">
            <num>Article 3</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <num>1.</num>
               <content>
                  <p>With effect from 24 April 2019, for the purposes of EC type-approval of new vehicle types with regard to their electronic stability control systems, Member States shall only accept approvals granted under UN Regulation No 140.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph>
               <num>2.</num>
               <content>
                  <p>With effect from 24 April 2019, for the purposes of EC type-approval of new vehicle types with regard to their tyre pressure monitoring systems, Member States shall only accept approvals granted under UN Regulation No 141.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <article xml:id="art_d159e209">
            <num>Article 4</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>This Regulation shall enter into force on the twentieth day following that of its publication in the <i>Official Journal of the European Union</i>.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <clause>
            <content>
               <p>This Regulation shall be binding in its entirety and directly applicable in all Member States.</p>
            </content>
         </clause>
      </body>
      <conclusions>
         <p>Done at Brussels, 3 April 2019.</p>
         <block name="signatory">
            <signature>
               <organization refersTo="">For the Commission</organization>
               <role refersTo="">The President</role>
               <person refersTo="">Jean-Claude JUNCKER</person>
            </signature>
         </block>
      </conclusions>
   </bill>
</akomaNtoso>
