<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0"
            xmlns:fmx="http://formex.publications.europa.eu/schema/formex-05.21-20110601.xd"
            xmlns:leos="urn:eu:europa:ec:leos"
            xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema">
   <bill name="">
      <meta xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions">
         <identification source="~COM">
            <FRBRWork>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRcountry value=""/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
         </identification>
      </meta>
      <preface>
         <longTitle>
            <p>
               <docStage/>
               <docType>COMMISSION REGULATION (EU) 2016/324</docType>of 7 March 2016<docPurpose>amending and correcting Annex II to Regulation (EC) No 1333/2008 of the European Parliament and of the Council as regards the use of certain food additives permitted in all categories of foods</docPurpose>
            </p>
         </longTitle>
         <container name="EEArelevance">
            <p>(Text with EEA relevance)</p>
         </container>
      </preface>
      <preamble>
         <formula name="actingEntity">
            <p>THE EUROPEAN COMMISSION,</p>
         </formula>
         <citations>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to Regulation (EC) No 1333/2008 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 16 December 2008 on food additives<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="1">
                     <p>OJ L 354, 31.12.2008, p. 16.</p>
                  </authorialNote>, and in particular Article 10(3) thereof,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to Regulation (EC) No 1331/2008 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 16 December 2008 establishing a common authorisation procedure for food additives, food enzymes and food flavourings<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="2">
                     <p>OJ L 354, 31.12.2008, p. 1.</p>
                  </authorialNote>, and in particular Article 7(5) thereof,</p>
            </citation>
         </citations>
         <recitals xml:id="recs_d347e82">
            <intro>
               <p>Whereas:</p>
            </intro>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d347e85">
               <num>(1)</num>
               <p>Annex II to Regulation (EC) No 1333/2008 lays down a Union list of food additives approved for use in foods and their conditions of use.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d347e91">
               <num>(2)</num>
               <p>That list may be updated in accordance with the common procedure referred to in Article 3(1) of Regulation (EC) No 1331/2008, either on the initiative of the Commission or following an application.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d347e97">
               <num>(3)</num>
               <p>The Union list of food additives was established based on the food additives permitted for use in foods in accordance with Directives of the European Parliament and of the Council 94/35/EC<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="3">
                     <p>European Parliament and Council Directive 94/35/EC of 30 June 1994 on sweeteners for use in foodstuffs (OJ L 237, 10.9.1994, p. 3).</p>
                  </authorialNote>, 94/36/EC<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="4">
                     <p>European Parliament and Council Directive 94/36/EC of 30 June 1994 on colours for use in foodstuffs (OJ L 237, 10.9.1994, p. 13).</p>
                  </authorialNote> and 95/2/EC<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="5">
                     <p>European Parliament and Council Directive 95/2/EC of 20 February 1995 on food additives other than colours and sweeteners (OJ L 61, 18.3.1995, p. 1).</p>
                  </authorialNote> and after reviewing their compliance with Articles 6, 7, 8 and 16 of Regulation (EC) No 1333/2008. The Union list includes food additives on the basis of the categories of food to which those additives may be added to.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d347e133">
               <num>(4)</num>
               <p>Due to the difficulties encountered during the transfer of food additives to the new categorisation system provided in Annex II to Regulation (EC) No 1333/2008, foods for infants and young children were not transferred from Article 2(3)(b) of Directive 95/2/EC to Table 1 of Part A of Annex II to Regulation (EC) No 1333/2008. It should be ensured that the carry-over principle does not apply to those foods. Therefore, that table should be corrected to include foods for infants and young children provided in Directive 2009/39/EC of the European Parliament and of the Council<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="6">
                     <p>Directive 2009/39/EC of the European Parliament and of the Council of 6 May 2009 on foodstuffs intended for particular nutritional uses (OJ L 124, 20.5.2009, p. 21).</p>
                  </authorialNote>, as replaced by Regulation (EU) No 609/2013 of the European Parliament and the Council<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="7">
                     <p>Regulation (EU) No 609/2013 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 12 June 2013 on food intended for infants and young children, food for special medical purposes, and total diet replacement for weight control and repealing Council Directive 92/52/EEC, Commission Directives 96/8/EC, 1999/21/EC, 2006/125/EC and 2006/141/EC, Directive 2009/39/EC of the European Parliament and of the Council and Commission Regulations (EC) No 41/2009 and (EC) No 953/2009 (OJ L 181, 29.6.2013, p. 35).</p>
                  </authorialNote>.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d347e161">
               <num>(5)</num>
               <p>In view of Article 16 on the use of food additives in foods for infants and young children of Regulation (EC) No 1333/2008, it is important to clarify the conditions of use of the food additives listed in food category 0. &apos;Food additives permitted in all categories of foods&apos; of part E of Annex II to that Regulation and to amend the title of that category.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d347e171">
               <num>(6)</num>
               <p>Therefore, the Union list of food additives should be clarified in order to reflect all the uses in accordance with Articles 6, 7, 8 and 16 of Regulation (EC) No 1333/2008.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d347e177">
               <num>(7)</num>
               <p>Pursuant to Article 3(2) of Regulation (EC) No 1331/2008, the Commission has to seek the opinion of the European Food Safety Authority (&apos;the Authority&apos;) in order to update the Union list of food additives set out in Annex II to Regulation (EC) No 1333/2008, except where the update in question is not liable to have an effect on human health. Since the Union list is amended in order to clarify uses already in accordance with Directives 94/35/EC, 94/36/EC and 95/2/EC, it constitutes an update of that list which is not liable to have an effect on human health. Therefore, it is not necessary to seek the opinion of the Authority.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d347e187">
               <num>(8)</num>
               <p>Annex II to Regulation (EC) No 1333/2008 should therefore be amended and corrected accordingly.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d347e193">
               <num>(9)</num>
               <p>The measures provided for in this Regulation are in accordance with the opinion of the Standing Committee on Plants, Animals, Food and Feed,</p>
            </recital>
         </recitals>
         <formula name="enactingFormula">
            <p>HAS ADOPTED THIS REGULATION:</p>
         </formula>
      </preamble>
      <body>
         <article xml:id="art_d347e202">
            <num>Article 1</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>Annex II to Regulation (EC) No 1333/2008 is amended in accordance with the Annex to this Regulation.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <article xml:id="art_d347e207">
            <num>Article 2</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>This Regulation shall enter into force on the twentieth day following that of its publication in the <i>Official Journal of the European Union</i>.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <clause>
            <content>
               <p>This Regulation shall be binding in its entirety and directly applicable in all Member States.</p>
            </content>
         </clause>
      </body>
      <conclusions>
         <p>Done at Brussels, 7 March 2016.</p>
         <block name="signatory">
            <signature>
               <organization refersTo="">For the Commission</organization>
               <role refersTo="">The President</role>
               <person refersTo="">Jean-Claude JUNCKER</person>
            </signature>
         </block>
      </conclusions>
   </bill>
</akomaNtoso>
