<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0"
            xmlns:fmx="http://formex.publications.europa.eu/schema/formex-05.21-20110601.xd"
            xmlns:leos="urn:eu:europa:ec:leos"
            xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema">
   <bill name="">
      <meta xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions">
         <identification source="~COM">
            <FRBRWork>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRcountry value=""/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
         </identification>
      </meta>
      <preface>
         <longTitle>
            <p>
               <docStage/>
               <docType>REGULATION (EU) 2021/943 OF THE EUROPEAN CENTRAL BANK</docType>of 14 May 2021<docPurpose>amending Regulation (EU) 2015/534 on reporting of supervisory financial information (ECB/2021/24)</docPurpose>
            </p>
         </longTitle>
      </preface>
      <preamble>
         <formula name="actingEntity">
            <p>THE GOVERNING COUNCIL OF THE EUROPEAN CENTRAL BANK,</p>
         </formula>
         <citations>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to Council Regulation (EU) No 1024/2013 of 15 October 2013 conferring specific tasks on the European Central Bank concerning policies relating to the prudential supervision of credit institutions<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="1">
                     <p>OJ L 287, 29.10.2013, p. 63.</p>
                  </authorialNote>, and in particular Article 4(1), Article 4(3), Article 6(2), Article 6(5)(d) and Article 10 thereof,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to Regulation (EU) No 468/2014 of the European Central Bank of 16 April 2014 establishing the framework for cooperation within the Single Supervisory Mechanism between the European Central Bank and national competent authorities and with national designated authorities (SSM Framework Regulation) (ECB/2014/17)<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="2">
                     <p>OJ L 141, 14.5.2014, p. 1.</p>
                  </authorialNote>, and in particular Article 21(1), Article 140 and Article 141(1) thereof,</p>
            </citation>
         </citations>
         <recitals xml:id="recs_d264e79">
            <intro>
               <p>Whereas:</p>
            </intro>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d264e82">
               <num>(1)</num>
               <p>The European Commission, based on the draft implementing technical standards submitted by the European Banking Authority (EBA), recently adopted Commission Implementing Regulation (EU) 2021/451<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="3">
                     <p>Commission Implementing Regulation (EU) 2021/451 of 17 December 2020 laying down implementing technical standards for the application of Regulation (EU) No 575/2013 of the European Parliament and of the Council with regard to supervisory reporting of institutions and repealing Implementing Regulation (EU) No 680/2014 (OJ L 97, 19.3.2021, p. 1).</p>
                  </authorialNote>, which repeals and replaces Commission Implementing Regulation (EU) No 680/2014<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="4">
                     <p>Commission Implementing Regulation (EU) No 680/2014 of 16 April 2014 laying down implementing technical standards with regard to supervisory reporting of institutions according to Regulation (EU) No 575/2013 of the European Parliament and of the Council (OJ L 191, 28.6.2014, p. 1).</p>
                  </authorialNote>.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d264e108">
               <num>(2)</num>
               <p>As Regulation (EU) 2015/534 of the European Central Bank (ECB/2015/13)<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="5">
                     <p>Regulation (EU) 2015/534 of the European Central Bank of 17 March 2015 on reporting of supervisory financial information (ECB/2015/13) (OJ L 86, 31.3.2015, p. 13).</p>
                  </authorialNote> (the &apos;ECB FINREP Regulation&apos;) provides for the use, for its purposes, of templates developed by the EBA and enacted in Implementing Regulation (EU) No 680/2014, references to Implementing Regulation (EU) No 680/2014 in the ECB FINREP Regulation need to be updated accordingly. It is also necessary to take account of other changes that require updates to cross references to Implementing Regulation (EU) 2021/451 to ensure that the ECB FINREP Regulation remains consistent with the applicable Commission Implementing Regulation. Those changes include certain changes in the naming and structure of certain templates in the Annexes to the ECB FINREP Regulation so as to align with the naming and structure of the templates in the Annexes to Implementing Regulation (EU) 2021/451.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d264e128">
               <num>(3)</num>
               <p>On 20 May 2019, the European Parliament and the Council of the European Union adopted Regulation (EU) 2019/876<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="6">
                     <p>Regulation (EU) 2019/876 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 20 May 2019 amending Regulation (EU) No 575/2013 as regards the leverage ratio, the net stable funding ratio, requirements for own funds and eligible liabilities, counterparty credit risk, market risk, exposures to central counterparties, exposures to collective investment undertakings, large exposures, reporting and disclosure requirements, and Regulation (EU) No 648/2012 (OJ L 150, 7.6.2019, p. 1).</p>
                  </authorialNote>, which amends Regulation (EU) No 575/2013 of the European Parliament and of the Council<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="7">
                     <p>Regulation (EU) No 575/2013 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 26 June 2013 on prudential requirements for credit institutions and investment firms and amending Regulation (EU) No 648/2012 (OJ L 176, 27.6.2013, p. 1).</p>
                  </authorialNote>. References to Regulation (EU) No 575/2013 in the ECB FINREP Regulation should be updated accordingly.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d264e158">
               <num>(4)</num>
               <p>In order to ensure legal certainty, it is necessary to ensure that the changes in references apply from the same date as the repeal of Implementing Regulation (EU) No 680/2014. This Regulation should therefore apply from the date of application of Implementing Regulation (EU) 2021/451, on 28 June 2021.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d264e167">
               <num>(5)</num>
               <p>Therefore, Regulation (EU) 2015/534 (ECB/2015/13) should be amended accordingly,</p>
            </recital>
         </recitals>
         <formula name="enactingFormula">
            <p>HAS ADOPTED THIS REGULATION:</p>
         </formula>
      </preamble>
      <body>
         <article xml:id="art_d264e176" leos:compliant="false">
            <num>Article 1</num>
            <heading>Amendments</heading>
            <paragraph>
               <subparagraph>
                  <content>
                     <p>Regulation (EU) 2015/534 (ECB/2015/13) is amended as follows:</p>
                  </content>
               </subparagraph>
               <list>
                  <point>
                     <num>(1)</num>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>Article 1 is amended as follows:</p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                     <list>
                        <point>
                           <num>(a)</num>
                           <alinea>
                              <content>
                                 <p>in paragraph 2, the reference to &apos;Implementing Regulation (EU) No 680/2014&apos; is replaced by a reference to &apos;Commission Implementing Regulation (EU) 2021/451 (*);</p>
                              </content>
                           </alinea>
                           <alinea>
                              <content>
                                 <p><!--not treated use of <NP> -->
                                    <p>
                                       <num>(*)</num>
                                       <content>
                                          <p>Commission Implementing Regulation (EU) 2021/451 of 17 December 2020 laying down implementing technical standards for the application of Regulation (EU) No 575/2013 of the European Parliament and of the Council with regard to supervisory reporting of institutions and repealing Implementing Regulation (EU) No 680/2014 (OJ L 97, 19.3.2021, p. 1).&apos;;</p>
                                       </content>
                                    </p>
                                 </p>
                              </content>
                           </alinea>
                        </point>
                        <point>
                           <num>(b)</num>
                           <alinea>
                              <content>
                                 <p>paragraph 3 is replaced by the following:</p>
                              </content>
                           </alinea>
                           <alinea>
                              <content>
                                 <p>
                                    <mod>
                                       <quotedStructure startQuote="" endQuote="">
                                          <paragraph>
                                             <num>&apos;3.</num>
                                             <content>
                                                <p>Where competent authorities, including the ECB, require institutions to comply with the obligations laid down in Parts Two to Eight of Regulation (EU) No 575/2013 and in Title VII of Directive 2013/36/EU on a sub-consolidated basis in accordance with Article 11(6) of Regulation (EU) No 575/2013, those institutions shall comply also on a sub-consolidated basis with the requirements laid down in this Regulation on a consolidated basis.&apos;;</p>
                                             </content>
                                          </paragraph>
                                       </quotedStructure>
                                    </mod>
                                 </p>
                              </content>
                           </alinea>
                        </point>
                     </list>
                  </point>
                  <point>
                     <num>(2)</num>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>Article 4 is replaced by the following:</p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>
                              <mod>
                                 <quotedStructure startQuote="" endQuote="">
                                    <article xml:id="art_d264e244">
                                       <num>&apos;Article 4</num>
                                       <heading>Format and frequency of reporting on a consolidated basis and reporting reference dates and remittance dates for significant credit institutions applying IFRS for supervisory reporting on a consolidated basis pursuant to Article 24(2) of Regulation (EU) No 575/2013</heading>
                                       <paragraph>
                                          <content>
                                             <p>In accordance with Article 430(4) of Regulation (EU) No 575/2013, significant credit institutions applying IFRS under Regulation (EC) No 1606/2002 for supervisory reporting on a consolidated basis pursuant to Article 24(2) of Regulation (EU) No 575/2013 shall report supervisory financial information, as provided for in Article 11 of Implementing Regulation (EU) 2021/451, on a consolidated basis.&apos;;</p>
                                          </content>
                                       </paragraph>
                                    </article>
                                 </quotedStructure>
                              </mod>
                           </p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                  </point>
                  <point>
                     <num>(3)</num>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>Article 5 is replaced by the following:</p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>
                              <mod>
                                 <quotedStructure startQuote="" endQuote="">
                                    <article xml:id="art_d264e262">
                                       <num>&apos;Article 5</num>
                                       <heading>Format and frequency of reporting on a consolidated basis and reporting reference dates and remittance dates for significant credit institutions applying national accounting frameworks on a consolidated basis based on Directive 86/635/EEC</heading>
                                       <paragraph>
                                          <content>
                                             <p>In accordance with Article 430(9) of Regulation (EU) No 575/2013, significant credit institutions other than those referred to in Article 4, which are subject to national accounting frameworks on a consolidated basis based on Directive 86/635/EEC, shall report supervisory financial information on a consolidated basis as provided for in Article 12 of Implementing Regulation (EU) 2021/451.&apos;;</p>
                                          </content>
                                       </paragraph>
                                    </article>
                                 </quotedStructure>
                              </mod>
                           </p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                  </point>
                  <point>
                     <num>(4)</num>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>Article 6 is amended as follows:</p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                     <list>
                        <point>
                           <num>(a)</num>
                           <alinea>
                              <content>
                                 <p>paragraph 2 is replaced by the following:</p>
                              </content>
                           </alinea>
                           <alinea>
                              <content>
                                 <p>
                                    <mod>
                                       <quotedStructure startQuote="" endQuote="">
                                          <paragraph>
                                             <num>&apos;2.</num>
                                             <content>
                                                <p>The supervisory financial reporting referred to in paragraph 1 shall include the information specified in Article 11 of Implementing Regulation (EU) 2021/451, including information specified in template 40.1 of Annex III to that Regulation, and shall take place with the frequency specified in that Article.&apos;;</p>
                                             </content>
                                          </paragraph>
                                       </quotedStructure>
                                    </mod>
                                 </p>
                              </content>
                           </alinea>
                        </point>
                        <point>
                           <num>(b)</num>
                           <alinea>
                              <content>
                                 <p>paragraph 4 is replaced by the following:</p>
                              </content>
                           </alinea>
                           <alinea>
                              <content>
                                 <p>
                                    <mod>
                                       <quotedStructure startQuote="" endQuote="">
                                          <paragraph>
                                             <num>&apos;4.</num>
                                             <subparagraph>
                                                <content>
                                                   <p>The supervisory financial reporting referred to in paragraph 3 shall include the information specified in Article 12 of Implementing Regulation (EU) 2021/451, including information specified in template 40.1 of Annex IV to that Regulation, and shall take place with the frequency specified in that Article.&apos;;</p>
                                                </content>
                                             </subparagraph>
                                          </paragraph>
                                       </quotedStructure>
                                    </mod>
                                 </p>
                              </content>
                           </alinea>
                        </point>
                        <point>
                           <num>(c)</num>
                           <content>
                              <p>in paragraphs 7 and 8, the reference to &apos;Implementing Regulation (EU) No 680/2014&apos; is replaced by a reference to &apos;Implementing Regulation (EU) 2021/451&apos;;</p>
                           </content>
                        </point>
                     </list>
                  </point>
                  <point>
                     <num>(5)</num>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>Article 7 is amended as follows:</p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                     <list>
                        <point>
                           <num>(a)</num>
                           <alinea>
                              <content>
                                 <p>the last sentence of paragraph 1 is replaced by the following:</p>
                              </content>
                           </alinea>
                           <alinea>
                              <content>
                                 <p>
                                    <mod>
                                       <quotedStructure startQuote="" endQuote="">
                                          <alinea>
                                             <content>
                                                <p>&apos;Supervisory financial reporting by these credit institutions shall take place with the frequency specified in Article 11 of Implementing Regulation (EU) 2021/451 and shall include the common minimum information specified in Annex I.&apos;;</p>
                                             </content>
                                          </alinea>
                                       </quotedStructure>
                                    </mod>
                                 </p>
                              </content>
                           </alinea>
                        </point>
                        <point>
                           <num>(b)</num>
                           <content>
                              <p>in paragraph 2, the reference to &apos;Implementing Regulation (EU) No 680/2014&apos; is replaced by a reference to &apos;Implementing Regulation (EU) 2021/451&apos;;</p>
                           </content>
                        </point>
                        <point>
                           <num>(c)</num>
                           <alinea>
                              <content>
                                 <p>paragraph 4 is replaced by the following:</p>
                              </content>
                           </alinea>
                           <alinea>
                              <content>
                                 <p>
                                    <mod>
                                       <quotedStructure startQuote="" endQuote="">
                                          <paragraph>
                                             <num>&apos;4.</num>
                                             <content>
                                                <p>The supervisory financial reporting referred to in paragraph 3 shall take place with the frequency specified in Article 12 of Implementing Regulation (EU) 2021/451 and shall include the common minimum information specified in Annex I.&apos;;</p>
                                             </content>
                                          </paragraph>
                                       </quotedStructure>
                                    </mod>
                                 </p>
                              </content>
                           </alinea>
                        </point>
                        <point>
                           <num>(d)</num>
                           <content>
                              <p>in paragraph 5, the reference to &apos;Implementing Regulation (EU) No 680/2014&apos; is replaced by a reference to &apos;Implementing Regulation (EU) 2021/451&apos;;</p>
                           </content>
                        </point>
                     </list>
                  </point>
                  <point>
                     <num>(6)</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>in points (a) and (b) of Article 8(4), the reference to &apos;Implementing Regulation (EU) No 680/2014&apos; is replaced by a reference to &apos;Implementing Regulation (EU) 2021/451&apos;;</p>
                     </content>
                  </point>
                  <point>
                     <num>(7)</num>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>Article 9(1) is amended as follows:</p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                     <list>
                        <point>
                           <num>(a)</num>
                           <alinea>
                              <content>
                                 <p>the last sentence of point (a) is replaced by the following:</p>
                              </content>
                           </alinea>
                           <alinea>
                              <content>
                                 <p>
                                    <mod>
                                       <quotedStructure startQuote="" endQuote="">
                                          <alinea>
                                             <content>
                                                <p>&apos;The supervisory financial reporting shall take place with the frequency specified in Article 11 of Implementing Regulation (EU) 2021/451.&apos;;</p>
                                             </content>
                                          </alinea>
                                       </quotedStructure>
                                    </mod>
                                 </p>
                              </content>
                           </alinea>
                        </point>
                        <point>
                           <num>(b)</num>
                           <alinea>
                              <content>
                                 <p>the last sentence of point (b) is replaced by the following:</p>
                              </content>
                           </alinea>
                           <alinea>
                              <content>
                                 <p>
                                    <mod>
                                       <quotedStructure startQuote="" endQuote="">
                                          <alinea>
                                             <content>
                                                <p>&apos;The supervisory financial reporting shall take place with the frequency specified in Article 12 of Implementing Regulation (EU) 2021/451.&apos;;</p>
                                             </content>
                                          </alinea>
                                       </quotedStructure>
                                    </mod>
                                 </p>
                              </content>
                           </alinea>
                        </point>
                     </list>
                  </point>
                  <point>
                     <num>(8)</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>in Article 10(2), the reference to &apos;Implementing Regulation (EU) No 680/2014&apos; is replaced by a reference to &apos;Implementing Regulation (EU) 2021/451&apos;;</p>
                     </content>
                  </point>
                  <point>
                     <num>(9)</num>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>Article 11 is amended as follows:</p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                     <list>
                        <point>
                           <num>(a)</num>
                           <alinea>
                              <content>
                                 <p>paragraph 2 is replaced by the following:</p>
                              </content>
                           </alinea>
                           <alinea>
                              <content>
                                 <p>
                                    <mod>
                                       <quotedStructure startQuote="" endQuote="">
                                          <paragraph>
                                             <num>&apos;2.</num>
                                             <content>
                                                <p>The supervisory financial reporting referred to in paragraph 1 shall take place with the frequency specified in Article 11 of Implementing Regulation (EU) 2021/451 and shall include the common minimum information specified in paragraph 1 of Annex I.&apos;;</p>
                                             </content>
                                          </paragraph>
                                       </quotedStructure>
                                    </mod>
                                 </p>
                              </content>
                           </alinea>
                        </point>
                        <point>
                           <num>(b)</num>
                           <content>
                              <p>in paragraph 3, the reference to &apos;Implementing Regulation (EU) No 680/2014&apos; is replaced by a reference to &apos;Implementing Regulation (EU) 2021/451&apos;;</p>
                           </content>
                        </point>
                        <point>
                           <num>(c)</num>
                           <alinea>
                              <content>
                                 <p>the last sentence of paragraph 4 is replaced by the following:</p>
                              </content>
                           </alinea>
                           <alinea>
                              <content>
                                 <p>
                                    <mod>
                                       <quotedStructure startQuote="" endQuote="">
                                          <alinea>
                                             <content>
                                                <p>&apos;That supervisory financial reporting shall take place with the frequency specified in Article 12 of Implementing Regulation (EU) 2021/451 and shall include the common minimum information specified in paragraph 2 of Annex I.&apos;;</p>
                                             </content>
                                          </alinea>
                                       </quotedStructure>
                                    </mod>
                                 </p>
                              </content>
                           </alinea>
                        </point>
                        <point>
                           <num>(d)</num>
                           <content>
                              <p>in paragraph 5, the reference to &apos;Implementing Regulation (EU) No 680/2014&apos; is replaced by a reference to &apos;Implementing Regulation (EU) 2021/451&apos;;</p>
                           </content>
                        </point>
                     </list>
                  </point>
                  <point>
                     <num>(10)</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>in points (a) and (b) of Article 12(4), the reference to &apos;Implementing Regulation (EU) No 680/2014&apos; is replaced by a reference to &apos;Implementing Regulation (EU) 2021/451&apos;;</p>
                     </content>
                  </point>
                  <point>
                     <num>(11)</num>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>Article 13 is amended as follows:</p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                     <list>
                        <point>
                           <num>(a)</num>
                           <alinea>
                              <content>
                                 <p>paragraph 2 is replaced by the following:</p>
                              </content>
                           </alinea>
                           <alinea>
                              <content>
                                 <p>
                                    <mod>
                                       <quotedStructure startQuote="" endQuote="">
                                          <paragraph>
                                             <num>&apos;2.</num>
                                             <content>
                                                <p>The supervisory financial reporting referred to in paragraph 1 shall take place with the frequency specified in Article 11 of Implementing Regulation (EU) 2021/451 and shall include the common minimum information specified in paragraph 1 of Annex I.&apos;;</p>
                                             </content>
                                          </paragraph>
                                       </quotedStructure>
                                    </mod>
                                 </p>
                              </content>
                           </alinea>
                        </point>
                        <point>
                           <num>(b)</num>
                           <alinea>
                              <content>
                                 <p>paragraph 5 is replaced by the following:</p>
                              </content>
                           </alinea>
                           <alinea>
                              <content>
                                 <p>
                                    <mod>
                                       <quotedStructure startQuote="" endQuote="">
                                          <paragraph>
                                             <num>&apos;5.</num>
                                             <content>
                                                <p>The supervisory financial reporting referred to in paragraph 4 shall take place with the frequency specified in Article 12 of Implementing Regulation (EU) 2021/451 and shall include the common minimum information specified in paragraph 2 of Annex I.&apos;;</p>
                                             </content>
                                          </paragraph>
                                       </quotedStructure>
                                    </mod>
                                 </p>
                              </content>
                           </alinea>
                        </point>
                        <point>
                           <num>(c)</num>
                           <content>
                              <p>in paragraphs 3 and 6, the reference to &apos;Implementing Regulation (EU) No 680/2014&apos; is replaced by a reference to &apos;Implementing Regulation (EU) 2021/451&apos;;</p>
                           </content>
                        </point>
                     </list>
                  </point>
                  <point>
                     <num>(12)</num>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>Article 14 is amended as follows:</p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                     <list>
                        <point>
                           <num>(a)</num>
                           <alinea>
                              <content>
                                 <p>paragraph 2 is replaced by the following:</p>
                              </content>
                           </alinea>
                           <alinea>
                              <content>
                                 <p>
                                    <mod>
                                       <quotedStructure startQuote="" endQuote="">
                                          <paragraph>
                                             <num>&apos;2.</num>
                                             <subparagraph>
                                                <content>
                                                   <p>The supervisory financial reporting referred to in paragraph 1 shall take place with the frequency specified in Article 11 of Implementing Regulation (EU) 2021/451 and shall include the common minimum information specified in Annex II.&apos;;</p>
                                                </content>
                                             </subparagraph>
                                          </paragraph>
                                       </quotedStructure>
                                    </mod>
                                 </p>
                              </content>
                           </alinea>
                        </point>
                        <point>
                           <num>(b)</num>
                           <alinea>
                              <content>
                                 <p>paragraph 5 is replaced by the following:</p>
                              </content>
                           </alinea>
                           <alinea>
                              <content>
                                 <p>
                                    <mod>
                                       <quotedStructure startQuote="" endQuote="">
                                          <paragraph>
                                             <num>&apos;5.</num>
                                             <content>
                                                <p>The supervisory financial reporting referred to in paragraph 4 shall take place with the frequency specified in Article 12 of Implementing Regulation (EU) 2021/451 and shall include the common minimum information specified in Annex II.&apos;;</p>
                                             </content>
                                          </paragraph>
                                       </quotedStructure>
                                    </mod>
                                 </p>
                              </content>
                           </alinea>
                        </point>
                        <point>
                           <num>(c)</num>
                           <content>
                              <p>in paragraphs 3 and 6, the reference to &apos;Implementing Regulation (EU) No 680/2014&apos; is replaced by a reference to &apos;Implementing Regulation (EU) 2021/451&apos;;</p>
                           </content>
                        </point>
                     </list>
                  </point>
                  <point>
                     <num>(13)</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>in points (a) and (b) of Article 15(4), the reference to &apos;Implementing Regulation (EU) No 680/2014&apos; is replaced by a reference to &apos;Implementing Regulation (EU) 2021/451&apos;;</p>
                     </content>
                  </point>
                  <point>
                     <num>(14)</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>the Annexes to Regulation (EU) 2015/534 (ECB/2015/13) are amended in accordance with the Annex to this Regulation.</p>
                     </content>
                  </point>
               </list>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <article xml:id="art_d264e665">
            <num>Article 2</num>
            <heading>Final provisions</heading>
            <paragraph>
               <num>1.</num>
               <content>
                  <p>This Regulation shall enter into force on the fifth day following that of its publication in the <i>Official Journal of the European Union</i>.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph>
               <num>2.</num>
               <content>
                  <p>It shall apply from 28 June 2021.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <clause>
            <content>
               <p>This Regulation shall be binding in its entirety and directly applicable in the Member States in accordance with the Treaties.</p>
            </content>
         </clause>
      </body>
      <conclusions>
         <p>Done at Frankfurt am Main, 14 May 2021.</p>
         <block name="signatory">
            <signature>
               <organization refersTo="">For the Governing Council of the ECB</organization>
               <role refersTo="">The President of the ECB</role>
               <person refersTo="">Christine LAGARDE</person>
            </signature>
         </block>
      </conclusions>
   </bill>
</akomaNtoso>
