<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0"
            xmlns:fmx="http://formex.publications.europa.eu/schema/formex-05.21-20110601.xd"
            xmlns:leos="urn:eu:europa:ec:leos"
            xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema">
   <bill name="">
      <meta xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions">
         <identification source="~COM">
            <FRBRWork>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRcountry value=""/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
         </identification>
      </meta>
      <preface>
         <longTitle>
            <p>
               <docStage/>
               <docType>COMMISSION REGULATION (EU) 2021/1247</docType>of 29 July 2021<docPurpose>amending Annex II to Regulation (EC) No 396/2005 of the European Parliament and of the Council as regards maximum residue levels for mandestrobin in grapes and strawberries</docPurpose>
            </p>
         </longTitle>
         <container name="EEArelevance">
            <p>(Text with EEA relevance)</p>
         </container>
      </preface>
      <preamble>
         <formula name="actingEntity">
            <p>THE EUROPEAN COMMISSION,</p>
         </formula>
         <citations>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to Regulation (EC) No 396/2005 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 23 February 2005 on maximum residue levels of pesticides in or on food and feed of plant and animal origin and amending Council Directive 91/414/EEC<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="1">
                     <p>OJ L 70, 16.3.2005, p. 1.</p>
                  </authorialNote>, and in particular Article 14(1)(a) thereof,</p>
            </citation>
         </citations>
         <recitals xml:id="recs_d504e71">
            <intro>
               <p>Whereas:</p>
            </intro>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d504e74">
               <num>(1)</num>
               <p>For mandestrobin, maximum residue levels (MRLs) were set in Annex II to Regulation (EC) No 396/2005.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d504e80">
               <num>(2)</num>
               <p>In accordance with Article 6(2) and (4) of Regulation (EC) No 396/2005 an application for import tolerance was submitted for mandestrobin used in Canada on strawberries and grapes. The applicant claims that the authorised uses of that substance on such crops in Canada lead to residues exceeding the MRLs contained in Regulation (EC) No 396/2005 and that higher MRLs are necessary to avoid trade barriers for the importation of grapes and strawberries.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d504e86">
               <num>(3)</num>
               <p>In accordance with Article 8 of Regulation (EC) No 396/2005, the application was evaluated by the Member State concerned and the evaluation report was forwarded to the Commission.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d504e92">
               <num>(4)</num>
               <p>The European Food Safety Authority (&apos;the Authority&apos;) assessed the application and the evaluation report, examining in particular the risks to the consumer and, where relevant, to animals and gave a reasoned opinion on the proposed MRLs<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="2">
                     <p>EFSA scientific reports available online: http://www.efsa.europa.eu Reasoned opinion on the setting of import tolerances for mandestrobin in strawberries and table and wine grapes. <i>EFSA Journal</i> 2018;16(8):5395.</p>
                  </authorialNote>. It forwarded that opinion to the applicant, the Commission and the Member States and made it available to the public.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d504e109">
               <num>(5)</num>
               <p>The Authority concluded that all requirements with respect to data were met and that the modifications to the MRLs requested by the applicant were acceptable with regard to consumer safety on the basis of a consumer exposure assessment for 27 specific European consumer groups. It took into account the most recent information on the toxicological properties of the substance. The lifetime exposure to the substance via consumption of all food products that may contain it showed that there is no risk that the acceptable daily intake is exceeded. Moreover, the Authority concluded that the establishment of an acute reference dose is not necessary due to the low acute toxicity profile of the substance.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d504e115">
               <num>(6)</num>
               <p>Based on the reasoned opinion of the Authority and taking into account the factors relevant to the matter under consideration, the proposed modifications to the MRLs fulfil the requirements of Article 14(2) of Regulation (EC) No 396/2005.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d504e121">
               <num>(7)</num>
               <p>Regulation (EC) No 396/2005 should therefore be amended accordingly.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d504e127">
               <num>(8)</num>
               <p>The measures provided for in this Regulation are in accordance with the opinion of the Standing Committee on Plants, Animals, Food and Feed,</p>
            </recital>
         </recitals>
         <formula name="enactingFormula">
            <p>HAS ADOPTED THIS REGULATION:</p>
         </formula>
      </preamble>
      <body>
         <article xml:id="art_d504e137">
            <num>Article 1</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>Annex II to Regulation (EC) No 396/2005 is amended in accordance with the Annex to this Regulation.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <article xml:id="art_d504e142">
            <num>Article 2</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>This Regulation shall enter into force on the twentieth day following that of its publication in the <i>Official Journal of the European Union</i>.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <clause>
            <content>
               <p>This Regulation shall be binding in its entirety and directly applicable in all Member States.</p>
            </content>
         </clause>
      </body>
      <conclusions>
         <p>Done at Brussels, 29 July 2021.</p>
         <block name="signatory">
            <signature>
               <organization refersTo="">For the Commission</organization>
               <role refersTo="">The President</role>
               <person refersTo="">Ursula VON DER LEYEN</person>
            </signature>
         </block>
      </conclusions>
   </bill>
</akomaNtoso>
