<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0"
            xmlns:fmx="http://formex.publications.europa.eu/schema/formex-05.21-20110601.xd"
            xmlns:leos="urn:eu:europa:ec:leos"
            xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema">
   <bill name="">
      <meta xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions">
         <identification source="~COM">
            <FRBRWork>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRcountry value=""/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
         </identification>
      </meta>
      <preface>
         <longTitle>
            <p>
               <docStage/>
               <docType>COMMISSION REGULATION (EU) 2017/1410</docType>of 2 August 2017<docPurpose>amending Annexes II and III to Regulation (EC) No 1223/2009 of the European Parliament and of the Council on cosmetic products</docPurpose>
            </p>
         </longTitle>
         <container name="EEArelevance">
            <p>(Text with EEA relevance)</p>
         </container>
      </preface>
      <preamble>
         <formula name="actingEntity">
            <p>THE EUROPEAN COMMISSION,</p>
         </formula>
         <citations>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to Regulation (EC) No 1223/2009 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 30 November 2009 on cosmetic products<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="1">
                     <p>OJ L 342, 22.12.2009, p. 59.</p>
                  </authorialNote>, and in particular Article 31(1) thereof,</p>
            </citation>
         </citations>
         <recitals xml:id="recs_d39e71">
            <intro>
               <p>Whereas:</p>
            </intro>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d39e74">
               <num>(1)</num>
               <p>The Scientific Committee on Consumer Safety (SCCS) concluded in its opinion of 26&#45;27 June 2012<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="2">
                     <p>SCCS/1459/11.</p>
                  </authorialNote> that 3- and 4-(4-Hydroxy-4-methylpentyl) cyclohex-3-ene-1-carbaldehyde (HICC), with the INCI name of Hydroxyisohexyl 3-Cyclohexene Carboxaldehyde, 2,6-Dihydroxy-4-methyl-benzaldehyde (atranol) and 3-Chloro-2,6-Dihydroxy-4-methyl-benzaldehyde (chloroatranol) should not be used in cosmetic products as they are the fragrance allergens which caused the highest number of contact allergies cases in past years.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d39e89">
               <num>(2)</num>
               <p>Consequently, there is a potential risk to human health and those substances should therefore be prohibited in cosmetic products.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d39e95">
               <num>(3)</num>
               <p>HICC is regulated in entry 79 of Annex III to Regulation (EC) No 1223/2009, where it is provided that its presence must be indicated in the list of ingredients referred to in Article 19(1)(g) of that Regulation when its concentration exceeds 0,001 % in leave-on products and 0,01 % in rinse-off products. Since HICC should be prohibited in cosmetic products, it is necessary to delete that entry.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d39e101">
               <num>(4)</num>
               <p>The SCCS indicated in its opinion of 26-27 June 2012 that atranol and chloroatranol are natural components of oak tree moss (<i>Evernia prunastri</i>) and treemoss (<i>Evernia furfuracea</i>) extracts regulated in entry 91 and 92, respectively, of Annex III to Regulation (EC) No 1223/2009.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d39e119">
               <num>(5)</num>
               <p>It is appropriate to provide for reasonable periods of time in order for the industry to adapt to the new prohibitions and for this reason no longer place or make available on the market products concerned which contain one or more of the prohibited substances. When determining those periods of time, due account should also be taken of the potential risk of those products to human health. The restriction for HICC set out in entry 79 of Annex III to Regulation (EC) No 1223/2009 should continue to apply until the making available of products containing that substance is no longer allowed. The deletion of that entry should therefore be deferred.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d39e126">
               <num>(6)</num>
               <p>In particular, the exceptionally complex and lengthy procedure for fragrance reformulation and consumers&apos; concerns over the change of the olfactory properties of fragrances should be reflected in longer than usual duration of the deadline given to the industry for adjustments of products. Manifestations of contact allergies to fragrances are normally confined to skin. Consumers with contact allergy to fragrance allergens often are aware that they cannot tolerate scented products on their skin and therefore can avoid them.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d39e132">
               <num>(7)</num>
               <p>Annex II and III to Regulation (EC) No 1223/2009 should therefore be amended accordingly.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d39e138">
               <num>(8)</num>
               <p>The measures provided for in this Regulation are in accordance with the opinion of the Standing Committee on Cosmetic Products,</p>
            </recital>
         </recitals>
         <formula name="enactingFormula">
            <p>HAS ADOPTED THIS REGULATION:</p>
         </formula>
      </preamble>
      <body>
         <article xml:id="art_d39e147">
            <num>Article 1</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>Annex II and III to Regulation (EC) No 1223/2009 are amended in accordance with the Annex to this Regulation.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <article xml:id="art_d39e152">
            <num>Article 2</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>From 23 August 2019 cosmetic products containing one or more of the substances prohibited by this Regulation shall not be placed on the Union market.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>From 23 August 2021 cosmetic products containing one or more of the substances prohibited by this Regulation shall be not be made available on the Union market.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <article xml:id="art_d39e165">
            <num>Article 3</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>This Regulation shall enter into force on the twentieth day following that of its publication in the <i>Official Journal of the European Union</i>.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>Point (2) of the Annex shall apply from 23 August 2021.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <clause>
            <content>
               <p>This Regulation shall be binding in its entirety and directly applicable in all Member States.</p>
            </content>
         </clause>
      </body>
      <conclusions>
         <p>Done at Brussels, 2 August 2017.</p>
         <block name="signatory">
            <signature>
               <organization refersTo="">For the Commission</organization>
               <role refersTo="">The President</role>
               <person refersTo="">Jean-Claude JUNCKER</person>
            </signature>
         </block>
      </conclusions>
   </bill>
</akomaNtoso>
