<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0"
            xmlns:fmx="http://formex.publications.europa.eu/schema/formex-05.21-20110601.xd"
            xmlns:leos="urn:eu:europa:ec:leos"
            xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema">
   <bill name="">
      <meta xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions">
         <identification source="~COM">
            <FRBRWork>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRcountry value=""/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
         </identification>
      </meta>
      <preface>
         <longTitle>
            <p>
               <docStage/>
               <docType>COMMISSION REGULATION (EU) 2020/205</docType>of 14 February 2020<docPurpose>amending Regulation (EC) No 2073/2005 as regards Salmonella in reptile meat</docPurpose>
            </p>
         </longTitle>
         <container name="EEArelevance">
            <p>(Text with EEA relevance)</p>
         </container>
      </preface>
      <preamble>
         <formula name="actingEntity">
            <p>THE EUROPEAN COMMISSION,</p>
         </formula>
         <citations>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to Regulation (EC) No 852/2004 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 29 April 2004 on the hygiene of foodstuffs<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="1">
                     <p>OJ L 139, 30.4.2004, p. 1.</p>
                  </authorialNote>, and in particular Article 4(4) thereof,</p>
            </citation>
         </citations>
         <recitals xml:id="recs_d49e74">
            <intro>
               <p>Whereas:</p>
            </intro>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d49e77">
               <num>(1)</num>
               <p>Commission Regulation (EC) No 2073/2005<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="2">
                     <p>Commission Regulation (EC) No 2073/2005 of 15 November 2005 on microbiological criteria for foodstuffs (OJ L 338, 22.12.2005, p. 1).</p>
                  </authorialNote> lays down the microbiological criteria for certain micro-organisms and the implementing rules to be complied with by food business operators in respect of the general and specific hygiene requirements referred to in Article 4 of Regulation (EC) No 852/2004.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d49e93">
               <num>(2)</num>
               <p>In particular, Regulation (EC) No 2073/2005 lays down food safety criteria which define the acceptability of a product or a batch of foodstuff applicable to products placed in the market. That Regulation does not provide for food safety criteria for reptile meat.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d49e99">
               <num>(3)</num>
               <p>The &apos;European Union summary report on trends and sources of zoonoses, zoonotic agents and food-borne outbreaks in 2016&apos;<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="3">
                     <p>
                        <i>EFSA Journal</i> 2017;15(12):5077.</p>
                  </authorialNote> published by the European Food Safety Authority (EFSA) and the European Centre for Disease Prevention and Control states that human salmonellosis is the second most reported human food-borne illness in the Union with around 95000 cases reported annually.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d49e117">
               <num>(4)</num>
               <p>In 2007, EFSA adopted a scientific opinion on public health risks involved in the human consumption of reptile meat<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="4">
                     <p>
                        <i>EFSA Journal</i> (2007) 578, 1-55.</p>
                  </authorialNote> according to which reptiles are well-known reservoirs for <i>Salmonella</i> species. The scientific opinion reviews farming practices and observes a documented high intestinal carrier rate in live crocodilians that is reflected in an equally high contamination rate in their fresh and frozen meat. The scientific opinion concludes that <i>Salmonella</i> is considered to be the most relevant bacterial hazard that may occur in reptile meat and it constitutes a significant public health risk.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d49e135">
               <num>(5)</num>
               <p>Production of reptile meat in the Union is limited, but according to data available in Eurostat&apos;s reference database for detailed statistics on international trade in goods (Comext)<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="5">
                     <p>Combined nomenclature codes 02085000 and 02109300 as defined in Commission Implementing Regulation (EU) 2017/1925 amending Annex I to Council Regulation (EEC) No 2658/87 on the tariff and statistical nomenclature and on the Common Customs Tariff (OJ L 282, 31.10.2017, p. 1).</p>
                  </authorialNote>, imports from third countries of fresh, chilled or frozen meat and edible offal of reptiles have shown an upward trend over the last 10 years with an increase of over 50 % in the quantity imported during the period 2007-2017 and an average yearly import in the Union of nearly 100 tons.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d49e154">
               <num>(6)</num>
               <p>Considering the potential significant health risk posed by the possible presence of <i>Salmonella</i> in reptile meat, a food safety criterion should be laid down in Regulation (EC) No 2073/2005 for reptile meat. This food safety criterion should oblige food business operators to take measures at previous stages of reptile meat production contributing to the reduction of the presence of all serotypes of <i>Salmonella</i> with public health significance.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d49e166">
               <num>(7)</num>
               <p>The international standard EN/ISO 6579-1 is the horizontal method for the detection of <i>Salmonella</i> in food and animal feeding stuffs. Annex I to Regulation (EC) No 2073/2005 provides for that standard to be the analytical reference method for <i>Salmonella</i> food safety criteria. It should, therefore, be laid down as the analytical reference method to verify the compliance of a <i>Salmonella</i> in reptile meat food safety criterion.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d49e182">
               <num>(8)</num>
               <p>Regulation (EC) No 2073/2005 should therefore be amended accordingly.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d49e188">
               <num>(9)</num>
               <p>The measures provided for in this Regulation are in accordance with the opinion of the Standing Committee on Plants, Animals, Food and Feed,</p>
            </recital>
         </recitals>
         <formula name="enactingFormula">
            <p>HAS ADOPTED THIS REGULATION:</p>
         </formula>
      </preamble>
      <body>
         <article xml:id="art_d49e197" leos:compliant="false">
            <num>Article 1</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <subparagraph>
                  <content>
                     <p>Regulation (EC) No 2073/2005 is amended as follows:</p>
                  </content>
               </subparagraph>
               <list>
                  <point>
                     <num>(1)</num>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>in Article 2, the following point (q) is added:</p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>
                              <mod>
                                 <quotedStructure startQuote="" endQuote="">
                                    <list>
                                       <num>&apos;(q)</num>
                                       <content>
                                          <p>&quot;reptile meat&quot; means reptile meat as laid down in point (16) of Article 2 of Commission Delegated Regulation (EU) 2019/625<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="6">
                                                <p>Commission Delegated Regulation (EU) 2019/625 of 4 March 2019 supplementing Regulation (EU) 2017/625 of the European Parliament and of the Council with regard to requirements for the entry into the Union of consignments of certain animals and goods intended for human consumption (OJ L 131, 17.5.2019, p. 18).&apos;;</p>
                                             </authorialNote>.</p>
                                       </content>
                                    </list>
                                 </quotedStructure>
                              </mod>
                           </p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                  </point>
                  <point>
                     <num>(2)</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>Annex I is amended in accordance with the Annex to this Regulation.</p>
                     </content>
                  </point>
               </list>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <article xml:id="art_d49e241">
            <num>Article 2</num>
            <heading/>
         </article>
         <clause>
            <content>
               <p>This Regulation shall enter into force on the twentieth day following that of its publication in the <i>Official Journal of the European Union</i>.</p>
            </content>
         </clause>
         <clause>
            <content>
               <p>This Regulation shall be binding in its entirety and directly applicable in all Member States.</p>
            </content>
         </clause>
      </body>
      <conclusions>
         <p>Done at Brussels, 14 February 2020.</p>
         <block name="signatory">
            <signature>
               <organization refersTo="">For the Commission</organization>
               <role refersTo="">The President</role>
               <person refersTo="">Ursula VON DER LEYEN</person>
            </signature>
         </block>
      </conclusions>
   </bill>
</akomaNtoso>
