L1622019EN2710120190619EN0002271271<p xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">Corrigendum to Regulation No 83 of the Economic Commission for Europe of the United Nations (UNECE) &#45; Uniform provisions concerning the approval of vehicles with regard to the emission of pollutants according to engine fuel requirements [2019/253]</p>
<p xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">(Official Journal of the European Union L 45 of 15 February 2019)</p>On page 2, point 1.1:<p xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0"><!--default P | TXT -->for:</p>
<mod xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
   <quotedStructure startQuote="" endQuote="">
      <p><!--default P | TXT -->&apos;This Regulation shall apply to vehicles of categories M<sub>1</sub>, M<sub>2</sub>, N<sub>1</sub> and N<sub>2</sub> with a reference mass not exceeding 2610 kg (<sup>1</sup>).</p>
      <p><!--default P | TXT -->At the manufacturer&apos;s request, type approval granted under this Regulation may be extended from vehicles mentioned above to special purpose vehicles of categories M<sub>1</sub>, M<sub>2</sub>, N<sub>1</sub> and N<sub>2</sub> regardless of their reference mass. The manufacturer shall demonstrate to the Type Approval Authority which granted the type approval that the vehicle in question is a special purpose vehicle.&apos;,</p>
   </quotedStructure>
</mod>
<p xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0"><!--default P | TXT -->read:</p>
<mod xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
   <quotedStructure startQuote="" endQuote="">
      <p><!--default P | TXT -->&apos;This Regulation shall apply to vehicles of categories M<sub>1</sub>, M<sub>2</sub>, N<sub>1</sub> and N<sub>2</sub> with a reference mass not exceeding 2610 kg (<sup>1</sup>).</p>
      <p><!--default P | TXT -->At the manufacturer&apos;s request, type approval granted under this Regulation may be extended from vehicles mentioned above to M<sub>1</sub>, M<sub>2</sub>, N<sub>1</sub> and N<sub>2</sub> vehicles with a reference mass not exceeding 2840 kg and which meet the conditions laid down in this Regulation.</p>
      <p><!--default P | TXT -->At the manufacturer&apos;s request, type approval granted under this Regulation may be extended from vehicles mentioned above to special purpose vehicles of categories M<sub>1</sub>, M<sub>2</sub>, N<sub>1</sub> and N<sub>2</sub> regardless of their reference mass. The manufacturer shall demonstrate to the Type Approval Authority which granted the type approval that the vehicle in question is a special purpose vehicle.&apos;.</p>
   </quotedStructure>
</mod>
