<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0"
            xmlns:fmx="http://formex.publications.europa.eu/schema/formex-05.21-20110601.xd"
            xmlns:leos="urn:eu:europa:ec:leos"
            xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema">
   <bill name="">
      <meta xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions">
         <identification source="~COM">
            <FRBRWork>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRcountry value=""/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
         </identification>
      </meta>
      <preface>
         <longTitle>
            <p>
               <docStage/>
               <docType>COMMISSION REGULATION (EU) 2018/1472</docType>of 28 September 2018<docPurpose>amending Annex II to Regulation (EC) No 1333/2008 of the European Parliament and of the Council and the Annex to Commission Regulation (EU) No 231/2012 as regards Cochineal, Carminic acid, Carmines (E 120)</docPurpose>
            </p>
         </longTitle>
         <container name="EEArelevance">
            <p>(Text with EEA relevance)</p>
         </container>
      </preface>
      <preamble>
         <formula name="actingEntity">
            <p>THE EUROPEAN COMMISSION,</p>
         </formula>
         <citations>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to Regulation (EC) No 1333/2008 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 16 December 2008 on food additives<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="1">
                     <p>OJ L 354, 31.12.2008, p. 16.</p>
                  </authorialNote>, and in particular Article 10(3) and Article 14 thereof,</p>
            </citation>
         </citations>
         <recitals xml:id="recs_d271e71">
            <intro>
               <p>Whereas:</p>
            </intro>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d271e74">
               <num>(1)</num>
               <p>Annex II to Regulation (EC) No 1333/2008 lays down a Union list of food additives approved for use in food and their conditions of use.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d271e80">
               <num>(2)</num>
               <p>Commission Regulation (EU) No 231/2012<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="2">
                     <p>Commission Regulation (EU) No 231/2012 of 9 March 2012 laying down specifications for food additives listed in Annexes II and III to Regulation (EC) No 1333/2008 of the European Parliament and of the Council (OJ L 83, 22.3.2012, p. 1).</p>
                  </authorialNote> lays down specifications for food additives that are listed in Annexes II and III to Regulation (EC) No 1333/2008.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d271e96">
               <num>(3)</num>
               <p>Cochineal, Carminic acid, Carmines (E 120) is a substance authorised as a colour in a variety of foods in accordance with Annex II to Regulation (EC) No 1333/2008.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d271e102">
               <num>(4)</num>
               <p>Article 32(1) of Regulation (EC) No 1333/2008 provides that all food additives that were already permitted in the Union before 20 January 2009 are subject to a new risk assessment by the European Food Safety Authority (&apos;the Authority&apos;).</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d271e115">
               <num>(5)</num>
               <p>For that purpose, a program for the re-evaluation of food additives is laid down in Commission Regulation (EU) No 257/2010<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="3">
                     <p>Commission Regulation (EU) No 257/2010 of 25 March 2010 setting up the program for the re-evaluation of approved food additives in accordance with Regulation (EC) No 1333/2008 of the European Parliament and of the Council on food additives (OJ L 80, 26.3.2010, p. 19).</p>
                  </authorialNote>, according to which the re-evaluation of colours had to be completed by 31 December 2015.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d271e134">
               <num>(6)</num>
               <p>On 18 November 2015 the Authority delivered a Scientific Opinion on the re-evaluation of cochineal, carminic acid, carmines (E 120) as a food additive<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="4">
                     <p>EFSA <i>Journal 2015</i>; 13(11):4288.</p>
                  </authorialNote>. The Authority concluded that the present dataset did not give reasons to revise the Acceptable Daily Intake (ADI) value for E 120 and that the refined exposure estimates were below the ADI for all population groups. However, the Authority recommended to revise the current title &apos;Cochineal, Carminic acid, Carmines&apos;, so that it would more accurately reflect the material used as a food additive and to update the specifications as regards the percentage of material not accounted for, the maximum limits for toxic elements and the presence of proteinaceous compounds.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d271e155">
               <num>(7)</num>
               <p>Pursuant to Article 10(3) of Regulation (EC) No 1333/2008, the Union list of approved food additives shall be amended in accordance with the procedure referred to in Regulation (EC) No 1331/2008 of the European Parliament and of the Council<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="5">
                     <p>Regulation (EC) No 1331/2008 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 16 December 2008 establishing a common authorisation procedure for food additives, food enzymes and food flavourings (OJ L 354, 31.12.2008, p. 1).</p>
                  </authorialNote>.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d271e171">
               <num>(8)</num>
               <p>Article 3(1) of Regulation (EC) No 1331/2008 provides that the Union list of food additives may be updated either on the initiative of the Commission or following an application.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d271e177">
               <num>(9)</num>
               <p>It is therefore appropriate to amend Annex II to Regulation (EC) No 1333/2008 and the Annex to Regulation (EU) No 231/2012.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d271e184">
               <num>(10)</num>
               <p>A reasonable period should be allowed to elapse before the amendments become applicable in order to permit food business operators to meet the new requirements laid down in this Regulation.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d271e190">
               <num>(11)</num>
               <p>The measures provided for in this Regulation are in accordance with the opinion of the Standing Committee on Plants, Animals, Food and Feed,</p>
            </recital>
         </recitals>
         <formula name="enactingFormula">
            <p>HAS ADOPTED THIS REGULATION:</p>
         </formula>
      </preamble>
      <body>
         <article xml:id="art_d271e199">
            <num>Article 1</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>In Annex II to Regulation (EC) No 1333/2008 whenever a reference is made to &apos;E 120 Cochineal, Carminic acid, Carmines&apos; it shall be replaced by &apos;E 120 Carminic acid, Carmine&apos;.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <article xml:id="art_d271e212">
            <num>Article 2</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>The Annex to Regulation (EU) No 231/2012 is amended in accordance with the Annex to this Regulation.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <article xml:id="art_d271e217">
            <num>Article 3</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>This Regulation shall enter into force on the twentieth day following that of its publication in the <i>Official Journal of the European Union</i>.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>It shall apply from 23 October 2019.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <clause>
            <content>
               <p>This Regulation shall be binding in its entirety and directly applicable in all Member States.</p>
            </content>
         </clause>
      </body>
      <conclusions>
         <p>Done at Brussels, 28 September 2018.</p>
         <block name="signatory">
            <signature>
               <organization refersTo="">For the Commission</organization>
               <role refersTo="">The President</role>
               <person refersTo="">Jean-Claude JUNCKER</person>
            </signature>
         </block>
      </conclusions>
   </bill>
</akomaNtoso>
