<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0"
            xmlns:fmx="http://formex.publications.europa.eu/schema/formex-05.21-20110601.xd"
            xmlns:leos="urn:eu:europa:ec:leos"
            xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema">
   <bill name="">
      <meta xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions">
         <identification source="~COM">
            <FRBRWork>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRcountry value=""/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
         </identification>
      </meta>
      <preface>
         <longTitle>
            <p>
               <docStage/>
               <docType>COMMISSION REGULATION (EU) 2016/1120</docType>of 11 July 2016<docPurpose>amending Annex IV to Regulation (EC) No 1223/2009 of the European Parliament and of the Council on cosmetic products</docPurpose>
            </p>
         </longTitle>
         <container name="EEArelevance">
            <p>(Text with EEA relevance)</p>
         </container>
      </preface>
      <preamble>
         <formula name="actingEntity">
            <p>THE EUROPEAN COMMISSION,</p>
         </formula>
         <citations>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to Regulation (EC) No 1223/2009 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 30 November 2009 on cosmetic products<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="1">
                     <p>OJ L 342, 22.12.2009, p. 59.</p>
                  </authorialNote>, and in particular Article 31(2) thereof,</p>
            </citation>
         </citations>
         <recitals xml:id="recs_d617e71">
            <intro>
               <p>Whereas:</p>
            </intro>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d617e74">
               <num>(1)</num>
               <p>Carbon Black is authorized as a colorant in cosmetics under entry 126 of Annex IV to Regulation (EC) No 1223/2009. The Scientific Committee on Consumer Safety (&apos;SCCS&apos;) carried out a risk assessment of Carbon Black (nano) and adopted an opinion on 12 December 2013<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="2">
                     <p>SCCS/1515/13 Revision of 15 December 2015, http://ec.europa.eu/health/scientific_committees/consumer_safety/docs/sccs_o_144.pdf</p>
                  </authorialNote>, in which it concluded that the use of Carbon Black in its nano-structured form (with a primary particle size of 20 nm or larger) at a concentration up to 10 % w/w as a colorant in cosmetic products does not pose any risk of adverse effects in humans after application on healthy, intact skin.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d617e93">
               <num>(2)</num>
               <p>Moreover, the SCCS indicated, in a further opinion of 23 September 2014 for clarification of the meaning of the term &apos;sprayable applications/products&apos; for the nano forms of Carbon Black CI 77266, Titanium Dioxide and Zinc Oxide<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="3">
                     <p>SCCS/1539/14 Revision of 25 June 2015, http://ec.europa.eu/health/scientific_committees/consumer_safety/docs/sccs_o_163.pdf</p>
                  </authorialNote>, that the opinion on Carbon Black (nano) does not apply to applications that might lead to exposure of the consumer&apos;s lungs to Carbon Black nanoparticles by inhalation.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d617e113">
               <num>(3)</num>
               <p>The SCCS conclusions apply to Carbon Black (nano) with a defined purity and impurity profile. Furthermore, the purity criteria set out for non-nano Carbon Black are no longer up-to-date and should be removed, as Commission Directive 95/45/EC<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="4">
                     <p>Commission Directive 95/45/EC of 26 July 1995 laying down specific purity criteria concerning colours for use in foodstuffs (OJ L 226, 22.9.1995, p. 1).</p>
                  </authorialNote> was repealed by Directive 2008/128/EC<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="5">
                     <p>Commission Directive 2008/128/EC of 22 December 2008 laying down specific purity criteria concerning colours for use in foodstuffs (OJ L 6, 10.1.2009, p. 20).</p>
                  </authorialNote>. Those criteria should be replaced by the criteria applicable to Carbon Black (nano).</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d617e139">
               <num>(4)</num>
               <p>In light of the SCCS opinions mentioned above, the Commission considers that Carbon Black (nano) (according to the SCCS&apos;s specifications) should be authorized for use as a colorant in cosmetic products at a maximum concentration of 10 % w/w, except in applications that may lead to exposure of the end user&apos;s lungs by inhalation.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d617e145">
               <num>(5)</num>
               <p>The Commission considers that Annex IV to Regulation (EC) No 1223/2009 should be amended for the purpose of adapting it to technical and scientific progress.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d617e152">
               <num>(6)</num>
               <p>The measures provided for in this Regulation are in accordance with the opinion of the Standing Committee on Cosmetic Products,</p>
            </recital>
         </recitals>
         <formula name="enactingFormula">
            <p>HAS ADOPTED THIS REGULATION:</p>
         </formula>
      </preamble>
      <body>
         <article xml:id="art_d617e161">
            <num>Article 1</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>Annex IV to Regulation (EC) No 1223/2009 is amended in accordance with the Annex to this Regulation.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <article xml:id="art_d617e166">
            <num>Article 2</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>This Regulation shall enter into force on the twentieth day following that of its publication in the <i>Official Journal of the European Union</i>.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <clause>
            <content>
               <p>This Regulation shall be binding in its entirety and directly applicable in all Member States.</p>
            </content>
         </clause>
      </body>
      <conclusions>
         <p>Done at Brussels, 11 July 2016.</p>
         <block name="signatory">
            <signature>
               <organization refersTo="">For the Commission</organization>
               <role refersTo="">The President</role>
               <person refersTo="">Jean-Claude JUNCKER</person>
            </signature>
         </block>
      </conclusions>
   </bill>
</akomaNtoso>
