<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0"
            xmlns:fmx="http://formex.publications.europa.eu/schema/formex-05.21-20110601.xd"
            xmlns:leos="urn:eu:europa:ec:leos"
            xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema">
   <bill name="">
      <meta xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions">
         <identification source="~COM">
            <FRBRWork>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRcountry value=""/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
         </identification>
      </meta>
      <preface>
         <longTitle>
            <p>
               <docStage/>
               <docType>COMMISSION REGULATION (EU) 2017/1221</docType>of 22 June 2017<docPurpose>amending Regulation (EC) No 692/2008 as regards the methodology for the determination of evaporative emissions (Type 4 test)</docPurpose>
            </p>
         </longTitle>
         <container name="EEArelevance">
            <p>(Text with EEA relevance)</p>
         </container>
      </preface>
      <preamble>
         <formula name="actingEntity">
            <p>THE EUROPEAN COMMISSION,</p>
         </formula>
         <citations>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to Regulation (EC) No 715/2007 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 20 June 2007 on type-approval of motor vehicles with respect to emissions from light passenger and commercial vehicles (Euro 5 and Euro 6) and on access to vehicle repair and maintenance information<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="1">
                     <p>OJ L 171, 29.6.2007, p. 1.</p>
                  </authorialNote>, and in particular Article 14(3) thereof,</p>
            </citation>
         </citations>
         <recitals xml:id="recs_d163e71">
            <intro>
               <p>Whereas:</p>
            </intro>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d163e74">
               <num>(1)</num>
               <p>Regulation (EC) No 715/2007 requires new light-duty vehicles to comply with certain emission limits including evaporative emissions. The specific technical provisions necessary to implement that Regulation were adopted by Commission Regulation (EC) No 692/2008<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="2">
                     <p>Commission Regulation (EC) No 692/2008 of 18 July 2008 implementing and amending Regulation (EC) No 715/2007 of the European Parliament and of the Council on type-approval of motor vehicles with respect to emissions from light passenger and commercial vehicles (Euro 5 and Euro 6) and on access to vehicle repair and maintenance information (OJ L 199, 28.7.2008, p. 1).</p>
                  </authorialNote>.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d163e90">
               <num>(2)</num>
               <p>The Commission established a working group in March 2011 involving all interested stakeholders for reviewing the existing methodology for measuring evaporative emissions and developing a new one, addressing mainly the issues of purging strategy, effect of ethanol on canister working capacity, durability, fuel permeation and refuelling emissions.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d163e96">
               <num>(3)</num>
               <p>The working group based its work on many elements contained in two reports published by the Joint Research Centre of the Commission entitled &apos;Estimating the Costs and Benefits of Introducing a new European Evaporative Emissions Test Procedure&apos; and &apos;Review of the European Test Procedure for Evaporative Emissions: Main Issues and Proposed Solutions&apos;.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d163e110">
               <num>(4)</num>
               <p>The analysis of the working group has identified a number of shortfalls which undermine the efficacy of the evaporative emissions control and need to be remedied in order to ensure an satisfactory level of environmental protection. It is therefore appropriate to introduce two new procedures for aging of the carbon canister and for the definition of a permeability of the fuel system in the existing type-approval procedure.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d163e116">
               <num>(5)</num>
               <p>The addition of ethanol in the European petrol fuels, especially when splash-blended has an effect in the vapour pressure of the fuel. The E10 reference fuel should therefore be used in testing in order to better reflect the currently used fuel in the Union.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d163e122">
               <num>(6)</num>
               <p>Monolayer plastic tanks are still being sold in the Union and are expected to be a significant part of the European fleet until the year 2030. However, such tanks are permeable to ethanol, which is thus emitted in the environment. Therefore, a dedicated procedure to measure the permeation of ethanol is needed in order to take into account this effect.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d163e128">
               <num>(7)</num>
               <p>The addition of ethanol was also proven to affect the durability of carbon canisters in studies performed by the Swedish Road Administration and TUV Nord. For this reason, a new procedure should be added in order to age the canister. The aged canister should then be used in the tested vehicle during the SHED test.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d163e134">
               <num>(8)</num>
               <p>The current purging strategies employed in vehicles in the Union are not adequate especially for urban driving and thus may lead to increased bleed emissions. Therefore, the test drive before the SHED test was reviewed and the duration of the diurnal test should be increased to 48 hours.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d163e140">
               <num>(9)</num>
               <p>Regulation (EC) No 692/2008 should therefore be amended accordingly.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d163e148">
               <num>(10)</num>
               <p>The measures provided for in this Regulation are in accordance with the opinion of the Technical Committee &#45; Motor Vehicles,</p>
            </recital>
         </recitals>
         <formula name="enactingFormula">
            <p>HAS ADOPTED THIS REGULATION:</p>
         </formula>
      </preamble>
      <body>
         <article xml:id="art_d163e157" leos:compliant="false">
            <num>Article 1</num>
            <heading>Amendments to Regulation (EC) No 692/2008</heading>
            <paragraph>
               <subparagraph>
                  <content>
                     <p>Regulation (EC) No 692/2008 is amended as follows:</p>
                  </content>
               </subparagraph>
               <list>
                  <point>
                     <num>(1)</num>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>In Article 2, the following points 45 to 48 are added:</p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>
                              <mod>
                                 <quotedStructure startQuote="" endQuote="">
                                    <list>
                                       <point>
                                          <num>&apos;45.</num>
                                          <content>
                                             <p>&quot;Fuel Storage System&quot; means devices which allow storing the fuel, comprising of the fuel tank, the fuel filler, the filler cap and the fuel pump;</p>
                                          </content>
                                       </point>
                                       <point>
                                          <num>46.</num>
                                          <content>
                                             <p>&quot;Permeability Factor (PF)&quot; means the hydrocarbon emissions as reflected in the permeability of the fuel storage system;</p>
                                          </content>
                                       </point>
                                       <point>
                                          <num>47.</num>
                                          <content>
                                             <p>&quot;Monolayer tank&quot; means a fuel tank constructed with a single layer of material;</p>
                                          </content>
                                       </point>
                                       <point>
                                          <num>48.</num>
                                          <content>
                                             <p>&quot;Multilayer tank&quot; means a fuel tank constructed with at least two different layered materials, one of which is impermeable to hydrocarbons, including ethanol.&apos;</p>
                                          </content>
                                       </point>
                                    </list>
                                 </quotedStructure>
                              </mod>
                           </p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                  </point>
                  <point>
                     <num>(2)</num>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>In Article 17, the following paragraph is inserted after the second subparagraph:</p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>
                              <mod>
                                 <quotedStructure startQuote="" endQuote="">
                                    <paragraph>
                                       <content>
                                          <p>&apos;Annex VI as amended by Commission Regulation (EU) 2017/1221<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="3">
                                                <p>OJ L 174, 7.7.2017, p. 3&apos;.</p>
                                             </authorialNote> shall apply from 1 September 2019 to all new vehicles registered on and after that date.</p>
                                       </content>
                                    </paragraph>
                                 </quotedStructure>
                              </mod>
                           </p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                  </point>
                  <point>
                     <num>(3)</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>Annex VI is replaced by the text set out in the Annex to this Regulation.</p>
                     </content>
                  </point>
               </list>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <article xml:id="art_d163e240">
            <num>Article 2</num>
            <heading>Entry into force and application</heading>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>This Regulation shall enter into force on the twentieth day following that of its publication in the <i>Official Journal of the European Union</i>.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <clause>
            <content>
               <p>This Regulation shall be binding in its entirety and directly applicable in all Member States.</p>
            </content>
         </clause>
      </body>
      <conclusions>
         <p>Done at Brussels, 22 June 2017.</p>
         <block name="signatory">
            <signature>
               <organization refersTo="">For the Commission</organization>
               <role refersTo="">The President</role>
               <person refersTo="">Jean-Claude JUNCKER</person>
            </signature>
         </block>
      </conclusions>
   </bill>
</akomaNtoso>
