<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0"
            xmlns:fmx="http://formex.publications.europa.eu/schema/formex-05.21-20110601.xd"
            xmlns:leos="urn:eu:europa:ec:leos"
            xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema">
   <bill name="">
      <meta xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions">
         <identification source="~COM">
            <FRBRWork>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRcountry value=""/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
         </identification>
      </meta>
      <preface>
         <longTitle>
            <p>
               <docStage/>
               <docType>COUNCIL REGULATION (EU) 2017/1133</docType>of 20 June 2017<docPurpose>amending Regulation (EU) No 1388/2013 opening and providing for the management of autonomous tariff quotas of the Union for certain agricultural and industrial products</docPurpose>
            </p>
         </longTitle>
      </preface>
      <preamble>
         <formula name="actingEntity">
            <p>THE COUNCIL OF THE EUROPEAN UNION,</p>
         </formula>
         <citations>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union, and in particular Article 31 thereof,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the proposal from the European Commission,</p>
            </citation>
         </citations>
         <recitals xml:id="recs_d132e59">
            <intro>
               <p>Whereas:</p>
            </intro>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d132e62">
               <num>(1)</num>
               <p>In order to ensure the sufficient and uninterrupted supply of certain goods insufficiently produced in the Union and to avoid any disturbances on the market for certain agricultural and industrial products, autonomous tariff quotas were opened by Council Regulation (EU) No 1388/2013<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="1">
                     <p>Council Regulation (EU) No 1388/2013 of 17 December 2013 opening and providing for the management of autonomous tariff quotas of the Union for certain agricultural and industrial products, and repealing Regulation (EU) No 7/2010 (OJ L 354, 28.12.2013, p. 319).</p>
                  </authorialNote>. Products within those tariff quotas can be imported into the Union at reduced or zero duty rates. For those reasons it is necessary to open, with effect from 1 July 2017, tariff quotas at zero duty rates for an appropriate volume as regards seven new products.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d132e81">
               <num>(2)</num>
               <p>In the case of five additional products, the tariff quota volumes should be increased, as this increase is in the interest of economic operators and of the Union.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d132e87">
               <num>(3)</num>
               <p>Moreover, for one product the increase in tariff quota volume should only apply to the second half of the year 2017, while the existing tariff quota for that product should be given an end date of 31 December 2017.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d132e96">
               <num>(4)</num>
               <p>Regulation (EU) No 1388/2013 should therefore be amended accordingly.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d132e102">
               <num>(5)</num>
               <p>As the changes regarding the tariff quotas for the products concerned provided for in this Regulation have to apply from 1 July 2017, this Regulation should enter into force as a matter of urgency,</p>
            </recital>
         </recitals>
         <formula name="enactingFormula">
            <p>HAS ADOPTED THIS REGULATION:</p>
         </formula>
      </preamble>
      <body>
         <article xml:id="art_d132e114">
            <num>Article 1</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <subparagraph>
                  <content>
                     <p>The Annex to Regulation (EU) No 1388/2013 is amended as follows:</p>
                  </content>
               </subparagraph>
               <list>
                  <point>
                     <num>(1)</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>the rows for the tariff quotas with order numbers 09.2828, 09.2842, 09.2844, 09.2846, 09.2848, 09.2850, 09.2868, and 09.2870 set out in Annex I to this Regulation are inserted following the order of the CN codes indicated in the second column of the table in the Annex to Regulation (EU) No 1388/2013;</p>
                     </content>
                  </point>
                  <point>
                     <num>(2)</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>the rows for the tariff quotas with order numbers 09.2629, 09.2658, 09.2668, 09.2669, 09.2687 and 09.2860 are replaced by the rows set out in Annex II to this Regulation.</p>
                     </content>
                  </point>
               </list>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <article xml:id="art_d132e134">
            <num>Article 2</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>This Regulation shall enter into force on the date of its publication in the <i>Official Journal of the European Union</i>.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>It shall apply from 1 July 2017.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <clause>
            <content>
               <p>This Regulation shall be binding in its entirety and directly applicable in all Member States.</p>
            </content>
         </clause>
      </body>
      <conclusions>
         <p>Done at Luxembourg, 20 June 2017.</p>
         <block name="signatory">
            <signature>
               <organization refersTo="">For the Council</organization>
               <role refersTo="">The President</role>
               <person refersTo="">H. DALLI</person>
            </signature>
         </block>
      </conclusions>
   </bill>
</akomaNtoso>
