<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0"
            xmlns:fmx="http://formex.publications.europa.eu/schema/formex-05.21-20110601.xd"
            xmlns:leos="urn:eu:europa:ec:leos"
            xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema">
   <bill name="">
      <meta xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions">
         <identification source="~COM">
            <FRBRWork>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRcountry value=""/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
         </identification>
      </meta>
      <preface>
         <longTitle>
            <p>
               <docStage/>
               <docType>COMMISSION REGULATION (EU) 2020/1683</docType>of 12 November 2020<docPurpose>amending Annexes II and III to Regulation (EC) No 1223/2009 of the European Parliament and of the Council on cosmetic products</docPurpose>
            </p>
         </longTitle>
         <container name="EEArelevance">
            <p>(Text with EEA relevance)</p>
         </container>
      </preface>
      <preamble>
         <formula name="actingEntity">
            <p>THE EUROPEAN COMMISSION,</p>
         </formula>
         <citations>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard Regulation (EC) No 1223/2009 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 30 November 2009 on cosmetic products<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="1">
                     <p>OJ L 342, 22.12.2009, p. 59.</p>
                  </authorialNote>, and in particular Article 31(1) thereof,</p>
            </citation>
         </citations>
         <recitals xml:id="recs_d233e71">
            <intro>
               <p>Whereas:</p>
            </intro>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d233e74">
               <num>(1)</num>
               <p>Following the publication of a scientific study in 2001, entitled &apos;Use of permanent hair dyes and bladder cancer risk&apos;, the Scientific Committee on Cosmetic Products and Non-Food Products intended for Consumers, subsequently replaced by the Scientific Committee on Consumer Products (SCCP) pursuant to Commission Decision 2004/210/EC<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="2">
                     <p>Commission Decision 2004/210/EC of 3 March 2004 setting up Scientific Committees in the field of consumer safety, public health and the environment (OJ L 66, 4.3.2004, p. 45).</p>
                  </authorialNote>, concluded that the potential health risks of the use of hair dyes were of concern.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d233e94">
               <num>(2)</num>
               <p>The SCCP further recommended an overall safety assessment strategy for hair dye substances including the requirements for testing substances used in hair dye products for their potential genotoxicity or carcinogenicity.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d233e100">
               <num>(3)</num>
               <p>Following the opinions of the SCCP, the Commission agreed with Member States and stakeholders on an overall strategy to regulate substances used in hair dye products according to which the industry was required to submit files, containing updated scientific data on the safety of hair dye substances, for a risk assessment by the SCCP.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d233e106">
               <num>(4)</num>
               <p>Having succeeded the SCCP pursuant to Commission Decision 2008/721/EC<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="3">
                     <p>Commission Decision 2008/721/EC of 5 September 2008 setting up an advisory structure of Scientific Committees and experts in the field of consumer safety, public health and the environment and repealing Decision 2004/210/EC (OJ L 241, 10.9.2008, p. 21).</p>
                  </authorialNote>, the Scientific Committee on Consumer Safety (SCCS) assessed the safety of individual hair dye substances for which updated files had been submitted by the industry.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d233e122">
               <num>(5)</num>
               <p>As a result of the assessement by the SCCS, in order to ensure the safety of hair dye products for human health it is necessary to prohibit the use of three hair dye substances, 1,2,4-Trihydroxybenzene<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="4">
                     <p>SCCS/1598/18.</p>
                  </authorialNote>, 2-[(4-Amino-2-nitrophenyl)-amino]-benzoic acid<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="5">
                     <p>SCCS/1497/12.</p>
                  </authorialNote> and 4-Amino-3-hydroxytoluene<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="6">
                     <p>SCCS/1400/11.</p>
                  </authorialNote>, based on the final opinions given by the SCCS on their safety. In addition, in light of the final opinions by the SCCS on other six hair dye substances, Dimethylpiperazinium Aminopyrazolopyridine HCl<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="7">
                     <p>SCCS/1584/17.</p>
                  </authorialNote>, Methylimidazoliumpropyl p-phenylenediamine HCl<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="8">
                     <p>SCCS/1609/19.</p>
                  </authorialNote>, HC Orange No 6<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="9">
                     <p>SCCS/1579/16.</p>
                  </authorialNote>, Acid Orange 7<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="10">
                     <p>SCCS/1536/14.</p>
                  </authorialNote>, Tetrabromophenol Blue<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="11">
                     <p>SCCS/1610/19.</p>
                  </authorialNote> and <i>Indigofera Tinctoria</i>
                  <authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="12">
                     <p>SCCS/1615/20.</p>
                  </authorialNote>, it is appropriate to limit their maximum concentrations for use in hair dye products.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d233e167">
               <num>(6)</num>
               <p>The definition of a hair product laid down in point (1)(c) of the Preamble to Annexes II to VI to Regulation (EC) No 1223/2009 excludes the application of hair dye substances on eyelashes, based on a different level of risk of applying a cosmetic product on the hair on the head as compared to applying the same product on eyelashes. A specific safety assessment was therefore needed for the application of hair dye substances on eyelashes.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d233e174">
               <num>(7)</num>
               <p>The substance 2-Methoxymethyl-p-Phenylenediamine and its sulfate are listed under entry 292 in Annex III to Regulation (EC) No 1223/2009. Taking into account the conclusions of the latest SCCS opinion<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="13">
                     <p>SCCS/1603/18.</p>
                  </authorialNote> on the use of those substances on eyelashes, the field of application of the restriction to which they are subject should be extended to products intended for colouring eyelashes.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d233e184">
               <num>(8)</num>
               <p>In order to avoid any risk related to self-application by consumers of products intended for colouring eyelashes that contain 2-Methoxymethyl-p-Phenylenediamine and its sulfate, those products should be allowed for professional use only.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d233e190">
               <num>(9)</num>
               <p>In order to inform consumers and professionals about possible adverse effects of the use of hair dyes and products intended for colouring eyelashes with the aim to lower the risk of skin sensitisation to those products, appropriate warnings should be printed on their labels.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d233e197">
               <num>(10)</num>
               <p>Regulation (EC) No 1223/2009 should therefore be amended accordingly.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d233e203">
               <num>(11)</num>
               <p>It is appropriate to provide for reasonable periods of time in order for the industry to adapt to the new requirements and to phase out cosmetic products which do not comply with those requirements.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d233e209">
               <num>(12)</num>
               <p>The measures provided for in this Regulation are in accordance with the opinion of the Standing Committee on Cosmetic Products,</p>
            </recital>
         </recitals>
         <formula name="enactingFormula">
            <p>HAS ADOPTED THIS REGULATION:</p>
         </formula>
      </preamble>
      <body>
         <article xml:id="art_d233e218">
            <num>Article 1</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>Regulation (EC) No 1223/2009 is amended in accordance with the Annex to this Regulation.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <article xml:id="art_d233e223">
            <num>Article 2</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>This Regulation shall enter into force on the twentieth day following that of its publication in the <i>Official Journal of the European Union</i>.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <clause>
            <content>
               <p>This Regulation shall be binding in its entirety and directly applicable in all Member States.</p>
            </content>
         </clause>
      </body>
      <conclusions>
         <p>Done at Brussels, 12 November 2020.</p>
         <block name="signatory">
            <signature>
               <organization refersTo="">For the Commission</organization>
               <role refersTo="">The President</role>
               <person refersTo="">Ursula VON DER LEYEN</person>
            </signature>
         </block>
      </conclusions>
   </bill>
</akomaNtoso>
