<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0"
            xmlns:fmx="http://formex.publications.europa.eu/schema/formex-05.21-20110601.xd"
            xmlns:leos="urn:eu:europa:ec:leos"
            xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema">
   <bill name="">
      <meta xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions">
         <identification source="~COM">
            <FRBRWork>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRcountry value=""/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
         </identification>
      </meta>
      <preface>
         <longTitle>
            <p>
               <docStage/>
               <docType>COUNCIL REGULATION (EU) 2021/406</docType>of 5 March 2021<docPurpose>amending Regulations (EU) 2021/91 and (EU) 2021/92 as regards certain provisional fishing opportunities for 2021 in Union waters and non-Union waters</docPurpose>
            </p>
         </longTitle>
      </preface>
      <preamble>
         <formula name="actingEntity">
            <p>THE COUNCIL OF THE EUROPEAN UNION,</p>
         </formula>
         <citations>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union, and in particular Article 43(3) thereof,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the proposal from the European Commission,</p>
            </citation>
         </citations>
         <recitals xml:id="recs_d77e59">
            <intro>
               <p>Whereas:</p>
            </intro>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d77e62">
               <num>(1)</num>
               <p>Regulation (EU) No 1380/2013 of the European Parliament and of the Council<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="1">
                     <p>Regulation (EU) No 1380/2013 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 11 December 2013 on the Common Fisheries Policy, amending Council Regulations (EC) No 1954/2003 and (EC) No 1224/2009 and repealing Council Regulations (EC) No 2371/2002 and (EC) No 639/2004 and Council Decision 2004/585/EC (OJ L 354, 28.12.2013, p. 22).</p>
                  </authorialNote> requires that conservation measures be adopted, taking into account available scientific, technical and economic advice, including, where relevant, reports drawn up by the Scientific, Technical and Economic Committee for Fisheries (STECF) and other advisory bodies, as well as any advice received from advisory councils.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d77e78">
               <num>(2)</num>
               <p>It is incumbent upon the Council to adopt measures on the fixing and allocation of fishing opportunities, including certain conditions functionally linked thereto, as appropriate. Pursuant to Article 16(4) of Regulation (EU) No 1380/2013, fishing opportunities are to be fixed in accordance with the objectives of the Common Fisheries Policy (CFP) set out in Article 2(2) of that Regulation. For stocks subject to specific multiannual plans the TACs should be established in accordance with the rules laid down in those plans. Pursuant to Article 16(1) of that Regulation, fishing opportunities allocated to Member States are to ensure relative stability of fishing activities of each Member State for each fish stock or fishery.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d77e84">
               <num>(3)</num>
               <p>The total allowable catch (TAC) should therefore be established, in line with Regulation (EU) No 1380/2013, on the basis of available scientific advice, taking into account biological and socioeconomic aspects whilst ensuring fair treatment between fishing sectors, as well as in the light of the opinions expressed during the consultation of stakeholders, in particular at the meetings of the advisory councils.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d77e90">
               <num>(4)</num>
               <p>Due to the withdrawal of the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland from the Union, a large number of stocks have become shared stocks. The Commission will undertake bilateral consultations with the United Kingdom, bilateral consultations with Norway and trilateral consultations with the United Kingdom and Norway on the basis of the draft Union position to be endorsed by the Council. As those consultations have not yet been concluded, the Council should, in a manner that fully respects the United Nations Convention on the Law of the Sea (UNCLOS) and rights and obligations of the coastal states as well as their sovereignty and jurisdiction, establish provisional TACs to be fished in Union and international waters, and waters to which the Union fishing vessels are granted access by third countries.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d77e97">
               <num>(5)</num>
               <p>On 15-16 December 2020, the Council reached a political agreement on fishing opportunities for 2021. The Council agreed that provisional TACs for stocks shared with third countries should be set until those consultations are concluded in compliance with the Union legal framework and international obligations or, if they cannot be concluded successfully, until the Council establishes unilateral Union TACs in 2021.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d77e109">
               <num>(6)</num>
               <p>The provisional TACs established in Council Regulations (EU) 2021/91<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="2">
                     <p>Council Regulation (EU) 2021/91 of 28 January 2021 fixing, for the years 2021 and 2022, the fishing opportunities for Union fishing vessels for certain deep-sea fish stocks (OJ L 31, 29.1.2021, p. 20).</p>
                  </authorialNote> and (EU) 2021/92<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="3">
                     <p>Council Regulation (EU) 2021/92 of 28 January 2021 fixing for 2021 the fishing opportunities for certain fish stocks and groups of fish stocks, applicable in Union waters and, for Union fishing vessels, in certain non-Union waters (OJ L 31, 29.1.2021, p. 31).</p>
                  </authorialNote>, which reflect the political agreement reached in the Council, aim to ensure continuation of sustainable Union fishing activities. Those provisional fishing opportunities should in no circumstances impede the fixing of definitive fishing opportunities in accordance with international agreements and the outcome of consultations, the Union legal framework and the scientific advice. As a general approach, they should correspond to 25 % of the Union share of the fishing opportunities fixed for 2020. However, in a very limited number of cases, another percentage should be used where the stocks are predominantly fished at the beginning of the year. This approach is without prejudice to the Union shares established in the Trade and Cooperation Agreement between the European Union and the United Kingdom<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="4">
                     <p>Trade and Cooperation Agreement between the European Union and the European Atomic Energy Community, of the one part, and the United Kingdom of Great Britain and the Northern Ireland, of the other part (OJ L 444, 31.12.2020, p. 14).</p>
                  </authorialNote> (&apos;Trade and Cooperation Agreement&apos;), which will be used to set definitive TACs.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d77e146">
               <num>(7)</num>
               <p>The list of stocks for which a percentage higher than 25 % should apply, should be based on the analysis of the quota uptake in the first quarter of the last three years (2018-2020) by the Member States that requested a higher provisional TAC. Provisional TACs should not exceed potential definitive TACs, which, without prejudice to the upcoming consultations with the third countries, have been assessed in accordance with the scientific advice and taking into account the Union shares established in the Trade and Cooperation Agreement. Those increases in provisional TACs are in accordance with the ICES advice, the applicable Union legal framework and the Trade and Cooperation Agreement. They will enable Union fishing vessels to use the fishing opportunities to which they are entitled and of which they would be otherwise deprived, due to the seasonality of fishing of the stocks concerned.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d77e152">
               <num>(8)</num>
               <p>The monthly catch data of the past years as reported to the Commission indicate that some other pelagic and demersal stocks are predominantly fished at the beginning of the year. Therefore, on the basis of that catch data and in accordance with the scientific advice, a higher percentage relative to the Union share of the fishing opportunities fixed for 2021 should be established for the corresponding TACs, without prejudice to an approach that may be taken in any future international agreements and/or consultations.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d77e158">
               <num>(9)</num>
               <p>Regulations (EU) 2021/91 and (EU) 2021/92 should therefore be amended accordingly.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d77e165">
               <num>(10)</num>
               <p>The catch limits provided for in Regulations (EU) 2021/91 and (EU) 2021/92 apply from 1 January 2021. The provisions introduced by this Regulation concerning catch limits should therefore enter into force as soon as possible and apply retroactively from 1 January 2021. Such retroactive application does not affect the principles of legal certainty and protection of legitimate expectations as the fishing opportunities concerned are increased and have not yet been exhausted. For reasons of urgency, this Regulation should enter into force immediately after its publication,</p>
            </recital>
         </recitals>
         <formula name="enactingFormula">
            <p>HAS ADOPTED THIS REGULATION:</p>
         </formula>
      </preamble>
      <body>
         <article xml:id="art_d77e180">
            <num>Article 1</num>
            <heading>Amendment of Regulation (EU) 2021/91</heading>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>The Annex to Regulation (EU) 2021/91 is amended in accordance with Part A of the Annex to this Regulation.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <article xml:id="art_d77e188">
            <num>Article 2</num>
            <heading>Amendment of Regulation (EU) 2021/92</heading>
            <paragraph>
               <subparagraph>
                  <content>
                     <p>Regulation (EU) 2021/92 is amended as follows:</p>
                  </content>
               </subparagraph>
               <list>
                  <point>
                     <num>(1)</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>Annex IA is amended in accordance with Part B of the Annex to this Regulation;</p>
                     </content>
                  </point>
                  <point>
                     <num>(2)</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>Annex IB is amended in accordance with Part C of the Annex to this Regulation.</p>
                     </content>
                  </point>
               </list>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <article xml:id="art_d77e209">
            <num>Article 3</num>
            <heading>Entry into force</heading>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>This Regulation shall enter into force on the day following that of its publication in the <i>Official Journal of the European Union</i>.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>It shall apply from 1 January 2021.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <clause>
            <content>
               <p>This Regulation shall be binding in its entirety and directly applicable in all Member States.</p>
            </content>
         </clause>
      </body>
      <conclusions>
         <p>Done at Brussels, 5 March 2021.</p>
         <block name="signatory">
            <signature>
               <organization refersTo="">For the Council</organization>
               <role refersTo="">The President</role>
               <person refersTo="">A. P. ZACARIAS</person>
            </signature>
         </block>
      </conclusions>
   </bill>
</akomaNtoso>
