<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0"
            xmlns:fmx="http://formex.publications.europa.eu/schema/formex-05.21-20110601.xd"
            xmlns:leos="urn:eu:europa:ec:leos"
            xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema">
   <bill name="">
      <meta xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions">
         <identification source="~COM">
            <FRBRWork>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRcountry value=""/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
         </identification>
      </meta>
      <preface>
         <longTitle>
            <p>
               <docStage/>
               <docType>COUNCIL REGULATION (EU) 2021/703</docType>of 26 April 2021<docPurpose>amending Regulations (EU) 2021/91 and (EU) 2021/92 as regards certain fishing opportunities for 2021 in Union and non-Union waters</docPurpose>
            </p>
         </longTitle>
      </preface>
      <preamble>
         <formula name="actingEntity">
            <p>THE COUNCIL OF THE EUROPEAN UNION,</p>
         </formula>
         <citations>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union, and in particular Article 43(3) thereof,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the proposal from the European Commission,</p>
            </citation>
         </citations>
         <recitals xml:id="recs_d114e59">
            <intro>
               <p>Whereas:</p>
            </intro>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d114e62">
               <num>(1)</num>
               <p>Council Regulation (EU) 2021/91<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="1">
                     <p>Council Regulation (EU) 2021/91 of 28 January 2021 fixing, for the years 2021 and 2022, the fishing opportunities for Union fishing vessels for certain deep-sea fish stocks (OJ L 31, 29.1.2021, p. 20).</p>
                  </authorialNote> establishes, for the years 2021 and 2022, the fishing opportunities for Union fishing vessels for certain deep-sea fish stocks. Council Regulation (EU) 2021/92<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="2">
                     <p>Council Regulation (EU) 2021/92 of 28 January 2021 fixing for 2021 the fishing opportunities for certain fish stocks and groups of fish stocks, applicable in Union waters and, for Union fishing vessels, in certain non-Union waters (OJ L 31, 29.1.2021, p. 31).</p>
                  </authorialNote> fixes for 2021 the fishing opportunities for certain fish stocks and groups of fish stocks applicable in Union waters and, for Union fishing vessels, in certain non-Union waters.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d114e88">
               <num>(2)</num>
               <p>The Trade and Cooperation Agreement between the European Union and the European Atomic Energy Community, of the one part, and the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland, of the other part<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="3">
                     <p>OJ L 444, 31.12.2020, p. 14.</p>
                  </authorialNote> (&apos;the Trade and Cooperation Agreement&apos;) applies provisionally from 1 January 2021.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d114e107">
               <num>(3)</num>
               <p>The fishing opportunities in Regulations (EU) 2021/91 and (EU) 2021/92 for stocks shared with certain third countries are provisional and in quantitative terms limited to a three-month rollover based on Council Regulations (EU) 2020/123<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="4">
                     <p>Council Regulation (EU) 2020/123 of 27 January 2020 fixing for 2020 the fishing opportunities for certain fish stocks and groups of fish stocks, applicable in Union waters and, for Union fishing vessels, in certain non-Union waters (OJ L 25, 30.1.2020, p. 1).</p>
                  </authorialNote> and (EU) 2018/2025<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="5">
                     <p>Council Regulation (EU) 2018/2025 of 17 December 2018 fixing for 2019 and 2020 the fishing opportunities for Union fishing vessels for certain deep-sea fish stocks (OJ L 325, 20.12.2018, p. 7).</p>
                  </authorialNote>. In a very limited number of cases, a different methodology was used for stocks that are predominantly fished at the beginning of the year or where scientific advice required severe reductions in fishing opportunities.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d114e133">
               <num>(4)</num>
               <p>In accordance with Article 499(2) of the Trade and Cooperation Agreement, the provisional total allowable catches (TACs) aim to ensure the continuation of sustainable Union fishing activities until the consultations between the Union and the United Kingdom pursuant to Article 498 of that Agreement are concluded and implemented in the Union legal order. They were set at levels consistent with what is allowed under Article 499 of that Agreement.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d114e140">
               <num>(5)</num>
               <p>The consultations between the Union and the United Kingdom are still ongoing. Therefore, Regulations (EU) 2021/91 and (EU) 2021/92 need to be amended in order to extend provisional unilateral Union TACs in order to create legal certainty for the Union operators and to ensure the continuation of sustainable fishing activities until those consultations are concluded in compliance with the Union legal framework and the Trade and Cooperation Agreement.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d114e146">
               <num>(6)</num>
               <p>This approach is based on Article 499(2) of the Trade and Cooperation Agreement, which provides that, if a stock listed in Annex 35 to that Agreement or in Tables A and B of Annex 36 to that Agreement remains without an agreed TAC, each Party is to set a provisional TAC corresponding to the level advised by the International Council for the Exploration of the Sea (ICES), applying from 1 January. Pursuant to Article 499(3) to (5) of the Trade and Cooperation Agreement, and by way of derogation from paragraph 2 of that Article, the TACs for special stocks shall be set in accordance with the guidelines to be adopted by the Specialised Committee on Fisheries by 1 July 2021.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d114e155">
               <num>(7)</num>
               <p>Therefore, as a general approach, the provisional fishing opportunities for the Union should be based on the ICES advice for 2021, and, for deep-sea stocks, also for 2022, when available. They should correspond to the Union share agreed under the Trade and Cooperation Agreement.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d114e161">
               <num>(8)</num>
               <p>As a general approach, the provisional TACs should be extended until 31 July 2021 and should correspond to a ratio of seven twelfths or 58,3 % of the annual catch level advised by ICES for 2021 and, for deep-sea stocks, also for 2022. In certain cases, they should correspond to that ratio of the Union position in the ongoing consultations with the United Kingdom as defined in the Council Decision of 5 March 2021 establishing the position to be taken on behalf of the Union in the consultations with the United Kingdom and as further specified in accordance with that Decision.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d114e173">
               <num>(9)</num>
               <p>This level is considered in principle to be sufficient for the Union fishing vessels at least until 31 July 2021, which is one month after the date by which the guidelines for special stocks need to be agreed with the United Kingdom.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d114e183">
               <num>(10)</num>
               <p>For a limited number of stocks, the provisional TACs should correspond to a higher ratio of the advised annual catch level in order to take into account the seasonality of fishing activities for those stocks.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d114e189">
               <num>(11)</num>
               <p>Without prejudice to, and taking into account the absence of, the guidelines for special stocks, the TACs for those stocks are consistent with Article 499 of the Trade and Cooperation Agreement.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d114e195">
               <num>(12)</num>
               <p>The Union, on the one hand, and the Government of Greenland and the Government of Denmark, on the other hand, are expected to conclude a sustainable fisheries partnership agreement, as the previous agreement expired on 31 December 2020. The Council should therefore fix fishing opportunities resulting from that agreement, taking into account exchanges of fishing opportunities with third countries. Those fishing opportunities should be effective from the date of provisional application of that agreement.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d114e204">
               <num>(13)</num>
               <p>Member States should make use of any applicable inter-area, inter-species and inter-annual flexibilities in a way which ensures that the overall level of Union catches in 2021 does not exceed the Union share of the maximum TAC level which the Union may set under the Trade and Cooperation Agreement.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d114e210">
               <num>(14)</num>
               <p>Taking into account the ratio that is applied, the quota uptake, the conditions for the use of flexibilities, as well as other conditions stipulated in existing Union legislation, in accordance with Article 499(7) of the Trade and Cooperation Agreement, the provisional TACs respect the Union shares agreed under that Agreement, as set out in Annexes 35 and 36 thereto.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d114e217">
               <num>(15)</num>
               <p>The provisional TACs also comply with the applicable Union legal framework, in particular Articles 4, 5(3) and 8 of Regulation (EU) 2019/472 of the European Parliament and of the Council<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="6">
                     <p>Regulation (EU) 2019/472 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 19 March 2019 establishing a multiannual plan for stocks fished in the Western Waters and adjacent waters, and for fisheries exploiting those stocks, amending Regulations (EU) 2016/1139 and (EU) 2018/973, and repealing Council Regulations (EC) No 811/2004, (EC) No 2166/2005, (EC) No 388/2006, (EC) No 509/2007 and (EC) No 1300/2008 (OJ L 83, 25.3.2019, p. 1).</p>
                  </authorialNote> and Articles 4, 5(3) and 7 of Regulation (EU) 2018/973 of the European Parliament and of the Council<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="7">
                     <p>Regulation (EU) 2018/973 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 4 July 2018 establishing a multiannual plan for demersal stocks in the North Sea and the fisheries exploiting those stocks, specifying details of the implementation of the landing obligation in the North Sea and repealing Council Regulations (EC) No 676/2007 and (EC) No 1342/2008 (OJ L 179, 16.7.2018, p. 1).</p>
                  </authorialNote>. They are based on the level advised by ICES, while taking into account the particular situation of stocks caught in a mixed fishery that may be affected by &apos;choke&apos; situations, having regard to ICES advice on mixed fisheries and on unavoidable by-catches.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d114e247">
               <num>(16)</num>
               <p>There are certain stocks for which ICES has issued scientific advice for no catches. If TACs for those stocks are established at the level indicated in the scientific advice, the obligation to land all catches, including by-catches from those stocks, in mixed fisheries would lead to the phenomenon of &apos;choke species&apos;. In order to strike the right balance between continuing fisheries in view of the potentially severe socio-economic implications and the need to achieve a good biological status for those stocks, taking into account the difficulty of fishing all stocks in a mixed fishery at maximum sustainable yield (MSY) at the same time, it is appropriate to establish specific TACs for by-catches for those stocks. The level of those TACs should be such that mortality for those stocks is decreased and that it provides incentives for improvements in selectivity and avoidance of catches of those stocks. In order to reduce catches of the stocks for which by-catch TACs are set, fishing opportunities for the fisheries in which fish from those stocks are caught should be set at levels that help the biomass of vulnerable stocks to recover to sustainable levels.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d114e257">
               <num>(17)</num>
               <p>These fishing opportunities should in no circumstances prejudge the establishment of the fishing opportunities in accordance with the outcome of the consultations with the United Kingdom, the guidelines on special stocks to be agreed with the United Kingdom pursuant to Article 499(5) of the Trade and Cooperation Agreement and the Union legal framework.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d114e263">
               <num>(18)</num>
               <p>According to scientific advice, the spawning-stock biomass of European seabass (<i>Dicentrarchus labrax</i>) in the Celtic Sea, the Channel, the Irish Sea and the southern North Sea (ICES divisions 4b, 4c, 7a, and 7d to 7h) has been declining since 2009 and is currently below MSY B<sub>trigger</sub> and just above B<sub>lim</sub>. Due to the measures taken by the Union, the fishing mortality has decreased and is currently below F<sub>MSY</sub>. However, recruitment is low, fluctuating without trend since 2008. Therefore, the catch limits should be continued, while ensuring that the target fishing mortality for this stock is in line with MSY.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d114e281">
               <num>(19)</num>
               <p>In Regulation (EU) 2021/92, the TAC for sandeels in ICES divisions 2a and 3a and in ICES subarea 4 was set at zero pending the publication of the relevant scientific advice, provided by ICES, which became available on 25 February 2021. The fishery for sandeels, which are a short-lived species, starts on 1 April, shortly after the publication of the scientific advice.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d114e291">
               <num>(20)</num>
               <p>The catch limits for sandeels in ICES divisions 2a and 3a and in ICES subarea 4 should be amended in line with the latest scientific advice from ICES.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d114e297">
               <num>(21)</num>
               <p>Regulation (EU) 2021/92 establishes preliminary fishing opportunities for the first quarter of 2021. Furthermore, Article 14 of that Regulation establishes a prohibition from 1 January to 31 March 2021 for vessels fishing for sandeels using certain gears in ICES divisions 2a and 3a and in ICES subarea 4. As this Regulation establishes fishing opportunities for the entire fishing year, that prohibition should also cover the period from 1 August to 31 December 2021, as in 2020.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d114e316">
               <num>(22)</num>
               <p>In accordance with the procedure provided for in the agreements on fisheries relations with Norway and in accordance with the Trade and Cooperation Agreement, the Union has held trilateral consultations with the United Kingdom and Norway and bilateral consultations with Norway on fishing rights for stocks. The fishing opportunities for North Sea cod should be established in order to ensure a level playing field for Union operators and to provide for the recovery of that stock. In accordance with the procedure provided for in the Sustainable Fisheries Partnership Agreement between the European Union, of the one part, and the Government of Greenland and the Government of Denmark, of the other part and the implementing Protocol thereto, the Joint Committee has established the level of fishing opportunities available for the Union in Greenland waters in 2021. It is therefore necessary to include those fishing opportunities in this Regulation.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d114e322">
               <num>(23)</num>
               <p>The Union and the United Kingdom have agreed on their respective shares of the TACs for certain stocks managed by ICCAT. Those shares are set out in Table C of Annex 36 to the Trade and Cooperation Agreement. The relevant fishing opportunities tables should be amended in order to take account of those shares.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d114e328">
               <num>(24)</num>
               <p>Effort limits for Union fishing vessels in the ICCAT Convention Area are based on information provided in the fishing, capacity and farming plans for bluefin tuna communicated by Member States to the Commission. Those effort limits are reported through the Union plan endorsed by ICCAT during the intersessional meeting of Panel 2 held on 4 and 5 March 2019. They should be established as part of the fishing opportunities under this Regulation.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d114e340">
               <num>(25)</num>
               <p>At its ninth annual meeting in 2021, the South Pacific Regional Fisheries Management Organisation (SPRFMO) adopted new catch limits for jack mackerel (<i>Trachurus murphyi</i>) and approved exploratory fisheries for toothfishes (<i>Dissostichus</i> spp.). The applicable measures should be implemented in Union law.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d114e352">
               <num>(26)</num>
               <p>Regulations (EU) 2021/91 and (EU) 2021/92 should therefore be amended accordingly.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d114e358">
               <num>(27)</num>
               <p>The catch limits provided for in Regulations (EU) 2021/91 and (EU) 2021/92 apply from 1 January 2021. The provisions introduced by this Regulation concerning catch limits should therefore also apply from that date. Such retroactive application does not affect the principles of legal certainty and protection of legitimate expectations, as the fishing opportunities concerned are increased or have not yet been exhausted.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d114e367">
               <num>(28)</num>
               <p>In view of the need to continue sustainable fishing activities and to start the fishing season for sandeels on time on 1 April 2021, this Regulation should enter into force on the date of its publication in the <i>Official Journal of the European Union</i>,</p>
            </recital>
         </recitals>
         <formula name="enactingFormula">
            <p>HAS ADOPTED THIS REGULATION:</p>
         </formula>
      </preamble>
      <body>
         <article xml:id="art_d114e382" leos:compliant="false">
            <num>Article 1</num>
            <heading>Amendment of Regulation (EU) 2021/91</heading>
            <paragraph>
               <subparagraph>
                  <content>
                     <p>Regulation (EU) 2021/91 is amended as follows:</p>
                  </content>
               </subparagraph>
               <list>
                  <point>
                     <num>(1)</num>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>Article 8(1) is replaced by the following:</p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>
                              <mod>
                                 <quotedStructure startQuote="" endQuote="">
                                    <paragraph>
                                       <num>&apos;1.</num>
                                       <content>
                                          <p>Where a reference is made to this paragraph in a table set out in the Annex to this Regulation, the fishing opportunities in that table are provisional and shall apply from 1 January to 31 July 2021. Those provisional fishing opportunities shall be without prejudice to setting definitive fishing opportunities for 2021 and 2022, based on the best available scientific advice, and in accordance with the outcomes of international negotiations and/or consultations, the guidelines on special stocks to be agreed with the United Kingdom, the applicable provisions of Regulation (EU) No 1380/2013 and relevant multiannual plans.&apos;;</p>
                                       </content>
                                    </paragraph>
                                 </quotedStructure>
                              </mod>
                           </p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                  </point>
                  <point>
                     <num>(2)</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>Part 2 of the Annex is amended in accordance with Part A of the Annex to this Regulation.</p>
                     </content>
                  </point>
               </list>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <article xml:id="art_d114e420" leos:compliant="false">
            <num>Article 2</num>
            <heading>Amendment of Regulation (EU) 2021/92</heading>
            <paragraph>
               <subparagraph>
                  <content>
                     <p>Regulation (EU) 2021/92 is amended as follows:</p>
                  </content>
               </subparagraph>
               <list>
                  <point>
                     <num>(1)</num>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>Article 7 is amended as follows:</p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                     <list>
                        <point>
                           <num>(a)</num>
                           <alinea>
                              <content>
                                 <p>paragraph 1 is replaced by the following:</p>
                              </content>
                           </alinea>
                           <alinea>
                              <content>
                                 <p>
                                    <mod>
                                       <quotedStructure startQuote="" endQuote="">
                                          <paragraph>
                                             <num>&apos;1.</num>
                                             <content>
                                                <p>Where a reference is made to this paragraph in a fishing opportunities table in Annex IA or Annex IB, the fishing opportunities in that table are provisional and shall apply from 1 January to 31 July 2021. Those provisional fishing opportunities shall be without prejudice to setting definitive fishing opportunities for 2021 and 2022, based on the best available scientific advice, and in accordance with the outcomes of international negotiations and/or consultations, the guidelines on special stocks to be agreed with the United Kingdom, the applicable provisions of Regulation (EU) No 1380/2013 and relevant multiannual plans.&apos;;</p>
                                             </content>
                                          </paragraph>
                                       </quotedStructure>
                                    </mod>
                                 </p>
                              </content>
                           </alinea>
                        </point>
                        <point>
                           <num>(b)</num>
                           <alinea>
                              <content>
                                 <p>the following paragraph is inserted:</p>
                              </content>
                           </alinea>
                           <alinea>
                              <content>
                                 <p>
                                    <mod>
                                       <quotedStructure startQuote="" endQuote="">
                                          <paragraph>
                                             <num>&apos;1a.</num>
                                             <content>
                                                <p>Member States shall make use of any applicable inter-area, inter-species and inter-annual flexibilities in a way which ensures that the overall level of Union catches in 2021 does not exceed the Union share of the maximum provisional TAC level which the Union may set under the Trade and Cooperation Agreement between the European Union and the European Atomic Energy Community, of the one part, and the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland, of the other part.&apos;;</p>
                                             </content>
                                          </paragraph>
                                       </quotedStructure>
                                    </mod>
                                 </p>
                              </content>
                           </alinea>
                        </point>
                     </list>
                  </point>
                  <point>
                     <num>(2)</num>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>the following Article is inserted:</p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>
                              <mod>
                                 <quotedStructure startQuote="" endQuote="">
                                    <article xml:id="art_d114e483">
                                       <num>&apos;Article 7a</num>
                                       <heading>Application of fishing opportunities in Greenland waters</heading>
                                       <paragraph>
                                          <content>
                                             <p>Where a reference is made to this Article in a fishing opportunities table in Annex IB, the fishing opportunities in that table shall apply from the date of provisional application of the Sustainable Fisheries Partnership Agreement between the European Union, of the one part, and the Government of Greenland and the Government of Denmark, of the other part, to 31 December 2021.&apos;;</p>
                                          </content>
                                       </paragraph>
                                    </article>
                                 </quotedStructure>
                              </mod>
                           </p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                  </point>
                  <point>
                     <num>(3)</num>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>Article 9 is amended as follows:</p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                     <list>
                        <point>
                           <num>(a)</num>
                           <content>
                              <p>in paragraph 2, &apos;31 March 2021&apos; is replaced by &apos;31 July 2021&apos;;</p>
                           </content>
                        </point>
                        <point>
                           <num>(b)</num>
                           <content>
                              <p>in paragraph 3, &apos;31 March 2021&apos; is replaced by &apos;31 July 2021&apos;;</p>
                           </content>
                        </point>
                     </list>
                  </point>
                  <point>
                     <num>(4)</num>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>Article 11 is amended as follows:</p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                     <list>
                        <point>
                           <num>(a)</num>
                           <alinea>
                              <content>
                                 <p>in paragraph 2, the introductory wording of the first subparagraph is replaced by the following:</p>
                              </content>
                           </alinea>
                           <alinea>
                              <content>
                                 <p>
                                    <mod>
                                       <quotedStructure startQuote="" endQuote="">
                                          <paragraph>
                                             <num>&apos;2.</num>
                                             <content>
                                                <p>By way of derogation from paragraph 1, in January 2021 and from 1 April to 31 July, Union fishing vessels in ICES divisions 4b, 4c, 7d, 7e, 7f and 7h may fish for European seabass, and retain, tranship, relocate or land European seabass caught in that area with the following gear and within the following limits:&apos;;</p>
                                             </content>
                                          </paragraph>
                                       </quotedStructure>
                                    </mod>
                                 </p>
                              </content>
                           </alinea>
                        </point>
                        <point>
                           <num>(b)</num>
                           <content>
                              <p>in point (c) of the first subparagraph of paragraph 2, &apos;1,43&apos; is replaced by &apos;3,32&apos;;</p>
                           </content>
                        </point>
                        <point>
                           <num>(c)</num>
                           <content>
                              <p>in point (d) of the first subparagraph of paragraph 2, &apos;0,35&apos; is replaced by &apos;0,82&apos;;</p>
                           </content>
                        </point>
                        <point>
                           <num>(d)</num>
                           <content>
                              <p>in point (b) of the first subparagraph of paragraph 5, &apos;from 1 to 31 March&apos; is replaced by &apos;from 1 March to 31 July&apos;;</p>
                           </content>
                        </point>
                     </list>
                  </point>
                  <point>
                     <num>(5)</num>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>Article 14 is replaced by the following:</p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>
                              <mod>
                                 <quotedStructure startQuote="" endQuote="">
                                    <article xml:id="art_d114e610">
                                       <num>&apos;Article 14</num>
                                       <heading>Closed fishing seasons for sandeels</heading>
                                       <paragraph>
                                          <content>
                                             <p>Commercial fishing for sandeels with demersal trawl, seine or similar towed gears with a mesh size of less than 16 mm shall be prohibited in ICES divisions 2a and 3a and in ICES subarea 4 from 1 January to 31 March 2021 and from 1 August to 31 December 2021.&apos;;</p>
                                          </content>
                                       </paragraph>
                                    </article>
                                 </quotedStructure>
                              </mod>
                           </p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                  </point>
                  <point>
                     <num>(6)</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>in Article 60, &apos;31 March 2021&apos; is replaced by &apos;31 July 2021&apos;;</p>
                     </content>
                  </point>
                  <point>
                     <num>(7)</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>Annex IA is amended in accordance with Part B of the Annex to this Regulation;</p>
                     </content>
                  </point>
                  <point>
                     <num>(8)</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>Annex IB is amended in accordance with Part C of the Annex to this Regulation;</p>
                     </content>
                  </point>
                  <point>
                     <num>(9)</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>Annex IC is amended in accordance with Part D of the Annex to this Regulation;</p>
                     </content>
                  </point>
                  <point>
                     <num>(10)</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>Annex ID is amended in accordance with Part E of the Annex to this Regulation;</p>
                     </content>
                  </point>
                  <point>
                     <num>(11)</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>Annex IH is amended in accordance with Part F of the Annex to this Regulation;</p>
                     </content>
                  </point>
                  <point>
                     <num>(12)</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>Chapter III of Annex II is amended in accordance with Part G of the Annex to this Regulation;</p>
                     </content>
                  </point>
                  <point>
                     <num>(13)</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>Annex VI is amended in accordance with Part H of the Annex to this Regulation.</p>
                     </content>
                  </point>
               </list>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <article xml:id="art_d114e692">
            <num>Article 3</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>This Regulation shall enter into force on the date of its publication in the <i>Official Journal of the European Union</i>.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>It shall apply from 1 January 2021.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <clause>
            <content>
               <p>This Regulation shall be binding in its entirety and directly applicable in all Member States.</p>
            </content>
         </clause>
      </body>
      <conclusions>
         <p>Done at Brussels, 26 April 2021.</p>
         <block name="signatory">
            <signature>
               <organization refersTo="">For the Council</organization>
               <role refersTo="">The President</role>
               <person refersTo="">A. P. ZACARIAS</person>
            </signature>
         </block>
      </conclusions>
   </bill>
</akomaNtoso>
