<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0"
            xmlns:fmx="http://formex.publications.europa.eu/schema/formex-05.21-20110601.xd"
            xmlns:leos="urn:eu:europa:ec:leos"
            xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema">
   <bill name="">
      <meta xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions">
         <identification source="~COM">
            <FRBRWork>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRcountry value=""/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
         </identification>
      </meta>
      <preface>
         <longTitle>
            <p>
               <docStage/>
               <docType>COUNCIL REGULATION (EU) 2020/875</docType>of 15 June 2020<docPurpose>amending Regulation (EU) No 1388/2013 quotas of the Union for certain agricultural and industrial products</docPurpose>
            </p>
         </longTitle>
      </preface>
      <preamble>
         <formula name="actingEntity">
            <p>THE COUNCIL OF THE EUROPEAN UNION,</p>
         </formula>
         <citations>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union, and in particular Article 31 thereof,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the proposal from the European Commission,</p>
            </citation>
         </citations>
         <recitals xml:id="recs_d89e59">
            <intro>
               <p>Whereas:</p>
            </intro>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d89e62">
               <num>(1)</num>
               <p>In order to ensure a sufficient and uninterrupted supply of certain agricultural and industrial products which are produced in insufficient quantities in the Union, and thereby avoid any disturbances in the market for those products, autonomous tariff quotas were opened by Council Regulation (EU) No 1388/2013<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="1">
                     <p>Council Regulation (EU) No 1388/2013 of 17 December 2013 opening and providing for the management of autonomous tariff quotas of the Union for certain agricultural and industrial products, and repealing Regulation (EU) No 7/2010 (OJ L 354, 28.12.2013, p. 319).</p>
                  </authorialNote>. Within those tariff quotas, products can be imported into the Union at reduced or zero duty rates.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d89e78">
               <num>(2)</num>
               <p>As it is in the Union&apos;s interest to ensure an adequate supply of certain industrial products, and having regard to the fact that identical, equivalent or substitute products are not produced in sufficient quantities within the Union, it is necessary to open new tariff quotas for order numbers 09.2580, 09.2581 and 09.2583 at zero duty rates for appropriate quantities of those products.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d89e84">
               <num>(3)</num>
               <p>As is it in the Union&apos;s interest to ensure an adequate supply of certain industrial products, the amounts for the tariff quotas for order numbers 09.2634 and 09.2668 should be increased.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d89e90">
               <num>(4)</num>
               <p>As the scope of the tariff quota for order number 09.2652 has become inadequate to fulfil the needs of economic operators in the Union, the description of the product covered by that tariff quota should be amended.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d89e96">
               <num>(5)</num>
               <p>For the tariff quota for order number 09.2588, the quota period should be extended until 31 December 2020, because that tariff quota was opened for a period of six months only but it is still in the Union&apos;s interest to maintain it.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d89e105">
               <num>(6)</num>
               <p>The substances Dimethyl Sulphate (CAS RN 77-78-1) with a purity of at least 99 %, 2-Methylaniline (CAS RN 95-53-4) with a purity by weight of at least 99 % and 4,4&apos;-Methanediyldianiline (CAS RN 101-77-9) with a purity by weight of at least 97 % are included on the candidate list referred to in Article 59 of Regulation (EC) No 1907/2006 of the European Parliament and of the Council<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="2">
                     <p>Regulation (EC) No 1907/2006 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 18 December 2006 concerning the Registration, Evaluation, Authorisation and Restriction of Chemicals (REACH), establishing a European Chemicals Agency, amending Directive 1999/45/EC and repealing Council Regulation (EEC) No 793/93 and Commission Regulation (EC) No 1488/94 as well as Council Directive 76/769/EEC and Commission Directives 91/155/EEC, 93/67/EEC, 93/105/EC and 2000/21/EC (OJ L 396, 30.12.2006, p. 1).</p>
                  </authorialNote> and the substance with CAS RN 101-77-9 is included in Annex XIV to that Regulation. For that reason, existing tariff quotas for those substances should be progressively closed and any newly opened tariff quotas should apply for a limited period. Therefore, the tariff quotas with order numbers 09.2648 and 09.2730 should apply until 31 December 2020 with a conventional rate of duty at 2 %. In addition, the tariff quota with order number 09.2590 should be closed and a new tariff quota with order number 09.2582 should be opened until 31 December 2020 with a conventional rate of duty at 2 %.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d89e127">
               <num>(7)</num>
               <p>Taking into account the amendments to be made, and for the sake of clarity, the Annex to Regulation (EU) No 1388/2013 should be replaced.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d89e133">
               <num>(8)</num>
               <p>In order to avoid any interruption of the application of the tariff quota scheme, and to comply with the guidelines in the communication from the Commission of 13 December 2011 concerning autonomous tariff suspensions and quotas, the changes provided for in this Regulation regarding the tariff quotas for the products concerned should apply from 1 July 2020. This Regulation should therefore enter into force as a matter of urgency,</p>
            </recital>
         </recitals>
         <formula name="enactingFormula">
            <p>HAS ADOPTED THIS REGULATION:</p>
         </formula>
      </preamble>
      <body>
         <article xml:id="art_d89e149">
            <num>Article 1</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>The Annex to Regulation (EU) No 1388/2013 is replaced by the text appearing in the Annex to this Regulation.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <article xml:id="art_d89e154">
            <num>Article 2</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>This Regulation shall enter into force on the day following that of its publication in the <i>Official Journal of the European Union</i>.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>It shall apply from 1 July 2020.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <clause>
            <content>
               <p>This Regulation shall be binding in its entirety and directly applicable in all Member States.</p>
            </content>
         </clause>
      </body>
      <conclusions>
         <p>Done at Brussels, 15 June 2020.</p>
         <block name="signatory">
            <signature>
               <organization refersTo="">For the Council</organization>
               <role refersTo="">The President</role>
               <person refersTo="">A. METELKO-ZGOMBIĆ</person>
            </signature>
         </block>
      </conclusions>
   </bill>
</akomaNtoso>
