<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0"
            xmlns:fmx="http://formex.publications.europa.eu/schema/formex-05.21-20110601.xd"
            xmlns:leos="urn:eu:europa:ec:leos"
            xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema">
   <bill name="">
      <meta xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions">
         <identification source="~COM">
            <FRBRWork>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRcountry value=""/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
         </identification>
      </meta>
      <preface>
         <longTitle>
            <p>
               <docStage/>
               <docType>REGULATION (EU) 2017/1952 OF THE EUROPEAN PARLIAMENT AND OF THE COUNCIL</docType>of 25 October 2017<docPurpose>repealing Regulations (EC) No 2888/2000 and (EC) No 685/2001 of the European Parliament and of the Council and Council Regulation (EEC) No 1101/89</docPurpose>
            </p>
         </longTitle>
         <container name="EEArelevance">
            <p>(Text with EEA relevance)</p>
         </container>
      </preface>
      <preamble>
         <formula name="actingEntity">
            <p>THE EUROPEAN PARLIAMENT AND THE COUNCIL OF THE EUROPEAN UNION,</p>
         </formula>
         <citations>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union, and in particular Article 91 thereof,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the proposal from the European Commission,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>After transmission of the draft legislative act to the national parliaments,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the opinion of the European Economic and Social Committee<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="1">
                     <p>OJ C 209, 30.6.2017, p. 58.</p>
                  </authorialNote>,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>After consulting the Committee of the Regions,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>Acting in accordance with the ordinary legislative procedure<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="2">
                     <p>Position of the European Parliament of 12 September 2017 (not yet published in the Official Journal) and decision of the Council of 9 October 2017.</p>
                  </authorialNote>,</p>
            </citation>
         </citations>
         <recitals xml:id="recs_d521e88">
            <intro>
               <p>Whereas:</p>
            </intro>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d521e91">
               <num>(1)</num>
               <p>The European Parliament, the Council and the Commission have confirmed their joint commitment to update and simplify legislation in the Interinstitutional Agreement of 13 April 2016 on Better Law-Making<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="3">
                     <p>OJ L 123, 12.5.2016, p. 1.</p>
                  </authorialNote>.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d521e106">
               <num>(2)</num>
               <p>In order to clean up, and reduce the volume of, the <i>acquis</i>, it is necessary to regularly analyse it to identify obsolete legislation. Repealing obsolete legislation is useful for keeping the legislative framework transparent, clear and easy to use by Member States and relevant stakeholders, in this case the inland waterway and road haulage sectors.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d521e115">
               <num>(3)</num>
               <p>In 1989, the Council adopted Regulation (EEC) No 1101/89<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="4">
                     <p>Council Regulation (EEC) No 1101/89 of 27 April 1989 on structural improvements in inland waterway transport (OJ L 116, 28.4.1989, p. 25).</p>
                  </authorialNote>. Ten years later, the Council adopted Regulation (EC) No 718/1999<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="5">
                     <p>Council Regulation (EC) No 718/1999 of 29 March 1999 on a Community-fleet capacity policy to promote inland waterway transport (OJ L 90, 2.4.1999, p. 1).</p>
                  </authorialNote> in order to ensure that the appropriate tools continued to be available to the inland waterway transport sector and to manage fleet capacity. Regulation (EC) No 718/1999 covers the same subject matter as Regulation (EEC) No 1101/89, without repealing it.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d521e141">
               <num>(4)</num>
               <p>In accordance with Article 8(6) of the Agreement between the European Community and the Swiss Confederation on the Carriage of Goods and Passengers by Rail and Road<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="6">
                     <p>OJ L 114, 30.4.2002, p. 91.</p>
                  </authorialNote>, all vehicles meeting the technical standards set out in Council Directive 96/53/EC<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="7">
                     <p>Council Directive 96/53/EC of 25 July 1996 laying down for certain road vehicles circulating within the Community the maximum authorized dimensions in national and international traffic and the maximum authorized weights in international traffic (OJ L 235, 17.9.1996, p. 59).</p>
                  </authorialNote> have been exempt from any quota or authorisation arrangements since 1 January 2005. Regulation (EC) No 2888/2000 of the European Parliament and of the Council<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="8">
                     <p>Regulation (EC) No 2888/2000 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 18 December 2000 on the distribution of permits for heavy goods vehicles travelling in Switzerland (OJ L 336, 30.12.2000, p. 9).</p>
                  </authorialNote>, which concerns the distribution of permits for heavy goods vehicles travelling in Switzerland, should therefore be considered to be obsolete.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d521e177">
               <num>(5)</num>
               <p>Following the accession of the Republic of Bulgaria and of Romania to the Union on 1 January 2007, Regulation (EC) No 685/2001 of the European Parliament and of the Council<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="9">
                     <p>Regulation (EC) No 685/2001 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 4 April 2001 concerning the distribution of authorisations among Member States received through the Agreements establishing certain conditions for the carriage of goods by road and the promotion of combined transport between the European Community and the Republic of Bulgaria and between the European Community and Romania (OJ L 108, 18.4.2001, p. 1).</p>
                  </authorialNote> is no longer necessary as those Member States are no longer required to obtain authorisation for the carriage of goods by road and for the promotion of combined transport.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d521e196">
               <num>(6)</num>
               <p>As a consequence, Regulations (EEC) No 1101/89, (EC) No 2888/2000 and (EC) No 685/2001 should be repealed,</p>
            </recital>
         </recitals>
         <formula name="enactingFormula">
            <p>HAVE ADOPTED THIS REGULATION:</p>
         </formula>
      </preamble>
      <body>
         <article xml:id="art_d521e205">
            <num>Article 1</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>Regulations (EEC) No 1101/89, (EC) No 2888/2000 and (EC) No 685/2001 are hereby repealed.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <article xml:id="art_d521e210">
            <num>Article 2</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>This Regulation shall enter into force on the twentieth day following that of its publication in the <i>Official Journal of the European Union</i>.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <clause>
            <content>
               <p>This Regulation shall be binding in its entirety and directly applicable in all Member States.</p>
            </content>
         </clause>
      </body>
      <conclusions>
         <p>Done at Strasbourg, 25 October 2017.</p>
         <block name="signatory">
            <signature>
               <organization refersTo="">For the European Parliament</organization>
               <role refersTo="">The President</role>
               <person refersTo="">A. TAJANI</person>
            </signature>
            <signature>
               <organization refersTo="">For the Council</organization>
               <role refersTo="">The President</role>
               <person refersTo="">M. MAASIKAS</person>
            </signature>
         </block>
      </conclusions>
   </bill>
</akomaNtoso>
