<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0"
            xmlns:fmx="http://formex.publications.europa.eu/schema/formex-05.21-20110601.xd"
            xmlns:leos="urn:eu:europa:ec:leos"
            xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema">
   <bill name="">
      <meta xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions">
         <identification source="~COM">
            <FRBRWork>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRcountry value=""/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
         </identification>
      </meta>
      <preface>
         <longTitle>
            <p>
               <docStage/>
               <docType>COMMISSION REGULATION (EU) 2018/605</docType>of 19 April 2018<docPurpose>amending Annex II to Regulation (EC) No 1107/2009 by setting out scientific criteria for the determination of endocrine disrupting properties</docPurpose>
            </p>
         </longTitle>
         <container name="EEArelevance">
            <p>(Text with EEA relevance)</p>
         </container>
      </preface>
      <preamble>
         <formula name="actingEntity">
            <p>THE EUROPEAN COMMISSION,</p>
         </formula>
         <citations>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to Regulation (EC) No 1107/2009 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 21 October 2009 concerning the placing of plant protection products on the market and repealing Council Directives 79/117/EEC and 91/414/EEC<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="1">
                     <p>OJ L 309, 24.11.2009, p. 1.</p>
                  </authorialNote>, and in particular Article 78(1)(a) and the second paragraph of point 3.6.5 of Annex II thereto,</p>
            </citation>
         </citations>
         <recitals xml:id="recs_d85e71">
            <intro>
               <p>Whereas:</p>
            </intro>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d85e74">
               <num>(1)</num>
               <p>Scientific criteria for the determination of endocrine disrupting properties of active substances, safeners and synergists, should be developed taking into account the objectives of Regulation (EC) No 1107/2009, which are to ensure a high level of protection of both human and animal health and the environment, in particular ensuring that substances or products placed on the market have no harmful effect on human or animal health or unacceptable effects on the environment, and to improve the functioning of the internal market while improving agricultural production.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d85e80">
               <num>(2)</num>
               <p>In 2002, the World Health Organisation (WHO) through its International Programme for Chemical Safety proposed a definition for endocrine disruptors<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="2">
                     <p>WHO/IPCS (World Health Organization/International Programme on Chemical Safety), 2002. Global Assessment of the State-of-the-science of Endocrine Disruptors. WHO/PCS/EDC/02.2, publicly available at http://www.who.int/ipcs/publications/new_issues/endocrine_disruptors/en/</p>
                  </authorialNote> and in 2009 a definition of adverse effects<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="3">
                     <p>WHO/IPCS (World Health Organization/International Programme on Chemical Safety), 2009. Principles and Methods for the Risk Assessment of Chemicals in Food. Environmental Health Criteria 240, publicly available at http://www.who.int/foodsafety/publications/chemical-food/en/</p>
                  </authorialNote>. Those definitions have by now reached the widest consensus among scientists. The European Food Safety Authority (&apos;the Authority&apos;) endorsed those definitions in its Scientific Opinion on endocrine disruptors adopted on 28 February 2013<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="4">
                     <p>&apos;Scientific Opinion on the hazard assessment of endocrine disruptors: Scientific criteria for identification of endocrine disruptors and appropriateness of existing test methods for assessing effects mediated by these substances on human health and the environment&apos;, <i>EFSA Journal</i> 2013;11(3):3132, doi: 10.2903/j.efsa.2013.3132.</p>
                  </authorialNote> (hereinafter &apos;the Scientific Opinion of the Authority&apos;). Such is also the view of the Scientific Committee on Consumer Safety<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="5">
                     <p>Scientific Committee on Consumer Safety, Memorandum on Endocrine disruptors, 16.12.2014 (SCCS/1544/14).</p>
                  </authorialNote>. It is therefore appropriate to base the criteria for the determination of endocrine disrupting properties on those WHO definitions.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d85e122">
               <num>(3)</num>
               <p>In order to implement those criteria, weight of evidence should be applied considering in particular the approach provided for in Regulation (EC) No 1272/2008 of the European Parliament and of the Council<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="6">
                     <p>Regulation (EC) No 1272/2008 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 16 December 2008 on classification, labelling and packaging of substances and mixtures, amending and repealing Directives 67/548/EEC and 1999/45/EC, and amending Regulation (EC) No 1907/2006 (OJ L 353, 31.12.2008, p. 1).</p>
                  </authorialNote> on the weight of evidence. Previous experience with the Guidance document on standardised test guidelines for evaluating chemicals for endocrine disruption of OECD<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="7">
                     <p>OECD Series on Testing and Assessment No 150.</p>
                  </authorialNote> should also be considered. In addition, the implementation of the criteria should be based on all relevant scientific evidence, including studies submitted in accordance with the current regulatory data requirements of Regulation (EC) No 1107/2009. These studies are mostly based on internationally agreed study protocols.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d85e142">
               <num>(4)</num>
               <p>The determination of endocrine disrupting properties with respect to human health should be based on human and/or animal evidence, therefore allowing for the identification of both known and presumed endocrine disrupting substances.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d85e149">
               <num>(5)</num>
               <p>As the specific scientific criteria laid down by this Regulation reflect the current scientific and technical knowledge and are to be applied instead of the criteria currently set out in point 3.6.5 of Annex II to Regulation (EC) No 1107/2009, they should be provided for in that Annex.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d85e155">
               <num>(6)</num>
               <p>In order to take into account the current scientific and technical knowledge, specific scientific criteria should also be specified in order to identify active substances, safeners or synergists having endocrine disrupting properties that may cause adverse effects on non-target organisms. Therefore point 3.8.2 of Annex II to Regulation (EC) No 1107/2009 should be amended to introduce these specific criteria.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d85e161">
               <num>(7)</num>
               <p>The Commission should assess, in light of the objectives of Regulation (EC) No 1107/2009, the experience gained from the application of the scientific criteria for the determination of endocrine disrupting properties introduced by the present Regulation.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d85e167">
               <num>(8)</num>
               <p>The criteria for the determination of endocrine disrupting properties reflect the current state of scientific and technical knowledge and allow identifying active substances having endocrine disrupting properties more accurately. The new criteria should therefore apply as soon as possible, while taking into account the time necessary for Member States and the Authority to prepare for applying those criteria. Therefore, from 20 October 2018, those criteria should apply except where the relevant Committee has voted on a draft Regulation by 20 October 2018. The Commission will consider the implications for each procedure pending under Regulation (EC) No 1107/2009 and, where necessary, take appropriate measures with due respect for the rights of the applicants. This may include a request for additional information from the applicant and/or for additional scientific input from the rapporteur Member State and the Authority.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d85e179">
               <num>(9)</num>
               <p>The measures provided for in this Regulation are in accordance with the opinion of the Standing Committee on Plants, Animals, Food and Feed,</p>
            </recital>
         </recitals>
         <formula name="enactingFormula">
            <p>HAS ADOPTED THIS REGULATION:</p>
         </formula>
      </preamble>
      <body>
         <article xml:id="art_d85e188">
            <num>Article 1</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>Annex II to Regulation (EC) No 1107/2009 is amended in accordance with the Annex to this Regulation.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <article xml:id="art_d85e193">
            <num>Article 2</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>Points 3.6.5 and 3.8.2 of Annex II to Regulation (EC) No 1107/2009, as amended by this Regulation, shall apply as of 20 October 2018, except for procedures where the Committee has voted on a draft Regulation by 20 October 2018.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <article xml:id="art_d85e204">
            <num>Article 3</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>By 20 October 2025, the Commission shall present to the Committee referred to in Article 79 of Regulation (EC) No 1107/2009 an assessment of the experience gained from the application of the scientific criteria for the determination of endocrine disrupting properties introduced by this Regulation.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <article xml:id="art_d85e212">
            <num>Article 4</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>This Regulation shall enter into force on the twentieth day following that of its publication in the <i>Official Journal of the European Union</i>.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>It shall apply from 20 October 2018.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <clause>
            <content>
               <p>This Regulation shall be binding in its entirety and directly applicable in all Member States.</p>
            </content>
         </clause>
      </body>
      <conclusions>
         <p>Done at Brussels, 19 April 2018.</p>
         <block name="signatory">
            <signature>
               <organization refersTo="">For the Commission</organization>
               <role refersTo="">The President</role>
               <person refersTo="">Jean-Claude JUNCKER</person>
            </signature>
         </block>
      </conclusions>
   </bill>
</akomaNtoso>
