<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0"
            xmlns:fmx="http://formex.publications.europa.eu/schema/formex-05.21-20110601.xd"
            xmlns:leos="urn:eu:europa:ec:leos"
            xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema">
   <bill name="">
      <meta xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions">
         <identification source="~COM">
            <FRBRWork>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRcountry value=""/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
         </identification>
      </meta>
      <preface>
         <longTitle>
            <p>
               <docStage/>
               <docType>COMMISSION REGULATION (EU) 2019/220</docType>of 6 February 2019<docPurpose>amending Regulation (EC) No 865/2006 laying down detailed rules concerning the implementation of Council Regulation (EC) No 338/97 on the protection of species of wild fauna and flora by regulating trade therein</docPurpose>
            </p>
         </longTitle>
      </preface>
      <preamble>
         <formula name="actingEntity">
            <p>THE EUROPEAN COMMISSION,</p>
         </formula>
         <citations>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to Council Regulation (EC) No 338/97 of 9 December 1996 on the protection of species of wild fauna and flora by regulating trade therein<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="1">
                     <p>OJ L 61, 3.3.1997, p. 1.</p>
                  </authorialNote>, and in particular Article 19(4) thereof,</p>
            </citation>
         </citations>
         <recitals xml:id="recs_d3e68">
            <intro>
               <p>Whereas:</p>
            </intro>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d3e71">
               <num>(1)</num>
               <p>The purpose of Commission Regulation (EC) No 865/2006<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="2">
                     <p>Commission Regulation (EC) No 865/2006 of 4 May 2006 laying down detailed rules concerning the implementation of Council Regulation (EC) No 338/97 on the protection of species of wild fauna and flora by regulating trade therein (OJ L 166, 19.6.2006, p. 1).</p>
                  </authorialNote> is to implement Regulation (EC) No 338/97 and to ensure full compliance with the provisions of the Convention on International Trade in Endangered Species of Wild Fauna and Flora (CITES) (&apos;the Convention&apos;).</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d3e91">
               <num>(2)</num>
               <p>At the seventeenth meeting of the Conference of the Parties to the Convention, certain changes to CITES Resolution Conf. 11.20 (Rev. CoP17) relating to the trade in live elephants and rhinoceroses were agreed. At the same meeting, the list of standard references for nomenclature annexed to CITES Resolution Conf. 12.11 (Rev. CoP17), which is to be used to indicate scientific names of species in permits and certificates, was restructured and updated.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d3e97">
               <num>(3)</num>
               <p>At its 67th meeting, the Standing Committee of the Convention adopted revised guidelines for the submission of annual reports. The guidelines comprise revised codes that are to be included in the description of specimens and units of measure that are to be used in permits and certificates.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d3e103">
               <num>(4)</num>
               <p>The changes to CITES Resolutions Conf. 11.20 and Conf. 12.11 and the revised codes and units of measure need to be reflected in Regulation (EC) No 865/2006.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d3e109">
               <num>(5)</num>
               <p>Therefore, Regulation (EC) No 865/2006 should be amended accordingly.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d3e115">
               <num>(6)</num>
               <p>The measures provided for in this Regulation are in accordance with the opinion of the Committee on Trade in Wild Fauna and Flora,</p>
            </recital>
         </recitals>
         <formula name="enactingFormula">
            <p>HAS ADOPTED THIS REGULATION:</p>
         </formula>
      </preamble>
      <body>
         <article xml:id="art_d3e124" leos:compliant="false">
            <num>Article 1</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <subparagraph>
                  <content>
                     <p>Regulation (EC) No 865/2006 is amended as follows:</p>
                  </content>
               </subparagraph>
               <list>
                  <point>
                     <num>(1)</num>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>The following Article 5b is inserted:</p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>
                              <mod>
                                 <quotedStructure startQuote="" endQuote="">
                                    <article xml:id="art_d3e139">
                                       <num>&apos;Article 5b</num>
                                       <heading>Specific content of permits and certificates for live rhinoceros and live elephants</heading>
                                       <paragraph>
                                          <content>
                                             <p>Permits and certificates issued under Article 4 or Article 5 of Regulation (EC) No 338/97 for import or re-export of live rhinoceroses or live elephants from populations included in Annex B to that Regulation shall contain a condition stating that horn or ivory from those animals or from their progeny may not enter commercial trade or commercial activities within the Union. In addition, live rhinoceroses or live elephants from those populations shall not be subject to trophy hunting outside of their historic range.&apos;;</p>
                                          </content>
                                       </paragraph>
                                    </article>
                                 </quotedStructure>
                              </mod>
                           </p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                  </point>
                  <point>
                     <num>(2)</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>Annexes VII and VIII are replaced by the text in the Annex to this Regulation.</p>
                     </content>
                  </point>
               </list>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <article xml:id="art_d3e156">
            <num>Article 2</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>This Regulation shall enter into force on the twentieth day following that of its publication in the <i>Official Journal of the European Union</i>.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <clause>
            <content>
               <p>This Regulation shall be binding in its entirety and directly applicable in all Member States.</p>
            </content>
         </clause>
      </body>
      <conclusions>
         <p>Done at Brussels, 6 February 2019.</p>
         <block name="signatory">
            <signature>
               <organization refersTo="">For the Commission</organization>
               <role refersTo="">The President</role>
               <person refersTo="">Jean-Claude JUNCKER</person>
            </signature>
         </block>
      </conclusions>
   </bill>
</akomaNtoso>
