<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0"
            xmlns:fmx="http://formex.publications.europa.eu/schema/formex-05.21-20110601.xd"
            xmlns:leos="urn:eu:europa:ec:leos"
            xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema">
   <bill name="">
      <meta xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions">
         <identification source="~COM">
            <FRBRWork>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRcountry value=""/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
         </identification>
      </meta>
      <preface>
         <longTitle>
            <p>
               <docStage/>
               <docType>COMMISSION REGULATION (EU) 2019/50</docType>of 11 January 2019<docPurpose>amending Annexes II, III, IV and V to Regulation (EC) No 396/2005 of the European Parliament and of the Council as regards maximum residue levels for chlorantraniliprole, clomazone, cyclaniliprole, fenazaquin, fenpicoxamid, fluoxastrobin, lambda-cyhalothrin, mepiquat, onion oil, thiacloprid and valifenalate in or on certain products</docPurpose>
            </p>
         </longTitle>
         <container name="EEArelevance">
            <p>(Text with EEA relevance)</p>
         </container>
      </preface>
      <preamble>
         <formula name="actingEntity">
            <p>THE EUROPEAN COMMISSION,</p>
         </formula>
         <citations>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to Regulation (EC) No 396/2005 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 23 February 2005 on maximum residue levels of pesticides in or on food and feed of plant and animal origin and amending Council Directive 91/414/EEC<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="1">
                     <p>OJ L 70, 16.3.2005, p. 1.</p>
                  </authorialNote>, and in particular Article 5(1), Article 14(1)(a) and Article 18(1)(b) thereof,</p>
            </citation>
         </citations>
         <recitals xml:id="recs_d31e71">
            <intro>
               <p>Whereas:</p>
            </intro>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d31e74">
               <num>(1)</num>
               <p>For clomazone, fluoxastrobin, lambda-cyhalothrin, mepiquat and thiacloprid, maximum residue levels (MRLs) were set in Annex II to Regulation (EC) No 396/2005. For chlorantraniliprole, fenazaquin and valifenalate, MRLs were set in Part A of Annex III to that Regulation. For cyclaniliprole, fenpicoxamid and onion oil, no specific MRLs were set nor were those substances included in Annex IV to that Regulation, so the default value of 0,01 mg/kg laid down in Article 18(1)(b) thereof applies.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d31e80">
               <num>(2)</num>
               <p>On 4 July 2009, Codex Alimentarius Commission adopted a Codex maximum residue limit (CXL) for lambda-cyhalothrin in rye<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="2">
                     <p>http://www.fao.org/fao-who-codexalimentarius/sh-proxy/en/?lnk=1&amp;url=https%253A%252F%252Fworkspace.fao.org%252Fsites%252Fcodex%252FMeetings%252FCX-718-41%252Fal32_24e.pdf</p>
                     <p>Joint FAO/WHO food standards programme Codex Alimentarius Commission. Appendices III and IV. Thirty-second Session. Rome, Italy, 29 June-4 July 2009.</p>
                  </authorialNote>.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d31e101">
               <num>(3)</num>
               <p>In accordance with Article 5(3) of Regulation (EC) No 178/2002 of the European Parliament and of the Council<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="3">
                     <p>Regulation (EC) No 178/2002 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 28 January 2002 laying down the general principles and requirements of food law, establishing the European Food Safety Authority and laying down procedures in matters of food safety (OJ L 31, 1.2.2002, p. 1).</p>
                  </authorialNote>, where international standards exist or their completion is imminent, they are to be taken into consideration in the development or adaptation of food law, except where such standards or relevant parts would be an ineffective or inappropriate means for the fulfilment of the legitimate objectives of food law or where there is a scientific justification, or where they would result in a different level of protection from the one determined as appropriate in the Union. Moreover, in accordance with point (e) of Article 13 of that Regulation, the Union is to promote consistency between international technical standards and food law while ensuring that the high level of protection adopted in the Union is not reduced.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d31e117">
               <num>(4)</num>
               <p>The CXL for lambda-cyhalothrin in rye is safe for consumers in the Union<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="4">
                     <p>Revision of the review of the existing maximum residue levels for the active substance lambda-cyhalothrin. <i>EFSA Journal</i> 2015;13(12):4324.</p>
                  </authorialNote> and should therefore be included in Regulation (EC) No 396/2005 as MRL.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d31e130">
               <num>(5)</num>
               <p>In the context of a procedure for the authorisation of the use of a plant protection product containing the active substance clomazone on chamomile and plantains, an application was submitted in accordance with Article 6(1) of Regulation (EC) No 396/2005 for modification of the existing MRLs.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d31e136">
               <num>(6)</num>
               <p>As regards fluoxastrobin, such an application was submitted for garlic, rapeseed, linseeds, poppy seeds, mustard seeds and gold of pleasure seeds. As regards mepiquat, such an application was submitted for rapeseed, linseeds, poppy seeds, mustard seeds, gold of pleasure seeds, sunflower seeds, liver (from swine, sheep and goat), kidney (from swine), milks and eggs. As regards thiacloprid, such an application was submitted for borage seeds and radishes. As regards valifenalate, such an application was submitted for tomatoes, aubergines, lettuces, onions, shallots and garlic.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d31e144">
               <num>(7)</num>
               <p>In accordance with Article 6(2) and (4) of Regulation (EC) No 396/2005 applications were submitted for chlorantraniliprole and fenazaquin used in the United States on hops and almonds, respectively. The applicants claim that the authorised uses of those substances on such crops in the United States lead to residues exceeding the MRLs contained in Regulation (EC) No 396/2005 and that higher MRLs are necessary to avoid trade barriers for the importation of those crops.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d31e150">
               <num>(8)</num>
               <p>In accordance with Article 8 of Regulation (EC) No 396/2005, those applications were evaluated by the Member States concerned and the evaluation reports were forwarded to the Commission.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d31e156">
               <num>(9)</num>
               <p>The European Food Safety Authority, hereinafter &apos;the Authority&apos;, assessed the applications and the evaluation reports, examining in particular the risks to the consumer and, where relevant, to animals and gave reasoned opinions on the proposed MRLs<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="5">
                     <p>EFSA scientific reports available online:</p>
                     <p>http://www.efsa.europa.eu:</p>
                     <alinea>
                        <list>
                           <indent>
                              <num> </num>
                              <content>
                                 <p>Reasoned opinion on the modification of the existing maximum residue levels for clomazone in chamomiles and plantains. <i>EFSA Journal</i> 2018;16(6):5316.</p>
                              </content>
                           </indent>
                           <indent>
                              <num> </num>
                              <content>
                                 <p>Reasoned opinion on the modification of the existing maximum residue levels for fluoxastrobin in oilseeds. <i>EFSA Journal</i> 2018;16(7):5381.</p>
                              </content>
                           </indent>
                           <indent>
                              <num> </num>
                              <content>
                                 <p>Reasoned opinion on the modification of the existing maximum residue levels for mepiquat in various oilseeds and animal commodities. <i>EFSA Journal</i> 2018;16(7):5380.</p>
                              </content>
                           </indent>
                           <indent>
                              <num> </num>
                              <content>
                                 <p>Reasoned opinion on the modification of the existing maximum residue levels for thiacloprid in corn gromwell seeds and radish. <i>EFSA Journal</i> 2018;16(6):5313.</p>
                              </content>
                           </indent>
                           <indent>
                              <num> </num>
                              <content>
                                 <p>Reasoned opinion on the modification of the existing maximum residue levels for valifenalate in various crops. <i>EFSA Journal</i> 2018;16(6):5289.</p>
                              </content>
                           </indent>
                           <indent>
                              <num> </num>
                              <content>
                                 <p>Reasoned opinion on the setting of an import tolerance for chlorantraniliprole in hops. <i>EFSA Journal</i> 2018;16(6):5312.</p>
                              </content>
                           </indent>
                           <indent>
                              <num> </num>
                              <content>
                                 <p>Reasoned opinion on the setting of an import tolerance for fenazaquin in almonds. <i>EFSA Journal</i> 2018;16(7):5330.</p>
                              </content>
                           </indent>
                        </list>
                     </alinea>
                  </authorialNote>. It forwarded those opinions to the applicants, the Commission and the Member States and made them available to the public.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d31e215">
               <num>(10)</num>
               <p>As regards fluoxastrobin in garlic, the Authority assessed an application with a view of setting an MRL for onions and gave a reasoned opinion on the proposed MRL<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="6">
                     <p>Reasoned opinion on the review of the existing maximum residue levels (MRLs) for fluoxastrobin according to Article 12 of Regulation (EC) No 396/2005. <i>EFSA Journal</i> 2012;10(12):3012.</p>
                  </authorialNote>. In accordance with the existing Union guidelines on extrapolation of MRLs, it is appropriate to set the MRL for onions also for garlic.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d31e229">
               <num>(11)</num>
               <p>As regards all other applications, the Authority concluded that all requirements with respect to data were met and that the modifications to the MRLs requested by the applicants were acceptable with regard to consumer safety on the basis of a consumer exposure assessment for 27 specific European consumer groups. It took into account the most recent information on the toxicological properties of the substances. Neither the lifetime exposure to these substances via consumption of all food products that may contain them, nor the short-term exposure due to high consumption of the relevant products showed that there is a risk that the acceptable daily intake or the acute reference dose is exceeded.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d31e235">
               <num>(12)</num>
               <p>For mepiquat temporary MRLs were set by Commission Regulation (EU) 2016/1003<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="7">
                     <p>Commission Regulation (EU) 2016/1003 of 17 June 2016 amending Annexes II and III to Regulation (EC) No 396/2005 of the European Parliament and of the Council as regards maximum residue levels for abamectin, acequinocyl, acetamiprid, benzovindiflupyr, bromoxynil, fludioxonil, fluopicolide, fosetyl, mepiquat, proquinazid, propamocarb, prohexadione and tebuconazole in or on certain products (OJ L 167, 24.6.2016, p. 46).</p>
                  </authorialNote> for cultivated fungi until 31 December 2018 to address a cross-contamination that affected untreated cultivated fungi with straw lawfully treated with mepiquat. Member States and the Authority have submitted recent monitoring data showing that residues of mepiquat still occur at levels above the relevant limit of determination. It is therefore appropriate to extend the validity of the current MRL set at 0,09 mg/kg. The MRL will be reviewed; the review will take into account the information available within four years from the publication of this Regulation.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d31e255">
               <num>(13)</num>
               <p>As regards lambda-cyhalothrin, several MRLs were modified by Commission Regulation (EU) 2018/960<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="8">
                     <p>Commission Regulation (EU) 2018/960 of 5 July 2018 amending Annexes II and III to Regulation (EC) No 396/2005 of the European Parliament and of the Council as regards maximum residue levels for lambda-cyhalothrin in or on certain products (OJ L 169, 6.7.2018, p. 27).</p>
                  </authorialNote>. That Regulation lowers the MRL for rye to the limit of determination, omitting the existing CXL for rye, as of 26 January 2019. In the interest of legal certainty, it is appropriate for the MRL provided for by this Regulation, to apply from the same date.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d31e274">
               <num>(14)</num>
               <p>In the context of the approval of the active substance fenpicoxamid, an MRL application was included in the summary dossier in accordance with Article 8(1)(g) of Regulation (EC) No 1107/2009 of the European Parliament and of the Council<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="9">
                     <p>Regulation (EC) No 1107/2009 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 21 October 2009 concerning the placing of plant protection products on the market and repealing Council Directives 79/117/EEC and 91/414/EEC (OJ L 309, 24.11.2009, p. 1).</p>
                  </authorialNote>. Such application was evaluated by the Member State concerned in accordance with Article 11(2) of that Regulation. The Authority assessed the application and delivered a conclusion on the peer review of the pesticide risk assessment of the active substance, where it recommended setting MRLs covering the representative uses on rye and wheat according to Good Agricultural Practices (GAPs) in the Union and an import tolerance request for bananas from Panama<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="10">
                     <p>Conclusion on the peer review of the pesticide risk assessment of the active substance fenpicoxamid (XDE-777). <i>EFSA Journal</i> 2018;16(1):5146.</p>
                  </authorialNote>.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d31e297">
               <num>(15)</num>
               <p>Onion oil is approved as basic substance by Commission Implementing Regulation (EU) 2018/1295<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="11">
                     <p>Commission Implementing Regulation (EU) 2018/1295 of 26 September 2018 approving the basic substance Onion oil in accordance with Regulation (EC) No 1107/2009 of the European Parliament and of the Council concerning the placing of plant protection products on the market, and amending the Annex to Commission Implementing Regulation (EU) No 540/2011 (OJ L 243, 27.9.2018, p. 7).</p>
                  </authorialNote>. The conditions of use of that substance are not expected to lead to the presence of residues in food or feed commodities that may pose a risk to the consumer. It is therefore appropriate to include that substance in Annex IV to Regulation (EC) No 396/2005.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d31e313">
               <num>(16)</num>
               <p>The active substance cyclaniliprole was not approved by Commission Implementing Regulation (EU) 2017/357<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="12">
                     <p>Commission Implementing Regulation (EU) 2017/357 of 28 February 2017 concerning the non-approval of the active substance cyclaniliprole, in accordance with Regulation (EC) No 1107/2009 of the European Parliament and of the Council concerning the placing of plant protection products on the market (OJ L 54, 1.3.2017, p. 4).</p>
                  </authorialNote>. As no MRLs were set in Regulation (EC) No 396/2005, it is appropriate to include the substance in Annex V to that Regulation.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d31e329">
               <num>(17)</num>
               <p>Based on the reasoned opinions and the conclusion of the Authority and taking into account the factors relevant to the matter under consideration, the appropriate modifications to the MRLs fulfil the requirements of Article 14(2) of Regulation (EC) No 396/2005.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d31e335">
               <num>(18)</num>
               <p>Regulation (EC) No 396/2005 should therefore be amended accordingly.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d31e341">
               <num>(19)</num>
               <p>The measures provided for in this Regulation are in accordance with the opinion of the Standing Committee on Plants, Animals, Food and Feed,</p>
            </recital>
         </recitals>
         <formula name="enactingFormula">
            <p>HAS ADOPTED THIS REGULATION:</p>
         </formula>
      </preamble>
      <body>
         <article xml:id="art_d31e350">
            <num>Article 1</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>Annexes II, III, IV and V to Regulation (EC) No 396/2005 are amended in accordance with the Annex to this Regulation.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <article xml:id="art_d31e355">
            <num>Article 2</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>This Regulation shall enter into force on the day following that of its publication in the <i>Official Journal of the European Union</i>.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>It shall apply from 1 January 2019. However, it shall apply from 26 January 2019 for the MRL for lambda-cyhalothrin in rye.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <clause>
            <content>
               <p>This Regulation shall be binding in its entirety and directly applicable in all Member States.</p>
            </content>
         </clause>
      </body>
      <conclusions>
         <p>Done at Brussels, 11 January 2019.</p>
         <block name="signatory">
            <signature>
               <organization refersTo="">For the Commission</organization>
               <role refersTo="">The President</role>
               <person refersTo="">Jean-Claude JUNCKER</person>
            </signature>
         </block>
      </conclusions>
   </bill>
</akomaNtoso>
