<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0"
            xmlns:fmx="http://formex.publications.europa.eu/schema/formex-05.21-20110601.xd"
            xmlns:leos="urn:eu:europa:ec:leos"
            xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema">
   <bill name="">
      <meta xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions">
         <identification source="~COM">
            <FRBRWork>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRcountry value=""/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
         </identification>
      </meta>
      <preface>
         <longTitle>
            <p>
               <docStage/>
               <docType>COMMISSION REGULATION (EU) 2017/2460</docType>of 30 October 2017<docPurpose>amending Annex VII to Regulation (EC) No 882/2004 of the European Parliament and of the Council on official controls performed to ensure the verification of compliance with feed and food law, animal health and animal welfare rules, as regards the list of Union reference laboratories</docPurpose>
            </p>
         </longTitle>
         <container name="EEArelevance">
            <p>(Text with EEA relevance)</p>
         </container>
      </preface>
      <preamble>
         <formula name="actingEntity">
            <p>THE EUROPEAN COMMISSION,</p>
         </formula>
         <citations>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to Regulation (EC) No 882/2004 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 29 April 2004 on official controls performed to ensure the compliance with feed and food law, animal health and animal welfare rules<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="1">
                     <p>OJ L 165, 30.4.2004, p. 1.</p>
                  </authorialNote>, and in particular Article 32(5) thereof,</p>
            </citation>
         </citations>
         <recitals xml:id="recs_d681e71">
            <intro>
               <p>Whereas:</p>
            </intro>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d681e74">
               <num>(1)</num>
               <p>Regulation (EC) No 882/2004 lays down general rules for the performance of official controls to verify compliance with, inter alia, rules on food hygiene. In accordance with that Regulation, European Union reference laboratories (&apos;EU reference laboratories&apos;) are responsible, in particular, for providing national reference laboratories with details of analytical methods and for the coordination of the application of such methods. The EU reference laboratories are listed in Annex VII to that Regulation.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d681e84">
               <num>(2)</num>
               <p>The EU reference laboratory on milk and milk products&apos; work programme is essentially aimed at providing analytical methods and ensuring a common approach to inter laboratory proficiency tests conducted by national reference laboratories on quality markers such as somatic cells counts and germs. State of the art expertise on how to properly conduct those analyses is now well established both with the official laboratories performing official controls and with laboratories increasingly utilised by food businesses to analyse those markers, which are a factor determining the price of milk collected at the farm.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d681e90">
               <num>(3)</num>
               <p>The EU reference laboratory for milk and milk products is no longer required within the Union. It should therefore be removed from the list of the EU reference laboratories set out in Annex VII to Regulation (EC) No 882/2004.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d681e96">
               <num>(4)</num>
               <p>Annex VII to Regulation (EC) No 882/2004 should therefore be amended accordingly.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d681e102">
               <num>(5)</num>
               <p>The measures provided for in this Regulation are in accordance with the opinion of the Standing Committee on Plants, Animals, Food and Feed,</p>
            </recital>
         </recitals>
         <formula name="enactingFormula">
            <p>HAS ADOPTED THIS REGULATION:</p>
         </formula>
      </preamble>
      <body>
         <article xml:id="art_d681e111">
            <num>Article 1</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>In Part I of Annex VII to Regulation (EC) No 882/2004, point 1 is deleted.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <article xml:id="art_d681e116">
            <num>Article 2</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>This Regulation shall enter into force on the third day following that of its publication in the <i>Official Journal of the European Union</i>.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <clause>
            <content>
               <p>This Regulation shall be binding in its entirety and directly applicable in all Member States.</p>
            </content>
         </clause>
      </body>
      <conclusions>
         <p>Done at Brussels, 30 October 2017.</p>
         <block name="signatory">
            <signature>
               <organization refersTo="">For the Commission</organization>
               <role refersTo="">The President</role>
               <person refersTo="">Jean-Claude JUNCKER</person>
            </signature>
         </block>
      </conclusions>
   </bill>
</akomaNtoso>
