L3302019EN10410120191129EN002010411041<p xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">Corrigendum to Commission Regulation (EU) 2019/2117 of 29 November 2019 amending Council Regulation (EC) No 338/97 on the protection of species of wild fauna and flora by regulating trade therein</p>
<p xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">(Official Journal of the European Union L 320 of 11 December 2019)</p>On page 103, footnote (<sup xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">1</sup>) is replaced as follows:<mod xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
   <quotedStructure startQuote="" endQuote="">
      <point>
         <num>&apos;(<sup>1</sup>)</num>
         <p>For the exclusive purpose of allowing international trade in fibre from vicuñas (<i>Vicugna vicugna</i>) and their derivative products, only if the fibre comes from the shearing of live vicuñas. Trade in products derived from the fibre may only take place in accordance with the following provisions:</p>
         <list>
            <point>
               <num>(a)</num>
               <p>Any person or entity processing vicuña fibre to manufacture cloth and garments must request authorization from the relevant authorities of the country of origin [Countries of origin: The countries where the species occurs, that is, Argentina, Bolivia, Chile, Ecuador and Peru] to use the &quot;vicuña country of origin&quot; wording, mark or logo adopted by the range States of the species that are signatories to the Convention for the Conservation and Management of the Vicuña.</p>
            </point>
            <point>
               <num>(b)</num>
               <p>Marketed cloth or garments must be marked or identified in accordance with the following provisions:</p>
               <list>
                  <point>
                     <num>(i)</num>
                     <p>For international trade in cloth made from live-sheared vicuña fibre, whether the cloth was produced within or outside of the range States of the species, the wording, mark or logo must be used so that the country of origin can be identified. The VICUÑA [COUNTRY OF ORIGIN] wording, mark or logo has the format as detailed below:</p>
                     <p><!--default P | TXT --></p>
                     <p><!--default P | TXT -->This wording, mark or logo must appear on the reverse side of the cloth. In addition, the selvages of the cloth must bear the words VICUÑA [COUNTRY OF ORIGIN].</p>
                  </point>
                  <point>
                     <num>(ii)</num>
                     <p>For international trade in garments made from live-sheared vicuña fibre, whether the garments were produced within or outside of the range States of the species, the wording, mark or logo indicated in paragraph (b)(i) must be used. This wording, mark or logo must appear on a label in the garment itself. If the garments are produced outside of the country of origin, the name of the country where the garment was produced should also be indicated, in addition to the wording, mark or logo referred to in paragraph (b)(i).</p>
                  </point>
               </list>
            </point>
            <point>
               <num>(c)</num>
               <p>For international trade in handicraft products made from live-sheared vicuña fibre produced within the range States of the species, the VICUÑA [COUNTRY OF ORIGIN] - ARTESANÍA wording, mark or logo must be used as detailed below:</p>
               <p><!--default P | TXT --></p>
            </point>
            <point>
               <num>(d)</num>
               <p>If live-sheared vicuña fibre from various countries of origin is used for the production of cloth and garments, the wording, mark or logo of each of the countries of origin of the fibre must be indicated, as detailed in paragraphs (b)(i) and (ii).</p>
            </point>
            <point>
               <num>(e)</num>
               <p>All other specimens shall be deemed to be specimens of species listed in Appendix I and the trade in them shall be regulated accordingly.&apos;</p>
            </point>
         </list>
      </point>
   </quotedStructure>
</mod>
