<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0"
            xmlns:fmx="http://formex.publications.europa.eu/schema/formex-05.21-20110601.xd"
            xmlns:leos="urn:eu:europa:ec:leos"
            xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema">
   <bill name="">
      <meta xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions">
         <identification source="~COM">
            <FRBRWork>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRcountry value=""/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
               <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
               <FRBRthis value=""/>
               <FRBRuri value=""/>
               <FRBRdate date="2999-01-01" name=""/>
               <FRBRauthor href=""/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
         </identification>
      </meta>
      <preface>
         <longTitle>
            <p>
               <docStage/>
               <docType>REGULATION (EU) 2017/1951 OF THE EUROPEAN PARLIAMENT AND OF THE COUNCIL</docType>of 25 October 2017<docPurpose>amending Regulation (EU) No 99/2013 on the European statistical programme 2013-17, by extending it to 2020</docPurpose>
            </p>
         </longTitle>
         <container name="EEArelevance">
            <p>(Text with relevance for the EEA and for Switzerland)</p>
         </container>
      </preface>
      <preamble>
         <formula name="actingEntity">
            <p>THE EUROPEAN PARLIAMENT AND THE COUNCIL OF THE EUROPEAN UNION,</p>
         </formula>
         <citations>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union, and in particular Article 338(1) thereof,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the proposal from the European Commission,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>After transmission of the draft legislative act to the national parliaments,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>Having regard to the opinion of the European Economic and Social Committee<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="1">
                     <p>OJ C 75, 10.3.2017, p. 53.</p>
                  </authorialNote>,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>After consulting the Committee of the Regions,</p>
            </citation>
            <citation>
               <p>Acting in accordance with the ordinary legislative procedure<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="2">
                     <p>Position of the European Parliament of 14 September 2017 (not yet published in the Official Journal) and decision of the Council of 9 October 2017.</p>
                  </authorialNote>,</p>
            </citation>
         </citations>
         <recitals xml:id="recs_d440e88">
            <intro>
               <p>Whereas:</p>
            </intro>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d440e91">
               <num>(1)</num>
               <p>Reliable, relevant evidence based on timely and publicly available European statistics that can be used for policy-making is essential for measuring the progress of and evaluating the efficiency of the Union&apos;s policies and programmes, especially in the context of the Europe 2020 Strategy set out in the Commission Communication of 3 March 2010 entitled &apos;Europe 2020: A strategy for smart, sustainable and inclusive growth&apos; (Europe 2020) and the Commission&apos;s Agenda for Jobs, Growth, Fairness and Democratic Change.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d440e104">
               <num>(2)</num>
               <p>European statistics should take a comprehensive Union-wide approach that provides accurate data to assist further integration processes in the Union.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d440e110">
               <num>(3)</num>
               <p>The availability of reliable, comprehensive European statistics is an important public good that benefits decision-makers, researchers and the public.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d440e116">
               <num>(4)</num>
               <p>A good balance between economic and social goals in the European Semester is particularly important for the sustainability and legitimacy of the Economic and Monetary Union. Accordingly, social and employment goals have become more prominent in the European Semester, with both country reports and country-specific recommendations assessing social and employment challenges and promoting policy reforms based on best practice. To that end, social statistics are of particular importance.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d440e123">
               <num>(5)</num>
               <p>Under Regulation (EC) No 223/2009 of the European Parliament and of the Council<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="3">
                     <p>Regulation (EC) No 223/2009 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 11 March 2009 on European statistics and repealing Regulation (EC, Euratom) No 1101/2008 of the European Parliament and of the Council on the transmission of data subject to statistical confidentiality to the Statistical Office of the European Communities, Council Regulation (EC) No 322/97 on Community Statistics, and Council Decision 89/382/EEC, Euratom establishing a Committee on the Statistical Programmes of the European Communities (OJ L 87, 31.3.2009, p. 164).</p>
                  </authorialNote>, the European statistical programme (the &apos;programme&apos;) is to provide the framework for the development, production and dissemination of high-quality European statistics, setting out the main fields and objectives of the actions envisaged for a period corresponding to that of the multiannual financial framework. The programme should be implemented by individual statistical actions in accordance with Article 14 of Regulation (EC) No 223/2009. Annual work programmes should be based on the programme.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d440e143">
               <num>(6)</num>
               <p>Regulation (EU) No 99/2013 of the European Parliament and of the Council<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="4">
                     <p>Regulation (EU) No 99/2013 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 15 January 2013 on the European statistical programme 2013-17 (OJ L 39, 9.2.2013, p. 12).</p>
                  </authorialNote> only covers the period from 2013 to 2017, whereas the current multiannual financial framework extends to 2020. That Regulation should therefore be amended without delay to extend the programme to 2020 and to fill statistical gaps where urgently required.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d440e159">
               <num>(7)</num>
               <p>In the context of the Commission&apos;s Better Regulation Agenda, Union policies should increasingly be designed and monitored on the basis of reliable evidence that has a solid statistical basis. European statistics have a distinct role to play in that respect, and can make a real difference, especially in policy areas where analytical value based on reliable data and responsiveness are key for policies to be successful.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d440e165">
               <num>(8)</num>
               <p>High-quality statistics are therefore crucial to achieving better results and to contributing to a better Europe. Greater efforts should be made to boost investment in official statistics at both the European and national level. The programme should also provide guidance on priority policy areas, capacity-building and the ongoing reprioritisation. Furthermore, in order to ensure a harmonised approach to achieving the objectives of this Regulation, cooperation with international organisations should be strengthened.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d440e171">
               <num>(9)</num>
               <p>Action should be taken to tackle the most urgent statistical gaps, to increase timeliness and to support political priorities and economic policy coordination throughout the European Semester. The Commission (Eurostat) should also provide new population projections in close cooperation with national statistical institutes, including as regards migration flows, in order to update the analyses of the social, economic and budgetary implications of population ageing and of economic inequalities.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d440e178">
               <num>(10)</num>
               <p>To support efficient policy-making, indicators should be published in a timely manner. In accordance with Article 12 of Regulation (EC) No 223/2009, the Commission (Eurostat) should communicate publicly on timeliness, including the provision of relevant information in respect of any insufficient timeliness that might occur, as an aspect of the statistical quality.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d440e184">
               <num>(11)</num>
               <p>Experimental ecosystem accounts and climate change statistics, including those relevant to climate change adaptation and &apos;footprints&apos;, should be further developed using existing data. The European Energy Union and the 2030 climate and energy framework, which aim to make the Union&apos;s economy and energy system more competitive, efficient, secure and sustainable, will require new statistics on energy consumption, energy efficiency, renewable energy sources, energy dependence and security of supply, as well as new statistics on the circular economy.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d440e194">
               <num>(12)</num>
               <p>High-quality statistics developed, produced and disseminated under the programme, in particular statistics on innovation, research and development, social statistics, environmental statistics as well as energy and transport statistics should allow the monitoring of objectives and targets of the United Nations 2030 Agenda for Sustainable Development that are to be set at the Union and Member State level and, in that way, contribute to the achievement of those objectives and targets.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d440e200">
               <num>(13)</num>
               <p>Progress should be made in improving qualitative and quantitative information that contributes to the exhaustiveness of national accounts and thus allows for better estimates of the tax gap and tax avoidance.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d440e206">
               <num>(14)</num>
               <p>The extension of the programme is an opportunity that should be taken to make adaptations and reflect the new orientations, in particular in line with the European Statistical System (ESS) Vision 2020, to complement the existing objectives, ongoing prioritisation and the availability of data in a context where the Union is facing important challenges in terms of economic development and social cohesion. It should ensure continuedcooperation between the Commission (Eurostat) and the national statistical institutes, and should ensure regular dialogues with the European Statistical Advisory Committee established by Decision No 234/2008/EC of the European Parliament and of the Council<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="5">
                     <p>Decision No 234/2008/EC of the European Parliament and of the Council of 11 March 2008 establishing the European Statistical Advisory Committee and repealing Council Decision 91/116/EEC (OJ L 73, 15.3.2008, p. 13).</p>
                  </authorialNote>. It should also ensure the coordination between the ESS and the European System of Central Banks. The Commission (Eurostat) should monitor Member States&apos; compliance with the European Statistics Code of Practice (Code of Practice).</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d440e224">
               <num>(15)</num>
               <p>It is particularly important to measure pockets of high unemployment, including youth unemployment in cross-border regions.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d440e230">
               <num>(16)</num>
               <p>An appropriate increase in the budget for statistics at Union level should support the changes to the programme and the ongoing efficiency work of the ESS by bringing significant added value and results for the improvement of the quality of data through large scale projects, structural leverage effects and economies of scale that can improve statistical systems across Member States.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d440e236">
               <num>(17)</num>
               <p>This Regulation lays down a financial envelope for the extension of the programme to cover the period from 2018 to 2020, which is to constitute the prime reference amount, within the meaning of point 17 of the Interinstitutional Agreement of 2 December 2013 between the European Parliament, the Council and the Commission on budgetary discipline, on cooperation in budgetary matters and on sound financial management<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="6">
                     <p>OJ C 373, 20.12.2013, p. 1.</p>
                  </authorialNote>, for the European Parliament and the Council during the annual budgetary procedure.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d440e251">
               <num>(18)</num>
               <p>In extending the programme, the Commission (Eurostat) should give particular consideration to the consequences of the withdrawal of a Member State from the Union.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d440e257">
               <num>(19)</num>
               <p>Since the objective of this Regulation, namely to extend the programme to cover the period from 2018 to 2020, cannot be sufficiently achieved by the Member States but can rather, by reason of the scale and effects of the action, be better achieved at Union level, the Union may adopt measures, in accordance with the principle of subsidiarity as set out in Article 5 of the Treaty on European Union. In accordance with the principle of proportionality, as set out in that Article, this Regulation does not go beyond what is necessary in order to achieve that objective.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d440e263">
               <num>(20)</num>
               <p>In accordance with Regulation (EC) No 223/2009, the draft proposal for an extension of the programme to cover the period from 2018 to 2020 has been submitted for prior examination to the European Statistical System Committee (ESSC), the European Statistical Advisory Committee and the Committee on Monetary, Financial and Balance of Payments Statistics established by Council Decision 2006/856/EC<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="7">
                     <p>Council Decision 2006/856/EC of 13 November 2006 establishing a Committee on monetary, financial and balance of payments statistics (OJ L 332, 30.11.2006, p. 21).</p>
                  </authorialNote>.</p>
            </recital>
            <recital xml:id="rec_d440e280">
               <num>(21)</num>
               <p>Regulation (EU) No 99/2013 should be amended accordingly,</p>
            </recital>
         </recitals>
         <formula name="enactingFormula">
            <p>HAVE ADOPTED THIS REGULATION:</p>
         </formula>
      </preamble>
      <body>
         <article xml:id="art_d440e289" leos:compliant="false">
            <num>Article 1</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <subparagraph>
                  <content>
                     <p>Regulation (EU) No 99/2013 is amended as follows:</p>
                  </content>
               </subparagraph>
               <list>
                  <point>
                     <num>(1)</num>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>in Article 1, the following paragraph is added:</p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>
                              <mod>
                                 <quotedStructure startQuote="" endQuote="">
                                    <paragraph>
                                       <content>
                                          <p>&apos;The programme shall be extended to cover the period from 2018 to 2020.&apos;;</p>
                                       </content>
                                    </paragraph>
                                 </quotedStructure>
                              </mod>
                           </p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                  </point>
                  <point>
                     <num>(2)</num>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>Article 3 is replaced by the following:</p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>
                              <mod>
                                 <quotedStructure startQuote="" endQuote="">
                                    <article xml:id="art_d440e317">
                                       <num>&apos;Article 3</num>
                                       <heading>Scope</heading>
                                       <paragraph>
                                          <content>
                                             <p>This Regulation provides the programming framework for the development, production and dissemination of European statistics, the main fields and the objectives of the actions envisaged for the period from 2013 to 2020, in accordance with Articles 13 and 14 of Regulation (EC) No 223/2009.&apos;;</p>
                                          </content>
                                       </paragraph>
                                    </article>
                                 </quotedStructure>
                              </mod>
                           </p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                  </point>
                  <point>
                     <num>(3)</num>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>in Article 7(1), the following subparagraph is added:</p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>
                              <mod>
                                 <quotedStructure startQuote="" endQuote="">
                                    <paragraph>
                                       <content>
                                          <p>&apos;The financial envelope for the implementation of the programme for 2018 to 2020 shall be EUR 218,1 million, covered by the programming period 2014 to 2020.&apos;;</p>
                                       </content>
                                    </paragraph>
                                 </quotedStructure>
                              </mod>
                           </p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                  </point>
                  <point>
                     <num>(4)</num>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>Article 9 is replaced by the following:</p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>
                              <mod>
                                 <quotedStructure startQuote="" endQuote="">
                                    <article xml:id="art_d440e349">
                                       <num>&apos;Article 9</num>
                                       <heading>Annual work programmes</heading>
                                       <paragraph>
                                          <content>
                                             <p>In order to implement the programme, the Commission shall adopt annual work programmes which shall satisfy the requirements laid down in Article 17 of Regulation (EC) No 223/2009 and which shall set out the objectives pursued and the expected results, in accordance with the general and specific objectives referred to in Article 4(1) and (2) of this Regulation. The Commission shall ensure that an appropriate emphasis is placed on actions aimed at promoting compliance with the Code of Practice. Each annual work programme shall be communicated to the European Parliament for information purposes.&apos;;</p>
                                          </content>
                                       </paragraph>
                                    </article>
                                 </quotedStructure>
                              </mod>
                           </p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                  </point>
                  <point>
                     <num>(5)</num>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>Article 13 is replaced by the following:</p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>
                              <mod>
                                 <quotedStructure startQuote="" endQuote="">
                                    <article xml:id="art_d440e367">
                                       <num>&apos;Article 13</num>
                                       <heading>Protection of the financial interests of the Union</heading>
                                       <paragraph>
                                          <num>1.</num>
                                          <content>
                                             <p>The Commission shall take appropriate measures to ensure that, when activities financed under this Regulation are implemented, the financial interests of the Union are protected by the application of preventive measures against fraud, corruption and any other illegal activities, by effective checks and, if irregularities are detected, by the recovery of the amounts wrongly paid and, where appropriate, by effective, proportionate and dissuasive administrative and financial penalties.</p>
                                          </content>
                                       </paragraph>
                                       <paragraph>
                                          <num>2.</num>
                                          <content>
                                             <p>The Commission or its representatives and the Court of Auditors shall have the power of audit, on the basis of documents and of on-the-spot inspections, over all grant beneficiaries, contractors and subcontractors who have received Union funds under the programme.</p>
                                          </content>
                                       </paragraph>
                                       <paragraph>
                                          <num>3.</num>
                                          <content>
                                             <p>The European Anti-Fraud Office (OLAF) may carry out investigations, including on-the-spot checks and inspections, in accordance with the provisions and procedures laid down in Regulation (EU, Euratom) No 883/2013 of the European Parliament and of the Council<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="8">
                                                   <p>Regulation (EU, Euratom) No 883/2013 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 11 September 2013 concerning investigations conducted by the European Anti-Fraud Office (OLAF) and repealing Regulation (EC) No 1073/1999 of the European Parliament and of the Council and Council Regulation (Euratom) No 1074/1999 (OJ L 248, 18.9.2013, p. 1).</p>
                                                </authorialNote> and Council Regulation (Euratom, EC) No 2185/96<authorialNote placement="bottom" marker="9">
                                                   <p>Council Regulation (Euratom, EC) No 2185/96 of 11 November 1996 concerning on-the-spot checks and inspections carried out by the Commission in order to protect the European Communities&apos; financial interests against fraud and other irregularities (OJ L 292, 15.11.1996, p. 2).&apos;;</p>
                                                </authorialNote>, with a view to establishing whether there has been fraud, corruption or any other illegal activity affecting the financial interests of the Union in connection with a grant agreement or grant decision or a contract funded under the programme.</p>
                                          </content>
                                       </paragraph>
                                       <paragraph>
                                          <num>4.</num>
                                          <content>
                                             <p>Without prejudice to paragraphs 1, 2 and 3, cooperation agreements with third countries and with international organisations, contracts, grant agreements and grant decisions resulting from the implementation of this Regulation shall contain provisions expressly empowering the Commission, the Court of Auditors and OLAF to conduct such audits and investigations, in accordance with their respective competence.</p>
                                          </content>
                                       </paragraph>
                                       <paragraph>
                                          <num>5.</num>
                                          <content>
                                             <p>Without prejudice to paragraphs 1, 2 and 3, where the implementation of an action is outsourced or sub-delegated, in whole or in part, or where it requires the award of a procurement contract or financial support to be given to a third party, the contract, grant agreement or grant decision shall include the contractor&apos;s or beneficiary&apos;s obligation to impose on any third party involved the explicit acceptance of those powers of the Commission, the Court of Auditors and OLAF.</p>
                                          </content>
                                       </paragraph>
                                    </article>
                                 </quotedStructure>
                              </mod>
                           </p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                  </point>
                  <point>
                     <num>(6)</num>
                     <alinea>
                        <content>
                           <p>Article 15 is amended as follows:</p>
                        </content>
                     </alinea>
                     <list>
                        <point>
                           <num>(a)</num>
                           <alinea>
                              <content>
                                 <p>the following paragraph is inserted:</p>
                              </content>
                           </alinea>
                           <alinea>
                              <content>
                                 <p>
                                    <mod>
                                       <quotedStructure startQuote="" endQuote="">
                                          <paragraph>
                                             <num>&apos;2a.</num>
                                             <content>
                                                <p>By 31 December 2019, the Commission (Eurostat) shall submit a progress report on the implementation of the programme to the ESSC. That report shall detail the Commission&apos;s (Eurostat) view on the outlook for the programme within the multiannual financial framework starting in 2021. That report shall also be submitted to the European Parliament and to the Council.&apos;;</p>
                                             </content>
                                          </paragraph>
                                       </quotedStructure>
                                    </mod>
                                 </p>
                              </content>
                           </alinea>
                        </point>
                        <point>
                           <num>(b)</num>
                           <alinea>
                              <content>
                                 <p>paragraph 3 is replaced by the following:</p>
                              </content>
                           </alinea>
                           <alinea>
                              <content>
                                 <p>
                                    <mod>
                                       <quotedStructure startQuote="" endQuote="">
                                          <paragraph>
                                             <num>&apos;3.</num>
                                             <subparagraph>
                                                <content>
                                                   <p>By 31 December 2021, the Commission shall, after consulting the ESSC and the European Statistical Advisory Committee, submit a final evaluation report on the implementation of the programme to the European Parliament and to the Council. The report shall in particular evaluate:</p>
                                                </content>
                                             </subparagraph>
                                             <list>
                                                <point>
                                                   <num>(a)</num>
                                                   <content>
                                                      <p>the outcome of the reprioritisation and cost evaluation of statistical products;</p>
                                                   </content>
                                                </point>
                                                <point>
                                                   <num>(b)</num>
                                                   <content>
                                                      <p>the actions taken by the ESS to reduce the implementation and production costs for Member States and to limit the overall burden stemming from the statistical projects and fields covered by the programme;</p>
                                                   </content>
                                                </point>
                                                <point>
                                                   <num>(c)</num>
                                                   <content>
                                                      <p>the progress on rendering access to official statistics easier and more user-friendly, including the provision of data on the Eurostat website; and</p>
                                                   </content>
                                                </point>
                                                <point>
                                                   <num>(d)</num>
                                                   <content>
                                                      <p>the progress on the improvement of data availability, including on social economy activities and on the Europe 2020 indicators.&apos;;</p>
                                                   </content>
                                                </point>
                                             </list>
                                          </paragraph>
                                       </quotedStructure>
                                    </mod>
                                 </p>
                              </content>
                           </alinea>
                        </point>
                     </list>
                  </point>
                  <point>
                     <num>(7)</num>
                     <content>
                        <p>the Annex to Regulation (EU) No 99/2013 is amended in accordance with the Annex to this Regulation.</p>
                     </content>
                  </point>
               </list>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <article xml:id="art_d440e499">
            <num>Article 2</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>This Regulation shall enter into force on the twentieth day following that of its publication in the <i>Official Journal of the European Union</i>.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph>
               <content>
                  <p>It shall apply from 1 January 2018.</p>
               </content>
            </paragraph>
         </article>
         <clause>
            <content>
               <p>This Regulation shall be binding in its entirety and directly applicable in all Member States.</p>
            </content>
         </clause>
      </body>
      <conclusions>
         <p>Done at Strasbourg, 25 October 2017.</p>
         <block name="signatory">
            <signature>
               <organization refersTo="">For the European Parliament</organization>
               <role refersTo="">The President</role>
               <person refersTo="">A. TAJANI</person>
            </signature>
            <signature>
               <organization refersTo="">For the Council</organization>
               <role refersTo="">The President</role>
               <person refersTo="">M. MAASIKAS</person>
            </signature>
         </block>
      </conclusions>
   </bill>
</akomaNtoso>
